PART THREE

1

August　21，1939

Morning

“I will not be hurried，”Doctor Copeland said.“Just let me be. Kindly allow me to sit here in peace a moment.”

“Father, us not trying to rush you. But it time now to get gone from here.”

Doctor Copeland rocked stubbornly, his gray shawl drawn close around his shoulders. Although the morning was warm and fresh, a small wood fire burned in the stove.The kitchen was bare of all furniture except the chair in which he sat.The other rooms were empty, too.Most of the furniture had been moved to Portia's house, and the rest was tied to the automobile outside.All was in readiness except his own mind.But how could he leave when there was neither beginning nor end, neither truth nor purpose in his thoughts?He put up his hand to steady his trembling head and continued to rock himself slowly in the creaking chair.

Behind the closed door he heard their voices：

“I done all I can. He determined to sit there till he good and ready to leave.”

“Buddy and me done wrapped the china plates and—”

“Us should have left before the dew dried，”said the old man.“As is, night liable to catch us on the road.”

Their voices quieted. Footsteps echoed in the empty hallway and he could hear them no more.On the floor beside him was a cup and saucer.He filled it with coffee from the pot on the top of the stove.As he rocked he drank the coffee and warmed his fingers in the steam.This could not truly be the end.Other voices called wordless in his heart.The voice of Jesus and of John Brown.The voice of the great Spinoza and of Karl Marx.The calling voices of all those who had fought and to whom it had been vouchsafed to complete their missions.The grief-bound voices of his people.And also the voice of the dead.Of the mute Singer, who was a righteous white man of understanding.The voices of the weak and of the mighty.The rolling voice of his people growing always in strength and in power.The voice of the strong, true purpose.And in answer the words trembled on his lips—the words which are surely the root of all human grief—so that he almost said aloud：“Almighty Host！Utmost power of the universe！I have done those things which I ought not to have done and left undone those things which I ought to have done.So this cannot truly be the end.”

He had first come into the house with her whom he loved. And Daisy was dressed in her bridal gown and wore a white lace veil.Her skin was the beautiful color of dark honey and her laughter was sweet.At night he had shut himself in the bright room to study alone.He had tried to cogitate and to discipline himself to study.But with Daisy near him there was a strong desire in him that would not go away with study.So sometimes he surrendered to these feelings, and again he bit his lips and meditated with the books throughout the night.And then there were Hamilton and Karl Marx and William and Portia.All lost.No one remained.

And Madyben and Benny Mae. And Benedine Madine and Mady Copeland.Those who carried his name.And those whom he had exhorted.But out of the thousands of them where was there one to whom he could entrust the mission and then take ease?

All of his life he had known it strongly. He had known the reason for his working and was sure in his heart because he knew each day what lay ahead of him.He would go with his bag from house to house, and on all things he would talk to them and patiently explain.And then in the night he would be happy in the knowledge that the day had been a day of purpose.And even without Daisy and Hamilton and Karl Marx and William and Portia he could sit by the stove alone and take joy from this knowledge.He would drink a pot of turnip-green liquor and eat a pone of cornbread.A deep feeling of satisfaction would be in him because the day was good.

There were thousands of such times of satisfaction. But what had been their meaning?Out of all the years he could think of no work of lasting value.

After a while the door to the hall was opened and Portia came in.“I reckon I going to have to dress you like a baby，”she said.“Here your shoes and socks. Let me take off your bedroom shoes and put them on.We got to get gone from here pretty soon.”

“Why have you done this to me?”he asked bitterly.

“What I done to you now?”

“You know full well that I do not want to leave. You pressed me into saying yes when I was in no fit condition to make a decision.I wish to remain where I have always been, and you know it.”

“Listen to you carry on！”Portia said angrily.“You done grumbled so much that I nearly worn out. You done fumed and fussed so that I right shamed for you.”

“Pshaw！Say what you will. You only come before me like a gnat.I know what I wish and will not be pestered into doing that which is wrong.”

Portia took off his bedroom shoes and unrolled a pair of clean black cotton socks.“Father, less us quit this here argument. Us have all done the best we know how.It entirely the best plan for you to go out with Grandpapa and Hamilton and Buddy.They going to take good care of you and you going to get well.”

“No, I will not，”said Doctor Copeland.“But I would have recovered here. I know it.”

“Who you think could pay the note on this here house?How you think us could feed you?Who you think could take care you here?”

“I have always managed, and I can manage yet.”

“You just trying to be contrary.”

“Pshaw！You come before me like a gnat. And I ignore you.”

“That certainly is a nice way to talk to me while I trying to put on your shoes and socks.”

“I am sorry. Forgive me, Daughter.”

“Course you sorry，”she said.“Course we both sorry. Us can't afford to quarrel.And besides, once we get you settled on the farm you going to like it.They got the prettiest vegetable garden I ever seen.Make my mouth slobber to think about it.And chickens and two breed sows and eighteen peach trees.You just going to be crazy about it there.I sure do wish it was me could get a chance to go.”

“I wish so, too.”

“How come you so determined to grieve?”

“I just feel that I have failed，”he said.

“How you mean you done failed?”

“I do not know. Just leave me be, Daughter.Just let me sit here in peace a moment.”

“O. K.But us got to get gone from here pretty soon.”

He would be silent. He would sit quietly and rock in the chair until the sense of order was in him once more.His head trembled and his backbone ached.

“I certainly hope this，”Portia said.“I certainly hope that when I dead and gone as many peoples grieves for me as grieves for Mr. Singer.I sure would like to know I were going to have as sad a funeral as he had and as many peoples—”

“Hush！”said Doctor Copeland roughly.“You talk too much.”

But truly with the death of that white man a dark sorrow had lain down in his heart. He had talked to him as to no other white man and had trusted him.And the mystery of his suicide had left him baffled and without support.There was neither beginning nor end to this sorrow.Nor understanding.Always he would return in his thoughts to this white man who was not insolent or scornful but who was just.And how can the dead be truly dead when they still live in the souls of those who are left behind?But of all this he must not think.He must thrust it from him now.

For it was discipline he needed. During the past month the black, terrible feelings had arisen again to wrestle with his spirit.There was the hatred that for days had truly let him down into the regions of death.After the quarrel with Mr.Blount, the midnight visitor, there had been in him a murderous darkness.Yet now he could not clearly recall those issues which were the cause of their dispute.And then the different anger that came in him when he looked on the stumps of Willie's legs.The warring love and hatred—love for his people and hatred for the oppressors of his people—that left him exhausted and sick in spirit.

“Daughter，”he said.“Get me my watch and coat. I am going.”

He pushed himself up with the arms of the chair. The floor seemed a far way from his face and after the long time in bed his legs were very weak.For a moment he felt he would fall.He walked dizzily across the bare room and stood leaning against the side of the doorway.He coughed and took from his pocket one of the squares of paper to hold over his mouth.

“Here your coat，”Portia said.“But it so hot outside you not going to need it.”

He walked for the last time through the empty house. The blinds were closed and in the darkened rooms there was the smell of dust.He rested against the wall of the vestibule and then went outside.The morning was bright and warm.Many friends had come to say good-bye the night before and in the very early morning—but now only the family was congregated on the porch.The wagon and the automobile were parked out in the street.

“Well, Benedict Mady，”the old man said.“I reckon you ghy be a little bit homesick these first few days. But won't be long.”

“I do not have any home. So why should I be homesick?”

Portia wet her lips nervously and said：“He coming back whenever he get good and ready. Buddy will be glad to ride him to town in the car.Buddy just love to drive.”

The automobile was loaded. Boxes of books were tied to the running-board.The back seat was crowded with two chairs and the filing case.His office desk, legs in the air, had been fastened to the top.But although the car was weighted down the wagon was almost empty.The mule stood patiently, a brick tied to his reins.

“Karl Marx，”Doctor Copeland said.“Look sharp. Go over the house and make sure that nothing is left.Bring the cup I left on the floor and my rocking-chair.”

“Less us get started. I anxious to be home by dinner-time，”Hamilton said.

At last they were ready. Highboy cranked the automobile.Karl Marx sat at the wheel and Portia, Highboy, and William were crowded together on the back seat.

“Father, suppose you set on Highboy's lap. I believe you be more comfortable than scrouged up here with us and all this furniture.”

“No, it is too crowded. I would rather ride in the wagon.”

“But you not used to the wagon，”Karl Marx said.“It going to be very bumpy and the trip liable to take all day.”

“That does not matter. I have ridden in many a wagon before this.”

“Tell Hamilton to come with us. I sure he rather ride in the automobile.”

Grandpapa had driven the wagon into town the day before. They brought with them a load of produce, peaches and cabbages and turnips, for Hamilton to sell in town.All except a sack of peaches had been marketed.

“Well, Benedict Mady, I see you riding home with me，”the old man said.

Doctor Copeland climbed into the back of the wagon. He was weary as though his bones were made of lead.His head trembled and a sudden spasm of nausea made him lie down flat on the rough boards.

“I right glad you coming，”Grandpapa said.“You understand I always had deep respect for scholars. Deep respect I able to overlook and forget a good many things if a man be a scholar.I very glad to have a scholar like you in the fambly again.”

The wheels of the wagon creaked. They were on the way.“I will return soon，”Doctor Copeland said.“After only a month or two I will return.”

“Hamilton he a right good scholar. I think he favors you some.He do all my figuring on paper for me and he read the newspapers.And Whitman I think he ghy be a scholar.Right now he able to read the Bible to me.And do number work.Small a child as he is.I always had a deep respect for scholars.”

The motion of the wagon jolted his back. He looked up at the branches overhead, and then when there was no shade he covered his face with a handkerchief to shield his eyes from the sun.It was not possible that this could be the end.Always he had felt in him the strong, true purpose.For forty years his mission was his life and his life was his mission.And yet all remained to be done and nothing was completed.

“Yes, Benedict Mady, I right glad to have you with us again. I been waiting to ask you about this peculiar feeling in my right foot.A queer feeling like my foot gone to sleep.I taken　666　and rubbed it with liniment.I hoping you will find me a good treatment.”

“I will do what I can.”

“Yes, I glad to have you. I believe in all kinfolks sticking together—blood kin and marriage kin.I believe in all us struggling along and helping each other out, and some day us will have a reward in the Beyond.”

“Pshaw！”Doctor Copeland said bitterly.“I believe in justice now.”

“What that you say you believe in?You speak so hoarse I ain't able to hear you.”

“In justice for us. Justice for us Negroes.”

“That right.”

He felt the fire in him and he could not be still. He wanted to sit up and speak in a loud voice—yet when he tried to raise himself he could not find the strength.The words in his heart grew big and they would not be silent.But the old man had ceased to listen and there was no one to hear him.

“Git, Lee Jackson. Git, Honey.Pick up your feets and quit this here poking.Us got a long way to go.”

2

Afternoon

Jake ran at a violent, clumsy pace. He went through Weavers Lane and then cut into a side alley, climbed a fence, and hastened onward.Nausea rose in his belly so that there was the taste of vomit in his throat.A barking dog chased beside him until he stopped long enough to threaten it with a rock.His eyes were wide with horror and he held his hand clapped to his open mouth.

Christ！So this was the finish. A brawl.A riot.A fight with every man for himself.Bloody heads and eyes cut with broken bottles.Christ！And the wheezy music of the flying-jinny above the noise.The dropped hamburgers and cotton candy and the screaming younguns.And him in it all.Fighting blind with the dust and sun.The sharp cut of teeth against his knuckles.And laughing.Christ！And the feeling that he had let loose a wild, hard rhythm in him that wouldn't stop.And then looking close into the dead black face and not knowing.Not even knowing if he had killed or not.But wait.Christ！Nobody could have stopped it.

Jake slowed and jerked his head nervously to look behind him. The alley was empty.He vomited and wiped his mouth and forehead with the sleeve of his shirt.Afterward he rested for a minute and felt better.He had run for about eight blocks and with short cuts there was about half a mile to go.The dizziness cleared in his head so that from all the wild feelings he could remember facts.He started off again, this time at a steady jog.

Nobody could have stopped it. All through the summer he had stamped them out like sudden fires.All but this one.And this fight nobody could have stopped.It seemed to blaze up out of nothing.He had been working on the machinery of the swings and had stopped to get a glass of water.As he passed across the grounds he saw a white boy and a Negro walking around each other.They were both drunk.Half the crowd was drunk that afternoon, for it was Saturday and the mills had run full time that week.The heat and the sun were sickening and there was a heavy stink in the air.

He saw the two fighters close in on each other. But he knew that this was not the beginning.He had felt a big fight coming for a long time.And the funny thing was he found time to think of all this.He stood watching for about five seconds before he pushed into the crowd.In that short time he thought of many things.He thought of Singer.He thought of the sullen summer afternoons and the black, hot nights, of all the fights he had broken up and the quarrels he had hushed.

Then he saw the flash of a pocket-knife in the sun. He shouldered through a knot of people and jumped on the back of the Negro who held the knife.The man went down with him and they were on the ground together.The smell of sweat on the Negro was mixed with the heavy dust in his lungs.Someone trampled on his legs and his head was kicked.By the time he got to his feet again the fight had become general.The Negroes were fighting the white men and the white men were fighting the Negroes.He saw clearly, second by second.The white boy who had picked the fight seemed a kind of leader.He was the leader of a gang that came often to the show.They were about sixteen years old and they wore white duck trousers and fancy rayon polo shirts.The Negroes fought back as best they could.Some had razors.

He began to yell out words：Order！Help！Police！But it was like yelling at a breaking dam. There was a terrible sound in his ear—terrible because it was human and yet without words.The sound rose to a roar that deafened him.He was hit on the head.He could not see what went on around him.He saw only eyes and mouths and fists—wild eyes and half-closed eyes, wet, loose mouths and clenched ones, black fists and white.He grabbed a knife from a hand and caught an upraised fist.Then the dust and the sun blinded him and the one thought in his mind was to get out and find a telephone to call for help.

But he was caught. And without knowing when it happened he piled into the fight himself.He hit out with his fists and felt the soft squash of wet mouths.He fought with his eyes shut and his head lowered.A crazy sound came out of his throat.He hit with all his strength and charged with his head like a bull.Senseless words were in his mind and he was laughing.He did not see who he hit and did not know who hit him.But he knew that the line-up of the fight had changed and now each man was for himself.

Then suddenly it was finished. He tripped and fell over backward.He was knocked out so that it may have been a minute or it may have been much longer before he opened his eyes.A few drunks were still fighting but two dicks were breaking it up fast.He saw what he had tripped over.He lay half on and half beside the body of a young Negro boy.With only one look he knew that he was dead.There was a cut on the side of his neck but it was hard to see how he had died in such a hurry.He knew the face but could not place it.The boy's mouth was open and his eyes were open in surprise.The ground was littered with papers and broken bottles and trampled hamburgers.The head was broken off one of the jinny horses and a booth was destroyed.He was sitting up.He saw the dicks and in a panic he started to run.By now they must have lost his track.

There were only four more blocks ahead, and then he would be safe for sure. Fear had shortened his breath so that he was winded.He clenched his fists and lowered his head.Then suddenly he slowed and halted.He was alone in an alley near the main street.On one side was the wall of a building and he slumped against it, panting, the corded vein in his forehead inflamed.In his confusion he had run all the way across the town to reach the room of his friend.And Singer was dead.He began to cry.He sobbed aloud, and water dripped down from his nose and wet his mustache.

A wall, a flight of stairs, a road ahead. The burning sun was like a heavy weight on him.He started back the way he had come.This time he walked slowly, wiping his wet face with the greasy sleeve of his shirt.He could not stop the trembling of his lips and he bit them until he tasted blood.

At the corner of the next block he ran into Simms. The old codger was sitting on a box with his Bible on his knees.There was a tall board fence behind him, and on it a message was written with purple chalk.

He Died to Save You

Hear the Story of His Love and Grace

Every Nite　7.15　P.M.

The street was empty. Jake tried to cross over to the other sidewalk, but Simms caught him by the arm.

“Come, all ye disconsolate and sore of heart. Lay down your sins and troubles before the blessed feet of Him who died to save you.Wherefore goest thou, Brother Blount?”

“Home to hockey，”Jake said.“I got to hockey. Does the Saviour have anything against that?”

“Sinner！The Lord remembers all your transgressions. The Lord has a message for you this very night.”

“Does the Lord remember that dollar I gave you last week?”

“Jesus has a message for you at seven-fifteen tonight. You be here on time to hear His Word.”

Jake licked his mustache.“You have such a crowd every night I can't get up close enough to hear.”

“There is a place for scoffers. Besides, I have had a sign that soon the Saviour wants me to build a house for Him.On that lot at the corner of Eighteenth Avenue and Sixth Street.A tabernacle large enough to hold five hundred people.Then you scoffers will see.The Lord prepareth a table before me in the presence of mine enemies；he anointeth my head with oil.My cup runneth—”

“I can round you up a crowd tonight，”Jake said.

“How?”

“Give me your pretty colored chalk. I promise a big crowd.”

“I've seen your signs，”Simms said.“‘Workers！America Is the Richest Country in the World Yet a Third of Us Are Starving. When Will We Unite and Demand Our Share?'—all that.Your signs are radical.I wouldn't let you use my chalk.”

“But I don't plan to write signs.”

Simms fingered the pages of his Bible and waited suspiciously.

“I'll get you a fine crowd. On the pavements at each end of the block I'll draw you some good-looking naked floozies.All in color with arrows to point the way.Sweet, plump, bare-tailed—”

“Babylonian！”the old man screamed.“Child of Sodom！God will remember this.”

Jake crossed over to the other sidewalk and started toward the house where he lived.“So long, Brother.”

“Sinner，”the old man called.“You come back here at seven-fifteen sharp. And hear the message from Jesus that will give you faith.Be saved.”

Singer was dead. And the way he had felt when he first heard that he had killed himself was not sad—it was angry.He was before a wall.He remembered all the innermost thoughts that he had told to Singer, and with his death it seemed to him that they were lost.And why had Singer wanted to end his life?Maybe he had gone insane.But anyway he was dead, dead, dead.He could not be seen or touched or spoken to, and the room where they had spent so many hours had been rented to a girl who worked as a typist.He could go there no longer.He was alone.A wall, a flight of stairs, an open road.

Jake locked the door of his room behind him. He was hungry and there was nothing to eat.He was thirsty and only a few drops of warm water were left in the pitcher by the table.The bed was unmade and dusty fluff had accumulated on the floor.Papers were scattered all about the room, because recently he had written many short notices and distributed them through the town.Moodily he glanced at one of the papers labeled“The T.W.O.C.Is Your Best Friend.”Some of the notices consisted of only one sentence, others were longer.There was one full-page manifesto entitled“The Affinity Between Our Democracy and Fascism.”

For a month he had worked on these papers, scribbling them during working hours, typing and making carbons on the typewriter at the New York Café，distributing them by hand.He had worked day and night.But who read them?What good had any of it done?A town this size was too big for any one man.And now he was leaving.

But where would it be this time?The names of cities called to him—Memphis, Wilmington, Gastonia, New Orleans. He would go somewhere.But not out of the South.The old restlessness and hunger were in him again.It was different this time.He did not long for open space and freedom—just the reverse.He remembered what the Negro, Copeland, had said to him，“Do not attempt to stand alone.”There were times when that was best.

Jake moved the bed across the room. On the part of the floor the bed had hidden there were a suitcase and a pile of books and dirty clothes.Impatiently he began to pack.The old Negro's face was in his mind and some of the words they had said came back to him.Copeland was crazy.He was a fanatic, so that it was maddening to try to reason with him.Still the terrible anger that they had felt that night had been hard to understand.Copeland knew.And those who knew were like a handful of naked soldiers before an armed battalion.And what had they done?They had turned to quarrel with each other.Copeland was wrong—yes—he was crazy.But on some points they might be able to work together after all.If they didn't talk too much.He would go and see him.A sudden urge to hurry came in him.Maybe that would be the best thing after all.Maybe that was the sign, the hand he had so long awaited.

Without pausing to wash the grime from his face and hands he strapped his suitcase and left the room. Outside the air was sultry and there was a foul odor in the street.Clouds had formed in the sky.The atmosphere was so still that the smoke from a mill in the district went up in a straight, unbroken line.As Jake walked the suitcase bumped awkwardly against his knees, and often he jerked his head to look behind him.Copeland lived all the way across the town, so there was need to hurry.The clouds in the sky grew steadily denser, and foretold a heavy summer rain before nightfall.

When he reached the house where Copeland lived he saw that the shutters were drawn. He walked to the back and peered through the window at the abandoned kitchen.A hollow, desperate disappointment made his hands feel sweaty and his heart lose the rhythm of its beat.He went to the house on the left but no one was at home.There was nothing to do except to go to the Kelly house and question Portia.

He hated to be near that house again. He couldn't stand to see the hatrack in the front hall and the long flight of stairs he had climbed so many times.He walked slowly back across the town and approached by way of the alley.He went in the rear door.Portia was in the kitchen and the little boy was with her.

“No, sir, Mr. Blount，”Portia said.“I know you were a mighty good friend of Mr.Singer and you understand what Father thought of him.But we taken Father out in the country this morning and I know in my soul I got no business telling you exactly where he is.If you don't mind I rather speak out and not minch the matter.”

“You don't have to minch anything，”Jake said.“But why?”

“After the time you come to see us Father were so sick us expected him to die. It taken us a long time to get him able to sit up.He doing right well now.He going to get a lot stronger where he is now.But whether you understand this or not he right bitter against white peoples just now and he very easy to upset.And besides, if you don't mind speaking out, what you want with Father, anyway?”

“Nothing，”Jake said.“Nothing you would understand.”

“Us colored peoples have feelings just like anybody else. And I stand by what I said, Mr.Blount.Father just a sick old colored man and he had enough trouble already.Us got to look after him.And he not anxious to see you—I know that.”

Out in the street again he saw that the clouds had turned a deep, angry purple. In the stagnant air there was a storm smell.The vivid green of the trees along the sidewalk seemed to steal into the atmosphere so that there was a strange greenish glow over the street.All was so hushed and still that Jake paused for a moment to sniff the air and look around him.Then he grasped his suitcase under his arm and began to run toward the awnings of the main street.But he was not quick enough.There was one metallic crash of thunder and the air chilled suddenly.Large silver drops of rain hissed on the pavement.An avalanche of water blinded him.When he reached the New York Café　his clothes clung wet and shriveled to his body and his shoes squeaked with water.

Brannon pushed aside his newspaper and leaned his elbows on the counter.“Now, this is really curious. I had this intuition you would come here just after the rain broke.I knew in my bones you were coming and that you would make it just too late.”He mashed his nose with this thumb until it was white and flat.“And a suitcase?”

“It looks like a suitcase，”Jake said.“And it feels like a suitcase. So if you believe in the actuality of suitcases I reckon this is one, all right.”

“You ought not to stand around like this. Go on upstairs and throw me down your clothes.Louis will run over them with a hot iron.”

Jake sat at one of the back booth tables and rested his head in his hands.“No, thanks. I just want to rest here and get my wind again.”

“But your lips are turning blue. You look all knocked up.”

“I'm all right. What I want is some supper.”

“Supper won't be ready for half an hour，”Brannon said patiently.

“Any old leftovers will do. Just put them on a plate.You don't even have to bother to heat them.”

The emptiness in him hurt. He wanted to look neither backward nor forward.He walked two of his short, chunky fingers across the top of the table.It was more than a year now since he had sat at this table for the first time.And how much further was he now than then?No further.Nothing had happened except that he had made a friend and lost him.He had given Singer everything and then the man had killed himself.So he was left out on a limb.And now it was up to him to get out of it by himself and make a new start again.At the thought of it panic came in him.He was tired.He leaned his head against the wall and put his feet on the seat beside him.

“Here you are，”Brannon said.“This ought to help out.”

He put down a glass of some hot drink and a plate of chicken pie. The drink had a sweet, heavy smell.Jake inhaled the steam and closed his eyes.“What's in it?”

“Lemon rind rubbed on a lump of sugar and boiling water with rum. It's a good drink.”

“How much do I owe you?”

“I don't know off-hand, but I'll figure it out before you leave.”

Jake took a deep draught of the toddy and washed it around in his mouth before swallowing.“You'll never get the money，”he said.“I don't have it to pay you—and if I did I probably wouldn't anyway.”

“Well, have I been pressing you?Have I ever made you out a bill and asked you to pay up?”

“No，”Jake said.“You been very reasonable. And since I think about it you're a right decent guy—from the personal perspective, that is.”

Brannon sat across from him at the table. Something was on his mind.He slid the salt-shaker back and forth and kept smoothing his hair.He smelled like perfume and his striped blue shirt was very fresh and clean.The sleeves were rolled and held in place by old-fashioned blue sleeve garters.

At last he cleared his throat in a hesitating way and said：“I was glancing through the afternoon paper just before you came. It seems you had a lot of trouble at your place today.”

“That's right. What did it say?”

“Wait. I'll get it.”Brannon fetched the paper from the counter and leaned against the partition of the booth.“It says on the front page that at the Sunny Dixie Show, located so and so, there was a general disturbance.Two Negroes were fatally injured with wounds inflicted by knives.Three others suffered minor wounds and were taken for treatment to the city hospital.The dead were Jimmy Macy and Lancy Davis.The wounded were John Hamlin, white, of Central Mill City, Various Wilson, Negro, and so forth and so on.Quote：‘A number of arrests were made.It is alleged that the disturbance was caused by labor agitation, as papers of a subversive nature were found on and about the site of disturbance.Other arrests are expected shortly.'”Brannon clicked his teeth together.“The set-up of this paper gets worse every day.Subversive spelled with a u in the second syllable and arrests with only one r.”

“They're smart, all right，”Jake said sneeringly.“‘Caused by labor agitation.'That's remarkable.”

“Anyway, the whole thing is very unfortunate.”

Jake held his hand to his mouth and looked down at his empty plate.

“What do you mean to do now?”

“I'm leaving. I'm getting out of here this afternoon.”

Brannon polished his nails on the palm of his hand.“Well, of course it's not necessary—but it might be a good thing. Why so headlong?No sense in starting out this time of day.”

“I just rather.”

“I do not think it behooves you to make a new start. At the same time why don't you take my advice on this?Myself—I'm a conservative and of course I think your opinions are radical.But at the same time I like to know all sides of a matter.Anyway, I want to see you straighten out.So why don't you go some place where you can meet a few people more or less like yourself?And then settle down?”

Jake pushed his plate irritably away from him.“I don't know where I'm going. Leave me alone.I'm tired.”

Brannon shrugged his shoulders and went back to the counter.

He was tired enough. The hot rum and the heavy sound of the rain made him drowsy.It felt good to be sitting safe in a booth and to have just eaten a good meal.If he wanted to he could lean over and take a nap—a short one.Already his head felt swollen and heavy and he was more comfortable with his eyes closed.But it would have to be a short sleep because soon he must get out of here.

“How long will this rain keep on?”

Brannon's voice had drowsy overtones.“You can't tell—a tropical cloudburst. Might clear up suddenly—or—might thin a little and set in for the night.”

Jake laid his head down on his arms. The sound of the rain was nice the swelling sound of the sea.He heard a clock tick and the far-off rattle of dishes.Gradually his hands relaxed.They lay open, palm upward, on the table.

Then Brannon was shaking him by the shoulders and looking into his face. A terrible dream was in his mind.“Wake up，”Brannon was saying.“You've had a nightmare.I looked over here and your mouth was open and you were groaning and shuffling your feet on the floor.I never saw anything to equal it.”

The dream was still heavy in his mind. He felt the old terror that always came as he awakened.He pushed Brannon away and stood up.“You don't have to tell me I had a nightmare.I remember just how it was.And I've had the same dream for about fifteen times before.”

He did remember now. Every other time he had been unable to get the dream straight in his waking mind.He had been walking among a great crowd of people—like at the show.But there was also something Eastern about the people around him.There was a terrible bright sun and the people were half-naked.They were silent and slow and their faces had a look in them of starvation.There was no sound, only the sun, and the silent crowd of people.He walked among them and he carried a huge covered basket.He was taking the basket somewhere but he could not find the place to leave it.And in the dream there was a peculiar horror in wandering on and on through the crowd and not knowing where to lay down the burden he had carried in his arms so long.

“What was it?”Brannon asked.“Was the devil chasing you?”

Jake stood up and went to the mirror behind the counter. His face was dirty and sweaty.There were dark circles beneath his eyes.He wet his handkerchief under the fountain faucet and wiped off his face.Then he took out a pocket comb and neatly combed his mustache.

“The dream was nothing. You got to be asleep to understand why it was such a nightmare.”

The clock pointed to five-thirty. The rain had almost stopped.Jake picked up his suitcase and went to the front door.“So long.I'll send you a postcard maybe.”

“Wait，”Brannon said.“You can't go now. It's still raining a little.”

“Just dripping off the awning. I rather get out of town before dark.”

“But hold on. Do you have any money?Enough to keep going for a week?”

“I don't need money. I been broke before.”

Brannon had an envelope ready and in it were two twenty-dollar bills. Jake looked at them on both sides and put them in his pocket.“God knows why you do it.You'll never smell them again.But thanks.I won't forget.”

“Good luck. And let me hear from you.”

“Adios.”

“Good-bye.”

The door closed behind him. When he looked back at the end of the block, Brannon was watching from the sidewalk.He walked until he reached the railroad tracks.On either side there were rows of dilapidated two-room houses.In the cramped back yards were rotted privies and lines of torn, smoky rags hung out to dry.For two miles there was not one sight of comfort or space or cleanliness.Even the earth itself seemed filthy and abandoned.Now and then there were signs that a vegetable row had been attempted, but only a few withered collards had survived.And a few fruitless, smutty fig trees.Little younguns swarmed in this filth, the smaller of them stark naked.The sight of this poverty was so cruel and hopeless that Jake snarled and clenched his fists.

He reached the edge of town and turned off on a highway. Cars passed him by.His shoulders were too wide and his arms too long.He was so strong and ugly that no one wanted to take him in.But maybe a truck would stop before long.The late afternoon sun was out again.Heat made the steam rise from the wet pavement.Jake walked steadily.As soon as the town was behind a new surge of energy came to him.But was this flight or was it onslaught?Anyway, he was going.All this to begin another time.The road ahead lay to the north and slightly to the west.But he would not go too far away.He would not leave the South.That was one clear thing.There was hope in him, and soon perhaps the outline of his journey would take form.

3

Evening

What good was it?That was the question she would like to know. What the hell good was it.All the plans she had made, and the music.When all that came of it was this trap—the store, then home to sleep, and back at the store again.The clock in front of the place where Mister Singer used to work pointed to seven.And she was just getting off.Whenever there was overtime the manager always told her to stay.Because she could stand longer on her feet and work harder before giving out than any other girl.

The heavy rain had left the sky a pale, quiet blue. Dark was coming.Already the lights were turned on.Automobile horns honked in the street and the newsboys hollered out the headlines in the papers.She didn't want to go home.If she went home now she would lie down on the bed and bawl.That was how tired she was.But if she went into the New York Café　and ate some ice cream she might feel O.K.And smoke and be by herself a little while.

The front part of the Café　was crowded, so she went to the very last booth.It was the small of her back and her face that got so tired.Their motto was supposed to be“Keep on your toes and smile.”Once she was out of the store she had to frown a long time to get her face natural again.Even her ears were tired.She took off the dangling green earrings and pinched the lobes of her ears.She had bought the earrings the week before—and also a silver bangle bracelet.At first she had worked in Pots and Pans, but now they had changed her to Costume Jewelry.

“Good evening, Mick，”Mister Brannon said. He wiped the bottom of a glass of water with a napkin and set it on the table.

“I want me a chocolate sundae and a nickel glass of draw beer.”

“Together?”He put down a menu and pointed with his little finger that wore a lady's gold ring.“See—here's some nice roast chicken or some veal stew. Why don't you have a little supper with me?”

“No, thanks. All I want is the sundae and the beer.Both plenty cold.”

Mick raked her hair from her forehead. Her mouth was open so that her cheeks seemed hollow.There were these two things she could never believe.That Mister Singer had killed himself and was dead.And that she was grown and had to work at Woolworth's.

She was the one who found him. They had thought the noise was a backfire from a car, and it was not until the next day that they knew.She went in to play the radio.The blood was all over his neck and when her Dad came he pushed her out of the room.She had run from the house.The shock wouldn't let her be still.She had run into the dark and hit herself with her fists.And then the next night he was in a coffin in the living-room.The undertaker had put rouge and lipstick on his face to make him look natural.But he didn't look natural.He was very dead.And mixed with the smell of flowers there was this other smell so that she couldn't stay in the room.But through ail those days she held down the job.She wrapped packages and handed them across the counter and rung the money in the till.She walked when she was supposed to walk and ate when she sat down to the table.Only at first when she went to bed at night she couldn't sleep.But now she slept like she was supposed to, also.

Mick turned sideways in the seat so that she could cross her legs. There was a run in her stocking.It had started while she was walking to work and she had spit on it.Then later the run had gone farther and she had stuck a little piece of chewing gum on the end.But even that didn't help.Now she would have to go home and sew.It was hard to know what she could do about stockings.She wore them out so fast Unless she was the kind of common girl that would wear cotton stockings.

She oughtn't to have come in here. The bottoms of her shoes were clean worn out.She ought to have saved the twenty cents toward a new half-sole.Because if she kept on standing on a shoe with a hole in it what would happen?A blister would come on her foot.And she would have to pick it with a burnt needle.She would have to stay home from work and be fired.And then what would happen?

“Here you are，”said Mister Brannon.“But I never heard of such a combination before.”

He put the sundae and the beer on the table. She pretended to clean her fingernails because if she noticed him he would start talking.He didn't have this grudge against her any more, so he must have forgotten about the pack of gum.Now he always wanted to talk to her.But she wanted to be quiet and by herself.The sundae was O.K.，covered all over with chocolate and nuts and cherries.And the beer was relaxing.The beer had a nice bitter taste after the ice cream and it made her drunk.Next to music beer was best.

But now no music was in her mind. That was a funny thing.It was like she was shut out from the inside room.Sometimes a quick little tune would come and go—but she never went into the inside room with music like she used to do.It was like she was too tense.Or maybe because it was like the store took all her energy and time.Woolworth's wasn't the same as school.When she used to come home from school she felt good and was ready to start working on the music.But now she was always tired.At home she just ate supper and slept and then ate breakfast and went off to the store again.A song she had started in her private notebook two months before was still not finished.And she wanted to stay in the inside room but she didn't know how.It was like the inside room was locked somewhere away from her.A very hard thing to understand.

Mick pushed her broken front tooth with her thumb. But she did have Mister Singer's radio.All the installments hadn't been paid and she took on the responsibility.It was good to have something that had belonged to him.And maybe one of these days she might be able to set aside a little for a second-hand piano.Say two bucks a week.And she wouldn't let anybody touch this private piano but her—only she might teach George little pieces.She would keep it in the back room and play on it every night.And all day Sunday.But then suppose some week she couldn't make a payment.So then would they come to take it away like the little red bicycle?And suppose like she wouldn't let them.Suppose she hid the piano under the house.Or else she would meet them at the front door.And fight.She would knock down both the two men so they would have shiners and broke noses and would be passed out on the hall floor.

Mick frowned and rubbed her fist hard across her forehead. That was the way things were.It was like she was mad all the time.Not how a kid gets mad quick so that soon it is all over—but in another way.Only there was nothing to be mad at.Unless the store.But the store hadn't asked her to take the job.So there was nothing to be mad at.It was like she was cheated.Only nobody had cheated her.So there was nobody to take it out on.However, just the same she had that feeling.Cheated.

But maybe it would be true about the piano and turn out O. K.Maybe she would get a chance soon.Else what the hell good had it all been—the way she felt about music and the plans she had made in the inside room?It had to be some good if anything made sense.And it was too and it was too and it was too and it was too.It was some good.

All right！

O. K.！

Some good.

4

Night

All was serene. As Biff dried his face and hands a breeze tinkled the glass pendants of the little Japanese pagoda on the table.He had just awakened from a nap and had smoked his night cigar.He thought of Blount and wondered if by now he had traveled far.A bottle of Agua Florida was on the bathroom shelf and he touched the stopper to his temples.He whistled an old song, and as he descended the narrow stairs the tune left a broken echo behind him.

Louis was supposed to be on duty behind the counter. But he had soldiered on the job and the place was deserted.The front door stood open to the empty street.The clock on the wall pointed to seventeen minutes before midnight.The radio was on and there was talk about the crisis Hitler had cooked up over Danzig.He went back to the kitchen and found Louis asleep in a chair.The boy had taken off his shoes and unbuttoned his trousers.His head drooped on his chest.A long wet spot on his shirt showed that he had been sleeping a good while.His arms hung straight down at his sides and the wonder was that he did not fall forward on his face.He slept soundly and there was no use to wake him.The night would be a quiet one.

Biff tiptoed across the kitchen to a shelf which held a basket of tea olive and two water pitchers full of zinnias. He carried the flowers up to the front of the restaurant and removed the cellophane-wrapped platters of the last special from the display window.He was sick of food.A window of fresh summer flowers—that would be good.His eyes were closed as he imagined how it could be arranged.A foundation of the tea olive strewn over the bottom, cool and green.The red pottery tub filled with the brilliant zinnias.Nothing more.He began to arrange the window carefully.Among the flowers there was a freak plant, a zinnia with six bronze petals and two red.He examined this curio and laid it aside to save.Then the window was finished and he stood in the street to regard his handiwork.The awkward stems of the flowers had been bent to just the right degree of restful looseness.The electric lights detracted, but when the sun rose the display would show at its best advantage.Downright artistic.

The black, starlit sky seemed close to the earth. He strolled along the sidewalk, pausing once to knock an orange peel into the gutter with the side of his foot.At the far end of the next block two men, small from the distance and motionless, stood arm in arm together.No one else could be seen.His place was the only store on all the street with an open door and lights inside.

And why?What was the reason for keeping the place open all through the night when every other café　in the town was closed?He was often asked that question and could never speak the answer out in words.Not money.Sometimes a party would come for beer and scrambled eggs and spend five or ten dollars.But that was rare.Mostly they came one at a time and ordered little and stayed long.And on some nights, between the hours of twelve and five o’clock, not a customer would enter.There was no profit in it—that was plain.

But he would never close up for the night—not as long as he stayed in the business. Night was the time.There were those he would never have seen otherwise.A few came regularly several times a week.Others had come into the place only once, had drunk a Coca-Cola, and never returned.

Biff folded his arms across his chest and walked more slowly. Inside the arc of the street light his shadow showed angular and black.The peaceful silence of the night settled in him.These were the hours for rest and meditation.Maybe that was why he stayed downstairs and did not sleep.With a last quick glance he scanned the empty street and went inside.

The crisis voice still talked on the radio. The fans on the ceiling made a soothing whirl.From the kitchen came the sound of Louis snoring.He thought suddenly of poor Willie and decided to send him a quart of whiskey sometime soon.He turned to the crossword puzzle in the newspaper.There was a picture of a woman to identify in the center.He recognized her and wrote the name—Mona Lisa—across the first spaces.Number one down was a word for beggar, beginning with m and nine letters long.Mendicant.Two horizontal was some word meaning to remove afar off.A six-letter word beginning with e.Elapse?He sounded trial combinations of letters aloud.Eloign.But he had lost interest.There were puzzles enough without this kind.He folded and put away the paper.He would come back to it later.

He examined the zinnia he had intended to save. As he held it in the palm of his hand to the light the flower was not such a curious specimen after all.Not worth saving.He plucked the soft, bright petals and the last one came out on love.But who?Who would he be loving now?No one person.Anybody decent who came in out of the street to sit for an hour and have a drink.But no one person.He had known his loves and they were over.Alice, Madeline and Gyp.Finished.Leaving him either better or worse.Which?However you looked at it.

And Mick. The one who in the last months had lived so strangely in his heart.Was that love done with too?Yes.It was finished.Early in the evenings Mick came in for a cold drink or a sundae.She had grown older.Her rough and childish ways were almost gone.And instead there was something ladylike and delicate about her that was hard to point out.The earrings, the dangle of her bracelets, and the new way she crossed her legs and pulled the hem of her skirt down past her knees.He watched her and felt only a sort of gentleness.In him the old feeling was gone.For a year this love had blossomed strangely.He had questioned it a hundred times and found no answer.And now, as a summer flower shatters in September, it was finished.There was no one.

Biff tapped his nose with his forefinger. A foreign voice was now speaking over the radio.He could not decide for certain whether the voice was German, French, or Spanish.But it sounded like doom.It gave him the jitters to listen to it.When he turned it off the silence was deep and unbroken.He felt the night outside.Loneliness gripped him so that his breath quickened.It was far too late to call Lucile on the telephone and speak to Baby.Nor could he expect a customer to enter at this hour.He went to the door and looked up and down the street.All was empty and dark.

“Louis！”he called.“Are you awake, Louis?”

No answer. He put his elbows on the counter and held his head in his hands.He moved his dark bearded jaw from side to side and slowly his forehead lowered in a frown.

The riddle. The question that had taken root in him and would not let him rest.The puzzle of Singer and the rest of them.More than a year had gone by since it had started.More than a year since Blount had hung around the place on his first long drunk and seen the mute for the first time.Since Mick had begun to follow him in and out.And now for a month Singer had been dead and buried.And the riddle was still in him, so that he could not be tranquil.There was something not natural about it all—something like an ugly joke.When he thought of it he felt uneasy and in some unknown way afraid.

He had managed about the funeral. They had left all that to him.Singer's affairs were in a mess.There were installments due on everything he owned and the beneficiary of his life insurance was deceased.There was just enough to bury him.The funeral was at noon.The sun burned down on them with savage heat as they stood around the open dank grave.The flowers curled and turned brown in the sun.Mick cried so hard that she choked herself and her father had to beat her on the back.Blount scowled down at the grave with his fist to his mouth.The town's Negro doctor, who was somehow related to poor Willie, stood on the edge of the crowd and moaned to himself.And there were strangers nobody had ever seen or heard of before.God knows where they came from or why they were there.

The silence in the room was deep as the night itself. Biff stood transfixed, lost in his meditations.Then suddenly he felt a quickening in him.His heart turned and he leaned his back against the counter for support.For in a swift radiance of illumination he saw a glimpse of human struggle and of valor.Of the endless fluid passage of humanity through endless time.And of those who labor and of those who—one word—love.His soul expanded.But for a moment only.For in him he felt a warning, a shaft of terror.Between the two worlds he was suspended.He saw that he was looking at his own face in the counter glass before him.Sweat glistened on his temples and his face was contorted.One eye was opened wider than the other.The left eye delved narrowly into the past while the right gazed wide and affrighted into a future of blackness, error, and ruin.And he was suspended between radiance and darkness.Between bitter irony and faith.Sharply he turned away.

“Louis！”he called.“Louis！Louis！”

Again there was no answer. But, motherogod, was he a sensible man or was he not?And how could this terror throttle him nice this when he didn't even know what caused it?And would he just stand here like a jittery ninny or would he pull himself together and be reasonable?For after all was he a sensible man or was he not?Biff wet his handkerchief beneath the water tap and patted his drawn, tense face.Somehow he remembered that the awning had not yet been raised.As he went to the door his walk gained steadiness.And when at last he was inside again he composed himself soberly to await the morning sun.

译者序

查尔斯·格兰特·布莱尔芬迪·艾伦（Charles Grant Blairfindie Allen）是加拿大籍作家。他于一八四八年二月二十四日生于加拿大安大略省金斯敦附近的沃尔夫岛，是家中的次子。他的父亲约瑟夫·安提赛尔·艾伦（Joseph Antisell Allen）是一名新教神职人员，母亲夏洛特·凯瑟琳·安·格兰特（Charlotte Catherine Ann Grant）为加拿大魁北克省隆格伊的第五男爵之女。艾伦自幼年时期开始一直在家中接受教育，平日喜欢在沃尔夫岛上探索大自然。他从小便对大自然怀有浓厚兴趣，这对他后来从事自然科学方面的写作大有帮助。

他十三岁时随父母离开沃尔夫岛来到美国，从此再也没有回到故乡。他就读于牛津大学的莫顿学院，于一八六七年获得奖学金，一八七一年夏毕业。他一生结过两次婚，第一任妻子去世后，他又于一八七三年同艾伦·杰拉德（Ellen Jerrard）结婚。此后，艾伦在牙买加西班牙镇的王后学院（Queen’s College）任教。他于一八七六年返回英国，成为一名职业作家，后来因肝癌于一八九九年十月二十五日在英国家中逝世。死后留下了独子杰拉德·格兰特·艾伦（Jerrard Grant Allen）。

艾伦最初的创作兴趣在自然科学领域，著有《生理美学》（PhysiologicalAesthetics）、《色觉：起源与发展》（The Colour-Sense：Its Origin and Development）、《花卉及其系谱》（Flowers and Their Pedigrees）等作品。而他后来之所以放弃科学领域，进而将精力转向《非洲的百万富翁》等文学小说的创作，是因为相较之下，小说创作带来的收入更高。“艾伦只是在发现写科学文章养活不了自己之后，才开始转向小说创作的。”菲利斯·罗森代尔（Phyllis Rozendal）指出。艾伦是那个时代最多产、多才的作家之一，在一八八四至一八九九年间共创作了约三十部长篇小说。其中包括《做过的女人》（The Woman Who Did），讲述的是女主人公未婚生育的故事。书中所宣扬的关于婚姻方面的观点，在相对保守的读者中间引起了一股骚动，也使之成为那个时代的畅销书。艾伦离世后，仍有部分作品先后发表，如《希尔达·韦德》（Hilda Wade）。小说的最后一章由其好友亚瑟·柯南·道尔爵士（Sir Arthur Conan Doyle）——大侦探福尔摩斯的创造者——帮助完成，之后发表在《海滨杂志》（Strand Magazine）上。

格兰特·艾伦一生涉猎广泛。爱德华·克劳德（Edward Clodd）在《格兰特·艾伦回忆录》（Grant Allen：A Memoir）中总结道：“现在几乎没有世人能够从事如此广泛的一系列研究——换句话说，没有谁能同时干这么多行当——并且这些行当五花八门、鲜有关联……他一心扑在求知上，也一心希望能将自己的所知传予他人。”不过，遗憾的是，艾伦大部分的作品如今早已尘封于历史之中，或者仅存在于历史的边缘。尽管如此，在他大量的著述之中，至少有一部传世之作，至今仍为世人称道，这便是他的《非洲的百万富翁》。芝加哥州立大学英语教授、美国通俗文化协会（American Popular Culture Association）前任主席、《大众文化杂志》（The Journal of Popular Culture）编辑盖里·霍彭斯丹德（Gary Hoppenstand）指出，“《非洲的百万富翁》毫无疑问是一本引人入胜、妙趣横生的读物，犯罪小说中众人深爱的经典”，也是艾伦“在文学界唯一一部传世之作”。

《非洲的百万富翁》全书共十二章，最初是作为十二篇前后衔接的短篇故事，先后于一八九六至一八九七年间发表在《海滨杂志》上，随后这些故事又被收集成册，于一八九七年作为精装本小说《非洲的百万富翁》出版发行。许多研究资料都认为格兰特·艾伦为侦探小说开辟了一条新的道路，其原因就在于作者在《非洲的百万富翁》一书中首次将一个流氓无赖作为全书的主角。

整部小说围绕无赖克雷上校（Colonel Cuthbert Clay）以及资本家查尔斯爵士（Sir Charles Vandrift）之间的智斗展开。虽然小说名为“非洲的百万富翁”——百万富翁就是查尔斯爵士——但真正的主角却是克雷上校。本部小说虽为犯罪小说，但处处都渗透着侦探小说的元素。不过，在这部小说中，受害者本人就是侦探，只不过是个失败的侦探，屡试屡败，而案情的揭露则是通过作案者（克雷上校）在事后发来的羞辱信（如《大师名作》《蒂罗尔城堡》《抓捕上校》《镀漆公文箱》《纸牌游戏》等故事）或者当面告白（如《打成平手》），把他是如何一步步实施作案的过程揭露出来的。

克雷上校是一位易容乔装方面的大师，这一点从他的名字中便可以看出。英语中“clay”一词有“泥土”之意，正如警方所说，“之所以称他为克雷上校，是因为他貌似有张橡皮脸，能像制陶工人把玩泥土一样重塑自己的脸型……职业，在巴黎格雷万蜡像馆当过塑像师”，因此也无怪乎他被称为“橡皮脸上校”。他先后乔装成墨西哥先知、小副牧师理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗、凡·莱本斯坦伯爵、大卫·格兰顿、施莱尔马赫教授、侦探梅德赫斯特、伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯医生、诗人阿尔杰农·克雷亚德等身份来骗查尔斯。他每次出现都是一副全新的面孔，令查尔斯防不胜防。查尔斯在经历了几次被骗的事件以后，已经开始疑神疑鬼，草木皆兵，觉得他周围的人都有可能是克雷上校乔装而成。“生活已经成了他的负担。他深信自己已识破克雷上校的成千上万种伪装，他还深信自己把对方吓跑十几次之多，认为对方有时扮成一位肥胖的酒吧侍者、一位高挑的警察、洗衣婆的儿子、律师的书记员、英格兰银行的小吏，还有收水费的，不过那些人都不是克雷上校。就像中世纪的圣徒能随时随地看到恶魔一样，查尔斯也能时时刻刻看到变化多端的上校。”但有意思的是，当查尔斯判定对方不是克雷上校的时候，对方反而就是克雷上校，比如《抓捕上校》的故事。为了捉住克雷上校，查尔斯决定去请一名侦探来暗中监视并保护自己及家人，谁能想到请来的这名侦探，到后来居然竟是克雷上校本人！可是每每当查尔斯判定对方是克雷上校而采取行动的时候，却总会栽个跟头，如《大师名作》《镀漆公文箱》的故事。对于大资本家查尔斯而言，克雷上校已经成了一个无时无处不在的幽灵、一个挥之不去的烦扰。

克雷上校是位高明的骗子，是十九世纪和二十世纪之交的罗宾汉。在《打成平手》一章中，克雷上校向查尔斯宣称道：“你呢，是资本家，是百万富翁。往大里看，你的猎物是整个社会……咱们再往小里看，我又从你掠夺来的财富中分一杯羹。我是这个时代的罗宾汉。”正如故事中的歌谣所唱：“大跳蚤身上寄生着小跳蚤/小跳蚤身上的跳蚤会更小/如此这般，无穷无尽、没完没了。”查尔斯是社会的寄生虫，他通过各种手段榨取社会的财富，而克雷上校则寄生在查尔斯身上。他自始至终一个人对抗着权势：“他只身一人，仅仅凭借一己之力还有两位柔弱的女人，这得需要多大的勇气才能在这场不平等的较量中，这么长时间对抗着财富、权威，还有欧洲所有的政府。”

查尔斯爵士是小说的另一个主要角色，他是英国国会议员，南非克罗地多普·戈尔康达有限公司的董事长，是“钻石大王”，身价百万，代表了资本主义英国的特权阶层。《打成平手》一章曾提到，有一块土地，“不管它以前有没有黄金，现在查尔斯把它弄到手，就凭这一点，它怎么都会出产黄金。这世上还没有谁能像查尔斯那样，有点石成金的真本事：不管什么，一经他手，即使不会变成钻石，也起码是黄金。”查尔斯作为大获成功的资本家，自以为有手段有头脑，能够智胜克雷上校，可现实情况却恰恰相反，他每次都败在了自己的小聪明上，如《钻石链扣》的故事。查尔斯聪明反被聪明误，这一点被克雷上校一语道破：“我对你了如指掌，而你对我却一无所知。”“我承认，你是证券交易所中最精明的，不过也是我在交易所之外碰到过的最容易上当的傻瓜。你错就错在一件事上——自以为聪明。不为别的，就因为这，我才盯着你不放。”

虽然查尔斯坐拥百万财产，但在生意场上却锱铢必较，这一点通过西摩之口幽默地道了出来：“别人总觉得从百万富翁身上榨出点钱，肯定要比从别人身上弄出点钱容易——而事实恰恰相反，要不然他们怎么会攒出自己那份百万家产呢？他们不是像树上渗出树胶那样往外冒金子，而是像吸墨纸那样把金子吸得一干二净，却几乎再也不吐出来。”查尔斯有着资本家的贪婪，为了金钱不择手段。他曾使用下流的手段，试图从一位穷牧师手中骗走价值不菲的钻石（《钻石链扣》）；心怀歹意地贿赂克雷盖拉奇勋爵的儿子，让他出卖自己的父亲，企图把他的矿产骗到自己手中（《打成平手》）；还用了见不得人的手段牺牲那些孤儿寡母的利益，来挽回自己的财富（《德国教授》）。因此，不管是在法官眼里还是在上校眼中，查尔斯都是无赖。克雷上校曾感叹道：“查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，咱俩是一丘之貉。唯一的区别在于，你受法律的保护，而我却受其迫害。”“我们俩都不是什么好东西……罪行轻的竟然站到了被告席，而罪行重的却站到了证人席。要说赏罚分明，咱们国家可真是煞费苦心——给他的是圣米迦勒及圣乔治大十字勋章，给我的却是囚衣。”从这里，我们也许看到了作者对当时资本主义制度的不满。

西摩·温特沃斯是查尔斯的妹夫，在查尔斯发迹之前娶了查尔斯之妹为妻。他也是查尔斯的私人秘书兼本书故事的讲述者，同查尔斯形影不离。查尔斯与西摩之间这一“英雄—助手”关系，在柯南·道尔笔下的夏洛克·福尔摩斯的探案故事中变得广为人知，后来也为其他作家所借鉴。二者既有相承也有相异之处。相承之处在于，无论是在福尔摩斯系列故事中，还是在本书故事中，作者均希望能够通过“英雄—助手”这一关系的设计来推动故事发展，揭露人物的内心活动。不过，福尔摩斯故事中的“英雄”与“助手”展现在读者面前的是一对正面的形象，福尔摩斯与华生这二人的行动目标总体一致。而在格兰特·艾伦的笔下，西摩和查尔斯则是一对反面的形象，二人之间除了“英雄—助手”关系外，还多了一层亲属关系及雇佣关系。西摩虽然表面上对查尔斯言听计从，但暗地里会有些自己的想法，谈不上什么忠诚。他曾说道：“作为员工，总得摆出一副对雇主的事情很上心的样子。”（《塞尔登金矿》）查尔斯则经常斥责甚至威胁西摩。在《德国教授》故事中，当查尔斯意识到自己的股票马上要跌得一文不值时，他便偷偷地将自己的股票全部清仓，但对外却冠冕堂皇地声称自己不能抛售，而对西摩却威胁道：“我还是要事先警告你：如果你把手中的股票都变卖了，不管是公开地还是偷偷摸摸地卖，你就再也不是我秘书了，我会给你六个月的薪水作为代通知金，让你马上卷铺盖走人。”在《蒂罗尔城堡》故事中，西摩为了能赚些回扣，还背着查尔斯主动接触城堡的主人，二人勾结将售价抬高。这件事当然也成了上校后来掌控他的一个把柄。另外，还值得一提的是，西摩是一位出色的讲述者，他以一种幽默风趣的方式将细节展现给读者，将人物的内心世界刻画得入木三分。

艾米莉亚作为查尔斯的妻子，也是艾伦批判的对象。她虚荣、执拗、附庸风雅，一心向上攀附。当看到了小牧师的两颗大钻石时，便一心想把它们弄到手，为的是“把她那相当丰满的脖子围上一圈”（《钻石链扣》）。她“一心痴迷于伦敦的各种享乐”，“这个世界上，除了伦敦，她一向哪儿都不喜欢……她是个不折不扣的伦敦佬”。艾米莉亚每周都要举行“家庭招待会”，邀请一些她想急于攀附的上流人物。后来她意识到自己的社交“不应当看起来仅仅局限于一些金融界和政界人物”，有议员还有百万富翁们作为后盾，“她现在转而钟爱文学、艺术以及音乐酒杯这股清雅的暗流”，但实际情况是，当真正有人同她谈论艺术时，她却“很反感，但又觉得作为查尔斯的妻子，偶尔假装有个高雅的兴趣爱好，是她义不容辞的责任”。

艾米莉亚与查尔斯二人虽为夫妻，但作者却向我们暗示了两人之间那种虚伪的情感。在《打成平手》故事中，查尔斯还有西摩被克雷上校搁置到了海岛之上，半夜未归。故事中提到艾米莉亚非常担心查尔斯的安全，但她却早已上床睡着了；与之相对照的是，西摩的妻子伊莎贝尔仍在那儿坐着，守到了半夜，等待丈夫的消息。本书的最后一章中，艾米莉亚把西摩叫到自己房间，声称不愿意指控自己的女仆西塞琳，还威胁道：“西摩，我告诉你，这事门儿都没有。女士的日常生活中有一些琐事——只有她的女仆知道——绝不可以公之于众。”艾米莉亚到底想隐藏些什么秘密？我们无从得知。不过，有意思的是，这段对话就发生在查尔斯爵士对西摩做了类似的叮嘱以后。查尔斯叮嘱西摩，说自己坚决不同意逮捕“白石南花”，因为他不愿将自己对她的爱慕在法庭上公开。《墨西哥先知》故事中提到查尔斯的兜里装了一封同皮卡迪特夫人的秘密信件，后来西摩指出：“实际上，说句实话，不论‘白石南花’以何种乔装出现，查尔斯总会第一眼就拜倒在她的石榴裙下。因此，我觉得，那精明的小妇人——你想怎么称呼都行——很可能手里攥着不止一封查尔斯写给她的秘密信件。”是不是查尔斯及艾米莉亚都有些婚外风流韵事，这就全凭读者自己评判了。

与查尔斯夫妇二人之间的关系形成鲜明对比的，是克雷上校、皮卡迪特夫人以及西塞琳这三人之间的关系。

西塞琳及皮卡迪特夫人（姑且这么称呼她，因为她先后用了不同的化名）这二人是克雷上校的共犯，二者也都是上校的妻子。故事的一开始就揭示了皮卡迪特夫人与克雷上校之间的关系，而西塞琳与上校之间的关系，直到故事的结尾才真相大白。表面上看，一直是克雷上校与皮卡迪特夫人二者联合起来欺骗查尔斯，但实际上，他们一直都离不开西塞琳这个内应的帮助。虽然艾伦没有正面对这三者之间的关系加以评价，但我们从字里行间不难发现他们彼此间的忠诚。克雷上校在《纸牌游戏》故事中曾说道：“即便最无耻的无赖，内心也总会有好的一面。我发现，他们常常能一直让女性爱自己，并且对自己忠诚。”当克雷上校被抓时，西塞琳扑向他，说道：“我不会牺牲你来保全自己。要是他们让你坐牢——保罗，保罗，我就同你一起坐牢！”当看到上校被带走时，“西塞琳已经在大门台阶上快晕过去了”。审判结果宣布时，皮卡迪特夫人及西塞琳“突然放声大哭，不省人事地倒在彼此的肩上，传达员费了好大劲儿才将二人扶出庭外”。事后的某一天，查尔斯及西摩等人发现皮卡迪特夫人及西塞琳身着重孝，当问及为谁戴孝时，西塞琳答道：“为了保罗！为了我们的王！就是你监禁起来的那个人！他一日不被释放，我们俩就一日为他戴孝！”小说的结尾处，查尔斯说：“我在想，要是我坐牢了，艾米莉亚和伊莎贝尔是否也会为我这么做？”而西摩内心应道：“就我而言，根本不用考虑，我心里十分清楚。对于查尔斯，我敢说，虽然他是两个无赖中更有权势的那个，却不是能让女性为之死心塌地的那个。”

虽然克雷上校精明狡猾，多数情况下能够一次次顺利地实施自己的计划，但本书作者还是让步于读者的期望，使得克雷上校最终被绳之以法。需要指出的是，将克雷上校抓住的，不是别的，正是科学。查尔斯虽然精明，却一次次败于克雷上校之手，最后只得求助于科学，请来了贝蒂荣识别法的专家弗兰克·贝德斯莱博士。克雷上校被抓以后，他对着博士感叹道：“要是你按照贝蒂荣识别法，一步步地找到了我，我倒不怎么介意。我愿屈身于科学，但不愿意屈身于蠢材。我觉得，这位钻石大王可没长那么多脑子，能想到求助于你。他是我这辈子碰到过的最好骗的老浑蛋。不过，要是你把我追捕到了，我只能认了。”艾伦对于科学的推崇可见一斑。

在小说的最后一章，克雷上校接受了审判。这在名义上是对克雷上校的审判，实际上是对查尔斯这个大资本家的种种劣行的责问。“查尔斯在律师的陪同下，早早地到场了。他面色苍白，愁眉不展，看起来更像是被告，而非原告。”“他（查尔斯）站在证人席中时，所有人都觉得他是被告，而克雷上校则是原告。”

文学翻译家杨苡在回顾自己的翻译经历时曾总结道：“回顾四十年翻译生涯，犹如吞下一枚酸果，它已经被我吞下了，我不知道它是甜中带酸，还是酸中有甜，也许它根本就是苦涩的。”文学翻译本身就是件辛苦的事，译文也总会有进一步提升的空间。这部小说从着手翻译到定稿经历了两年多的时间，前后多次修改，其中的酸甜滋味也许只有译者自己最为清楚。本书作为一部通俗犯罪小说，提供给读者的不仅仅是简单的消遣娱乐，字里行间还流露着对资本主义的幽默讽刺。假如读者能够被本书中的故事吸引，能够对故事背后的弦外之意领略一二，那么我也就觉得这所有的付出都是值得的。鉴于本人能力有限，译文之中难免会有疏漏之处，还请广大读者批评指正。

徐洋

二〇一八年三月二十七日

第二章　钻石链扣

“咱们去瑞士旅行吧。”凡德里夫特夫人提议。于是，我们果真去瑞士旅行了。对于了解艾米莉亚的人来说，这没什么值得大惊小怪的。这世上除了艾米莉亚，没有谁能说服查尔斯爵士，至于艾米莉亚，谁也说服不了她。

我们一开始就遇到了些麻烦，因为我们没有提前在酒店订好房间，刚好又是旅游旺季。不过，这些问题在一贯的贿赂面前最终迎刃而解，我们如期舒舒服服地住进了位于卢塞恩的施维泽霍夫大酒店，这是全欧洲最舒适的酒店。

我们一行四人，两男两女——查尔斯爵士和艾米莉亚，我和伊莎贝尔。房间很大，很漂亮，在二楼，俯瞰着湖泊。那种旅行初期的狂热劲儿，主要是不顾一切地想去爬陡得要命，还到处是雪的大山，还好我们中间谁都丝毫没有这种念头，因此我可以大胆而肯定地讲，我们都玩儿得很开心。我们比较明智，大部分时间都坐在小蒸汽船上，在湖面上惬意地漂荡着；也爬过一次山，记不清是瑞吉山还是皮拉图斯山——不过，我们是坐车上去的。

同平时一样，在酒店，大量各色人等都对我们热情似火，极为殷勤。要是你想看看人性中友善和迷人的一面，就试着当一个星期的众所周知的百万富翁吧，这样你就能略为体验一二。不管查尔斯爵士走到哪儿，总会被一群讨人喜爱、大公无私的人围着。这些人都急切地想结识他，他们要么都熟知几个不错的投资项目，要么就是知道几个需要基督教慈善事业救助的对象。我作为查尔斯的妹夫兼秘书，有责任去婉言谢绝那些不错的投资项目，还得巧妙地给那些需要救济的泼些冷水。甚至连我自己，做了这位大人物的施赈人员，也常常被这些人穷追不舍。他们常常不经意间在我面前讲起些朴实的故事，“温特沃斯先生，你也了解，坎伯兰郡的那些穷牧师”，或者是康沃尔郡的寡妇，再或者是面对书桌上的史诗却身无分文的诗人，再者就是一些年轻的画家，只需有位赞助人金口一开，便能帮他们打开心仪的学院之门。我一边面带微笑，摆出一副已经知晓的神情，一边给他们泼了少许冷水。这些我都没给查尔斯说，除非有些罕见或者从未听说过的情况，并且觉得其中确实另有隐情。

查尔斯爵士天生谨慎，自打在尼斯经历了先知那件小事后，他变得比平时更为小心，以提防那些可能出现的骗子。这时，我们在施维泽霍夫酒店吃客饭（艾米莉亚突发奇想，要在施维泽霍夫酒店吃客饭，说是受不了和“那么多家人”天天待在私人房间里），刚好对面就坐着这么一位，看起来不像是什么好人，黑头发，黑眼睛，一副浓眉十分惹眼。我之所以开始注意到那眉毛，是因为我们旁边坐着一位和善的小副牧师，他发现那人的眉毛又粗又硬，还说达尔文认为这遗传自我们那些猴子祖先。这位年轻的小副牧师面目清秀，十分开朗活泼，正和他漂亮的小娇妻在蜜月旅行，她是位苏格兰姑娘，说起话来有些口音，十分悦耳。

我仔细地端详着那眉毛，接着突然冒出一个念头。“你觉得那眉毛是天生的吗？”我问那小副牧师，“是不是粘上去的——只是某种伪装？看起来可真像。”

“莫非你觉得——”查尔斯张口道，突然又止住。

“对，我觉得是，”我答道，“那位先知。”接着，我意识到自己犯了大错，不好意思地低下了头。因为，说实话，查尔斯老早就直接嘱咐过我，关于在尼斯的那段痛苦的小插曲，不要在艾米莉亚面前提到任何字眼。怕她一旦听说此事，就会天天把这事挂在嘴边。

“什么先知？”小副牧师带着出于自己职业的那种好奇心问道。

我注意到那位浓眉男子一惊，有些可疑。查尔斯的目光紧紧地盯着我，我不知该如何回答。

“哦，是去年同我们一起待在尼斯的一个人，”我结结巴巴地说，尽量看上去一副若无其事的样子，“是当地人谈论的一个家伙，就是这样。”接着，我便转移了话题。

但那个小副牧师蠢得像头驴，不愿让我转换话题。

“他就是那种眉毛吗？”他低声问道。我真的很生气，要是那人真的是克雷上校，这位小副牧师很明显给了他个暗示。现在，我们也许已经暴露出要抓他的信号了，这样一来，要抓他就更难了。

“不是的，”我不耐烦地答道，“我只是随便说说，这个人不是他，我认错人了，认错了。”我用胳膊肘轻轻推了他一下。

小副牧师信以为真。“哦，我明白了。”他答道，自作聪明地使劲点头。接着，他转向妻子，做了个明显的鬼脸，那个浓眉的家伙肯定注意到了。

还好，饭桌隔着几个座位之外的地方，有人正谈论着政治，声音传过来，暂时转移了我们的注意力，格莱斯顿[7]这个神奇的名字解救了我们。查尔斯勃然大怒，我却满心欢喜，因为我看到艾米莉亚此时已经控制不住自己的好奇心了。

饭后，在台球室里，那位浓眉男子从一边凑过来，跟我搭话。如果他就是克雷上校的话，那么很明显，他对上次从我们这骗走五千英镑并不在意。他还准备伺机再骗我们五千。这一次，他立刻说自己是赫克托·麦克弗森博士，从巴西政府手中获得一大块广袤土地的开采权，就在亚马孙河的上游，他是唯一的受让人。他立刻开门见山地同我谈到了他在巴西地产里那丰富的矿产资源——白银、铂金，已经发现的红宝石，还有那些可能会发现的钻石。我边听边微笑，知道他接下来要说些什么。要开发这片价值连城的土地，他只需要再投入一点资金。就因为缺少几百英镑加以适当地开发，那些价值成千上万英镑的铂金，还有一车车的红宝石，只能碎在土地中或被河水冲走，想一想都难受。要是知道目前谁有钱投资，他就会推荐——不对，是双手奉上一个赚钱的机会，回报率百分之四十，而且绝对安全。

“不是所有人都可以来做，”赫克托·麦克弗森博士把身子凑过来说道，“不过，要是我看中了哪位手上有现金的主，我就会让他的钱袋子迅速地鼓起来，那速度绝无仅有。”

“你可真够大公无私的。”我讽刺道，眼睛盯着他的眉毛。

此时，小副牧师正在同查尔斯爵士打台球。他目光随着我，也看了一会儿那猴毛似的眉毛。

“假的，很明显是假的。”他用嘴型示意道。说实话，我从没见过谁能只靠口型就把话说得这么好，虽然没出声，但你能知道他说的每一个字。

那天晚上余下的时间，赫克托·麦克弗森博士一直像芥末膏药一样贴着我，都快让人恼火了。听到亚马孙河上游这个字眼，我就打心底厌烦。我早已在红宝石矿山中（我的意思是，在矿山的售股章程中）劳神费时太久，到后来，一看到红宝石就反感至极。有一次，查尔斯爵士一反常态，慷慨地送了他妹妹伊莎贝尔（我有幸娶之为妻）一条红宝石项链（次品），我让伊莎贝尔换成了蓝宝石和紫水晶的，理由很明智：后者同她的肤色更般配（顺便提一句，因为考虑到了伊莎贝尔的肤色，我这次把她说服了）。到睡觉的时候，我早就想好了，准备将亚马孙河上游这个地方沉到海底，再把那位手握土地开采权、贴着假眉毛的男子用刀刺，用枪打，用药毒，再或者，把他折磨得体无完肤。

在接下来的三天里，他仍时不时地过来缠我。他说的那些铂金和红宝石把我烦得要死。他不愿意让哪位有钱的主儿单独开发这些宝藏，而是希望能够让自己独自来做，然后给投资人一些自己胡编乱造出来的公司的优惠债券，外加土地开采权抵押产生的利息。一开始，我边听边微笑，然后打哈欠，之后有点暴躁，最后根本不去听了，但他还在那儿叨叨个没完。有一天，我在蒸汽船上睡着了，十分钟后醒来，听到他还在絮叨：“经认证，每吨里面铂金的产量是——”我记不得是几磅，还是几盎司，还是几本尼威特[8]了。化验分析的这些细节，再也激不起我的兴趣：就像“不相信有鬼”的人，这一套我见得太多了。

然而面目清秀的小副牧师，还有他妻子，则完全是另外一种类型。他是牛津人，打板球；而她是位活泼的苏格兰姑娘，散发着苏格兰高地那蓬勃的气息。我叫她“白石南花”。他们姓布拉巴宗。由于百万富翁们习惯了形形色色贪得无厌的人的纠缠，因而，当碰到一对心地单纯的年轻夫妇时，他们会对这纯粹的人际关系感到欢喜。我们多次同这对度蜜月的年轻人一起野餐，在周围游玩。他们对彼此的爱慕毫不掩饰，也不怕别人打趣他们，我们都非常喜欢他们俩。不过，每当我称那位漂亮的小姑娘“白石南花”时，她总是看起来很震惊，然后叫道：“啊！温特沃斯先生！”不过，我们仍是关系最好的朋友。一天，在湖上，小副牧师主动要为我们划船，而这时，那位苏格兰姑娘则向我们保证，她能和他划得一样稳。不过，我们没有接受他们的好意，因为划船对艾米莉亚的消化系统不太好。

“那个姓布拉巴宗的，是个不错的小伙子，”一天，我和查尔斯爵士沿着码头散步时，他对我说，“绝口不提什么受俸牧师推荐权，也不提以后的圣职推荐。他好像根本不在乎什么晋升提拔。他说，他对于自己副牧师这一职位十分满意，薪俸足够家用，再也别无他求；他妻子有一点点，非常少的一点点积蓄。我问了问他教区里的穷人怎么样，想故意试探他一下：这些牧师总是绞尽脑汁，想为教区里的穷人骗点什么。有人说，穷人总是无处不在，处在我这种位置的人深知此话不假。说出来你也许不会相信，他说他的教区里没有穷人，都是些富足的农民，还有些身强力健的劳工，他唯一害怕的是哪天来个人，想试着把他们变穷。‘要是哪位做慈善的今天给我五十英镑，让我在艾宾汉姆花掉，’他说，‘查尔斯先生，我敢保证，我都不知道该怎么花。我觉得，该给杰西买些新衣服，但她的情况和村里其他人差不多——也就是说，根本不需要。’西，老弟，这牧师正是你所欣赏的类型。多希望我们在塞尔登也能有一位他这样的牧师。”

“他绝对没打算从你身上算计点什么。”我答道。

那天晚上吃晚饭时，发生了一个奇怪的小插曲。那名浓眉的男子，像往常一样开始隔着桌子对着我说话，张口闭口全是亚马孙河上游那块让人厌烦的土地的开采权。我打算尽可能委婉地让他闭嘴，这时我注意到了艾米莉亚的眼睛。她的表情引起了我的兴趣。她示意自己身旁的查尔斯，让他去观察小副牧师那不同寻常的袖口链扣。我扫了一眼，立即意识到，这么一个不起眼的人物有这么一对链扣，是有点奇怪。每条链扣都有一短片金条，通过一条小金链连着钻石。以我相当丰富的经验来看——那是一颗最上等的钻石。钻石相当大，外形、光泽、切割也都堪称精品。我立刻明白了艾米莉亚的意思。她有一条钻石项链，据说来自印度，不过还差两颗钻石，才能把她那相当丰满的脖子围上一圈。她早就打算再要两颗同样的钻石，同自己的项链配成一套，但她的钻石形状奇特，切割样式过时，所以一直没能配成她心仪的项链。要做成这条项链，最起码得有一块相当大的极品钻石，从上面切割掉相当一部分。

那位苏格兰姑娘此刻也注意到了艾米莉亚的目光，突然绽放出了愉快、甜美的微笑。“迪克，亲爱的，又俘获了一个人，”她转向丈夫，欢快地大声说道，“凡德里夫特夫人正盯着你的钻石链扣呢！”

“钻石相当不错。”艾米莉亚没多想便脱口而出。（要是她打算买的话，刚说出的这话就不太明智了。）

不过和蔼的小副牧师心地太单纯，没有顺着她脱口而出的话往下说。“的确很不错，”他答道，“就各方面而言，都相当不错。但实话告诉你，它们根本不是什么钻石，只不过是上等的东方老式铅玻璃。在塞林伽巴丹之围后，我曾祖父花了几个卢比从一个印度兵手里买来的，而那印度兵则是从提普苏丹的王宫里掳掠来的。他和你一样，觉得自己得了个宝，但事实是，经过专家的检测，它们只不过是铅玻璃做的——极好的铅玻璃。据说都瞒过了提普本人，因为仿制得太像了。但它们也就值——嗯，大概最多五十先令。”

就在他说话的当儿，查尔斯盯着艾米莉亚，艾米莉亚也望着查尔斯。他们四目相对，目光中来回传递着大量讯息。她的项链据说也曾经是提普的藏物。两人立刻得出了一致的结论：这两颗钻石和艾米莉亚的是一样的，很有可能在占领印度王宫的打斗中被扯断了，所以就此同其他部分失散开来。

“你能把它们取下来吗？”查尔斯爵士平静地问道。他说话的语气中流露出一些买卖的意味。

“当然可以，”小副牧师笑着，答道，“把它们取下来，我也习惯了。它们总会引起别人的注意。自从那次围攻之后，它们就一直放在家中，算是件无价的传家宝。原因嘛，你也知道，就是那背后的传奇故事。别人和你一样，谁见了都要仔细地检验一下。一开始，甚至把专家都瞒过了。不过，虽然这样，但它们就是铅玻璃，彻头彻尾的东方铅玻璃。”

小副牧师把两个链扣都取了下来，递给查尔斯。说到鉴别珠宝，全英国没有谁能比得上我内兄。我眯着眼睛看着他，他仔细地检查着链扣，先是用肉眼看，接着又用他口袋里随身携带的放大镜看。“相当不错的赝品，”他咕哝道，将其递给艾米莉亚，“怪不得它们能瞒过一些没经验的人。”

不过，从他说这话的语气来看，我立刻明白，他十分高兴，因为这是真正的价值不菲的珠宝。查尔斯做买卖的方式，我再清楚不过了。他递给艾米莉亚的眼神仿佛在说：“这正是你长久以来苦苦寻求的钻石。”

那位苏格兰姑娘欢快地笑了出来。“迪克，他看出来了，”她大声嚷道，“我敢保证，查尔斯爵士肯定是位鉴定钻石的专家。”

艾米莉亚将链扣翻来覆去地把玩。我也了解艾米莉亚，从她看链扣的眼神中可以看出，她打算把它们弄到手。要是艾米莉亚打算把什么东西弄到手，那些想阻止她的人最好还是省省心，不要白费功夫了。

那两颗钻石很漂亮。后来我们才发现，小副牧师的话说得不错：它们同艾米莉亚的宝石项链确实都来自同一条项链，那条为提普的爱妃打造的项链。她大概也同我那位亲爱的舅嫂一样，有着同样奢华的个人饰品。再也没有见过比这更完美的钻石了。不论是盗贼，还是鉴赏家，都对之赞叹不已。事后，艾米莉亚告诉我，传说一位印度兵在洗劫王宫时偷走了那条项链，后来为了争这条项链，又同另一位印度兵大打出手。据说两人在扭打中丢了两颗钻石，却被一名旁观的第三者捡到卖掉了，那人根本不了解他自己所捡到的物品的价值。艾米莉亚几年来一直在寻找它们，想配成一条完整的项链。

“这是些极好的铅玻璃，”查尔斯一边把链扣还回去，一边评论道，“只有一流的行家才能将它与真品鉴别开来。凡德里夫特夫人也有一条质地大致相同的项链，不过她的是真钻石。既然它们这么相仿，从外表上看，也刚好能配成她的项链，那我出十英镑买你这一对，也就不计较了。”

布拉巴宗夫人看起来挺高兴。“哎，迪克，卖给他们，”她大声说，“再用这钱给我买枚胸针！你戴一对普通的链扣也一样。两块铅玻璃能卖十英镑，这钱已经相当多了！”

她说话的声音很甜美，带着悦耳的苏格兰口音，我无法想象迪克怎能狠下心拒绝她。但不管怎样，他就是这么做了。

“不行，杰西，亲爱的，”他答道，“我知道它们不值什么钱，但对我来讲，它们却有着一种情感价值，我也经常这么给你说。我那亲爱的母亲在世的时候，把它们当耳环戴；她一去世，我就把它们做成了链扣，这样就能时时刻刻把它们带在身边。不仅这样，它们还牵扯一些历史以及家族因素于其中。传家宝，哪怕一分不值，也终究是传家宝。”

赫克托·麦克弗森博士朝这边看过来，打断了我们：“我那片土地上有一块地方，我们有理由相信能开发出另一个完美的金伯利[9]。查尔斯爵士，要是我的钻石发掘出来，不论什么时候您愿意赏光想看一眼，我都会将它们交到您手中，这会是我此生莫大的荣幸。”

查尔斯再也受不了了。“先生，”查尔斯用最严厉的目光盯着他，说道，“要是你的土地里真的满是钻石，就像水手辛巴达的山谷那样[10]，我是不会不去看的。这种挂羊头卖狗肉、言过其实的事情，我见得多了。”他盯着那位浓眉男子，像是要把他活吃了一样。可怜的赫克托·麦克弗森博士立刻闭了嘴。我们稍后才知道，他精神有问题，但并没什么恶意。他满世界到处跑，如影随形的还有他那一块块满是红宝石矿山、铂金矿脉的土地。因为他之前被这些项目的投机活动搞得家破人亡，自己也疯了，现在成天臆想着从缅甸、巴西或者脑袋里随时蹦出来的某个地方的政府手中获得的土地，借此聊以自慰。对了，还有他那眉毛，是天生的。发生这件事，我们非常抱歉。不过，处于查尔斯这种地位的人，就是无赖们的目标，要是不及时采取些手段保护自己，就会一直被他们骗来骗去。

我们当天晚上回到客厅，艾米莉亚就一屁股坐在沙发上。“查尔斯，”她突然爆发了，一副如同悲剧女演员的腔调，“那可是真钻石，要是不把它们弄到手，我是永远不会开心的。”

“确实是真钻石，”查尔斯应道，“艾米莉亚，你会弄到手的。那钻石至少值三千英镑，不过我要慢慢地把价格加上去。”

于是，第二天，查尔斯开始同那位小副牧师讨价还价，但布拉巴宗不愿卖掉它们。他说自己不是个贪财的人，即使查尔斯出价一百英镑，他还是不愿舍弃母亲遗留给他的这份礼物，这份家族的传承。查尔斯眼睛一亮，试探地说道：“我出两百英镑呢？多好的机会！这样，你就能给村子的校舍再盖上一个新的侧厅了！”

“我们的校舍足够了，”副牧师答道，“算了，我是不会卖的。”

不过，他说话的声音有些支吾，接着低头犹疑不定地盯着那链扣。

查尔斯有些过于急躁。

“多一百英镑少一百英镑，对我而言没什么区别，”他说，“我妻子铁了心要得到它们。哄妻子开心，是每个男人的责任——我说的对不对，布拉巴宗夫人？——我出三百英镑。”

那位苏格兰小姑娘紧扣着双手。

“三百英镑！迪克，想想咱们能做多少开心的事啊，想想咱们能用它做多少好事啊！卖给他吧！”

她那语气让人难以拒绝，但小副牧师还是摇摇头。

“不行，”他答道，“这是我母亲的耳环！要是知道我把它们卖了，奥布里舅舅会大发雷霆的。我还怎么敢去见他？”

“他会从奥布里舅舅那里继承一笔财产吗，”查尔斯爵士问，“白石南花？”

布拉巴宗夫人笑道：“奥布里舅舅！哎，亲爱的，别想了。可怜的老奥布里舅舅！哎，他那位亲爱的老舅舅，除了养老金外，一个子儿都给他留不下。他以前是上校舰长，退休了。”她笑道，声音很悦耳，很招人喜爱。

“这么说，我就不用考虑奥布里舅舅的感受了。”查尔斯爵士果断地说。

“不行，不行，”副牧师答道，“可怜的老奥布里舅舅！不管怎样，我是不会惹他生气的。他肯定迟早会发现的。”

我们回去见艾米莉亚。“有没有买到手？”她问道。

“还没有，”查尔斯爵士回答道，“不过，我觉得他就快要卖了。现在他正犹豫不决，自己倒是想卖，就是担心那位叫‘奥布里’的舅舅会说三道四。他妻子会劝劝他，让他不必去考虑奥布里舅舅的感受。明天咱们就能把这笔生意敲定了。”

第二天早上，我们在客厅待到很晚，通常在那儿吃早饭。直到快到早饭的时间，我们才下楼到大厅，因为我和查尔斯一起忙着处理大量待办的信件。我们下楼时，门房走上前来，递给艾米莉亚一张女性用的短笺，小小的，折了起来。她接过来，看了看，脸沉了下来。“这下好了，查尔斯，”她把短笺递给他，大声吼道，“你让机会溜掉了。我再也开心不起来了！他们带着钻石离开了。”

查尔斯一把抓过短笺，看了看，接着递给了我。内容很短，但已无可挽回：

星期四，早上六点

亲爱的凡德里夫特夫人：

未及说声再见，我们就匆匆而别，请勿见怪。刚刚电报传来噩耗，迪克心爱的妹妹在巴黎身患热病，病情严重。我本想与您握手道别——您对我们一向很友善——但无奈得乘坐早班列车出发，早得有些荒唐，因此不愿搅扰您。也许我们有朝一日会再次相逢——不过这已不大可能，因为我们深居于北方村落。无论如何，我将永远珍惜这段记忆，并心怀感激。

您亲爱的，

杰西·布拉巴宗

附——代我向查尔斯以及亲爱的温特沃斯夫妇问好。吻你，恕我冒昧。

“她连去了哪里都没说。”艾米莉亚叫道，很生气。

“也许门房知道。”伊莎贝尔一边从我身后探过头来看，一边提醒道。

我们于是到门房打听。

找到了，他的地址是诺森伯兰郡，艾宾汉姆村，霍姆布什村舍，理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗牧师。

在巴黎有没有地址可以立即写信寄过去？

歌剧院大街，德蒙大酒店。接下来的十天会用这个地址，如有变更，会另行通知。

艾米莉亚立刻拿定了主意。

“要趁热打铁，”她叫道，“在他们快度完蜜月时，这突如其来的疾病，再加上在这么昂贵的酒店多待上十天，很可能让小副牧师经济上感到捉襟见肘。现在他肯定乐于出手了，花三百英镑就能买到。查尔斯真蠢，一开始不应该出那么高的价的。不过既然出了这个价，当然就得坚持这个价。”

“你觉得该怎么办？”查尔斯问道，“写信还是发电报？”

“唉，男人们真糊涂！”艾米莉亚大声吼道，“这种事是写信能解决得了的吗？还发什么电报！不行，西摩必须立即动身，坐夜间的火车去巴黎，一下车就和那位副牧师或者布拉巴宗夫人碰面商量此事。最好和布拉巴宗夫人商量。她不会傻乎乎地谈什么感情，跟你说什么奥布里舅舅的一些废话。”

做钻石掮客并不是秘书的职责。不过，一旦艾米莉亚下定了决心，就是铁了心了——关于这一点，她不愿重申。于是，当天晚上，我就老老实实坐上火车赶往巴黎，第二天一早在斯特拉斯堡站下了那舒适的卧铺车。我的任务就是要千方百计把那两颗钻石装进口袋，带回卢塞恩。价格要多少，就给多少，但最多不超过两千五百英镑，要立即买到手。

到了德蒙大酒店，我看到可怜的小副牧师夫妇俩都十分坐立不安。他们说他俩整夜坐着，陪着那位生病的妹妹，坐了长时间的火车，接着又是失眠，又是担心，影响了身体。两人都面色苍白，十分疲惫，尤其是布拉巴宗夫人，看起来像是病了，满面愁容——太像白石南花了。这种时候，要是再拿钻石的事情搅扰他们，我感到非常难为情。不过我突然意识到，也许艾米莉亚说得对——他们目前应该把去大陆旅行的预算也花得差不多了，或许正盼望能立刻得到点现金。

我小心地引向了正题。我说，凡德里夫特夫人一时性起，一心想要这些没用的小玩意儿，没有它们不行，她必须要把它们买到手。但副牧师很执拗，还是拿奥布里舅舅说事。三百？——不行，肯定不行！这是母亲的礼物，不可能的事情，亲爱的杰西！杰西又是祈求又是祷告，说自己特别喜欢凡德里夫特夫人，但副牧师压根不听。我试探着把价格出到四百，他还是忧郁地摇摇头，说不是钱多钱少的问题，是情感。看到此路不通，我就另辟一条新径。“我觉得有必要告诉你们，”我说，“这两颗钻石是真的，这一点查尔斯爵士敢确定。像你这种职业、这种身份的人戴着一对这么大的钻石，价值几百英镑，只把它当成普通链扣来戴，你觉得合适吗？如果是女人戴呢？——我说合适。但对于男人来说，像个男人吗？再说，你还是个打板球的！”

他看着我，笑了出来。“说什么你能信呢？”他大声说道，“有六位珠宝商都检验过了，我们都知道这只是铅玻璃。不管我多想卖，但不能用欺骗的手段把它们卖给你，这是不义之举。我不能这么做。”

“这样吧，”我说，把价位稍稍抬了一下，让他满意，“咱们这么说：这些珠宝确实是铅玻璃做的，但凡德里夫特夫人不知什么原因，就是一心想得到它们。钱对她而言没什么大不了，况且她还是你妻子的朋友。就算私下里帮个忙，愿不愿意一千英镑卖给她呢？”

他摇摇头，说：“这是不义之举，还有可能是违法行为。”

“我们这边来承担一切风险。”我大声说。

他太固执，答道：“我是神职人员，我觉得不能做这种事。”

“布拉巴宗夫人，你能不能劝劝他？”我问道。

漂亮的苏格兰小姑娘弯下身子，在他耳边低声劝说，又是哄又是骗，她这一套还挺奏效。我听不清她说了什么，不过他最终好像让步了。“我愿意把它们卖给凡德里夫特夫人，”她转向我，低声说道，“她太招人喜欢了！”接着把链扣从她丈夫的袖口上取下，递过来给我。

“多少钱？”我问。

“两千？”她试探着答道。价格一下涨得太多，但这毕竟是女人做事的风格。

“成交！”我答道，“你同意吗？”

副牧师抬起头，显得有点难为情。

“既然杰西想这样，”他缓缓说道，“我也同意。但是作为一名神职人员，为了避免以后的任何误会，我得让你给我写一份声明，上面注明你购买时，我已经明确告知你，它们是由铅玻璃做的——古老的东方铅玻璃——而不是真钻石；还有，如果出现了其他质量上的问题，我概不负责。”

我当即把钻石装进了钱包，很是高兴。

“一定。”我边说边取出一张纸。查尔斯凭他那准确无误的经商本能，早料到他会提这种要求，给了我一份签过名的协议，内容差不多。

“你要不要支票？”我问。

他犹疑了一下。

“最好还是给我法兰西银行的钞票吧。”他答道。

“好，”我答道，“我到外面给你取。”

有些人就是这么信任别人！他竟然答应让我出去——兜里揣着这些钻石出去！

查尔斯爵士给了我一张空白支票，额度不超过两千五百英镑。我把支票给了我们的代理人，兑换成了法兰西银行的钞票。副牧师高高兴兴地紧紧抓住这些钞票。当天晚上，我也高高兴兴地赶回卢塞恩，觉得自己以低于实际价值约一千英镑的价格，就把这些钻石买到手了！

艾米莉亚在卢塞恩车站接我，她显然很焦急。

“西摩，买回来了吗？”她问。

“买来了。”我答道，以一种胜利的姿态掏出“战果”。

“啊，太可怕了！”她叫道，往后一退，“你觉得它们是真品吗？确定他没骗你？”

“确定，”我一边打量着，一边回答，“说到钻石，没人能骗得了我。你究竟为什么怀疑它们不是真品？”

“我在酒店里同欧黑根夫人聊天，她说有一种非常知名的骗局——她是在书中看到的。骗子准备两套东西——一套真的，一套假的。他向你展示的是真品，但卖给你的却是假的，卖的时候还装得像是给了你什么特殊优惠。”

“不用担心，”我答道，“我是品鉴钻石的专家。”

“我还是不放心，”艾米莉亚低声道，“还是让查尔斯看看吧。”

我们一起回到酒店。当我把钻石交给查尔斯检验时，生平第一次看到艾米莉亚真的紧张起来。她的担心也影响到了我们。我自己也有点担心，查尔斯也许会发出一声简短而低沉的感叹，接着突然火冒三丈。事情出问题时，他经常会这样。不过，当我告诉他价钱时，他面带微笑地盯着它们。

“比实际价值便宜了八百英镑。”他心满意足地答道。

“你不怀疑它们是假的？”我问。

“一点也不用怀疑，”他注视着它们，答道，“这都是真钻石，质地还有款式都同艾米莉亚的项链一模一样。”

艾米莉亚松了口气，缓缓说道：“我上楼把我的项链拿下来，让你们俩对比一下。”

一分钟后，艾米莉亚又冲了下来，上气不接下气。艾米莉亚可算不上不苗条，不过我还从未见过她的动作像现在这般伶俐。

“查尔斯！查尔斯！”她大叫道，“知道发生了什么可怕的事了吗？我自己的钻石有两颗不见了！他从我项链上偷了两颗，然后又卖给了我！”

她把项链拿了出来。一点都不错，果真少了两颗钻石——而这两颗刚好能嵌在空缺的地方！

我突然灵光一闪，用手拍拍头。“我的天，”我大声叫道，“那位小副牧师是——克雷上校！”

查尔斯的两只手来回不断地拍着前额，叫道：“杰西，白石南花——那位单纯的苏格兰小姑娘！虽然她说话有点悦耳的高地口音，不过我常从她的声音中听出些熟悉的味道。杰西就是——皮卡迪特夫人！”

我们当然没什么证据，但就跟尼斯的警长一样，我们凭直觉敢肯定事情就是这样。

查尔斯下定决心要抓住这个无赖。这第二次上当让他铁下心来，说道：“这人最可恶的一点在于，他有一套手段，他不是上门来骗我们，而是让我们主动上钩。他下个套，我们就跌跌撞撞地钻了进去。西，明天我们必须紧随他去巴黎。”

艾米莉亚向他解释了欧黑根夫人说的话，查尔斯以他一贯的精明，立刻豁然开朗，说道：“这就解释了，为什么那无赖会用这种把戏一步步来引诱我们。要是我们怀疑，他就可以向我们展示钻石是真的，这样就逃过了检验。这只是一种掩饰，把我们的注意力从抢劫这件事上转移开。他动身去巴黎，是为了在事迹败露后逃之夭夭，比我们提前整整一天动身。这个无赖真够高明的！接连骗了我两次！”

“可是，他是如何拿到我的珠宝盒的？”艾米莉亚高声问道。

“这是个问题，”查尔斯回答，“先不管这个了！”

“还有，他为什么不把整条项链都偷走，然后把钻石卖掉？”我问。

“这人太狡猾了，”查尔斯答道，“不过他目前的这种做法会更好。要处理掉那么一大件珠宝并非易事。首先，那些钻石很大，价值不菲；其次，谁都知道这些钻石——每位做珠宝生意的都听说过凡德里夫特家的宝石项链，看过它们外观的照片。可以这么说，这些钻石都是标了记号的。他不会去这么做，但玩的手段更高明——从上面取下两颗钻石，然后卖给世上唯一有可能买，而且不会起疑心的人。他到这儿就是为了实施这个骗局，他提前按照钻石的形状准备好了一副链扣，之后偷来钻石，镶到预留的位置上。一场相当精明的骗局。我发誓，我自己都有点佩服这个家伙了。”

因为查尔斯自己是位商人，他能够察知他人的生意头脑。

克雷上校是如何知道那条项链，又是如何偷走两颗钻石的，我们直到很久以后才知道。在此我也就不提前透露了。一时专一事，这是生活中的金科玉律。现在，他把我们所有人都骗了。

我们紧跟他赶到巴黎，提前给法兰西银行发了电报，让他们拒绝承兑这些票据。可是已经太晚了。就在我支付后半小时内，钞票已经兑换成了现金。我们发现，副牧师夫妇在当天下午已经离开德蒙大酒店，不知去了哪里。同克雷上校平日一样，他们凭空蒸发了，没留下任何线索。换句话说，他们肯定又改变了伪装，当天晚上以另外某种身份出现在了其他某个地方。不管怎么说，此后再也没有听说过理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗牧师这个人——还有，实际上在诺森伯兰郡根本没有艾宾汉姆这个村庄。

我们将情况告知了巴黎警方。他们一点同情心也没有。“肯定是克雷上校，”接见我们的警官说道，“但你们好像没什么正当的理由来指控他。据我所知，先生们，你们彼此也都是半斤八两。你，爵士先生，想用铅玻璃的价格把钻石买到手。你，夫人，害怕自己用买钻石的价格买到铅玻璃。你，秘书先生，想试着以半价从一位毫无戒备的人手中买这些钻石。那位勇敢的橡皮脸上校，把你们都骗了——可谓强中自有强中手。”

当然，话虽没错，但听了之后，心里也没有觉得有所宽慰。

我们回到格兰德大酒店，查尔斯火冒三丈，叫道：“太过分了，这个浑蛋真有种！不过，他休想再骗我，西。我倒希望他再骗我试试，我会抓住他的。我保证，下一次不管他怎么伪装，我一定能把他认出来。我接连两次这样被他骗，太荒唐了。只要我还有一口气，他就休想再得逞！休想！我把话放在这儿！”

“闻所未闻！”附近大厅中一名送信人用法语低声应道。我们站在格兰德大酒店外廊下面，在宽敞的玻璃庭院中。我十分怀疑，那送信人就是乔装的克雷上校。

也许，我们已经处处在怀疑他了。

第三章　大师名作

查尔斯和大多数南非人一样，最不喜欢久坐不动。他讨厌坐着，必须常常“跋涉”一下。要是不能随心所欲地到处走动，就会要了他的命。在梅费尔一下子待上六个星期，这是他能忍受的极限了。之后，他就会忍不住，跑到苏格兰、洪堡、蒙特卡洛、比亚里茨去休息休息，换换环境。“我才不会像帽贝一样永远趴在石头上。”他说。于是，早秋时候，我们就入住到了布莱顿市的大都市酒店。和往常一样，还是我们和睦的一小家人——查尔斯和艾米莉亚，伊莎贝尔和我，还是和平日一样住的套房。

到那里之后的第一个周日早上，我和查尔斯就出去溜达了——很遗憾，是在做礼拜的时间出去的——走到英皇大道，去呼吸一点新鲜空气，看看海峡中翻滚的波浪。那两位女士（戴着软帽）去做礼拜了。查尔斯劳累了一周，非常疲惫，很晚才起床，而我早起后有些头痛，我觉得是由于台球室的空气不流通；再者，还有可能是我喝的一种不太习惯的苏打水在作怪，我喝它主要是想冲淡一下晚上饮的威士忌。我们打算稍后在教堂巡行的人群中与她们见面——我觉得艾米莉亚还有伊莎贝尔对于这一仪式的重视程度要胜于这之前的布道。

我们一起坐在玻璃座位上。查尔斯的目光来来回回地在英皇大道上搜寻，想找位卖星期日报纸的报童。最后终于有个报童过来。“《观察家新闻报》。”我内兄简短地叫道。

“没有了，”报童答道，在我们面前晃了晃他那一摞报纸，“要不要《裁判员报》？或者《粉安报》[11]？”

查尔斯不看《裁判员报》，至于《粉安报》，他觉得不太适合周日早上在大庭广众之下看。也许可以在房间里看看，但在外面看的话，报纸粉红的颜色把一切都暴露了。于是，他摇摇头，低声说道：“要是你碰到卖《观察家新闻报》的，让他马上到我这儿来。”

这时，我们旁边紧挨着坐的一位文质彬彬的陌生人转过身，面带微笑。“我给你一份怎么样？”他一边说，一边从口袋里掏出一份报纸，“我想，我买的是最后一份。今天大家都争着买它，它今天早上登了来自德兰士瓦[12]的重要新闻。”

查尔斯扬了扬眉毛，接了过来，在我看来，他的态度有点粗暴。为了避免这位好心人对他产生一种粗暴无礼的误解，于是我便同这位热心的陌生人攀谈起来。他是个中年人，中等身材，举手投足间透露着涵养，戴了一副金边夹鼻眼镜，他目光犀利，声音透着优雅。不一会儿，他就谈到了当时布莱顿的知名人士。很显然，他同许多名流都交情不浅。我们谈到了尼斯、罗马、佛罗伦萨还有开罗。我们的许多朋友他好像也都认识；说实话，虽然我们双方的交际圈有这么多交集，不过很奇怪，在这之前却没有碰到过对方。

“查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，那位了不起的非洲百万富翁，”他最后问了一句，“你知不知道他？听说他目前就在这儿，住在大都会酒店。”

我朝我们正在谈论着的那人挥了挥手。

“这位就是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，”我答道，心里有一种独有的自豪感，“我是他妹夫，西摩·温特沃斯。”

“哦，这样！”那陌生人答道，很奇怪，给人一种欲言又止的感觉。我在想，他是不是刚才要装作认识查尔斯，或者是不是刚准备要贬损他几句，庆幸还好没有说出口。

这时，查尔斯放下报纸，同我们一起攀谈起来。我从他缓和的语气中立刻明白，德兰士瓦的新闻，对他克罗地多普·戈尔康达公司的经营有利，因此他的态度变得友善和蔼起来。他整个人立刻都变了，对那位文雅的陌生人也变得礼貌起来。此外，我们还了解到，那名男子在上流社会活动，结识了一些人士，一些艾米莉亚渴望能邀请来参加她在梅费尔举办的“家庭招待会”的人士——年轻的小说家费斯，还有了不起的北极旅行家理查德·蒙特罗斯爵士。说到画家，很明显，这人同他们中许多人都是莫逆之交。他同美术院会员一起吃过饭，每周还请协会成员共进早餐。现在，艾米莉亚极其希望，她的沙龙不应当看起来仅仅局限于一些金融界和政界人物——有下院议员还有百万富翁们作为坚实的后盾——她现在转而钟爱文学、艺术以及音乐这股清雅的暗流。我们的这位新相识极其健谈。“西，他知道自己在社会中的位置，”查尔斯后来对我说，“因此说起话来天马行空，不必过虑。不过，很多人拿不准自己的位置，往往会担心这一点。”我们起身告别时交换了名片。这位新朋友的名字是爱德华·伯尔派罗博士。

“你在这儿行医吗？”我问，不过他的装束不太像医生。

“哦，我不是医生，”他答道，“是法学博士，你该知道的。我对艺术感兴趣，就某种意义上来讲，可以说我是为国家美术馆购买一些作品。”

这正是艾米莉亚“家庭招待会”所要的人！查尔斯立即稳住他。“我把自己的马车也带过来了，”他以自己最友好的态度说，“我们打算明天驾车去刘易斯市。要是您愿意赏光一同前去，我敢保证，凡德里夫特夫人见到你一定会非常高兴。”

“咱们仅有一面之交，”博士说，“你就如此热情。我明天肯定会欣然前去。”

“我们十点半从大都会酒店出发。”查尔斯接着说。

“我一定到。早安！”他边说边起身离开，点点头，会心地笑了。

我们又回到草坪，来到艾米莉亚和伊莎贝尔身边。那位新朋友从我们面前经过一两次，查尔斯拦住他，并做了介绍。当时，他正同两位女士一起散步，她们装束精致、奇特，极其优雅。艾米莉亚一下子就注意到了他的举止。“谁都能一眼看出，”她说，“他这人有涵养，真正卓尔不群。我在想，他能不能把英国皇家艺术院院长一起请来，参加我两周后的周三举办的议会‘家庭招待会’？”

第二天十点半，我们驾车启程。我们的车马可以算是苏塞克斯地区最棒的。查尔斯虽说有点急躁——或者，最好说是有点小心翼翼？——但驾车技术不错。他现在实际上正忙着驾驭两匹前马两匹后马，没时间和我们闲谈。来自比肯的贝莱斯尔夫人在他旁边，坐在车夫座位上，容光焕发（她一直都是这样，这得归功于她的女仆）；伯尔派罗博士坐在后排，同我和艾米莉亚一起。他大部分时间在同凡德里夫特夫人交谈：他谈的都是关于画廊的。艾米莉亚很反感，但又觉得作为查尔斯的妻子，偶尔假装有个高雅的兴趣爱好，是她义不容辞的责任。是贵族就得名副其实。我们在罗斯郡的住所，塞尔登堡，几乎满墙都是钱玛还有奥查德森的作品。事情起因于一件小小的意外。查尔斯爵士想要一匹前马——你也知道，为他马车准备的前马——于是把此事告诉了一位搞艺术的朋友。这位搞艺术的朋友第二周就给他弄来一幅钱玛的作品，把牲畜当成了人名。查尔斯爵士吃了一惊，羞于承认所犯的这个错误。于是后来稀里糊涂地成了绘画的赞助人。

虽然伯尔派罗博士张口闭口谈的都是艺术，不过仔细观察一番，你就会发现他是位极为称心如意的伴侣。谈论艺术时，他巧妙地穿插着一些逸事丑闻。他告诉我们，哪位知名画家和自己的厨子结了婚，哪位画家又娶了自己的模特，如此这般，和他谈话非常有趣。不过，他有一次提到，说自己发现了一幅伦勃朗的真迹——千真万确，在某个不知名的荷兰人家中保存了多年。大家一直都认为那幅画是伦勃朗的杰作，不过，除了几个关系亲近的人之外，在过去半个世纪中很少有人亲眼看见该画作。那幅肖像画，画的是哈勒姆[13]的玛丽亚·范雷内，他从她在荷兰豪达[14]的子孙们的手中买了过来。

虽然查尔斯看起来没怎么太在意，但我却注意到他支起了耳朵。这位叫玛丽亚·范雷内的，碰巧是凡德里夫特家族在1780年移民到开普敦之前的一位旁系先人。虽然不知道这幅画到底在哪儿，但整个家族都知道它确实存在。伊莎贝尔也经常提起它。要是价格合适能把它买到手，让孩子们（我应该提一句，查尔斯爵士有两个儿子在伊顿公学读书）拥有一幅先人的肖像画，还是伦勃朗的真迹，该是多么光彩的事情。

之后，关于这个重大发现，伯尔派罗博士又说了很多。他一开始先想方设法把它卖给国家美术馆，不过尽管美术馆的董事们十分欣赏这幅作品，也承认它是真品，但很遗憾，他们今年手头的资金不足，无法以合适的价格购买这么名贵的一幅画。南肯辛顿也一样，太缺钱。不过，他目前正和罗浮宫还有柏林方面谈判。但很可惜，这么精美的一件艺术作品，一度流入国内，竟又得再次流失海外。应由某位爱国的艺术赞助人把它买下来，放在自己家中，或者慷慨地献给国家。

查尔斯自始至终没说一句话，但我可以察觉到他一直在思考。他甚至在快到一个急转弯时，还往后看了一眼（刹车员正忙着嘟嘟地吹喇叭，提醒路人有马车过来），给艾米莉亚递了个眼神，提醒她不要做出任何承诺，这立刻就让她暂时闭了嘴。查尔斯驾车的时候回头看，这很不寻常。从他这一举止中，我猜他非常迫切地想要得到这幅伦勃朗的作品。

我们到刘易斯市后，把马匹寄在了旅店，查尔斯同平日一样点了一顿豪华奢侈的午餐。与此同时，我们两两一起在小镇还有城堡附近闲逛。我选择同贝莱斯尔夫人一起，她至少比较有趣。出发前，查尔斯把我拉到一边，说道：“西，听我说，咱们必须万分小心。咱们只是偶然碰到伯尔派罗这个人。狡猾的无赖打算骗人，再没有什么比大师作品更容易得逞了。如果那幅伦勃朗的作品是真的，那么我就应当拥有它；如果画的真是玛丽亚·范雷内，那么我就有义务替孩子们把它买到手。不过，最近我已经被骗了两次，我可不想再被骗一次。咱们必须要小心行事。”

“说得不错，”我应道，“别再来什么先知或者副牧师了！”

“不论他如何谈论国家美术馆之类的，我们都对他一无所知，”查尔斯继续说道，“如果这人是个骗子，那么他所讲的故事都是这种人临时捏造出来骗我的。他很容易就能知道我是谁——我可是位知名人物。他知道我在布莱顿，很可能星期天就一直坐在那玻璃座位上，专门来引我上钩。”

“他提到了你的名字，”我说，“当他得知我的身份时，就立刻和我攀谈起来。”

“对，”查尔斯继续道，“他也许知道玛丽亚·范雷内这幅肖像。我奶奶经常提到，说这幅画保存在豪达。实际上，我也常常提到它，你肯定也记得。这样的话，一个无赖一开始就跟艾米莉亚谈那幅画，还装作毫不知情，还有比这更自然不过的吗？如果他想要一幅伦勃朗的作品，我相信在伯明翰想要多少就会有多少。我说这番话，是想说咱们应当小心行事。”

“说得对，”我答道，“我会时刻留心他的。”

我们从另一条路驾车回去，路上满是金秋时节山毛榉树的树影。这次出行很愉快。伯尔派罗博士吃了午饭，喝了香醇的独家干红葡萄酒，兴致很高。他说起话来口若悬河，我从没见过谁能抖出这么多杂七杂八的趣事。他哪儿都去过，知道所有人的一切事情。艾米莉亚当即“预约”，让他去参加自己下周三的“家庭招待会”，他则答应将她引见给几位文艺界的名人。

那天晚上大约七点半，我和查尔斯饭前一起在英皇大道上散散步，吹吹风。我们八点钟吃饭。空气很怡人。我们途经一家新开的小酒店，酒店很小很独特，有扇非常大的弓形窗。在灯光的明暗交界处，我们的朋友伯尔派罗坐在那里，穿着晚礼服，对面是位年轻、优雅、漂亮的女士。他面前开着一瓶香槟，自己尽情地吃着温室的葡萄，谈笑风生。很显然，他同那位女士都被某个滑稽的笑话完全逗乐了，因为他们彼此奇怪地盯着对方，时不时爆发出阵阵愉快的笑声。

我退后几步，查尔斯也是。我们两人头脑中突然闪过同一个念头。我小声说道：“克雷上校！”他应声道：“还有皮卡迪特夫人！”

他们根本不像理查德副牧师还有布拉巴宗夫人。不过，这也刚好说明了问题。因为我也没看到墨西哥先知那鹰钩鼻子的踪迹。即便这样，当时我已经明白，不要完全相信外表。如果他们俩真是那位知名的骗子以及他妻子（或者称之为共犯），那我们必须得十分小心。这一次，我们提前戒备了起来。假如他胆敢试着第三次骗我们，他绝对逃不出我们的掌心。不过，我们必须得采取一些措施，不让他从我们手中狡猾地溜掉。

“他能像泥鳅一样溜走。”尼斯的警长这么说。我们俩都想起了这句话，便开始精心地制订计划，以免他第三次从我们手中溜掉。

“西，我给你说说计划，”我内兄缓缓说道，“这一次，我们必须故意让自己受骗，必须主动要求购买那幅画，让他以书面形式保证画是真品，并且要想方设法用最苛刻的条件来约束他。不过，与此同时，我们必须看起来没有任何怀疑，要装作像婴儿般天真。不管他对我们撒什么谎，都全盘接受。为肖像画支付的钱，用支票付——只是做做样子。只要交易一完成，就立刻抓捕他，证据俱在。当然，接下来他会用尽浑身解数立刻逃之夭夭，就像在尼斯和巴黎碰到他时那样；但这次，我们会让警方随时待命，把一切准备妥当。不能鲁莽，但也不能耽搁误事。一定要等到他真正地接过钱，装进腰包时才能动手。那时，我们就立刻抓住他，把他送到当地的法庭。这就是我这次的行动计划。在此期间，我们要看起来单纯、朴实，得让他深信不疑。”

于是，我们开始实施这个周详的计划，第二天就去伯尔派罗博士下榻的酒店拜访他，他把我们引见给了他妻子，她是一位秀丽的小妇人。我们假装不去在她身上找傲慢无礼的皮卡迪特夫人，还有心思单纯的“白石南花”的身影。博士（同往常一样）饶有兴致地谈着艺术——他可真是个无所不知的无赖，绝对的！——查尔斯爵士也对那幅假定的伦勃朗的作品表现出了些许兴趣。我们的这位新朋友很高兴，从他那努力抑制的急促语气中，我们可以看出，他一眼就知道我们是潜在的买家。他说，他会第二天去伦敦，把那幅肖像画带过来。实际上，第二天早上，当我和查尔斯跟平常一样坐上普耳曼卧车[15]，去参加半年一度的克罗地多普·戈尔康达会议时，我们的那位博士也在那车上，躺在靠椅上，好像整个车子都是他的。查尔斯给我递了个意味深长的眼神。“他可真会享受，不是吗？”他低声说，“这车费是从我那被骗走的五千英镑中出的，或者，就当是那幅假的伦勃朗的作品少骗了我一点。”

到了伦敦，我们就立刻投入工作。我们从马维尔那里请了位私家侦探，安排他去监视我们那位朋友。从他口中得知，那位所谓的博士当天去了西区，从一位商贩那里取了幅画（我隐去那人的名字，因为担心会有人告我诽谤），据了解，那人此前牵扯到几件名声不好，或者说声名狼藉的交易。不过，说真的，我一直以为画商就只是——卖画的。在我看来，赛马是最容易造就一些寡廉鲜耻的经纪人的，但有了字画，赛马就只能屈居第二了。言归正传，我们发现那位著名的艺术评论家从这位商贩的铺子里取走了伦勃朗的画，当天晚上小心翼翼地带到了布莱顿。

为了不贸然行事，以免破坏我们的计划，我们诱劝伯尔派罗（名字起得可真够巧妙！）把那幅伦勃朗的画带到大都市酒店，让我们检验一番，把画留在我们那儿，好听听伦敦专家的意见。

专家来了，就这幅据称是大师的画作，向我们做了一个全面的汇报。据他判断，这根本不是伦勃朗的作品，只不过是一幅笔法精妙，又刻意弄旧的现代荷兰赝品。此外，他还用档案证据向我们展示，真正的玛丽亚·范雷内的肖像画实际上已经在五年前被带到了英国，卖给了J.H.汤姆林森爵士，就是那位知名的鉴赏家，卖了八千英镑。所以伯尔派罗博士的画，充其量是伦勃朗自己的复制品，或者更有可能是他学生的作品；不过，最有可能的，只是现代的伪造品罢了。

因此，我们做好了充分准备，去指控这位自称博士的人的犯罪阴谋。但为了确保万无一失，我们隐隐地给他提个醒，说玛丽亚·范雷内的肖像画真的有可能在别处，甚至还当面暗示道，那画极有可能落入了那位无所不收的收藏家J.H.汤姆林森爵士之手。不过，这位卖主根本不去理会对他商品如此这般的诋毁。他居然厚颜无耻地不顾档案证据，宣称J.H.汤姆林森（英国最见多识广、最精明狡黠的绘画买家之一）被一位穷困潦倒、有伪造天赋的荷兰艺术家巧妙地骗了。他宣称，真正的玛丽亚·范雷内的肖像画，就是他给我们的这幅，还发了誓。“让胜利冲昏了头脑，”查尔斯向我高兴地说道，“他觉得，不论自己对我们撒多大的慌，我们都会全盘接受。‘常在河边走，哪能不湿鞋。’我们这次将他一军。”说实话，他打的这个比方前后没什么逻辑，不过查尔斯打的比方，总是能让人挑出毛病来。

于是，我们假装相信他，并相信了他的保证。接下来是价格的问题。讨论得很激烈，不过也仅仅是为了做做样子。J.H.汤姆林森花了八千英镑买了玛丽亚的真画，可对这幅赝品，博士却要价一万。实际上，我们根本没什么必要和他讨价还价、争来争去，因为查尔斯只是打算根据他要的数额开张支票，然后把这家伙抓起来；不过，为了不让他起疑心，我们觉得最好还是假装还价一番，最后把价格压到了九千基尼[16]。不过，他得给我们一份书面保证，保证他卖给我们的作品是伦勃朗的真迹，保证画的是哈勒姆的玛丽亚·范雷内，并且保证毫无疑问这幅画是他从荷兰豪达那位女士的后人们手中直接购买过来的。

一切都做得很漂亮，我们的安排堪称完美。我们叫来一名警察在大都市酒店房间外待命，决定让伯尔派罗博士在某个固定的时间到酒店来签保证书，然后收钱。双方起草了一份正式的协议，完整地盖了印章。“甲方”在约定的时间到了，把肖像画交给了我们。查尔斯取出一张约定金额的支票，签了字，接着递给了博士。伯尔派罗刚拿过支票，我就站到了门旁，这时，警局派来的两名便衣侦探就装作男仆守着，盯着窗户。我们生怕这个骗子一旦拿到支票就会逃掉，就像他在尼斯还有巴黎那样。在他带着胜利的微笑把支票装进口袋的那一刻，我迅速地走向他，手里拿着一副手铐。还没等他弄明白是怎么一回事，我早已敏捷地将手铐套到他手腕上并锁住。这时，警察也走上前来。“这次我们可抓到你了！”我喊道，“我们知道你是谁，伯尔派罗博士。你就是——克雷上校，化名安东尼奥·赫雷拉先知，还有理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗牧师。”

我这辈子还从未见过谁会如此这般震惊！他完全惊呆了。查尔斯觉得，他肯定料想自己会立刻脱身走人，而我们及时采取的措施让他大吃一惊，一下子慌张失措。他凝视着周围，仿佛没有反应过来这到底是怎么一回事。

“他们俩是疯子吗？乱说些什么？”他最后问道，“他们说的什么安东尼奥·赫雷拉的疯话是什么意思？”

警察把手搭在囚犯的肩上。

“别瞎费口舌了，伙计，”他说，“我们有逮捕令。爱德华·伯尔派罗，化名理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗，我逮捕你，因为你被指控通过欺诈手段从一等勋爵士、下院议员查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士手中骗取钱财。他对此发了誓，并在这儿签了字。”因为查尔斯事先已经将相关材料起草好了。

那囚犯挺直了身子。“听着，长官，”他说，很生气，“咱们在这件事上有些误会。我这辈子从来没用过什么化名。你怎么知道他真的是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士？说不定有人要冒名胁迫我。要我看，他们俩是一对从精神病院逃出来的疯子。”

“明天再说这些！”警察抓着他，说道，“现在你得乖乖地跟我去一趟警局，这两位先生会在那儿把对你的指控登个记。”

他们把他带走了，他还在抗议。我和查尔斯在案情记录表上签了字，警察把他锁了起来，等着第二天在法官面前进行审讯。

即便现在这么做了，我们仍然担心这家伙会想方设法保释出去，从我们手中溜掉。实际上，他歇斯底里地抗议我们竟如此对待一位“他这种地位的绅士”。不过，查尔斯特地嘱咐警方，不要理睬他，说他是位十分危险、极其狡猾的罪犯，在法官审讯完毕之前，不论何种事由何种借口，都绝不能把他放走。

说来也怪，我们当晚在酒店得知，真有位叫伯尔派罗的博士，那是位知名的艺术评论家。不过，我们觉得，抓住的这个骗子肯定一直在盗用他的名字。

第二天早上，我们来到法庭，一位巡官过来迎接我们，脸拉得很长。“我说，先生们，”他说，“恐怕你们犯了一个十分严重的错误。你们可真行，把事情搞得一团糟。你们惹上麻烦了，更糟的是，把我们也牵扯了进来。你们搞的那些宣誓材料未免有点聪明过头了。我们已经质询过这位绅士了，发现他关于自己的描述完全没有问题。他叫伯尔派罗，是位知名的艺术评论家、绘画收藏家，在海外受雇于国家美术馆。他之前是南肯辛顿博物馆的官员、外科学士、法学博士，极其德高望重的一个人。你们犯了一个非常可悲的错误，事情就是这样。你们很可能会受到一项非法监禁的指控，这恐怕把我们部门也牵扯了进来。”

查尔斯倒吸了一口气，声音中满是恐惧，大声叫道：“你们不会就凭着这些荒唐的陈词就把他放了吧？不会让他像那个杀人犯那样从你们手中溜掉了吧？”

“让他从我们手中溜掉？”巡官叫道，“我倒是希望他能溜掉。很不幸，没这个机会了。此刻，他就在法庭上，被你们俩气得火冒三丈。我们到这儿是为了保护你们，怕他万一袭击你们。因为你们的虚假证词，他被关了一整夜，当然了，他现在气得要发疯。”

“只要你没放他走就好，”查尔斯答道，“他是只狡猾的狐狸。他在哪儿？让我见见他。”

我们来到法庭。在庭中，我们看到那囚犯正兴高采烈地同法官亲切交谈（貌似法官是他的一位私交）。查尔斯立刻上前同他们说话，伯尔派罗博士转过身，透过夹鼻眼镜瞪着他。

“这个人行为怪异，让人难以置信，”他说，“唯一可能的解释就是，他一定疯了——他的秘书也是。他在英皇大道的玻璃座椅上主动同我结识，然后邀请我乘他的马车去刘易斯市。再后来，他主动要购买我一幅名贵的画作，最后莫名其妙地给了我这个愚蠢、荒谬、莫须有的指控。我要求以非法监禁罪给他下传票。”

突然，我们渐渐明白，局面已经扭转了。我们渐渐意识到自己犯了个错误。伯尔派罗博士确实是他自己所声称的那个人，并且一直都是。我们也了解到，他的画上是真的玛丽亚·范雷内，是伦勃朗的真迹，他把它放在那位可疑的商贩那里，只是为了清洗和修复一下。J.H.汤姆林森爵士被一个狡猾的荷兰人骗了，他的画虽然也确实是伦勃朗的作品，但画的不是玛丽亚，只不过是一件保存不善、略次一些的样品。我们所咨询的专家是个无知、自负的江湖骗子。还有，其他专家对那幅玛丽亚画像的估价，最多不超过五六千基尼。查尔斯想撤销这次交易，但伯尔派罗博士当然一个字也不听，那份协议是具有法律约束力的武器。不过，当时查尔斯头脑中所想的，同那份书面合同没有半点关系。对方要查尔斯在《泰晤士报》上刊登一份道歉信，并付他五百英镑作为对他人格玷污的补偿，否则他就要控告我们非法监禁。我们精心设计的去抓那个骗子的计划，就这么收场了。

不过，这件事到此还未结束；因为，当然啦，此后整个事件逐渐登了报。伯尔派罗博士是文学界、艺术界的熟人，结果他起诉了那位所谓的专家，是那位专家否认了自己伦勃朗画作的真实性，并且指控他愚昧无知，却还信口雌黄。之后报刊的短评就传开了。《环球报》登了一篇讽刺文章，来揭露我们的事；一向对查尔斯爵士还有其他南非人不依不饶的《真理报》登了一首辛辣的诗歌《金伯利的高雅艺术》。不出我们所料，这样一折腾，整个事件就传到了克雷上校的耳朵里；因为一两周以后，我内兄收到了一张幸灾乐祸的短笺，信笺还散发着清香，写信的是那位对我们穷追不舍的骗子。内容如下：

哈，你这天真的孩子！

愿上帝保佑你那天真的小脑瓜！你是不是觉得自己确确实实抓住了厉害的上校？你是不是准备了一个漂亮的圈套来抓住他？你的大名是不是叫“笨蛋爵士”？看到你那巧妙的小诡计，我和“白石南花”笑得不知有多开心！顺便说一句，让“白石南花”到你家中，花上半年时间，教教你如何做业余侦探，这会对你大有裨益。你那迷人的天真，让我俩好不嫉妒。像我这种头脑的人会屈尊用绘画大师这么平淡、老套、愚蠢、俗气的骗术？亏你能想得到！还是在所谓的十九世纪！哦，神圣的单纯！我什么时候能像婴儿一样被人一眼看穿？什么时候？告诉我什么时候？不过，不用担心，亲爱的朋友。虽然你没抓到我，但咱们不久还会再来次愉快的会面。

致以最崇高的敬意和感激。

安东尼奥·赫雷拉，

或理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗

查尔斯放下信，长叹一口气。“西，老弟，”他沉思着大声说道，“世上没有谁的财产——哪怕是我的——能经得起这么折腾。财产这样源源不断地流失，真的让我开始感到害怕。我看到了自己的结局：我最后会死在济贫院。想一想当他是克雷上校时从我身上掠走的钱，再想想当他不是克雷上校时我在他身上浪费的钱，这个人开始让我变得紧张兮兮的了。我要从这种担惊受怕的生活中全身而退。我要离开这个诡诈、败坏的世界，到清新、纯净的大山中某个清净的角落中去。”

“既然你能说出这种话，看来是时候换个环境，得休息一下了，”我说，“咱们去蒂罗尔吧！”

第四章　蒂罗尔城堡

我们去了梅兰。实际上，这个地方是艾米莉亚的法国女仆替我们定的。在这种事情上，她就是我们的向导和情报员。

艾米莉亚的这位法国女仆非常聪明。无论我们去哪儿，选哪家酒店，住哪家带家具的别墅，艾米莉亚一般都会问问（并接受）她的建议。西塞琳早已把整个欧洲大陆都转遍了，并且，她是阿尔萨斯人，当然德语说得跟法语一样流利。此外，她长期同艾米莉亚在一起生活，这让她把我们的母语英语也说得同样上口。那位姑娘，是个不可多得的万事通；她干净利落、敏捷灵巧，不论让她做什么事，都能得心应手。不管走到哪儿，她都一手拿着针线盒，一手拿着小酒精炉。她偶尔会做个煎蛋卷，也能驾驭挪威雪橇；她会针线，能编织，会做衣服，也能治感冒，你要她做什么，全都能做得来。她做的沙拉，是我尝过最可口的。说到她煮的咖啡（她在我们坐火车长途旅行时准备的），在西区俱乐部里，没有哪位主厨能和她相提并论。

因此，当艾米莉亚颐指气使地说道：“西塞琳，我们打算去蒂罗尔——现在十月中旬——立刻就动身，你建议我们住在哪里？”西塞琳旋即答道：“夫人，要是秋天，肯定就是约翰大公爵了，在梅兰。”

“他是——大公爵吗？”艾米莉亚问道，看到她同皇室的要人这么熟，感到有些吃惊。

“是的！不，夫人。这只是个酒店的名字——就像在英国所说的‘维多利亚’酒店，或者‘威尔士亲王’酒店——这是蒂罗尔南部最舒适的酒店。一年之中的这个时候，你肯定是要到阿尔卑斯山的那边去的，因斯布鲁克已经开始冷了。”

于是，我们去了梅兰。说实话，我很少见过比这更漂亮、更秀丽的地方。滔滔的水流，高高的山峰，沿坡种植的葡萄园，古老的城墙与塔楼，古雅的带有拱廊的街道，崎岖峭壁上的瀑布，模仿德国温泉疗养胜地风格的人行漫步道；举目远眺，会看到起伏的多洛米蒂山山峰。我之前从未目睹过这么一派景象。一个莱茵小镇沿着阿尔卑斯山峦顺势而下，中间点缀着雄伟的意大利柱廊。

我赞成西塞琳的选择，当她建议住一切从简的酒店，而不是住配有家具的别墅时，我非常高兴，因为这样我就无须费心；而如果选择后者，大部分各项安排，自然要落到我这可怜的秘书头上。不论哪种情形，我都得每天工作三小时，这种正常工作之外的额外负担，还是能少些就少些的好。我给西塞琳半个金镑作为小费，说实在的，是为了她做的这个明智的决策。西塞琳神秘、好奇、似笑非笑地瞥了一眼手心中的金币，然后立刻丢到了兜里，用法语说了声：“谢谢，先生！”有点瞧不起的意味。我一直以为，西塞琳在小费这件事上，有着很高的期望，根本看不上我这小小的秘书所能给得起的这点钱。

梅兰最为特别之处在于，它有许多城堡（我觉得，严格来讲，这个地方用复数是不符合语法规则的，不过英国人能立刻会意）[17]，你站在郊区向任何一个方向都能看得到。据说，要是站在库切尔伯格山上数一数，能看到不下四十座这种别具一格、摇摇欲坠的老城堡。就我个人而言，我不喜欢统计（金融招股说明书除外），我也确实不知道，在西塞琳的指点下，伊莎贝尔和艾米莉亚到底数出了多少座破败的城堡。不过，我记得，大部分城堡都十分典雅、美观，它们所呈现的各式建筑，的确看似让人眼花缭乱。这座是方形的，每个角都会探出古怪的小炮塔；而那座则坐拥一栋高大的主楼，长长的城墙向两边延展，上面爬满了常春藤，还有赏心悦目的棱堡。查尔斯对这些城堡十分痴迷，他喜欢这种美景，在他那金融灵魂的深处，潜伏着诗人的影子（只不过隐藏得特别深，这一点我可以向你保证）。自从到这儿的那一刻起，他便立刻想在这些浪漫的山峦中拥有一座属于自己的城堡。“塞尔登！”他不屑地大声说道，“人们把塞尔登称作城堡！西，你我都很清楚，它不过是在一八六〇年由丘比特公司——伦敦那家声名显赫的承包商——按市价为塞尔登的麦克弗森建造的，用的全是些假的古石。对于那座假城堡，麦克弗森向我开了一个荒唐的价格，这个价都能买下一座真正的古代宅第了。看一看，这些城堡才是真正的城堡，历尽沧桑，颜色都有些灰白了。蒂罗尔城堡有罗马风格——十世纪或十一世纪的风格。”（这些话他是在旅行指南中读到的。）“这才是我想要的地方！——十世纪或十一世纪的东西。我可以在这里生活，远离那些公债还有股票，彻底地远离它们。在这幽静的峡谷中，西，伙计，想想，不会有什么克雷上校，也不会有什么傲慢的皮卡迪特夫人！”

实际上，他只能在那儿待上六周，之后就会厌倦，接着就想去帕克港、蒙特卡洛，还有布莱顿转转。

说来也怪，艾米莉亚也被查尔斯这一时兴起的念头迷住了。这个世界上，除了伦敦，她一向哪儿都不喜欢。不过，要是在伦敦也没什么有头有脸的人物可见，或者当朴实无华的百叶窗遮住了梅费尔还有贝尔格拉维亚区那让人反感的外观，那就另当别论。即便在罗斯郡的塞尔登城堡，她也无聊得要命，在巴黎或维也纳，也成天提不起精神。她是个不折不扣的伦敦佬。可是，我那和蔼可亲的舅嫂鬼使神差地爱上了南蒂罗尔区这个地方。她想在那片郁郁葱葱的草木间平平淡淡地过日子。人们正在采摘葡萄，南瓜挂在墙上，攀缘植物从灰白而古雅的墙头垂下，像是给墙披了件深红色的外衣；这里的一切都如同伯恩·琼斯[18]的梦境般美丽（我知道，自己提到伯恩·琼斯很合时宜，尤其是和罗马风格的建筑联系到一起时，因为我曾听到我们那亦敌亦友的爱德华·伯尔派罗博士对此地大肆称赞过）。因此，这样一来，艾米莉亚竟能喜欢上这个地方，这也许是情理之中的事了。此外，她也很大程度上受西塞琳的影响，西塞琳信誓旦旦地说，全欧洲没有哪个地方冬天的气候能像梅兰这么好。这一点我可不同意。因为下午三点，太阳就落山了，在一二月份，猛烈的暖风会在雪面上吹起一股潮气。

虽然这样，艾米莉亚还是派西塞琳向酒店的人打听一下这些破败的城堡市价几何，再打听打听附近有多少符合条件的城堡此刻在售。西塞琳带着一个写得满满的、精准可靠、非常特别的单子回来了，又花言巧语了一番，即便让老约翰·罗宾斯听到，也定会满心欢喜。这些城堡个个都景致如画，都是罗马风格，都爬满了常春藤，都宽敞明亮，都有历史底蕴，并且其主人都是出身高贵的伯爵以及声誉卓著的男爵。大部分城堡都曾举办过知名的赛事，其中一些还举办过神圣的罗马皇帝的盛大婚礼；每个都牵扯到一些绝妙一流的凶杀案。闹不闹鬼，可以根据要求安排；要是再适当加点钱，还可以有护城河，另外免费赠送徽章。

在这些所有让人心驰神往的城堡中，我们最喜欢的两座是普兰塔城堡和莱本斯坦城堡。我们驾车从它们旁边经过，说真的，甚至连我自己也被它们深深吸引。（另外，还有一个原因，当购买这么一大宗物品时，一位穷似乞丐的秘书也总有机会做做工作，给自己赚点回扣。）我觉得，从外面看，普兰塔堡最为震撼，有着莱茵河一般雄伟的塔楼，常春藤枝干粗壮多瘤，看起来似乎比哈布斯堡王朝还要久远；但据说，莱本斯坦堡内部保存较好，各方面都更适合现代居家，它那楼梯前前后后被七千位业余爱好者拍过照。

我们拿到了参观的门票，是得力助手西塞琳替我们买的。这样，我们在一个风和日丽的下午就驾车出发了，打算去看普兰塔城堡，这是西塞林的建议。不过我们在半路改了主意，因为天气很不错，我们就沿着长长的缓坡上山，去看莱本斯坦城堡。我必须得提一句，沿路驾车从这些宅第中间穿梭而过，真是再惬意不过了。城堡孤独地屹立在一堆石块，或者说峭壁上（就像意大利画作中的天使长圣米迦勒那般泰然自若），从各个方向都能俯瞰到自家茂盛的葡萄园。峡谷两旁是些栗树，埃施这片谷地如画一般在脚下延展开来。

顺便说一句，光是这些葡萄园就是一份相当不错的产业；这些葡萄园产出一种香醇的红酒，出口到波尔多，在那儿以蒙尼维酒庄的名义装瓶，作为年份红酒售卖。查尔斯对于自己种葡萄酿酒这一想法陶醉不已。

“在这儿，”他向艾米莉亚高声说道，“咱们是确确实实坐在自家的葡萄树和无花果树下！多么美好的闲居之处！我是受够了针线街[19]的喧嚣了。”

我们敲了敲门——因为没有门铃，只有一个笨重、老式的锻铁门环。这种中世纪的风格真让人心醉！我们了解到，莱本斯坦伯爵最近过世，他儿子，也就是现在的伯爵，这位年轻的富豪，从他母亲家里继承了一座位于萨尔茨堡更为古老、更为宏伟的城堡，于是打算出售这份较为偏远的产业，来给自己买艘游艇，这股潮流当前在德国还有奥地利的贵族绅士们中方兴未艾。

一位高贵的仆人给我们开了门，穿着古朴、体面的制服。精致典雅的大厅，先人的盔甲套装，蒂罗尔狩猎者的战利品，古代伯爵的盾徽——这些东西刚好满足了艾米莉亚对贵族、罗马遗风的神往。整座城堡按照目前的样子原封不动进行出售，包括先人们留下的这些东西。

我们穿过接待室，房间高高耸立，引人入胜，看起来光彩夺目，再加上那些雅致的罗马风格的窗户、纤细的顶柱、古雅的圆顶拱门，就更显得如此。查尔斯爵士下定了决心。“我必须并且一定会得到它！”他大声说道，“这才是我想要的地方。塞尔登，哼，塞尔登不过是个惹人厌的现代品。”

我们能不能见一见高贵的伯爵？那身着制服的仆人（略显高傲地）说，他会去问一下他尊贵的主人。查尔斯递上自己还有凡德里夫特夫人的名片，这些外国人明白，在英国，头衔就意味着金钱。

他猜对了。两分钟后，伯爵手持名片进来了。他是位相貌堂堂的年轻人，嘴巴上方留着蒂罗尔这一带典型的黑长胡须，一身依照本国服饰改装的绅士行头。他一副打猎的派头，一根常见的黑雄松鸡的羽毛插在圆锥形帽子（他拿在手上）的一侧，欢快地抖动着。这追随的是奥地利普遍的流行时尚。

他招手示意我们坐下，我们就坐了下来。他用法语同我们交谈，脸上挂着和善的笑容，说自己不怎么说英语。他继续道，说我们可以说英语，他听起来没有任何问题，但如果我们同意，他想用法语或德语回答我们。

“法语吧。”查尔斯答道，商谈就继续用法语进行。除了英语，还有他祖先的荷兰语之外，这是我那内兄唯一能用来和一位点头之交交谈的语言了。

我们称赞这儿的美景。伯爵面露喜色，流露出一股民族自豪感。的确，这儿挺漂亮，这青翠漂亮的蒂罗尔是属于他自己的。他为之感到自豪，也十分喜爱这个地方。他之所以能狠下心把这块父辈们的家园卖掉，是因为他在萨尔茨卡默古特有一个更好的地方，在因斯布鲁克附近有个临时住所。蒂罗尔这里只是少了一点乐趣——大海，而他又对游艇痴迷，于是决定出售此处地产。再者，毕竟三处乡下房产、一艘游艇、维也纳一处庄园，这么多地方，他一个人也住不过来。

“一点不错！”查尔斯答道，“要是你我能就此处漂亮的地产达成协议，我就把自己在苏格兰高地的宅邸卖掉。”他努力使自己看起来像位自豪的苏格兰酋长正对着族人慷慨陈词。

接着他们转入正题。和那位伯爵做买卖十分愉快，他的言谈举止无可挑剔。我们正谈着，一个板着脸的家伙，约莫是招待员之类的，突然走进房间，用德语跟他说什么事情，我们谁也听不懂。他对这位愠怒的仆人举止中流露出的罕见的风度和慈爱，让我们大为触动。很明显，他在向这家伙解释我们是谁，并十分温和地斥责他不应该打搅我们。那位管家会意后，显然为自己的无礼态度感到抱歉，因为他说了几句话之后就出去了，边说边鞠躬，还用德语客气地解释了一番。伯爵转向我们，微笑着说：“我们国家的人同你们苏格兰的农民很像——热心肠，有个性，不拘束，爱音乐，有诗才。不过，嗯，对待陌生人，需要再多些礼貌。”要是他的这种说法成立，那他自己绝对是个例外，因为自打进门的那一刻起，我们就感到宾至如归。

他坦诚地报出了自己的价格。他在梅兰的律师手里有些必要的文件，他们会同我们安排具体的商谈。不得不说，这个要价太高了——高得离谱，不过话又说回来，他为一座顶呱呱的城堡开出了个顶呱呱的价格。“他早晚会把价格降下来的，”查尔斯说道，“在所有的交易中，第一次出的价都只是想试探你一下。他们知道我是百万富翁，别人总觉得百万富翁浑身上下全都是钱。”

我得补充一句，别人总觉得从百万富翁身上榨出点钱，肯定要比从别人身上弄出点钱容易——而事实恰恰相反，要不然他们怎么会攒出自己那份百万家产呢？他们不是像树上渗出树胶那样往外冒金子，而是像吸墨纸那样把金子吸得一干二净，却几乎再也不吐出来。

在这第一次会面之后，我们驾车回府，非常满意。价格太高了，不过双方已经做了初步的安排，至于其余的细节问题，伯爵希望我们去和他在林登大道的律师们商谈。我们也打听了这些律师，了解到他们极为德高望重，他们这份家族事业已经延续了七代人，买卖双方的生意都做。

他们给我们看了看房屋平面图，还有地契，一切都按部就班。在谈到价格之前，一切都进行得十分顺利。

不过，这些律师在价格问题上很执拗。他们坚持伯爵第一次的要价，一个子儿也不降。那估价相当高，我们的商谈进展很慢，有些僵持，最后查尔斯终于受不了了，发了脾气。

“西，他们知道我是百万富翁，”他说道，“想故技重施来诈我一把。我才不吃这一套。这世上除了克雷上校，还没有谁能宰过我一把。我会像这与世无争的大山深处那岩羚羊一样任人宰割吗？休想！”接着，他静静地想了一会儿，最后，若有所思地讲道，“西，问题是，他们果真没什么恶意吗？知不知道，我现在开始觉得，这世上再也没有最初的那份纯真了。这位蒂罗尔的伯爵十分清楚每一块钱的价值，好像他在卡佩尔厅和金伯利混过似的。[20]”

事情就这样拖拖拉拉了一两周，没有任何结果。我们压低价格，律师们则坚持原价。查尔斯开始对这笔荒唐的买卖有点厌烦。要我说，我敢保证，要是那位尊贵的伯爵再不加快点进度，我那位可敬的内兄很快就会对整个蒂罗尔心生厌烦，到时候哪怕峰顶的城堡再迷人，也勾不起他的半点兴趣。可惜，伯爵没有意识到这一点。他到酒店来拜访我们——对于陌生人而言，蒂罗尔这些上流的高傲贵族的造访，是极其难得的荣耀——甚至拿出最友好的姿态，未提前打招呼就进来了。不过当谈到价钱时，他又固执得不行。哪怕降一个子儿，他都不愿意。

“你不知道，”他傲慢地说，“我们蒂罗尔的绅士不是什么商人，也不是什么店铺老板。我们说一不二，不讨价还价。假如你是奥地利人，还想试图砍价的话，这就太欠考虑了，我会觉得你是在侮辱我。不过，你来自一个伟大的商业国度——”他鼻子哼了一声，突然打住，同情地耸了耸肩。

好几次我们见他驾车从城堡里进进出出，每次他都优雅地向我们挥挥手。但我们每次砍价，结果都一样：他总会拿自己的蒂罗尔贵族身份做挡箭牌。要么买下，要么走人。这可是莱本斯坦城堡。

律师们也好不到哪儿去。我们用尽浑身解数，却还在原地踏步。

查尔斯对此事感到厌烦，最终放弃了。如我所料，他也烦得慌。“这是我这辈子见到的最美的地方，”他说，“不过，西，去他妈的，谁也别想宰我一把。”

现在已经到了十二月，他于是决定回伦敦。我们第二天又碰到了伯爵，便拦住了他的马车，向他说了我们的打算。查尔斯本以为这会立刻让那家伙清醒过来，但他只是扬了扬插着黑雄松鸡羽毛的帽子，漠然一笑，答道：“卡尔大公目前也正打听本宅。”说罢便扬长而去。

查尔斯说了几句难听的话，我在此也就不转述了（家丑不可外扬），我们于是就这样回了英国。

在接下来的两个月里，艾米莉亚除了对伯爵不愿把莱本斯坦城堡卖给我们这事表示遗憾，我们几乎没听过她说过其他的事情。那座城堡的尖顶将她的心刺得好痛。说来也怪，她一如既往地迷恋着那城堡。她在蒂罗尔时想得到它，并且觉得一定会得到；现在感觉得不到了，但她的灵魂（要是她有的话）却还疯狂地扑在上面。另外，西塞琳稍稍向她暗示说——也是她在酒店信使的饭桌上偶然听到的——那伯爵根本不急着把这份祖传的历史遗产卖给南非的钻石大王。他觉得，考虑到家族的荣耀，他至少也得找一位出身于古老望族的有钱买主。这番话进一步点燃了她的欲望。

不过，二月的一天早上，艾米莉亚从弓街回来，满脸的兴奋与笑容（查尔斯见她衣带渐紧，就让她骑骑马，瘦瘦腰身）。

“你猜，我看到谁在公园里骑马？”她说道，“哈，莱本斯坦伯爵。”

“不可能。”查尔斯说，有点怀疑。

“千真万确。”艾米莉亚答道。

“你肯定看错了。”查尔斯大声说道。

但艾米莉亚坚持说自己没看走眼，并且还派了人到伦敦的律师那里——就是林登大道上那家祖传的公司曾提到的他们在英国的代理律师——不断地打听伯爵的行踪。据了解，伯爵现在就在伦敦，住在莫利酒店。

“我明白了，”查尔斯大声说，“他意识到自己犯了个错误，现在到这儿来，打算重新谈判一下。”

我极力主张要耐心等待，要让伯爵主动找上门，便说：“不要让他看出你的迫切心理。”但艾米莉亚现在的那股迫切劲儿，捂也捂不住。她坚持说，查尔斯应当去拜访一下伯爵，不为别的，就为了回馈伯爵在蒂罗尔的殷勤接待。

伯爵还是那么风度翩翩，愉快地向我们讲述着在伦敦碰到的古怪事儿。他非常乐意第二天同查尔斯共进晚餐，还向凡德里夫特夫人以及“芬特霍斯”夫人致以诚挚的问候。

他同我们吃了饭，就像一家人一样。艾米莉亚的厨子还真有两下子。大约半夜了，查尔斯在台球室又旧事重提。看到在这个有着五百万人口的大都市的花花世界中，我们竟然还满心惦记着他那心爱的莱本斯坦城堡，伯爵大为感动。

“明天到我律师那里来，”他说，“咱们到时候谈谈这件事。”

我们去了——那是一家相当体面的事务所，位于南安普顿街，里面都是些来自古老家族的律师。他们为过世的伯爵经办业务也有年头了，那位伯爵曾从祖母那里继承了一些位于爱尔兰的地产。能获得伯爵后人的信任，他们也倍感荣幸。当然，他们也乐于结识查尔斯·凡德里夫特这样的金融界大亨，于是便急迫地（搓着双手）要把事情的方方面面安排得让大家都满意。（读者们也明白，这样就可以同两个有头有脸的家族攀上些关系了。）

查尔斯出了个价，告知了他的律师。

伯爵把价格抬了抬，不过比以前降了些，剩下的就交给双方的律师去打理了。他说，自己当过兵，是位绅士，他一边说一边跟其他蒂罗尔人一样，把自己那高贵的头扬了扬，他打算把那些细枝末节留给代理人来处理。

由于我真心急于给艾米莉亚帮个忙，于是第二天在莫利酒店的台阶上，碰巧遇到了伯爵（碰巧，是对伯爵而言，我为了碰到他，在特拉法尔加广场晃悠了半个小时）。我小心谨慎地向他解释道，我能在很大程度上影响查尔斯，要是我说句话——我突然打住。他茫然地盯着我。

“佣金？”最终他试探道，略微一笑，有些古怪。

“这个嘛，不能说是佣金，”我回答，有些回避，“不过帮你说句好话，你也明白。礼尚往来嘛！”

他十分不解，从头到脚仔细地打量我一番。当时，我担心这位蒂罗尔贵族会抬脚走人。但紧接着，我意识到查尔斯说得对，人们最初的纯真已经从这地球上消失了，去了别的地方。

他报了自己的最低价。“芬特霍斯先生，”他说道，“我是蒂罗尔的庄园主，我自己本人是不会过问佣金、回扣这类事情的。不过，要是你能在查尔斯身边吹吹风——你我都懂的，对不对？咱们作为绅士之交——我会送你一份小小的礼物——肯定不是金钱——不管你诱使他出什么价，我会把高出他今天出价那部分的百分之五，以珠宝的形式给你。——咱们就这么定了？”

“通常都是百分之十。”我低声道。

他此时又变得如同奥地利骑兵一般。“要么百分之五，先生——要么一分都没有！”

我鞠了一躬，退后一步。“好，百分之五就百分之五，”我答道，“就权当为阁下您效劳了。”

毕竟秘书能做许多事情。说到价钱的问题，有艾米莉亚的帮助，再加上伊莎贝尔和西塞琳的支援，我毫不费力地就说服查尔斯，让他接受了伯爵要的那个更为合理的价格。南安普顿街的这些人，对于波尔多市场上红酒的价值知晓一些实情，这让此事最终板上钉钉。一两周以后，一切都商量妥当。我和查尔斯如约在南安普顿街同伯爵会面，看着他在莱本斯坦城堡的地契上签名，加盖印章，然后交付给我们。我内兄则把购房款交到了伯爵的手中，给的是画线支票，收款的是伦敦一家极好的公司，支票的抬头就是这位高贵的伯爵。之后，查尔斯想着自己成了莱本斯坦城堡的主人，便得意地离开了。对我而言，更为重要的是，第二天一早我收到了一张寄过来的百分之五的佣金的支票，不过令人遗憾的是，由于有些误解，付款的是同一家银行，抬头写的就是我本人，签的是伯爵的名字。里面还附有一张短笺，说现在事情已经圆满完成，他觉得他向我许诺的金额还是直接付现钱为好。

我立刻将支票兑现了，对此事只字未提，甚至对伊莎贝尔也没说。我的经验是，佣金回扣这些复杂的事情，不适宜掏心窝子讲给妇人听。

尽管现在是三月底，议院还在开会，查尔斯却坚持说我们所有人都必须马上动身去接管我们那宏伟的蒂罗尔城堡。艾米莉亚也早已急不可耐，摆出一副伯爵夫人的架子。我们乘东方快车一直抵达慕尼黑，接着经由布伦纳抵达梅兰，当晚在约翰大公爵酒店住下。尽管我们早已发电报说会过来，料想会引起些许轰动，不过我们一点轰动的迹象都没看到。第二天一早，我们就驾车隆重前往城堡，投进自家葡萄树还有无花果树的怀抱。

在门口，我们碰到了那个板着脸的仆人。“我要让他滚蛋，”查尔斯低声道，他已是莱本斯坦的主人了，“我觉得他看着太苦大仇深了，从没见过如此无礼的人！也不笑一笑欢迎我！”

他走上台阶，那位板着脸的男子则走上前，用德语低声咕哝了几句。查尔斯把他拨到一边，继续向前走。接下来的事情让人有些摸不着头脑，双方都有些误会。那位板着脸的男子拼命地叫唤仆人把我们轰出去。过了许久，我们才逐渐知道真相：那位板着脸的男子才是真正的莱本斯坦伯爵。

那位留着小胡子的伯爵又是谁呢？我们现在才渐渐回过神来。又是克雷上校！他胆子可比之前大多了！

事情的真相逐渐浮出水面。我们第一天参观城堡时，他就紧跟在我们后面，对仆人说，是和我们一伙的，并在接待室同我们会合。我们问真正的伯爵，他为什么要同那位不请自入的人说话，他用法语解释道，那名留有小胡子的男子说，我内兄是一位了不起的南非百万富翁，而自己则是我们的向导兼翻译。这样一来，那男子便同真正的伯爵，还有伯爵在梅兰的律师频频接触，几乎每天都驱车前往城堡。城堡的主人一开始出了价，并一直坚持这个价。他现在还是坚持这个价，要是查尔斯爵士打算把莱本斯坦再买一次的话，他也乐于拱手让出。至于他在伦敦的律师是怎么被骗的，伯爵本人也毫不知情。他对此事感到惋惜，并（冷冷地）向我们道了声早安。

事已至此，我们也只好回到约翰大公爵酒店，个个垂头丧气，提不起精神，我们给伦敦警方发了封电报，详细说明了事件的经过。

我同查尔斯赶紧奔往英国去探寻那无赖的下落。在南安普顿街，我们找到了那家律师事务所，他们不但毫不愧疚，反而很生气，因为我们居然以这种方式来骗他们。骗子用莱本斯坦的信笺从梅兰给他们写信，说他即将到伦敦，同知名的百万富翁查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士商量城堡及周围财产的出售事宜。查尔斯爵士当面一口承认他就是真正的莱本斯坦伯爵。事务所的人从未见过当时的那位伯爵，但凭着查尔斯爵士的明确指认，也就全盘相信了骗子的话。他带来了一些极其精心伪造的文件——原件的复制品——他冒充我们的向导兼翻译，完全有机会在梅兰的律师那里检验查证这些原件。这是一场精心策划的骗局，令人惊讶的是，它居然成功了。不过，这一切都怪我们轻信了城堡大厅中蓄有长胡子的男子的一面之词，认为他就是莱本斯坦伯爵。

他进来时，手里拿着我们的名片，不过当时仆人并没有把名片给他，给的是真正的伯爵。这也是整个事件中一个未解的谜团。

晚上有两封信送到了查尔斯的住所，一封是我的，一封是查尔斯的。查尔斯的信内容如下：

尊敬的无能阁下：

我仅仅是勉强得手！一点小失算差点让我功亏一篑。我相信，你那天准备要去普兰塔城堡，而不是去莱本斯坦城堡，只是在半路上你改变了主意，这可差点把我的整个计划都搞砸了。

幸好，我及时发现了这一点，便走了条捷径，急急忙忙赶在你之前抵达，接着我说了自己的身份。不过比这更糟的是，突然有人闯了进来，就是被我冒用了名字和头衔的那位伯爵。不过，天助勇者，你一点德语都不懂，这救了我一把。剩下的也都没什么值得一提的了，几乎是水到渠成。

你奉上的这些支票，我却之不恭，也请允许我送你一件大有裨益、价值连城的礼物，聊表寸心——一本德语词汇、语法和短语书！

吻你的手。

曾经的，

凡·莱本斯坦

另一封短笺是给我的，内容如下：

亲爱的、好心的昏特霍斯：

哈哈哈！我只是把你的名字“温特沃斯”念成“芬特沃斯”，就把你骗了！虽然有点头脑的人都知道外国人发“TH”这个音比发“W”更难，可我还是在说你名字中的“斯”这个字时冒了点险。不过，俗话说，结果好，一切都好。现在我可是抓住了你，上天把你送到了我的手中，亲爱的朋友——还是你自己主动找上门来的。我手上有张支票，有你的背书，在我的开户行兑的现，可以说算是我手中一个“把柄”吧，为的是让你以后老实一点。要是你以后认出了我，把我出卖给你老板，就是那个一本正经的老浑蛋，记住，我就会向他揭发此事，连带着你一起揭发。所以，咱们现在是在同一条船上。我本来没有想到这条妙计，是你启发了我，我不过是顺势而为罢了。我付了你那么一点佣金，却能保证你今后不再乱说话，这钱不是花得也值了吗？现在就把你的嘴堵住了，就价钱看，也算便宜。

你亲爱的同道中人、铁杆无赖兄弟，

库斯伯特·克雷上校

查尔斯放下信，发了一通牢骚。“西，谁给你写的信？”他问道。

“一位女士写的。”我答道。

他怀疑地盯着我。“哦，我还以为是同一个人的手笔。”他说着，目光已将我刺穿。

“不是的，”我答道，“莫蒂默夫人写的。”不过，说真的，我有些发抖。

他顿了一下，深叹一口气，继续问道：“你在这家伙的银行那儿详细地询问过了？”

“嗯，问过了，”我立刻接过话（在这方面我极其小心，你也知道，怕他发现佣金的事情），“他们说，那个冒牌的凡·莱本斯坦伯爵，是由南安普顿街的一些人引荐给他们的，同以前一样，钱是从莱本斯坦的账户上取走的，所以他们一点疑心都没起。你也知道，像这种级别的闯荡世界的无赖，还带着你们双方的证件，自然能骗过所有人。银行连他的身份都没有正式地核实，有那家事务所就够了。他是过来存钱，不是往外取。就在两天后才把余额取走，说是要急着回维也纳。”

他会不会要账户的明细呢？说实话，这一刻十分尴尬。不过，此时他满心懊丧，哪儿还有心思顾及账户的事情。他向后躺在安乐椅上，双手插在衣兜里，两腿直直地搭在前面的挡板上，一副沮丧至极的表情。

过了一两分钟，他捅了捅炉火，若有所思地说道：“西，那人的本事也够大的！我发誓，我都钦佩他了。有时，我想——”他突然打住，犹豫了一下。

“想什么？”我问道。

“有时，真想……让他加入克罗地多普·戈尔康达董事会。他会在伦敦打造出些了不起的集团来！”

我站了起来，严肃地盯着我那胡思乱想的内兄。

“查尔斯，”我说，“你疯了？你经历了太多的克雷上校的事件，这已经影响了你明晰、卓越的心智。有些话，不管多么真实，也不是一位自重的金融家应该讲出口的，哪怕是在自己的房间，没有外人，讲给最亲密的朋友、最信任的顾问也不行。”

查尔斯已经完全垮了，禁不住哭出声来。“你说得对，西，太对了。原谅我这一时的冲动。动情时，有时也顾不得其他，就把真话吐出来了。”

我不愿乘人之危，甚至都没利用这个得天独厚的机会，让他给我涨涨薪水。

第五章　打成平手

八月十二日，我们同往常一样待在罗斯郡的塞尔登城堡。十一日早上，不论天气是晴是雨，不论议院是否开会，也不管那些十万火急的指令，查尔斯一定要离开伦敦，这缘于他不安分的天性。十二日拂晓，他定会在荒野上不遗余力地猎幼鸟，只要不犯法，能多早开始就多早开始。

他就像扫罗和大卫[21]一样，勇往直前，杀死千千万万，满屋的枪支供他使用，最后养鸟人提醒他，松鸡也已经打得够多了。此时，他觉得自己这方面的“工作”也完成得差不多了，于是就在大获全胜之后迅速抽身，去布莱顿，去尼斯，去蒙特卡洛或者其他地方。他必须要一直“跋涉”。他要是去世了，我想，他也一定不会老老实实地在坟墓里安息，他的鬼魂会在全世界游荡，吓吓那些老妇人。

“在塞尔登，”他步入普耳曼卧车时，叹了口气，对我说，“至少我不会碰到那个骗子！”

实际上，他刚刚稍微有点厌倦了每天都要紧绷神经的日子，便发现了一笔送到嘴边的小生意，这也暂时让他不再去想什么克雷上校、他的同伙，还有他们一起干的那些好事儿！

我得提一句，就在那年夏天，查尔斯在非洲德兰士瓦边境处购得一块不错的土地，据说出产黄金。不管它以前有没有黄金，现在查尔斯把它弄到手了，就凭这一点，它怎么都会出产黄金。这世上还没有谁能像查尔斯那样，有点石成金的真本事：不管什么，一经他手，即使不会变成钻石，也起码会变成黄金。因此，当我内兄刚从当地卖主（一位名叫蒙特索瓦德的德高望重的酋长）手中购得这块土地，督促自己的一家公司进行开发时，他在当地的一个死对头克雷盖拉奇勋爵（曾经的大卫·亚历山大·格兰顿爵士）也立即购入了一块类似的土地，紧挨着查尔斯，那块地的大部分地质状况同查尔斯的那块别无二致。

结果没让我们失望。一两个月以后，当时我们还在塞尔登，当地的探矿者给我们写了一封鼓舞人心的长信。他们一直在那儿寻找金矿矿脉，告诉我们在地块的一角，发现了一条很好的金矿岩脉，掘地即可得；不过，可惜只有几码在查尔斯的地界内，其余的全在当地称作克雷盖拉奇勋爵的地块上。

信中还说，还好我们的探矿人员很机智，虽然小格兰顿先生也在探矿，就在离他们不远的同一条矿脉上，但他们的那些探矿人员没有发现这些含金石英，于是我们的人对此三缄其口，秘而不宣，等着查尔斯本人来处理此事。

“能不能说土地边界有争议？”我问。

“不行，”查尔斯答道，“要知道，边界是按照经线来画的，这没办法变，我们不能矢口否认。想变更经线，总不能把太阳也买下来吧？总不能贿赂一下测量器具吧？再说了，那是我们自己画的边界。办法只有一个了，西，联合，两家联合起来！”

查尔斯的脑子可真好使！他说到“联合”这个词时，那语气语调听起来如同诗歌般悦耳。

“太妙了！”我答道，“别透露一点风声，立刻和克雷盖拉奇联手。”

查尔斯闭了一只眼，若有所思。

就在当天晚上，我们在当地的首席工程师发来密电：“小格兰顿不知何故动身回家，我们怀疑他已知晓一切，不过我们还未将此秘密向任何人透露。”

“西摩，”我内兄郑重地说道，“时不我待！我必须今晚就得写信给大卫爵士——我指的是那位尊敬的勋爵。你知不知道他现在何处？”

“两三天前的《晨报》上说，他在格兰拉奇。”我答道。

“那我就请他过来，一同商量这件事，”我内兄继续道，“他们说那条矿脉资源非常丰富，我一定要分一杯羹。”

我们走进书房，查尔斯给他的商业对手草拟了一封——我不得不说——极为高明的信件。他在信中指出，这个国家的矿藏有可能很丰富，但目前还不能确定，说碎石和研磨的成本也许会让人望而却步；获取燃料的费用也很高，并且运输不便；还说水也匮乏，并且还都在我们这边。还说你我两家公司万一要是碰巧真的发现了矿石，就会建起两套冶炼炉或泵站，各自引水过来，而实际上，一套足矣。这样一来，双方都会元气大伤。总之——引用那句金玉良言——双方联合起来，也许比彼此竞争来得好。并且，他还建议，至少双方应该就这个问题进行一次会谈。

我替他把信写好，他拿出克伦威尔[22]那副不可一世的派头，在上面署了名。

“这封信十分要紧，西，”他说，“最好还是寄挂号信，以免落入小人之手。不要给多布森，让西塞琳带着信坐马车到弗里斯寄出去。”

尽管我们在塞尔登能看到全苏格兰最美的峡湾，不过它有一点不便之处：离火车站有十二英里之远。

西塞琳按照指示接过信件——那姑娘，可是一位不可多得的帮手！在这段时间里，我们从第二天的《晨报》中得知，小格兰顿已经比我们抢先了一步。我们的眼线给我们发出密电的同时，他已经从非洲赶回来了，并且立刻在格兰拉奇同他父亲碰了头。

两天后，我们收到了对方十分客气的回复，内容如下：

克雷盖拉奇度假屋，格兰拉奇，因弗内斯郡

尊敬的查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士：

阁下二十日信件已收悉，万分感谢。阁下之意，南非之事，不应使之损伤你我双方利益，此等好意，鄙人鼎力赞同。阁下建议你我双方面谈，共同商讨联合之可能，万分歉意，日前敝处有诸客造访——想必阁下亦是如此——故实不能离开格兰拉奇。所幸，犬子从金伯利归来，暂休在家，乐意前往讨教，聆听阁下高见。阁下安排，宜顾全双方利益，亦是鄙人之意。小儿于明日午后抵达塞尔登，全权代理鄙人及其余诸位董事代为协商事宜。亦向尊夫人及令郎问安。

您忠诚的，

克雷盖拉奇

“狡猾的老狐狸！”查尔斯鼻子哼了一声，高声说道，“他现在想干吗？西，他和我们一样，也急于同我们联合。”他突然冒出个念头，抬头大声说道：“你知不知道，我真觉得，我们这两家探矿的肯定都在做同样的事情。他们也肯定在我们的地皮下面发现了矿脉，于是这个老浑蛋想就此骗我们一把！”

“就像我们要骗他一样。”我斗胆插了一句。

查尔斯一动不动地盯着我，顿了一下，低声道：“虽然只有和他们联起手来，告诉他们我们的发现之后，我们才能知道他们在哪儿发现了矿藏。不过，要是这样的话，双方的运气都还不错。不过，不管怎么看，都划得来。虽说这样，我还是要留心——一定要留心。”

待我们把这件事的原委告知艾米莉亚后，她叫道：“真够讨厌的！我猜我们得留他住一晚——我敢说，他绝对是个居心叵测、骨瘦如柴、肤浅的苏格兰人。”

星期三下午，约莫三点钟，小格兰顿到了。他面目清秀，红色的头发，浅黄褐色的络腮胡子，极像他父亲。不过，奇怪的是，他只是过来拜访，没带任何行李。

“怎么没有行李？你不会打算今晚再回到格兰拉奇去吧？”查尔斯吃惊地问道，“这样的话，凡德里夫特夫人就太失望了！再说，这事也不是坐火车一来一回中间这点时间能商量妥的，是不是，格兰顿先生？”

小格兰顿微微一笑，他笑起来平易近人——精明，但很坦率。

“噢，不是的，”他坦诚地说道，“我没打算回去，我们已经在旅店安顿好了。我妻子也过来了，你也知道——嗯，之前没收到你们的邀请。”

我们把这段话讲给艾米莉亚听，她觉得大卫·格兰顿之所以不愿住在塞尔登，是因为他是位有头有脸的人物；伊莎贝尔则认为，原因在于他娶了一位不知南非哪个地方的姑娘，上不了厅堂；查尔斯觉得，他是和我们有利益冲突一方的代表，要是住在竞争公司董事长的家中，有可能谈判时会有所拘束；而我则觉得，他之前听说过这地方，心里十分清楚，这是全苏格兰地区最无趣的乡下宅院。

不管怎样，小格兰顿坚持住在克罗默蒂·阿姆斯旅店，不过他说，要是凡德里夫特夫人，还有温特沃斯夫人能前去他们的住处小坐一下，他的妻子定会万分高兴。于是我们同他一起回到旅店，把格兰顿夫人接到塞尔登城堡喝了下午茶。

她身材娇小，长相俊俏，十分害羞怕人，俨然一位淑女，绝非登不上厅堂之辈。她每说完一句话，都会咯咯一笑，眼睛微微眯着，仿佛让自己显得更略为俏皮一些。南非以外的事，她知之甚少，不过对于南非的事，她口若悬河。虽然有些不敢正眼看人，但她的率性天真，让我们每个人都很喜欢。

第二天早晨，我和查尔斯同小格兰顿正式商讨双方土地的有关事宜。谈的全是什么氰化法、反应炉、本尼威特、水套之类的。没过多久，我们也渐渐意识到，别看他留着红头发，表现出一副天真的样子，我们的这位大卫·格兰顿阁下对这方面还是略懂一二的。他巧妙地让我们逐渐意识到，克雷盖拉奇勋爵派他来是为公司谋利益，可他却是为自己的利益而来。

“查尔斯爵士，我是小儿子，”他说，“所以得为自己谋点好处。我也是个明白人。在这件事上，我的建议会潜移默化地影响到我父亲的决定。你我都深谙世事。现在，咱们言归正传。你打算双方合并，你肯定掌握了一些对我父亲公司有利的消息——比如，我们的土地上发现了矿脉——你想通过合并来据为己有，否则你肯定不会这么做。这么说吧，我能实现你的计划，也可以毁了它。你要是让我觉得不虚此行，我会劝诱我父亲还有各位董事同意合并。否则，我一点忙也不帮。我要说的就这么多！”

查尔斯十分欣赏地望着他。

“年轻人，”他说，“你可真有城府——就你的年龄来说，城府可够深的。你这番话算是坦诚相见了，还是另有他意？你说的话可当真？你是不是知道了为什么这么做符合你父亲和我彼此的利益？你是不是在试图破坏我的计划？”他用手指揉搓着下巴，继续道，“我要是知道这些，我就知道该怎么对付你了。”

小格兰顿又笑了笑，说道：“查尔斯爵士，你是位金融家，你在人生的这把年纪居然还问自己的同行，问他是努力让自己的钱袋子鼓起来呢，还是让他父亲的钱袋子鼓起来！我父亲的一切最终都会留给他的大儿子——可我，是他最小的儿子。”

“总的来看，你说的也对，”查尔斯十分亲切地答道，“合情合理，自圆其说。不过，我怎么知道你没有像今天这样同你父亲讨价还价？你们有可能早就商量妥当，想联起手来骗我。”

那位年轻人摆出一副直话直说的姿态，身子前倾，说道：“听好了，我给了你这次机会。要么抓住它，要么咱们别谈。你愿不愿意花钱请我促成这宗合并？按照我父亲的那块地对于你的净值给我一些适当的佣金——大体的数额我也知道。”

“那就百分之五吧。”我试探道，自己也不能总在一边干看着。

他上上下下打量我一番，答道：“通常是百分之十。”说话的语气有些怪，还莫名其妙地瞪了我一眼。

我的天！我倒吸了一口凉气！我知道他说的这话是什么意思，这就是我曾经对克雷上校说的话，一字未变。当时他冒充莱本斯坦伯爵，我们谈到城堡的价钱时说的这番话——就是这种口音。我现在全明白了。那张该死的支票！眼前的这个人就是克雷上校，他想让我闭嘴、为虎作伥，否则就要揭发我。

我心惊胆战，不知怎么回答。那场谈话接下来说了什么，我真的不知道了。我的大脑不停地运转，只是隐约听到一句“燃料”还有“还原反应”之类的。我到底该怎么办？要是我对查尔斯说，有点怀疑这个人——仅仅是怀疑——他就会回头咬我一口，把支票的事儿兜出来，这足以让我身败名裂。要是不说，我担心查尔斯会认为我同他是一伙的，是共犯。

这次会谈的时间太长了，我都不知道自己是怎么熬过去的。最后，小格兰顿（要是他真的是小格兰顿的话）心满意足地起身离去，艾米莉亚还邀请了他和夫人一起到城堡共进晚餐。

别的不说，同他们的相处还是挺愉快的。他们在克罗默蒂·阿姆斯旅店又多住了三天。查尔斯同小格兰顿不停地商谈讨论，他拿不定主意究竟该怎么做，我也是爱莫能助。我此生从未身处如此两难的境地，只能尽力保持绝对的中立。

小格兰顿极其随和，他那位羞怯、率真的妻子也是如此。当得知艾米莉亚在德班没碰到过她母亲时，她竟然天真地对此大惊小怪。她们二人相谈甚欢，说了许多彼此感兴趣的事情——主要是关于克雷盖拉奇这帮人的不是。另外，小格兰顿游泳不错，他和我们一起坐船出海，潜起水来就像海豹一样。当他得知我和查尔斯都是旱鸭子时，便极其迫切地要教我俩游泳。他说，这是每位真正的英国人必备的一项技能。可是，查尔斯讨厌水；而我，凡是需要花力气的运动，都不喜欢。

不过，我们都同意他可以在峡湾替我们划船，于是，一天我们和他们夫妇二人约定第二天下午四点钟碰面。

当天晚上，查尔斯到我卧室来，神色凝重。“西，”他小声地说，“你有没有仔细观察？有没有留心注意？发没发现什么可疑的地方？”

我抖得厉害，感觉一切都完了。“怀疑谁？”我问，“你不会怀疑辛普森吧？”（他是查尔斯的贴身男仆。）

我那位备受敬重的内兄轻蔑地盯着我。

“西，”他说，“你是不是在耍我？不是他，不是辛普森，我说的是这两位年轻人。我觉得——他们俩就是克雷上校和皮卡迪特夫人。”

“怎么可能！”我叫道。

他点点头，说：“我敢肯定。”

“你怎么知道？”

“凭直觉。”

我一把抓住他的胳膊，乞求道：“查尔斯，不要贸然行事。还记不记得在伯尔派罗那件事上，那些不明事理的笨蛋是怎么讥笑你的？”

“我也考虑了，”他答道，“我得打听一下。”（查尔斯待在苏格兰做塞尔登城堡的主人时，他喜欢让自己的衣着打扮、言谈举止完完全全地符合这一身份）“明天一早，我就发电报到格兰拉奇去问问，到时候就知道这位是不是真的小格兰顿了。不过在这期间，我还是要紧盯着那家伙。”

于是，第二天一大早，查尔斯就派了个车夫去给克雷盖拉奇勋爵发电报。他先驾车到弗里斯，然后立刻把电报发出，接着等待回复。不过，由于克雷盖拉奇勋爵很有可能在收到电报前，就已经从度假屋动身去了野外，我料想当晚七八点之前是收不到回复的。此时，我们还远远不能断定眼前这人是不是冒牌的大卫·格兰顿，因此，对于这两位友好的敌手，我们仍然还得以礼相待。经历了伯尔派罗事件，我们也明白了一个道理：过分警惕有时甚至比缺乏警惕更危险。不过，因为有以前的教训，我们一直紧紧地监视着那人，相信这次他至少骗不了我们，也逃不掉。

大概四点钟，那位红头发的年轻人同他漂亮的小娇妻如约到了我们这儿来。她看起来如此迷人，双目微眯，妩媚至极，谁能想得到这种表面的单纯、天真都是装出来的呢？她同查尔斯并肩同行，步态轻盈，边走边咯咯笑个不停，眯着眼睛，这样一直走到塞尔登的船库。接着，帮她丈夫把船准备好。这时，查尔斯凑过来，小声对我说：“西，我不是什么黄毛小子，不会轻易上钩。我一直同那小姑娘聊天，我发誓，我没发现她有任何问题。她是位迷人的小妇人。我们也许错了，当然，我说的是小格兰顿。不管怎样，我们眼下最好还是客客气气的。那可是块相当重要的土地！他要真的是小格兰顿，我们绝对不能惹他不高兴，也不能让他察觉到我们在怀疑他。”

我也的确注意到，格兰顿夫人一开始就极力让自己亲近查尔斯。查尔斯有一点说的对，她羞羞怯怯、若即若离、十分迷人，让人无法抗拒。那眼神中流露的满是顽皮。

我们继续向峡湾划行，更确切地说，是格兰顿夫妇二人划船，我和查尔斯则坐在船尾，舒舒服服地斜躺在垫子上。他们划得又快又稳，不一会儿就绕过了岬角，已经看不到塞尔登城堡那伦敦风格的塔楼还有假城垛了。

格兰顿夫人划着船。即便在划船时，她也不停地暗中同查尔斯欢快地说笑，一路咯咯笑个不停，半推半就，就仿佛一个在校的女学生正同一位足以当她爷爷的男人调情。

查尔斯非常高兴，能受到异性的关注，尤其是年轻、天真、单纯的异性，他很容易就飘飘然了。世上女人的小伎俩他再清楚不过了，可是一位漂亮娇小的天真少女却能把他哄得团团转。他们一直向前划，最后划到了海鸥岛。上面尽是些参参差差、高低不平的石头，那是个礁石小岛，向海里延伸，靠近陆地的那一面十分荒凉、险峻，另一面向海里缓缓倾斜；大概有一英亩见方，灰色的崖壁陡峭地矗立着，当时上面爬满了一层厚厚的深红色的缬草。格兰顿夫人划到跟前。“多漂亮的花呀！”她扭过头，看着花，大声喊道，“真想摘一些！我们在这上岸去采花吧！查尔斯爵士，你得替我采一大束，我要放在客厅里。”

查尔斯也没多想，就满口应了下来，像是鳟鱼见到了苍蝇，会立马上钩。

“一定给你采，亲爱的姑娘，我——我看到花也是喜欢得要命。”他这话说得如同花一样漂亮，不过还挺管用。

他们把船划到岛的另一面，那里比较容易上岸。我突然感到很奇怪，他们似乎十分清楚这个小岛的情况。小格兰顿轻盈地跳上岸，他的妻子紧随其后。那位天真的姑娘直接越过船舷跳到岸上，而我和查尔斯却还在横梁上蹑手蹑脚，生怕把船踩翻了。想想我们俩笨成那样，真让人羞愧至极。她简直太像白石南花了！不过，我们最终还是安全地上了岸，开始攀石而上，寻找缬草。

接着，那两位年轻人跳回船上，随着一阵放浪的笑声，船也离岸而去，只剩下我们俩眼巴巴地望着他们。你可以想象得出，我们是怎么一副目瞪口呆的样子。

他们把船划到深水区，离岸约二十码的距离。接着，小格兰顿转过身，优雅地向我们挥挥手，说道：“再见啦！再见！希望你们能摘到一大束花！我们这就动身去伦敦啦！”

“动身！”查尔斯面如死灰，大叫道，“动身？什么意思？该不是说真要把我们俩留在这儿吧？”

小格兰顿脱帽致意，而他的妻子则边点头微笑，边用她那漂亮的小手向我们送飞吻。“是的，”他答道，“目前是这样。我们退出游戏，真正的原因是，这游戏有点太容易被识破，可谓是一次夭折的行动。”

“一次什么？”查尔斯大叫道，很明显在冒汗。

“一次夭折的行动，”那年轻人叫道，脸上露出同情的微笑，“你不知道吗？我们的计划失败了，这一招很不明智，彻底失败了。我从眼线那里得知，你今天早上让专门的信使给克雷盖拉奇勋爵发了封电报。这说明你对我已经起疑心了。要是我发现别人怀疑自己了，就再也不会向前走一步，这是我玩游戏的原则。哪怕有一丁点的疑心，那我也立即退出。只有‘病人’完全信任我时，我的计划才能完美地执行。这是医学界的金科玉律。对于那些挣扎的人，我是不会去宰他们一把的。所以，我们得走啦。多保重！再见！”

他距我们也仅仅只有二十码的距离，所以和我们说话不费什么力气。不过水很深，这座小岛可能从不知多深的海底直直地竖出水面，而我们俩谁都不会游泳。查尔斯祈求似的张开双臂，喊道：“我的天！不要告诉我，你真的要把我们俩丢在这儿吧？”

痛苦和恐惧让查尔斯看起来很可笑，格兰顿夫人，或者叫皮卡迪特夫人——不管她叫什么吧——看到查尔斯这副模样，便极尽可爱之态，发出银铃般的笑声。“亲爱的查尔斯，”她大声喊道，“不要害怕！你只是暂时被困在这儿，我们会派人来接你的，我和亲爱的大卫只是要争取点时间上岸，然后再——再改变一下我们的个人形象。”她一边笑，一边用手指着大卫的红色假发，还有浅黄褐色的假络腮胡子，这让我们深信，所有的这些都是假的。她看了看那胡子还有头发，哧哧地笑了。此时，她哪里还有什么羞怯可言？实际上，我敢说那就是一个胆大妄为、不顾颜面的疯丫头。

“原来，你就是克雷上校！”查尔斯叫道，用手帕抹了一把前额。

“随你怎么叫吧！”那年轻人斯斯文文地答道，“我敢保证，你真是太热心肠了，给了我这一头衔来为女王陛下效劳。不过，时间不多了，我们得走了。不用过分担心，在确保我们俩人身安全的前提下，我会尽快派小船来把你们从这儿接走。”他把手放在胸前，摆出一副感伤的姿态，“查尔斯爵士，虽然你不太情愿，但前前后后也双手奉上了不少好意，”他继续道，“这次你什么都没送我，让你吃点苦头倒也不觉得有什么不妥。好好待着吧，放心，最迟半夜之前肯定有人来救你。还好，现在天气不错，不可能下雨，所以你们最多也就是肚子暂时挨一下饿罢了。”

格兰顿夫人这时也不眯着眼了——那不过是她装出来的把戏——她从船上站起来，向我们摊开一条毯子。“接着！”她欢快地冲我们喊道，把毯子对折，向我们扔过来。毯子刚好落在我们脚下，她扔得也够准的。

“嗨！亲爱的查尔斯，”她继续道，“拿着它，别冻着！你也知道，我非常喜欢你。要是有人给你指条明路，你也不是什么坏人。你也有人性的一面。对了，在尼斯，我还是皮卡迪特夫人的时候，你送我的那枚漂亮的胸针，我还经常戴着。在卢塞恩，我打扮成副牧师的妻子时，你对我的好意，我也将永远铭记在心。你在苏格兰的这座漂亮的宅院，总让你感到自豪，能在这儿见到你，我们也非常高兴。不过，不用害怕，我们绝不会伤害你。以这么一种不友好的方式避开你，我们也万分抱歉。可是，亲爱的大卫——不过，我还得接着称他为亲爱的大卫——本能地觉得，你开始怀疑我们俩了，他受不了别人不相信他。他太敏感了！一旦有人怀疑他，他就得立刻摆脱他们。为了摆脱你们，为我们动身做点必要的准备，这是唯一的方法，我们也是迫不得已。不过，我以一名淑女的身份向你保证，今晚会有人过来接你。要是亲爱的大卫不派人，那我就亲自来。”接着她又给了我们个飞吻。

查尔斯一会儿暴跳如雷，一会儿又担心害怕，像是要疯了。“啊，我们会死在这儿的！”他吼道，“谁能想到来这个小岛上找我们啊！”

“当初你不让我教你游泳，真遗憾呀！”克雷上校插话道，“游泳是贵族运动，在这种特别的紧急情况下非常有用！好啦，我们走啦！再见！这一次你差点就赢了；不过，在我们离开前，把你暂时撂在这儿，也可以说，咱们这盘棋又让我重新摆了一下，咱们就当是打了个平手，怎么样？尊敬的查尔斯，这场比赛我已赢得三局——前前后后几千英镑落入囊中。”

“先生，这是谋杀！”查尔斯高声尖叫道，“我们会饿坏的，甚至会死在这儿的！”

克雷上校摆起了架子，说得句句在理。“听着，尊敬的先生，”他一只手手心向外摊着，劝诫道，“你觉得我会杀掉一只给我下金蛋的鹅，却还能像现在这样毫无懊悔之心吗？不会的，绝对不会的。查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，你对于我的价值，我再清楚不过了。从你那里每年得到的年收入，我在所得税申报表上填的是五千，就我这个行当来说，这是净利润。假如你死了，我还得重新寻找其他财源，他们可都比不上你那么大方。你的继承人、遗嘱执行人、受让人，都满足不了我的要求。先生，实际上，你我的性情刚好互补。我对你了如指掌，而你对我却一无所知——这也常是坚实友谊的基础。在你努力从别人那儿捞一把的时候，我刚好能从你那儿捞一把。我承认你很聪明，可正是你的小聪明帮了我一把。说到金融这方面，我承认只能望你项背。不过，在我们这个卑微的行当中，我知道如何利用你。我会引着你一步一步向前走，让你觉得你会从别人那儿得到点好处；我不过是巧妙地利用你爱占便宜、争强好胜的心理，才一次次骗了你。明白了吗？先生，这就是咱们彼此之间的关系。”

说罢，他鞠了一躬，脱帽致意。查尔斯看着他，有些胆怯。虽说查尔斯也并非等闲之辈，但显然已经胆怯了，冒出一句：“你的意思是，你打算继续骗我？”

上校漠然一笑，答道：“查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，刚刚我把你称为一只会下金蛋的鹅。在你看来，这个比方也许有伤大雅。不过，在许多方面，你的的确确就是一只鹅，一只蠢鹅。我承认，你是证券交易所中最精明的，不过也是我在交易所之外碰到过的最容易上当的傻瓜。你错就错在一件事上——自以为聪明。不为别的，就因为这，我才叮着你不放。亲爱的爵士，就把我当成一只寄生在百万富翁身上的微生物吧，一条靠资本家为生的寄生虫。你也听过这古老的歌谣：

大跳蚤身上寄生着小跳蚤，

小跳蚤身上的跳蚤会更小，

如此这般，无穷无尽、没完没了。

好啦，这就是我对自己的看法。你呢，是资本家，是百万富翁。你往大里看，你的猎物是整个社会，通过垄断、期权、特许，还有联合等手段，你吸光了这个世界的血液和金钱。就跟蚊子一样，你也有一个非常漂亮的吸食工具——公司发起人股份——有了它，你把整个社会的剩余财富全都吸走了。我再往小里看，我又从你掠夺来的财富中分一杯羹。我是这个时代的罗宾汉，在我眼里，你就是那种十恶不赦的百万富翁——也是只头脑极其简单的笨鸟，让我这种有才能的人给你拔一拔毛——打个比方来说，我已经寄生到了你身上。”

查尔斯望着他，叹着气。

那年轻人并没就此打住，仍以一种略带嘲弄的语气继续道：“我喜欢这场游戏所能带来的好处，亲爱的杰西也是，我们俩都非常喜欢。只要我能在你身上找到这么好的机会捞一笔，我肯定不会吃力不讨好地放弃这么一大块肥肉，转而去打那些小资本家的主意，从那些人身上榨出几百英镑都相当费事。你过去可能一直不明白为什么我老抓住你不放，现在你明白了吧？如果肝蛭发现了一只适合自己的绵羊，那它就会寄生在上面。你是我的寄主，我是你身上的寄生虫。这次的计划失败了，不过不要高兴太早，咱们还有下一次。”

“你为什么要告诉我这些来羞辱我？”查尔斯喊道，显得十分痛苦。

上校摆摆手，他的手很小很白。“因为我喜欢这游戏，”他饶有兴致地答道，“并且，你事先准备得越充分，骗你之后就会越觉得有意思，越有成就感。好啦，再会吧！我浪费的可是如金的光阴哪！有这个时间，我还可以去骗骗别人。我们必须立刻出发了……温特沃斯，照顾好自己。我知道你会的，你总是能照顾好自己。通常都是百分之十！”

他把我们丢在那儿，划船走了。船在小岛拐角处快要消失不见时，“白石南花”——当时看着很像——在船尾站了起来，边挥动着那漂亮的双手，边朝着我们大喊：“再见了，亲爱的查尔斯！一定要把毯子披在身上！我一定会尽快让人来接你。谢谢你采的这些漂亮的花！”

小船绕过崖壁不见了，岛上只剩下我们俩。查尔斯完全泄了气，一屁股直接坐在光光的石头上。他已经习惯了奢华，没有那加厚的舒适坐垫怎么能行。至于我，则吃力地爬上朝向陆地那边的悬崖顶，试着用手绢发个落难的信号，让陆地上哪位路人看到。这一切都是白费工夫。查尔斯把庄园里的佃农都打发了，那天打猎的也都在另一面，近处根本看不到有什么人能叫过来救我们。

于是我又爬下来，回到查尔斯身边。夜幕慢慢降临，水上海鸟的叫声让人毛骨悚然。落日余晖下海鹦还有鸬鹚在我们头顶盘旋。查尔斯说，它们也许会俯冲下来啄我们。但它们没有啄我们，不过，那不断拍打着的翅膀，又给我们的饥饿、孤寂增添了一阵难耐的恐惧。就我而言，克雷上校没有就佣金的事情公开出卖我，让我感到如释重负，甚至还略感舒畅。

我们蜷缩在坚硬的崖石上，大约晚上十一点钟的光景，我们听到了人的声音。“喂，船！”我喊道。对方的回应让我们一激灵站了起来。我们冲到上岸的地方，朝着那声音“喂！喂！”地喊着，让他们知道我们的位置。他们立刻划着查尔斯的船过来了，他们是峡湾对面尼盖瑞地区的渔民。

他们说是一位先生还有一位女士派他们把船划过来，到岛上来找我们的。他们所描述的人正是冒牌的格兰顿夫妇。他们一路上几乎不说话，划船把我们送到塞尔登就回家了。回到城堡时，门房的挂钟显示已经十二点半了。家里派人沿着海滩朝各个方向搜寻我俩。艾米莉亚已经睡了，十分担心我们的安全。伊莎贝尔还在坐着等消息。当夜要去抓捕那两位罪大恶极之人，未免也太迟了，但查尔斯坚持派一名车夫去弗里斯，去给因弗尼斯的警方发份电报。

一切像石沉大海，杳无音讯。克雷盖拉奇勋爵已传信过来，说他儿子根本没离开格兰拉奇的度假屋。第二天经过调查发现，我们的通信员根本没收到什么信，送来的只是一个空信封。此时邮局方面也正以闪电般的速度，忙着“调查此次事件”。西塞琳亲自在弗里斯寄的信，还拿了收条。所以，我们得出的唯一结论就是——克雷上校肯定同邮局里的某个人是一伙的。至于克雷盖拉奇勋爵的回信，那只是别人伪造的；不过，奇怪的是，回信是写在格兰拉奇家的信笺上的。

不过，几只松鸡还有一瓶香醇的吕德斯海姆酒下肚之后，查尔斯很快又精神焕发了。不用说，他从自己布尔祖先[23]那里继承了些荷兰人的那股勇气。他现在又精神饱满起来了。

“西，不管怎么说，”他靠在椅子上说道，“这次我们算是赢了一回。他没能骗到我们，至少被咱们识破了。这次能识破他，就离抓住他之日不远啦。就是咱们这塞尔登城堡位置太偏远，要不然早就抓住他了。下一次较量，我觉得咱们不光能识破他，还一定能拿住他。要是他在伦敦这么骗咱们试试！”

不过，最奇怪的是，这两人在尼盖瑞地区上岸，告诉渔夫有几位绅士困在了海鸥岛之后，就又消失得无影无踪了。沿线的所有车站都没有他们的消息，他们的女佣也在当天早上带着他们的行李离开了旅店。我们一直追到因弗尼斯，但线索一下子就断了，再也找不到任何踪迹。这件事太蹊跷，谜团一直没能解开。

查尔斯余生的最大心愿就是要在伦敦抓住这个骗子。

至于我，我觉得这泼皮无赖在划船远去时，扭头嘲讽我们的那句话也有几分道理：“查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，咱俩是一丘之貉。唯一的区别在于，你受法律的保护，而我却受其迫害。”

第六章　德国教授

那年冬天，我那尊贵的内兄在伦敦几乎没什么闲工夫来操心克雷上校此类蝇头小事。他在南非的利益受到了威胁，这威胁非同小可、毫无征兆，足以使他倾家荡产，可谓一个晴天霹雳。

虽然查尔斯做点黄金生意，也做点土地生意，不过主要精力还是在钻石生意上。说实话，我这辈子只有一次见到他对诗歌抱有那么一丁点兴趣。当时，碰巧有一天，我在吟诵这两行诗：

世上有多少纯净明媚的玉石，

淹没在深不可测的幽幽海底。

他立刻摩挲着双手，兴奋地低声说道：“这一点我还从没想到过。我们可以成立一个大西洋勘探联合有限公司。”他满脑子想的都是钻石，因此，当他意识到科学的飞速进步，也许会让他心爱的宝石某一天变得无人问津时，你也能猜得出他该有多么震惊。钻石贬值这件烦心事一直折磨着他，而那年冬天，他与那场可怕的灾难擦肩而过。

事情经过是这样的。

一天下午，我同查尔斯一起沿着皮卡迪利广场散步，去他的俱乐部——他是帕玛街克罗伊斯富翁俱乐部的知名会员——在快到伯林顿馆时，猜猜我们撞见了谁？阿道弗斯·科德里爵士，他是响当当的矿物学家，皇家学会的领导人物。他向我们点头问好，非常高兴。“好哇，凡德里夫特，”他喊道，嗓门大得出奇，有些刺耳，“我今天正想找你。早上好，温特沃斯。对了，最近钻石生意怎么样，富翁爵士？不过，你以后得老实点了。有件事和你们这些点石成金的富人有关。有没有听过施莱尔马赫那了不起的新发现？估计会让你的钻石王国就像热锅上的蚂蚁那样煎熬难耐。”

我能看到，查尔斯的身体在衣服的遮掩下扭动，他十分不安。科德里这种身份的人，竟然在皮卡迪利广场公然说出这些话，还这么大嗓门儿，不管有没有什么根据，都足以成为别人眼中敏感的晴雨表，让克罗地多普公司股价走低一两个点。

“嘘，嘘！”查尔斯一脸严肃地提醒他，那语气中充满惊恐，当有人咒骂金钱时，他就常常这种口气，“再也不要这么大声喊了！整个伦敦都听见了。”

阿道弗斯爵士极为友善地挽过查尔斯的胳膊。查尔斯最讨厌别人挽他胳膊了。

“走，同我一起去雅典娜神庙俱乐部[24]，”他继续道，嗓门儿还是那么大，“到那儿，我把一切都告诉你。这个发现非常有意思，能让钻石就像粪土一样一文不值，估计能把南非彻底踩到脚下。”

查尔斯任由他拉扯着自己向前走，不这样做也没辙。阿道弗斯爵士还在不停地说，只是声音略低了一些，看到查尔斯没发话制止，他就更加口无遮拦。事情让人忧心忡忡，但他却讲得津津有味。据他说，貌似耶拿有一位叫施莱尔马赫的教授，是“宝石化学这方面仍然健在的、最伟大的权威专家”，教授最近发明了，或者说声称自己发明了一套制造人工宝石的方法，已经取得了令人难以置信、无可挑剔的成果。

查尔斯稍稍撇了撇嘴，说道：“哦，我知道这回事儿，之前也听说过。都是些非常次的钻石，非常小，一分钱也不值，虽然制造成本巨大，但根本不值一看。科德里，你清楚，我也是久经沙场了，才不会上这个当。讲点有意思的事情吧！”

阿道弗斯爵士从口袋里掏出一小块切割好的钻石。“这块能不能称得上顶级钻石？”他一边咧着嘴笑，一边把钻石递给查尔斯，说道：“就在我眼皮底下制作的——成本相当低！”

查尔斯立刻站住，靠在圣詹姆士广场的栏杆上，拿着便携放大镜仔细检验起来。说得没错，事实就摆在那儿，这就是一小块精美的钻石，质量上乘。

“就在你眼皮底下做出来的？”查尔斯大声问道，还是不敢相信，“在哪儿？在耶拿吗？”

“不是在耶拿，就在伦敦做的，就是昨晚，我和格雷博士亲眼所见，英国皇家学会主席还打算在各位会员面前展示一番。”这些话简直就是晴天霹雳！

查尔斯深吸一口气，决然地说：“再也不能这么胡闹下去了。必须把这事消灭在萌芽状态！老兄，这可不行，事关一些重要人物，咱们可不能这么瞎糊弄。”

“你是什么意思？”科德里问，十分震惊。

查尔斯一动不动地盯着他。我偷偷地瞥了一眼，从查尔斯的眼中很明显能看出他十分害怕。“这家伙在哪儿？”他问，“他是自己过来的吗？还是让别人代他过来的？”

“他就在伦敦，”阿道弗斯爵士答道，“现在在我家里，他说不论是谁，只要因为科学研究而对钻石感兴趣，他都会乐于展示。我们提议，让他今晚在兰卡斯特门做一番展示。你要不要顺便过来看看？”

他要不要“顺便”过来看看？“顺便”到这么一个重要的场合！他能不过来吗？他紧张地一把抓住科德里的胳膊，颤抖着说道：“听着，科德里，这件事会影响到十分重要的一伙人。做事不要鲁莽，也不能糊涂。记住，这会影响到公司股票的涨跌。”他说“股票”这个词时那种深深的敬意，我很难用三言两语描述得清楚。这是他信仰中的关键字眼。

“我觉得，这很有可能。”阿道弗斯爵士冷冰冰地答道，流露出一位纯粹的科学家对金钱损失的漠然态度。

查尔斯虽然语气温和，但不容半点商议，说道：“现在，想一想，这么重大的责任落在了你肩上，市场的走势也取决于你。绝对不能让其他外人前来观看这次实验，要是你愿意，叫几位矿物学家和专家过来就行了。不过一定记得，要邀请一些利益受到威胁的人作为代表。我会亲自到场——本来我约了别人一起吃晚饭，不过可以推掉，就说我身体不适。我建议你应该请一下莫森海默，还有小菲普森。他们可作为采矿业的代表，你和那些矿物学家作为科学界的代表。最重要的是，不要乱说，看在老天的分儿上，在事情没有定论前，不要说长道短。告诉施莱尔马赫，别让他在伦敦到处胡乱吹嘘自己的成果。”

“我们对此事都守口如瓶，这也是施莱尔马赫的要求。”科德里答道，比刚才严肃多了。

查尔斯厉声责备道：“那你刚才还在皮卡迪利广场扯着嗓子叫唤，这就是你所谓的守口如瓶吗？”

不过，夜幕降临之前，一切都按照查尔斯的意思安排妥当了。我们于是前往兰卡斯特门，真心希望那德国教授捣鼓不出什么名堂来。

他的外表引人注目，从他瘦长的身材能看出来，以前个儿挺高，不过由于成天埋头钻研，俯身围着坩埚转来转去，现在腰也弯了，背也驼了，头发早早地变白了，在前额披散着，但双目炯炯有神，说出的话很有远见。他同科学家们亲切握手，像是老相识，但对于南非利益的代表们，他只是远远地鞠个躬。接着，他操着一口德式英语开始讲话了，碰到不会说的词时，时不时地用那沾满化学药品的脏手比画说明，好让别人明白他的意思。他的指甲很难看，不过，不得不说，由于老是做些精细的操作，他的手指是男人中最为纤细灵巧的。他立刻转入正题，同样带着浓重的口音，简要地向我们说明，他“现菜，要通过侧宠新方法，为各位糙出一些次量上乘，大恰满意的窜石”。

他拿出仪器，向大家解释——用他的话说，是“且释”——他的新方法。“窜石，没什么大不了，”他说道，“只不过是结晶碳罢了。”他知道如何将之制成晶体“侧求是秘密所菜”。那些科学家仔细地检查了他那些盆盆罐罐。之后，他放入一定的原材料，就在众目睽睽之下，忙碌起来。一共有三种不同的方法，他用每种方法都能同时造出两块钻石。他说，自己的方法了不起的地方在于用时短、成本低。他还（面露讥讽地）笑道，他在四十五分钟之内就能造出一块目前市价为两百英镑的钻石。“大恰等一下马上求能看到，”他说道，“求用侧些浅单的仪器。”

倒进去的那些东西不断地起泡冒烟，教授则不停地搅拌。整个房间充满了难闻的气味儿，像是羽毛烧焦了。科学家们，一个个你压我，我压你，都急切地伸直了脖子，尤其是文—卫文恩，眼睛眨都不眨一下。四十五分钟后，教授仍然面带微笑，开始清空那些仪器，从里面倒出大量的灰土，或者说粉末，他简单地称之为“副产品”，接着用拇指和另一根手指从炼锅中取出一小块白色的晶体，显然没有经过水的打磨，有点粗糙，表面像是长了瘤一样。

每一口小锅中都做出了两块这种钻石，他在我们面前得意扬扬地举着，说道：“侧个，是尘蹭的窜石，每块的成本十四先令六便士[25]！”接着他把第二个锅中的两块拿了出来，更加高兴地说道：“侧个，每块成本十一先令求便士！”最后他拿起第三个锅中的两块钻石，在惊异的众人眼前晃来晃去，激动地喊道：“侧个，成本不到三先令八便士！”

大家把钻石传来传去，一探究竟。因为它们很粗糙，还没切割，因此不能判断价值几何。不过，有件事错不了，科学家们在最开始的时候，一直紧紧地盯着，保证施莱尔马赫没有提前把这些钻石放进去；在取钻石的时候，也盯得很紧，确定他是老老实实地从坩埚中取出来的，没动什么手脚。

“我现在把它们发下去。”教授说道，语气很轻松，好像发的不是钻石，而是豌豆。说话的同时看看四周，挑中了我内兄。“一颗给查尔斯瘸士，”边说边递了过来，“一颗给莫森海默先生，菜给菲普森先生一颗——你们是窜石生意的代表。然后呢，也给阿道弗斯爵士、格雷博士、费恩—费凡先生每人各一颗，代表的是科学切。你们可以及时腔它们切割，并去此做一份报告。后天，我们还会菜侧个地方欠面。”

查尔斯瞪着他，眼中充满了责备。这触动了他内心最深处的道德感。“教授，”他说，声音很严肃，有警告的意味，“你有没有想过，你要是成功了，就会让成千上万英镑的宝贵财产灰飞烟灭？”

教授耸了耸肩。“侧对我又沉样呢？”他反问道，带着些好奇与鄙视，“我不搞亲融，我是科学恰，我求痴识，不求钱财。”

“真是开眼界了！”查尔斯喊道，“真开眼界了！我这辈子还从没见过这么怪的人！对别人的请求竟如此置若罔闻！”

大家早早地散了。那些科学家高兴得有些得意忘形，钻石生意的代表们则都阴沉着脸。如果这是真的，他们预计市场即将经历一次暴跌。所有人的眼神都暗淡下来。这件事情太可怕了。

查尔斯同教授一道朝着回家的方向走。他谨慎地对教授旁敲侧击，要是有必要，得出多少钱，才能让他就此事封口不谈。虽然阿道弗斯爵士让我们所有人都暂时保密——好像真有此必要似的，不过，查尔斯还是想知道，施莱尔马赫得要多少钱，才不会将这一发现公布于众。可那德国人并不为所动。

“不行，不行，”他答道，显然生气了，“你不懂，我不错买卖。侧是化学现象。考虑到它的理论恰迟，我们必须腔它发表出来。我不菜乎什么钱不钱，我根本没时签浪费菜蹭钱上。”

“像他这么虚度一生，想想都可怕。”查尔斯后来对我说道。

确实，教授好像什么都不关心，除了那个毫无实用价值的问题——不是他能不能造出上等的钻石，而是能不能用纯粹的碳元素造出晶状物！

查尔斯在约定的那天晚上又来到兰卡斯特门，我注意到，他当时完全沉浸在痛苦的思索之中，神情有些反常。我还从未见过他如此焦急。

钻石已经切割成形，切割的工匠在每颗钻石上面都略微做了记号，用以表示净度。接着出现了一件令人费解的事情。说来也怪，分发给三位钻石大王的钻石，每颗都是最次、最不值钱的，而交给科学家的那三颗，颗颗都是最纯净、最上等的。

说实话，出现这种巧合，怎能不让人起疑心？钻石利益的代表们用余光盯着彼此，以探究竟，接着突然垂下眼来：他们都在相互回避。是不是每个人都把施莱尔马赫造的晶石偷偷换成了天然的残次矿石呢？貌似还真是这样。我承认，一时间我自己都有点相信事实肯定如此。不过，转念间，我又改变了想法。像查尔斯这种品行端正、这么有高度原则的人，会为了点蝇头小利，而用这下三烂的伎俩吗？——况且，即便他这么做了，莫森海默也这么做了，但交到科学家手中的钻石就足以证明这次实验是真实的、成功的。

不过，不得不说，查尔斯仍心虚地看着莫森海默，而莫森海默也心虚地盯着菲普森，当时在威斯敏斯特市再也找不出比他们仨更尴尬、脸色更难看的人了。

接着，阿道弗斯爵士开始讲话——或者说，叫演说更合适。他的嗓门还是那么大，那么刺耳。他说，我们在座的诸位在当天晚上以及前一天晚上，都见证了科学史上一个新时代的诞生。施莱尔马赫教授是他的家乡萨克森[26]为之感到骄傲的人之一，不过他现在是英国人，只能略为遗憾地说，这个发现（同很多其他发现一样）原本是可以“在德国做出来的”。尽管如此，施莱尔马赫教授仍是科学家们的高贵典范，在他眼里，金子只不过是一种化学符号为Au的稀有金属，而钻石也不过是碳元素在众多同素异形体中最稀有的一种表现形态。他没有仰仗着这个发现去大赚一笔，他根本不理会那些卑鄙的、贪婪的资本家。能将碳元素还原到钻石这一晶体状态，他也就心满意足了，他所要的只不过是科学界的认可。不过，考虑到那些金融界的绅士的感受，他们一心只在乎晶体状态的碳的现价——换句话说，也就是在钻石上的利益——最后决定，大家当前一定要严守这个秘密，前来观看实验的这几位，谁也不能公开透露真相。要等到教授本人以及皇家学会的一个小规模的委员会亲自抽时间调查，验证教授这些高明的、巧妙的方法——这种调查验证也是博学的教授所期望、所建议的。（他点头表示同意。）之后，如果这方法通过了检验，那么再怎么遮遮掩掩，也都无济于事了。到时候，钻石的价格肯定会立刻暴跌，比铅玻璃还便宜，金融界再怎么反对也都是徒劳的。百万富翁改变不了自然规律。同时，由于查尔斯爵士的钻石生意做得风生水起，这一点有目共睹，考虑到查尔斯的意见，大家一致同意，不向报社走漏任何风声，也不在公共场合提起这套高明的、简单的工艺的任何字眼。他张口“高明”，闭口“高明”。现在，他代表英国矿物学界，对我们尊敬的嘉宾施莱尔马赫教授表示祝贺，祝贺他为我们光辉而闪耀的钻石珠宝科学事业做出了真正光辉而闪耀的贡献。

大家都鼓掌祝贺。这是个尴尬的时刻。查尔斯爵士咬着嘴唇，莫森海默阴沉着脸，小菲普森的表情也就不在此加以描述了。（因为我明白，这本书也许会在各家传阅。）接着，大家庄严地承诺要死守秘密，之后就散了。

我注意到，我内兄在门口有点明显地要避开莫森海默，而菲普森则迅速地跳进马车。我们俩上车坐好之后，查尔斯郁郁地向车夫吼了声：“回家！”在回梅费尔的路上，查尔斯一直躺在座椅上，双唇紧闭，一个字都未说。

在查尔斯休息前，台球室没有别人，我壮着胆子问他：“查尔斯，要不要明天把戈尔康达的股票全部清仓？”“清仓”这个词，无须我多费口舌解释，是交易所的行话，意思是甩卖掉不想要的证券。我突然想到，如果这项发明真的变成了现实，今后几周内没人会愿意买进克罗地多普的A股。

他严厉地瞪着我，说道：“温特沃斯，你这笨蛋！”（除非有时非常生气，他从不叫我“温特沃斯”，私下里他通常叫我“西”——“西摩”的简称。）“在这个关头，我能全部卖光自己的股票，毁掉公众对克罗地多普公司的信心吗？作为董事——作为董事长——我这么做合适吗？公正吗？先生，我先问问你，这么做我能对得起自己的良心吗？”

“查尔斯，”我说，“你说得对，你这么做称得上高风亮节。你不会为了一己私利，而去牺牲那些信任你的人的利益。唉，金融界中到哪儿去找这么正派的人去！”我不由自主地叹了口气，因为我脑海里浮现的全都是解放者、大救星。

这时，我也思忖着：“我不是什么董事，没人把信任压在我身上。我得首先考虑到亲爱的伊莎贝尔和孩子。趁着暴跌还没开始，我明天得把手中为数不多的一点克罗地多普公司的股票全部卖掉，这些股票，当时还是查尔斯好心帮我弄到手的。”

查尔斯凭着他那非凡的经商本能，好像察觉到了我的想法，因为他突然转过身，对着我严厉地说道：“听着，西，记住，你是我妹夫，也是我的秘书。明天整个伦敦都会监视咱俩的一言一行。如果你卖掉了所有的股票，那些股票交易人肯定会知道，他们就会怀疑是不是出了什么状况，这样的话公司就会遭殃。当然，你自己的财产，你想怎么处置就怎么处置，我无权干涉，不能命令你该怎么做不该怎么做。不过，作为戈尔康达公司的董事长，我一定要确保那些孤儿寡母的财产不能在这次危机中有任何闪失，他们把一切都压在了这上面。”他的声音似乎有些颤抖，“因此，虽然我不喜欢威胁别人，”他继续说道，“但我还是要事先警告你：如果你把手中的股票都变卖了，不管是公开地还是偷偷摸摸地卖，你就再也不是我秘书了，我会给你六个月的薪水作为代通知金，让你马上卷铺盖走人。”

“知道了，查尔斯。”我顺从地答道。不过，我在脑海中也斗争了一番：到底是放弃这艘正在沉没的巨轮拿到现钱好呢，还是坚定地站在朋友身旁，支持他去对抗教授的那套科学好？经过头脑中一番简短的、激烈的权衡之后，我可以很自豪地说，我选择了友谊和感恩。我敢保证，不论钻石价格是涨是跌，查尔斯这种人总能排除万难，最终取得成功，于是我决定支持他！

那一夜，我几乎无眠，内心一直无法平静。早饭时，查尔斯看起来也是面容憔悴、郁郁寡欢。他早早地叫了马车，直奔伦敦。

齐普赛街有些拥堵。查尔斯又急躁又紧张，干脆从车上跳下来走过去。我则陪着他一起走。快到伍德街时，以前偶然认识的一个人拦住了我们。

“我觉得，我还是告诉你一声为好，”他说，生怕别人听到，“根据最可靠的消息，耶拿的施莱尔马赫教授——”

“谢了，”查尔斯粗暴地说，“我听说了——全是些胡说八道。”

他匆忙前行，在一两码远的地方，一位经纪人在我们面前停了下来。

“您好哇，查尔斯爵士！”他带着些嘲弄的语气叫道，“关于钻石的这些消息是怎么回事？克罗地多普公司今天表现怎么样？是坐拥金山银山，还是狼狈不堪？”

查尔斯身子挺得笔直，一脸威严地回道：“我不明白你在说什么。”

“哦，您当时不是也在场吗？”那人大声说道，“昨天晚上，在阿道弗斯爵士家里！哦，对了，这消息已经传遍了。耶拿的施莱尔马赫成功地造出了最完美的钻石，每颗只需六便士，足以同南非那些久负盛名的钻石相媲美。他们说，不到六周，金伯利就会成为一块哀鸿遍野的不毛之地。怀特查佩尔的每个小贩都会将科依诺尔钻石[27]钉在外套上当扣子用；柏蒙西的每个姑娘去看最喜欢的杂耍时都会佩戴同凡德里夫特夫人一样的首饰。戈尔康达股票要暴跌。阴险，真够阴险的。我看出来了；不过，我们也都知道了！”

查尔斯继续向前走，甚是反感。那人的嘴脸可恶至极。快到银行时，我们碰到了一位极为体面的股票经纪人。

“哎呀，查尔斯爵士，”他说道，“您来啦！嗯，这消息有点没头没脑，对不对？要我来看，建议你不必太在意。今天早上，您公司的股价将会暴跌。不过，明天就会涨起来，相信我，在还没证实那项发现是真是假之前，股价每时每刻都会波动。我敢保证，这段时间股票交易人可要忙坏了。一会儿这么说，一会儿又那么说。谣言，到处是谣言。在阿道弗斯爵士没有证实以前，都不知道该相信谁。”

我们继续朝议院方向走去。查尔斯一路上忧心忡忡。我们一路上看到，大家都在讨论当下发生的这件事。要想让别人知道什么事情，与其在显眼处张贴告示，还不如让知情人严守秘密要来得奏效。有些人在我们耳边悄声低语，告诉我们这一爆炸性新闻，生怕别人听到；有些人则是扯着嗓门宣布这一消息，一副得意忘形的样子。大家普遍认为克罗地多普公司要完了，越及早抽身，损失越小。

查尔斯大步前行，一副将军派头；只不过，这位将军像是拿破仑，战场失利后，厚着脸皮面对从莫斯科的败退。他态度坚决，最后走到办公区，摆手示意我回去，接着不见了踪影。他要在里面商讨许久之后，才出来同我碰面。

那一整天，整个伦敦到处都在谈论着戈尔康达公司，都在小声嘀咕：“暴跌，戈尔康达的股票要暴跌了。”各位经纪人事情多得忙不过来，只不过几乎所有人都在卖出，没人买进。可查尔斯仍如磐石般坚定，他的经纪人也是。“我不愿意卖出，”他固执地说，“整体情况正在好转。这只不过是场骗局。就我而言，我相信施莱尔马赫教授是被别人骗了，或者他在骗我们。一周之后，谣言就会被揭穿，股价就会回升。”不管问及什么问题，他手下芬戈摩尔家的那些经纪人都众口一词：“查尔斯爵士对戈尔康达公司的稳定十分有信心，不会卖出公司股票，以免增加恐慌。”

所有人都说他是好样的，真是好样的！他自己就像块花岗岩，屹立在交易所，风浪汹涌扑来，全被击得粉碎。他不但对股票暴跌置若罔闻，而且还大张旗鼓地将一些零星的少量股票全部买进，以便恢复公众的信心。

“我还会继续买进，来赚上一笔，”查尔斯说道，语气轻松，“不过，因为昨晚我也碰巧在阿道弗斯爵士家，大家也许会认为，是我促成了这次谣言的散播，造成股价暴跌，这样我就可以在大家恐慌时以极低的价格买进，为的是自己的利益。董事会主席，应该同恺撒的妻子一样，容不得别人半点怀疑[28]。因此，我会时不时地买进一些，但是会适可而止，让大家知道，至少我对克罗地多普公司的未来抱有信心。”

他当天晚上回家时，看起来比任何时候都要疲惫不堪。第二天也是一样，股价仍断断续续向下跌。一会儿传言四起，说阿道弗斯爵士已经宣布整个事件是场骗局，这时股价稍微稳定一点；一会儿，又有人爆料说，这些钻石已经一车一车地投放到了柏林的市场上，于是，胆子小点的老妇人们就一通电报发给经纪人，让他们不管有何种风险，一定要把股票立刻变现。那天可真够糟心的，我永远忘不了。

第三天早上，突然间，一切都奇迹般地恢复了正常。正当我们纳闷这背后到底发生了什么时，查尔斯收到了阿道弗斯·科德里爵士的电报：

“那人是个骗子，根本不是施莱尔马赫。刚接到耶拿的电报，说施莱尔马赫教授根本不认识此人。我并非存心给你添麻烦，抱歉。速来见我。”

“并非存心给你添麻烦，抱歉。”查尔斯火冒三丈，气得发疯。阿道弗斯爵士在这四十八小时内，把股票市场搅得昏天黑地，差不多有十来位殷实的股票交易人近乎倾家荡产。整个伦敦都受到了剧烈震动，议院也快乱套了。可现在——他为此事道的歉，就像是谁参加晚宴时迟到了十分钟一样！查尔斯跳上马车，急急忙忙去见他。他怎敢向这些富人引见这个骗子，说他是施莱尔马赫教授？阿道弗斯爵士耸了耸肩，说那家伙到这儿来说自己在耶拿是位了不起的化学家；他一头长长的白发，还有点驼背，也没什么理由怀疑他在说谎啊。（我这时想到，查尔斯当时轻信大卫·格兰顿阁下还有莱本斯坦伯爵的理由同这也差不多。）不过，这家伙设这么一个不同寻常的骗局，有什么企图呢？查尔斯再清楚不过了。很明显，这么做就是想搅乱钻石市场，我们也意识到（不过已经太迟了）这一切的幕后主使都是——克雷上校，他不过乔装成了“众多同素异形体中”的另一种形象。查尔斯的愿望成真了，的的确确又在伦敦碰到了他的宿敌。

现在我们清楚了整个事件。克雷上校，就像碳元素一样，有不同的“形态”。毫无疑问，他用出色的手法，把从仪器中倒出来的一堆不成形的东西调换成了真钻石，这一切都发生在他拿着做出来的晶体四处走动，一颗颗发给科学界以及钻石生意的代表，供大家检验的空当儿。他打开坩埚时，我们当然都仔细地盯着他，不过当我们看到确实造出了什么东西时，也就心满意足了，便放松了警惕，于是就忘了观察他是不是真的将这些东西分发下去。骗子能得手，总要靠着暂时转移别人的注意力或者他人的一时疏忽。和以前一样，他的诡计得逞后，就消失得无影无踪了。就像伯爵还有先知那样，像一道烟似的凭空消失了，再也没有任何消息。

查尔斯回到家，比以往任何时候都大为光火。我不明白他为什么会这样。他看似十分忧郁，仿佛损失了成千上万英镑。我试着安慰他：“虽然戈尔康达公司暂时有些损失，”我说，“不过，想想你如此坚定，力挽狂澜，在恐慌中都没有损失一分一毫，这也值得宽慰了。不过，当然，我替那些孤儿寡母感到难过。但，如果是克雷上校在幕后操纵了市场，至少这次受损失的不是你。”

查尔斯对我怒目而视，毫不掩饰轻蔑之意，吓得我向后一缩。“温特沃斯，你个笨蛋！”他又训了我一次，接着便沉默不语。

“可是，你没有把股票清仓卖出啊！”我说。

他直直地盯着我，最终说道：“要是我打算全部卖出，我能告诉你吗？或者，我会通过芬戈摩尔那位经常为我办事的经纪人公开卖出，这可能吗？这样一来，全世界都会知道了，那戈尔康达就完了。既然如此，我不想告诉你这头蠢驴我到底损失了多少。不过，我的确全部卖出了，不知哪位交易人立刻全部买进，现款结清，今早又再次卖出；事已至此，也不可能找得到他了。他没等账单到，就立刻付了款，卖出的时候也是如此。现在我明白了所发生的一切，也知道这一切是如何巧妙地加以伪装和掩饰的了。不过，我今天最想告诉你的是——这是迄今为止，克雷上校从我身上捞的最大的一笔。要是他愿意，就可以靠此度过余生了。我的希望是，这也许会让他此生心满意足，就此罢手；不过话又说回来，世上谁也不嫌钱多。”

“你全部卖出了！”我叫道，“你，公司的董事长！你舍他人抽身而去！你的信誉呢？那些信任你的孤儿寡母怎么办？”

查尔斯起身，对着我，以最严肃的口吻说道：“西摩·温特沃斯，你跟了我这么多年，可谓占尽先机。你也见过巨额融资，可你居然还问这种问题！我觉得你这辈子永远、永远都不可能明白商业的本质。”

第七章　抓捕上校

查尔斯在克罗地多普公司的股票暴跌中到底损失了多少钱，我无从得知。不过，这件事以后，他成天垂头丧气，打不起精神。

“去他妈的，西，”几日后的一天晚上，他在吸烟室对我说，“哪怕是约伯这么能沉得住气的人，也会让这个克雷上校惹烦——要是我没记错的话，那些迦勒底人还有那个时代的其他主要交易人，也让约伯同样损失惨重[29]。”

“三千匹骆驼，一下子说没就没了，”我一边回忆亲爱的母亲给我讲的故事，一边小声道，“更不用提被示巴人带走的那五百对牛，那伙人可是当时主要的搞投机倒把的牲畜贩子！”

“嗯，”查尔斯一边将雪茄烟灰弹到日式托盘中——那是件精美的古董铜皿，一边若有所思地大声说，“原来早在那个时候就有大宗家畜交易了！先不说什么约伯不约伯，那个家伙我是受够了。”

“问题在于，”我赞成道，“你压根就不知道在哪儿能找到他。”

“说得对，”查尔斯思忖道，“要是他始终一个模样，就像霍尼曼茶，或知名的白兰地酒，事情自然就好办得多，你还有可能认出他来。但他每次都以不同的伪装出现，笑眯眯的，简直天衣无缝，还总有些让别人相信他的力证。西，真他妈的见鬼，咱们和他根本没法正面交锋。”

“就像上次的大卫阁下，”我表示赞同，“怀疑谁也怀疑不到他呀！”

“就是，”查尔斯咕哝道，“我为了自己的利益，亲自把他请过来。然后他就来了，摆出一副格兰拉奇家不可一世的派头。”

“还有那个教授，”我继续说道，“是经由英国矿物学家大佬引荐的。”

我戳到了痛点，查尔斯面部抽搐着，一言不发。

“还有女人，”查尔斯痛苦地顿了顿，又继续道，“我在社交中肯定要接触很多有魅力的女人，总不能时时刻刻都提防着她们。可是，哪一天我一旦放松警惕——即使不放松警惕——那位高傲的皮卡迪特夫人，或者一眼望去心思单纯的小骚货格兰顿夫人，她们就会来骗我，天天给我找麻烦。那个贱人（随咱们怎么叫她），是我这辈子遇到的最精明的女人。她每次都像是换了个人，妈的，每次我都被她迷得像丢了魂似的。”

我向四处瞥了几眼，以确保艾米莉亚听不到我们的谈话。

我那可敬的内兄许久不语，若有所思地啜着咖啡，接着说道：“西，要干这件非常人所及的事，我觉得必须找位专业人士，帮我识破一切狡猾的伪装。我明天得去马维尔那里——他是我的福星——让他给我找位真正有本事的侦探，待在家中，监视每一个靠近我的人。每个鼻子、每双眼睛、每顶假发、每根胡须，他都要留神。他就是我的另一半，时刻警惕，永不休息。他的任务就是怀疑一切男男女女，哪怕是坎特伯雷大主教，也得时时刻刻处在他的监视之下；他还得留心别让哪位皇室公主把汤匙偷掉，或者把珠宝箱顺走。不管克雷上校乔装成什么列车保安或者教区牧师，他都一定会识破。要是皮卡迪特夫人装成年轻的小姑娘，同艾米莉亚喝茶，或者扮成肥胖的老妇人来拜访伊莎贝尔，他也都会识破。就这样，我决心已定，明天就立即动身，到马维尔那儿去物色这么个人。”

“查尔斯爵士，打扰一下，”西塞琳从门房探出头，打断我们，“夫人说，您和温特沃斯先生还记不记得，她今晚要同二位一道去凯里斯布鲁克夫人家？”

“我的天！”查尔斯叫道，“把这事忘了！现在已经十点多了！五分钟后，马车会在门口等我们！”

于是，第二天早上，查尔斯驾车去马维尔家。那位知名的侦探听了查尔斯的遭遇，两眼放光，接着摩挲着双手，心满意足地说：“克雷上校！克雷上校！那是位难对付的对手！欧洲的警方都在搜寻他，伦敦、巴黎、柏林都在通缉他。这儿有橡皮脸上校，那儿也有橡皮脸上校，到处都是！后来就有人问，到底有没有橡皮脸上校这个人？还是说，警方为了方便起见，把一伙未侦破的骗子通通叫作橡皮脸上校？不过，查尔斯爵士，我们一定会尽力。我现在马上就把全英国最能干、最精明的侦探请过来。”

“我要找的就是这种人，”查尔斯说，“马维尔，他叫什么？”

他微微一笑，说道：“叫什么都行，他不会在意。家里人叫他梅德赫斯特，我们管他叫乔。我下午肯定会把他派到你家去。”

“别，”查尔斯立刻说道，“千万别这样。这样的话，来的不是侦探，而是克雷上校。我被骗得也够多的了。不要随便来个陌生人，我就在这儿等他。”

“可他现在不在。”马维尔提出异议。

查尔斯像块石头，一动不动。“那就派人把他叫过来。”

当然，半小时后侦探就到了。他身材矮小，长相奇特，头发剪得很短，在头上直直地立着，像位巴黎的侍者；双眼敏锐，极像雪貂；鼻子扁平，嘴唇薄而苍白。左脸有道疤——说是当时有位亡命的法国走私犯伪装成非洲猎兵的长官，他在抓捕这个人时负了剑伤。他神色坚定。总的来说，我这辈子从未见过这么古怪有趣、敏锐精明的小个子男人。他走了进来，步态轻盈，上下打量了查尔斯一番，接着随口问起把他叫来做什么。

“这位是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，就是那位了不起的钻石大王。”马维尔介绍道。

“久仰。”那人答道。

“你认识我？”查尔斯问。

“要是我谁也不认识，”那侦探答道，“那不是徒有虚名了吗？很容易就能认出你，街上随便拉个人过来都认得你。”

“爽快！”查尔斯说道。

“先生，只要您愿意，”那人毕恭毕敬地答道，“我会尽力让自己的言行举止、衣着打扮，随时随地符合雇主的喜好。”

“你叫？”查尔斯微笑着问道。

“约瑟夫·梅德赫斯特，愿意为您效劳。要我做什么？钻石被盗了吗？还是有非法的钻石买卖？”

“都不是，”查尔斯盯着他说道，“完全是另外一件事。你听没听说过克雷上校？”

梅德赫斯特点点头，答道：“当然，我的本职工作就是打探他这类人。”我第一次从他的话语中发现一丝美国口音。

“那就好，我想让你抓住他。”查尔斯继续说道。

梅德赫斯特深吸了一口气，大吃一惊，低声道：“这一单未免也太大了吧？”

查尔斯仔仔细细地向他说明了需要他做的事情，梅德赫斯特答应照办。他稍顿一下，接着说：“如果他接近你，我就会认出他来。我敢这么保证。我能识破一切伪装，能立刻知道他是否乔装打扮过。假发、假胡子、假脸皮，在这些方面我是高手。要是碰到他，我会仔细盘问那无赖。只要我在你身边，你大可放心，克雷上校不论做什么，我都能立刻识破。”

“他做得到，”马维尔插话道，“他能说到，就一定能做到。他是我最得力的助手。说到揭露那些最巧妙的伪装，我还从没见过谁能比得上他。”

“那他刚好适合我，”查尔斯接过话，“说到伪装自己并且一直不露破绽，我还从未见过像克雷上校这样的。”

于是我们安排梅德赫斯特目前暂住家中，告诉仆人说他是助理秘书。他当天就过来了，带了个非常小的旅行皮箱。不过，自打他到的那一刻起，我们就发现，西塞琳对他有一种极度的厌恶。

梅德赫斯特是位极为能干的侦探。我和查尔斯向他讲述了我们所知道的克雷上校所“幻化”的各种模样，他据此给我们提了许多宝贵的意见和建议。我们开始怀疑大卫·格兰顿阁下的时候，为什么不试着“不小心”把他的假发碰掉呢？当理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗副牧师首次谈及铅玻璃钻石这个问题时，我们为什么不去看看艾米莉亚那举世无双的珠宝是否还在呢？当施莱尔马赫教授向聚集在兰卡斯特门的科学家们鞠躬致意时，我们为什么不提前去仔细打听下，阿道弗斯·科德里爵士还有其他矿物学家同他的私交到底如何？关于假发，还有乔装，他也给了我们一些有益的指点。比如，施莱尔马赫要比他的实际身高矮得多，他只不过在后背垫了块垫子，装作驼背，给别人造成一种高大驼背的假象；可实际上，他并不比小副牧师或者莱本斯坦伯爵高多少，剩下的就是高高的鞋跟在作怪了。我们所看到的他脸上表现出的对科学的热情，毫无疑问是他鼻头那点蜡搞的鬼，让鼻子翘得特别，效果极其明显。总之，我不得不承认，梅德赫斯特让我们自惭形秽。虽然查尔斯的观察力也相当敏锐，不过，在这位训练有素、经验丰富的职业侦探面前，他就显得微不足道了。

最糟糕的是，梅德赫斯特同我们一起时，克雷上校就躲得远远的，仿佛冥冥之中有一种奇怪的安排。当然，我们也会偶尔碰到某个梅德赫斯特怀疑的对象，不过，他稍作调查（这调查做得可谓相当巧妙）就会发现，被怀疑的人确实是某位知名人物，和克雷上校没什么关系，他还把那人的过去还有现在的情况讲得如数家珍。在怀疑别人这方面，他也是登峰造极。每个人他都怀疑。要是有位老友顺便来访，同查尔斯谈谈生意，我们随后就会发现，梅德赫斯特一直藏在窗帘后面，把整个谈话内容全都速记了下来，还用一台柯达相机抓拍了几张嫌疑人的照片。要是哪位肥胖的老妇人前来拜访艾米莉亚，梅德赫斯特肯定会潜伏在客厅的软垫搁脚凳下面，全身心仔细观察她到底是不是塞了衬垫乔装后的皮卡迪特夫人。有天晚上，特雷斯科夫人同她那四位相貌平平的女儿一道前来参加“家庭招待会”；梅德赫斯特穿着晚礼服，装作侍者，在屋子里跟着她们到这儿到那儿，冒冒失失地问她们要不要冰块，以便搞清楚她们的皮肤到底有多少是天然的，又有多少是胭脂水粉的功劳。他怀疑查尔斯的贴身男仆辛普森会不会是穿便装的克雷上校，还隐约觉得西塞琳就是俏丽的“白石南花”的另一个化身。我们告诉他，辛普森经常同大卫·格兰顿同现一室，西塞琳在卢塞恩时为布拉巴宗夫人梳过头。不过，这些话只能打消他的部分疑虑，只是部分疑虑。他说，辛普森也许同我们不认识的某个人一起扮演了这两个角色；至于西塞琳，她也许有位双胞胎姊妹，在她冒充皮卡迪特夫人时就来顶替她。

不过，尽管他如此费心——或者说，由于他如此费心——克雷上校已经有整整几周没有现身了。我们想到了一种解释：克雷上校是否有可能知道现在有人正保护、监视着我们呢？是不是不敢同这位训练有素的侦探一决高下？

如果真是如此，那么他是怎么知道的？我自己隐约有种感觉，只是自己的感觉——不过从未向查尔斯提起。很明显，西塞琳很不喜欢凡德里夫特家的这位新客，只要那位侦探待在屋里，她绝不在室内停留，对他也没有常人之礼。每次提到他，她总要说“梅德赫斯特那个讨厌透顶的人”。她会不会猜到了其他仆人不知道的事情呢，即：此人是暗中侦察上校的间谍？我觉得很有可能。接着我慢慢意识到，关于钻石那场风波，西塞琳前前后后全知道，带着我们去看莱本斯坦城堡的是她，寄信给克雷盖拉奇的还是她！我现在有点倾向于猜测西塞琳是同克雷上校一伙的，如果真是这样，那么，她看到这个打算抓她主子的侦探，就明显心生厌恶，还有比这再正常不过的吗？去提醒她的共犯接近这位梅德赫斯特时所面临的危险，还有比这更容易解释的吗？

不过，关于支票的那段插曲让我十分害怕，不敢把这刚刚萌生的怀疑告诉查尔斯。我倒是想看看事情会怎么发展下去。

过了一阵子，梅德赫斯特的监视变得越来越让人厌烦。他不止一次手持报告还有速记笔记找到查尔斯，我那位了不起的内兄显然很反感。“这家伙掌握了我们太多的信息，”一天查尔斯对我说，“西，他什么都监视。你信不信，前几天我同布鲁克菲尔德就戈尔康达公司的最新决议进行密谈时，那家伙就躲在安乐椅下面，我还提前检查了房间，确保他不在场；事后，他拿着我们的谈话笔记过来找我，向我保证说，他觉得布鲁克菲尔德——我结识了十年的老友——高了半英寸，有可能是克雷上校乔装的。”

“不过，查尔斯爵士，”梅德赫斯特突然从书架后面冒了出来，大声抗议道，“你绝不能因为和谁结交了十年或多长时间而不去怀疑他。克雷上校可能会在不同的时间以不同的伪装接近你。他很可能是一步步地把这一切设计好的。对了，你说我知道得太多，当然啦，一名侦探总是要了解雇主家的方方面面，很多是他不应该了解的。不过，同医生和律师一样，职业荣誉和操守会让他对这些事守口如瓶。放心好了，我绝不会透露半点出去。否则，我的职业生涯也就走到头了，名声也毁了。”

查尔斯惊骇地看着他，突然冒出一句：“怎么？原来你一直在偷听我和我妹夫兼我秘书的谈话？”

“当然啦！”梅德赫斯特答道，“我的职责就是监听，并且怀疑所有的人。要是你非逼着我这么说，我怎么知道温特沃斯不是克雷上校？”

查尔斯瞪了他一眼，吓了他一跳。“梅德赫斯特，今后如果我不知情、不同意，你绝不能躲在我待的房间里。”

梅德赫斯特客客气气地鞠了一躬，答道：“好的，查尔斯爵士，听您的。您让我怎么做，我就怎么做。不过，要是您现在坚持对我束手束脚的，我以后还怎么能有效地干侦探的活儿呢？”

我又一次略微听出点美国口音。

然而，从那之后，梅德赫斯特仿佛又重整旗鼓，对方方面面都加强了警惕。“这也不是我的错，”一天，他哀怨地说，“要是我的名声太大，有我在您身边，那个无赖不敢接近您。如果抓不到他，至少有我在，他不敢靠近您！”

不过，几天后，他给查尔斯拿来几张相片。他拿出相片时，一脸的自豪。他先给我们看了一张小副牧师的半身照。“看看，这是谁？”他问道，非常高兴。

我们都瞪大眼睛盯着看，不约而同地说出一个词：“布拉巴宗！”

“再看看这张呢？”他又拿出一张，问道——相片上是个年轻的家伙，很开心，穿着蒂罗尔服饰。

我们低声道：“凡·莱本斯坦！”

“这张呢？”他又问道，这次给我们看的是一位女士的画像，眼睛眯着，相当迷人。

我们异口同声道：“格兰顿夫人！”

梅德赫斯特自然对此次丰硕的战果扬扬自得，接着又神气地把相片放回了手提包。

“你是怎么弄到的？”查尔斯问。

梅德赫斯特看起来神神秘秘的，挺直了身子，答道：“查尔斯爵士，在这件事上，我得请您相信我一回。记住，有些人您不愿意去怀疑他们。据我了解，对于资本家们来说，往往正是这些人才是最危险的。要是我现在就把他们的名字告诉您，您肯定会不相信。所以，我目前还是悄悄地保密吧。不过，我可以告诉您一件事。我知道克雷上校目前的行踪，这点我有把握。不过我要精心策划一番，希望不久就可以将他捉拿归案。到时候您肯定会在场，我会让他公开承认自己的身份。除此之外，您也就不要白费口舌问其他的事情了。到时候，会让您来决定要不要抓捕他。”

对方什么都不透露，查尔斯没生气，而是十分困惑。他乞求对方说出名字，但梅德赫斯特很倔强。“不行，不行，”他回答道，“我们侦探这一行有自己的脸面，我要是现在告诉您了，您有可能未等时机成熟就采取行动，破坏全盘计划。您管不住自己的嘴，太意气用事！我只能跟您透露这么一点：克雷上校很快就会抵达巴黎，不久会从那个城市前来，再试着骗您一次，他现在正在酝酿计划。记住我的话，到时候就知道我是不是对这家伙的行踪了如指掌了！”

他说得丝毫不差。果然，两天后，查尔斯收到了一封巴黎来的“密”信，写信人声称自己掌管着一家二流金融商行，这家商行曾经同查尔斯就克雷盖拉奇合并这件事上有业务往来——我得说一句，这时两家已经确确实实合并到了一起。这封信本身无足轻重——只不过说了些鸡毛蒜皮的事情，不过梅德赫斯特认为，要是这件事继续发展下去，性质就严重了。这时，再一次验证了他那惊人的洞察力。因为，一周以后我们又收到一封信，信中微妙地提及了另外一些涉及金钱往来的提议，牵扯到向一家巴黎公司的负责人转账约两千英镑，地址也提供了。梅德赫斯特把这两封信同过去以克雷上校还有莱本斯坦伯爵的名义写的信巧妙地做了对比。一眼望去，二者之间确实有天壤之别：巴黎的来信，字体又粗又黑、遒劲有力；而以前的信件，字体细小、整齐、飘逸。不过，梅德赫斯特向我们指出，写信人在写大写字母时，转折处有些固定不变的特点。另外还有，字母t、l、b还有h的相对笔画长度有些奇怪。我们看得出，他说得不错：这些信都是出自同一人之手，一些是用尖尖的羽管笔尖写的，字迹很小；而另一些则是用鹅毛笔写的，字体大而随意。

这一发现相当重要。现在要抓住克雷上校，定下他伪造证件、诈取钱财等罪名，已经指日可待。

不过，为了确保万无一失，梅德赫斯特还联系了巴黎警方，把他们的回复给我们看了看。与此同时，查尔斯继续同那位公司负责人通信，他给了我们一个位于让·雅克大街的私人地址，还极其巧妙地（这一点不得不承认）解释了为什么目前谈判需要秘密进行。不过，以克雷上校的绝顶聪明，这谁都能想得到。最终决定我们仨一同前去巴黎，梅德赫斯特乔装成查尔斯，付给那冒牌的金融家两千英镑，我和查尔斯则同警方一同在门外等候，听到暗号就破门而入抓捕罪犯。

我们于是赶过去，在格兰德酒店住了一晚，查尔斯常在这儿住。我喜欢布莱斯托酒店，不过他觉得太安静了。我们第二天一大早就坐着马车前往让·雅克大街。梅德赫斯特已经提前同巴黎警方安排妥当，三名警察身着便衣在楼梯口等着，准备随时援助我们。查尔斯还带了价值两千英镑的法兰西银行的钞票，这样，一旦对方将密谋的犯罪加以实施，我们就能立刻把款项交给他——要知道，实施犯罪会监禁十五年，而密谋犯罪只会监禁三年。查尔斯非常兴奋。我们最终找到了这个无赖，一小时内就能将他缉拿归案，想想这事本身就让他士气大涨。不出所料，我们发现对方给的位于让·雅克大街的地址是家旅馆，不是私宅。梅德赫斯特先走进去，问了问店主我们要找的人是否在房间内，还告诉他我们这次行动的来由，好让他明白，要是我们在他善意的帮助下抓捕成功，查尔斯爵士会全额付清那骗子的所有账单，算作他的酬劳。店主鞠了一躬，说太遗憾了，因为，上校先生——我们听到他是这么称呼的——非常平易近人，这儿的人都非常喜欢他；不过当然啦，正义必须得到伸张。接着，他叹了口气，感到惋惜，决定帮助我们。

虽然警察一直待在下面，可查尔斯还有梅德赫斯特，也都各自准备了一副手铐。吸取了伯尔派罗事件的教训，我们决定在使用手铐时要极为慎重，只有在对方极力反抗时才能用。我们蹑手蹑脚地来到那个无赖的房间门口，查尔斯把装着纸币的信封交给梅德赫斯特，没有封口，梅德赫斯特迅速地一把抓了过来，拿在手中，准备行动。我们约定了暗号，只要他打喷嚏——这事他做得相当自然——我们就打开门，冲进去，把罪犯拿下！

他进去了几分钟，我和查尔斯一直在门外等候，不敢喘气。梅德赫斯特打喷嚏了！我们立刻把门撞开，径直奔向那家伙。

这时，梅德赫斯特站了起来，用手指着说：“他就是克雷上校！好好看着他，我到楼下叫警察来抓他！”

此时，一名男子站了起来，温文尔雅，中等身材，胡子花白，一副军人模样，演得惟妙惟肖。查尔斯装钱的信封放在他面前的桌子上，他紧张地攥着信封。“我完全糊涂了，先生们，”他说，情绪激动，“你们为什么突然闯进来？”他说话时声音有些发抖，但很客气，这种客气劲儿是小副牧师还有大卫阁下身上常有的，我们认得出。

“少废话！”查尔斯大声喝道，语气不容置疑，“我们知道你是谁。这一次，我们把你识破了。你就是克雷上校！要是你胆敢反抗——小心点——我就把你铐上！”

那位军人模样的男子吓了一跳。“对，我是克雷上校，”他回答道，“你凭什么抓我？我犯了什么罪？”

查尔斯怒不可遏。这家伙貌似能始终保持冷静。“你就是克雷上校！”查尔斯发着牢骚说道，“你居然还敢厚颜无耻地站在这儿承认？”

“为什么不敢！”上校答道，也生气了，“我又没干什么见不得人的事。你这么做什么意思？还竟敢口口声声说要抓我？”

查尔斯把手搭在那个人的肩上，说道：“得了，得了，朋友。再也别想就这样把我们糊弄过去。我为什么要抓你，你心里比谁都清楚。让警察来告诉你吧！”

他用法语喊了声“请进！”，警察进了房间。查尔斯操着那没什么把握的巴黎方言，尽可能清楚地说明接下来要做什么。上校则一脸怒色，挺直了身子，转过身，用极流利的法语向他们解释。

“先生们，我是名军官，为大不列颠女王陛下效劳，”他说道，“先生们，你们凭什么胆敢干涉我？”

警长解释了一番。上校又转向查尔斯，问道：“先生，您是哪位？”

“你比谁都清楚，”查尔斯答道，“我是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士。虽然你伪装得很巧妙，我还是能一眼就认出你。我认得出你的眼睛，还有你的鼻子。看得出，你就是那个在尼斯骗了我，还在岛上羞辱过我的家伙。”

“你是查尔斯·凡德里夫特？”那无赖叫道，“不可能，不可能，先生，你就是个疯子！”他看看四周，又看看警察，大声说道：“仔细掂量掂量你们在做什么！这是个胡言乱语的疯子，我刚和查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士谈完生意，这两位先生进来时他刚出去。这个人疯了，还有你，先生，”他向我鞠了一躬，“我敢保证，你肯定是专门看护他的。”

“别被他蒙骗了，”我对警察大声说，开始担心，以他那一贯的聪明劲儿，即使在现在这种情形下，这家伙肯定也能从我们手中溜掉，“按照咱们的安排，抓住他，一切由我们负责。”不过，想到他手中还捏着我的那张支票，我有些发抖。

三名警察的长官走上前，把手放在罪犯的肩上，打着官腔说道：“上校，我建议你目前还是老老实实地跟我们走一趟，有什么问题留着在调查法官面前详细说。”

上校屈服了，和他们一起走了，不过还是很恼火——还别说，他的演技可真够绝的。

“梅德赫斯特呢？”我们走到门口时，查尔斯看看四周，问道，“我希望他能跟着一起来。”

“在找你们的那位朋友吗？”店主问道，说着侧身向上校弯腰致敬，“他坐马车走了，让我把这个短笺留给您。”

他递给我们一张卷起来的短笺。查尔斯打开看了看，叫道：“神机妙算！西，看看人家说的：‘已经抓住了克雷上校，我现在正去追赶皮卡迪特夫人，她就住在同一栋楼里，刚刚驾车逃走；我知道她会去哪里，现在正全力追赶，要将她缉拿归案。十万火急，未及告辞。梅德赫斯特。’这才叫精明，那个可怜的小妇人，我想他本来是可以放她一马的。”

“是不是有个叫皮卡迪特夫人的住在这儿？”我问店主，想着她有可能又用了以前的化名。

他点点头表示同意，答道：“嗯，是的，是的。她刚刚乘车离开，你们那位朋友正急急忙忙追过去了。”

“万里挑一！”查尔斯大声说道，“马维尔说得不错，这人是侦探之王！”

我们叫了几辆马车，分两批前往调查法官那里。在那儿，克雷上校仍厚颜无耻地一再声称自己是驻印部队的一名军官，休六个月的假回家探亲，在巴黎逗留了几周。还说大使馆有人认识他，他有一位堂兄在那儿做专员。他要求我们大使这边立刻派人请他堂兄过来证明自己的身份。调查法官坚持一定得这么办，查尔斯则无奈地等着走完这荒唐的程序，气急败坏。我们感觉像是，费了九牛二虎之力好不容易才把他抓到手，他马上又想耍些滑头逃掉。

克雷上校同我们一样，又气又急，等了一个多小时，专员到了，他上前同囚犯热情洋溢地打招呼，让我们又惊又恐。

“好哇，阿尔吉！”他抓住对方的手，大声说道，“怎么了？这帮无赖想干吗？”

这时我们才渐渐明白梅德赫斯特说的“怀疑所有人”是什么意思：真正的克雷上校不是一个普通老百姓，而是位出身高贵的绅士！

上校瞪着我们。“这家伙口口声声称自己是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，”他不高兴地说，“不过这样一来，就有两位查尔斯了。伯蒂，他还指控我伪造文件、诈取钱财、偷盗财物。”

专员仔细地盯着我们。“这位就是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，”过了一会儿，他说道，“我记得有一次在市里的晚宴中，我听过他讲话。查尔斯爵士，你指控我堂弟什么罪名？”

“你堂弟？”查尔斯叫道，“这是克雷上校，那个臭名昭著的骗子！”

专员一笑，虽显傲慢但又不失风度。“这位克雷上校，”他回答道，“是孟加拉参谋团的。”

我们这才意识到肯定不知哪个地方出岔子了。

“不管他是谁，两年前他在尼斯骗了我，”查尔斯说道，“后来又骗了我多次。就在今天，他又骗了我价值两千英镑的法国银行的钞票，钞票就在他身上！”

上校一言不发，不过专员笑了。“他今天做了什么，我不知道，”他说，“不过，你说的他两年前做的事，也未免太没有根据了，你说得太离谱了。因为他那时还在印度，我当时也在印度，到那儿去看望他。”

“那两千英镑呢？”查尔斯叫道，“你可是拿到手了！信封还在你手上！”

上校把信封拿了出来。“这个信封，”他说道，“是那位留着又短又硬头发的男子留下的，就是在你进来之前的那位。他说自己是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，说自己对印度阿萨姆邦的茶叶感兴趣，想让我加入某个皮包公司的董事会。我想，这里面装的就是他的文件。”说着，把它递给了自己的堂兄。

“这样，不管怎么说，钱还在，这也让我欣慰了，”查尔斯低声说道，如释重负，不过又觉得有点不对，“你能把钱还给我吗？”

专员把信封里的东西拿了出来，全是当时一些皮包公司的售股章程，没什么用。

“肯定是梅德赫斯特装进来的，”我叫道，“然后自己携款逃跑了。”

查尔斯吓了一跳，拍着自己的脑门，惊恐地吼道：“梅德赫斯特就是克雷上校！”

“对不起，先生，”那上校插话道，“我只有一个身份，没用过什么化名。”

我们足足花了半个小时才向他解释清楚事件的原委，不过等到我们用法语和英语把来龙去脉都解释完，让法官还有我们感到欣慰的是，这位真正的上校极为体谅地同我们握手言和，还说自己不止一次纳闷，为什么在巴黎说出自己名字的时候，别人总是投来那种深疑的目光。我们告知警方真正的罪犯是梅德赫斯特，他们亲眼所见，我们还督促他们全力追捕。与此同时，我和查尔斯来到法兰西银行，打算马上终止那些钞票的支付。与我们同行的还有上校以及他堂兄——用他们的话说，想“把好戏看完”。不过，我们晚了一步。一位穿着一身美国服饰的讨人喜欢的小妇人，立刻把这些期票贴现并取走了，换成了黄金。后来，旅店老板（根据我们的描述）指认，她就是自己的房客皮卡迪特夫人。很显然，为了接近那位印度上校，她在这家旅店开了房间，那些信件全是她收发的。至于我们那死对头，同以前一样，消失得无影无踪。

两天后，我们同以前一样，收到了一封羞辱信，是在查尔斯自己精美的纸签上写的。上一次，他用的是克雷盖拉奇家的信签，这一次，他就像是嬉戏的田凫一样，又飞跃了一个新的高度。

世上最聪明的百万富翁！——我还是梅德赫斯特的时候，不是说过嘛，谁都不能轻信。你做梦都想不到，有个不该相信的人就是——梅德赫斯特。不过也看得出别人对我多么信任！我告诉过你，我知道克雷上校的下落——我确实知道他在哪儿。我也答应过你，把你带到他的房间，让你抓他——这个诺言也兑现了。甚至还超过了你的预期，因为我给你带来的不是一位克雷上校，而是两位——不过，你抓错了——换句话说，你把真的克雷上校抓着了。虽说是个小伎俩，不过也让我费了不少心思。

首先，我发现，真的有一位叫克雷上校的，在驻印部队里，还发现他刚好这个时节要告假回家。当然，我本可以在他身上再多做点文章，不过我不想把他惹恼，我倒是更愿意享受一下这一独特骗局的乐趣。于是，我就等他抵达巴黎；与伦敦相比，这里的警力安排对我更有利。就在我四处打探、准备推迟行动的时候，碰巧得知你想找位侦探，于是我就给老东家马维尔说，自己失业了，以前他给我找过不少好活儿。总之，于是你就这样见到了上校本人。

当然了，这件事以后，我再也不能回到马维尔那儿做侦探了。不过，从长远来看，自从有幸认识你以来，我便学会了如何工作赚钱，这点小事也就不足为道了。说句真心话，我开始觉得侦探这类工作比我的工作还是低了一两个层次。我现在是位有钱有闲的绅士。还有，我在你家时又掌握了有关你行踪的大量信息，这有助于让我将来通过各种方式进一步把控你。所以，肝蛭依然会忠心耿耿地叮着自己的宠物羊。换个比方，就是，你的羊毛还没有完全剪干净。

代我向你那可爱的家人致以诚挚的问候，也代我向温特沃斯问好，告诉西塞琳我恨她，我会永远记在心底。她显然在怀疑我。亲爱的查尔斯，你的钱太多了，我替你分担一点，给你的钱袋子放点血。因此，我觉得自己是——你最忠实的朋友，

克雷-布拉巴宗-梅德赫斯特，

皇家外科医师学会会员

查尔斯要中风了，这次受的打击太大。“我还能相信谁呢？”查尔斯悲伤地问道，“我雇来保护自己的侦探，到头来却是个骗子？你还记不记得拉丁语中有这么一句——我想原话大概是‘Quis custodes custodiet ipsos？’，意思大致是‘监管之人，谁人监管？’”。

而我却觉得，至少这件事打消了我对可怜的西塞琳的疑心。

第八章　塞尔登金矿

在回伦敦的路上，查尔斯同马维尔就梅德赫斯特这件事产生了不同的看法。

查尔斯认为，马维尔应该清楚那名剪了短发的男子就是克雷上校，绝不该向他举荐此人。马维尔则认为，查尔斯同克雷上校会面也有六七次了，而他自己则从未见过克雷上校；还说，查尔斯被骗，谁都不怨，只能怪我内兄自己。这位侦探头头说，自己认识梅德赫斯特有十年了，他是个相当体面的人，甚至还交地方税。还说自己发现他是侦探里面最聪明的，他实际上靠的也是常见的“以贼捕贼”这一方法。不过，说归说，同以往一样，到头来还是一场空。马维尔为失去了一位这么能干的助手感到遗憾，不过他说自己已尽了最大努力来帮查尔斯爵士，要是查尔斯爵士还不满意，那查尔斯以后就自己去抓克雷上校好了。

“西，我会抓住他的。”查尔斯对我说，此时我们正从皮卡迪利广场边的斯特兰德酒店里的办公室往家走。“我再也不相信这些私人侦探了。我觉得他们自己就是一帮贼，同他们要抓的无赖是一伙的，跟那祖鲁的钻石劳工一样，没有什么廉耻可言。”

“还是让警察试试吧！”我提议，想帮帮他。作为员工，总得摆出一副对雇主的事情很上心的样子。

但查尔斯摇摇头。“算了，算了，”他说，“我受够了这些家伙。以后，我只能靠自己的聪明才智了。西，咱们吸取经验教训——我也学了一两招。其中一条就是：光是怀疑所有人还不够，而且你不得有任何先入之见。要对付这种无赖，你必须要彻底摒弃所有的成见，不要急于下结论。对任何人、任何事，我们都要怀疑。这样方能成功，我就打算这么做。”

查尔斯回到塞尔登，着手此事。

“那人越来越得寸进尺，”一天早上，他对我说，“他就像一只舔到血的老虎。每一次得手之后，只会让他更加渴盼下一次的行动。现在，我完全相信，咱们不久就会在这儿再次碰到他。”

大约三周后，我内兄果然收到了一封信，是那个寡廉鲜耻的骗子写的，贴了张奥地利的邮票，盖的是维也纳的邮戳。

亲爱的凡德里夫特（咱们在各种场合彼此交往的时间也不短了，就没什么必要傻乎乎一本正经地称彼此“查尔斯爵士”“克雷上校”了吧）：

我写这信是想问你一个敏感的问题。能否劳烦你告诉我，在过去三年中，我从你各种慷慨的行为中到底收了多少钱？这个时候我该申报个人所得税了，可我的账簿不知放到哪儿了。我是位诚实守信有良知的公民，要急着填上这三年来平均每年从你那儿赚的钱。不管我是在巴黎还是在其他地方，这一次我没有写自己的个人住址，原因想必你很快就会十分清楚的。你要是能把总额登个广告，署名“傻子彼得”，登在《泰晤士报》

的私事广告栏上，也就给税收专员们帮了个大忙了，同时也给你这位忠实的朋友帮了个大忙。

库斯伯特·克雷，

一位实干的社会主义者

“西，记住我的话，”查尔斯把信放下，说道，“不出一周，他就会采取进一步行动。他想用这种狡猾的手段让我觉得他现在不在国内，离塞尔登还远着呢！这也就意味着，他现在正在盘算着下一次的行动。不过，上一次他还是梅德赫斯特侦探的时候，已经向我们透露得太多。他说的关于伪装以及如何识破伪装的那几点，我一直都记着呢。这一次，我要跟他把账算清楚。”

那一周的星期六，我们沿着道路往前走，那条路一直通向村子，这时我们碰到一位风度翩翩的男子，身着一身粗糙、相当随便的棕色花呢外衣，看起来像是游客。他是个中年人，中等身材，肩上挂着一个小皮包，盯着石头仔细看，形迹可疑。他的步态引起了我们的注意。

“早上好！”我们路过时，他抬头向我们打招呼。查尔斯低沉着声音，含含糊糊地咕哝了句“早上好”。

我们继续往前走，没说话。等走到别人听不到我们说话时，我说：“不管怎么说，那个家伙不是克雷上校，因为是他先跟我们搭的讪。你也许记得，克雷上校最奇特的一点就是，他就像个乖巧的孩子，别人不跟他说话，他绝不先张口——从不会主动去结识谁。总是等着我们先行动，他不会主动上前骗我们，而是等着我们去请他来骗我们。”

“西摩，”我内兄答道，口气严厉，“你现在就犯了这个错误，做了我提醒你千万别做的事！你有偏见。抛开这些固有的成见。这个人很可能就是克雷上校。塞尔登这儿很少有陌生人，我倒想知道，他要不是克雷上校，那他在这儿干吗呢？这儿还有别的路子赚钱吗？我得打听打听这个人。”

我们顺路到了克罗默蒂·阿姆斯旅店，去问问好心的拉克伦夫人，看看她能不能告诉我们一些关于这位温文尔雅的陌生人的事。她说，他来自伦敦，她认为他是位非常和善的绅士，他妻子也同他一起。

“哈，年轻吗？漂亮吗？”查尔斯问道，意味深长地看了我一眼。

“怎么说呢，查尔斯爵士，她绝不是你眼中所谓的漂亮小姑娘，”拉克伦夫人答道，“不过，她是位好人，一位不错的妇人。”

“果然不出我所料，”查尔斯低声说，“他又改变套路了。那家伙让她扮过副牧师的妻子‘白石南花’，扮过皮卡迪克夫人，扮过眯着眼的小格兰顿夫人，还充当过梅德赫斯特的同谋。可现在，想再让她扮成一位真正年轻漂亮的女人，他已黔驴技穷，所以最后只好把她打扮得更成熟一点——一位有气质的妇人。聪明，相当聪明，不过——我们开始看穿他了。”说罢，他一个人悄悄地笑出声来。

第二天，我们在山坡上又碰到了那位陌生人，他还和上次一样，正全神贯注地盯着石头，还拿着锤子敲敲，听听声音。查尔斯用胳膊肘推了我一下，悄声说道：“这次我全猜到了，他乔装成了一位地质学家。”

我仔细地打量着那个人。当然，对于克雷上校的各种乔装，我们目前也有了一定的经验。可以看到，虽然他鼻子、头发还有胡子都变了，但眼睛和身材仍同以前一样。他有一点发福，当然啦，因为他要乔装成四五十岁的人。他额头的皱纹，即便一个比克雷上校技术差得多的骗子也能轻易学得来。不过，我觉得，我们起码要有一定的根据，才能认为他就是克雷上校；要是对这些表明他身份的特征置之不顾，以为只不过是我们一时的凭空想象，这也不妥。

他妻子就坐在附近一块突起的石头上，正读着一本诗集。哈！一本诗集，这一转变也够妙的！这同一个有教养的家庭简直是绝配。“白石南花”还有格兰顿夫人从不读诗。不过，这也是克雷上校夫妇——我觉得我该这么称呼他俩——乔装的过人之处。他们不仅仅对外表进行伪装；在伪装这方面，这两人配合得可谓天衣无缝。这两人都是演员，也是一对无赖；在这两方面，他俩简直无人能敌。

对于那些擅自闯入塞尔登的人，查尔斯从不客气，只给他们短短的一点时间，接着便立即将他们轰出去。不过，因为他这次另有目的，所以就客客气气的。他走近那位女士，鞠了个躬，搭话道：“天气很不错，不是吗？海边这一带，石南花散发着清香。我猜，你住在旅店？”

“是的，”女士答道，抬头看他，脸上挂着迷人的微笑，（“我认得这个笑容，”查尔斯小声对我说，“多少次我都被它迷住了。”）“我们住在旅店，我丈夫在这儿的山上做点地质学方面的事情。希望查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士不会过来抓我们。他对那些不请自入的人毫不客气，旅店的人说他通常脾气很坏。”

（“还是那股漂亮风骚劲儿，”查尔斯对我低声说，“她是故意这么说的。”）“你误会了，亲爱的女士，”他继续道，声音很大，“别人说的根本不对。我就是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，我脾气并不坏。你丈夫要是科学家，我会敬重和仰慕他。我能有今天，也全靠地质学。”说到这儿，他自豪地挺了挺身子，“一切都要归功于当今南非采矿业的发展。”

她的脸红了，是那种真的很少见到的成熟妇女的脸红——不过，我见过皮卡迪特夫人还有“白石南花”就如此这般红过脸。“啊，万分抱歉，”她说，语气有点不知所措，让人想起了格兰顿夫人，“我说得这么草率，请原谅。我——我不知道您就是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士。”

（“她肯定知道，”查尔斯小声说，“不过，先不管它。”）“哈，这事就别再想了。想必你也知道，太多的人侵扰鸟类，我们有时出于自我防卫，有责任警告一下那些擅自闯入的人，让他们离开这些漂亮的山川。这么做，我也很遗憾——非常遗憾。我自己热爱——嗯——大自然的美景；因此，也希望其他所有人都尽可能有机会亲近自然——说‘尽可能’，意思就是，总得弄清楚是在谁的地盘上。”

“我明白了，”女士答道，抬起头奇怪地望着他，“我很欣赏您的这一想法，不过，我觉得您不应该有这些顾虑。我刚读到华兹华斯这些优美的诗句——

哦，泉水，草地，山川，果园，

我们之间的爱永不会断。

“想必您也读过吧？”她冲他甜甜一笑。

“读过吧？”查尔斯答道，“读过！当然读过。我过去最喜欢这几句——实际上，我仰慕华兹华斯。”（我怀疑查尔斯这辈子到底有没有读过诗，《体育时报》上多斯·柴德多斯[30]写的诗除外。）他接过书，扫了几眼。“哦，优美，写得太优美了！”他说道，语气极为兴奋。不过，他两眼一直盯着的是那妇人，而不是书上诗人的名字。

突然间，我明白了。不管那女子乔装成什么样，也不论他有没有认出她，查尔斯总会被皮卡迪特夫人的魅力折服。此刻，他实际上已经怀疑她了，可他还是像飞蛾绕着蜡烛那样，尽自己最大的努力把翅膀烧焦！有这么精明的头脑，却还做出这种事来，我都要鄙视他了。我坚信，一旦涉及女人这个问题，那些最了不起的人也就变成了最糊涂的人。

此时，她丈夫溜达了过来，同我们交谈。据他说，他叫福布斯—盖斯克尔，是北方一所新式学院的地质学教授，到塞尔登这儿来寻找矿石，发现了很多让他感兴趣的东西。他喜欢化石，不过对岩石还有矿石有一种特殊爱好。他对烟水晶、玛瑙以及其他诸如此类的漂亮石头相当了解，还给查尔斯看了看山坡崖壁中的石英、长石、红色光玉髓，以及其他一些山坡峭壁上我所不知道的矿石。查尔斯装着抱有极大兴趣甚至怀着崇敬之情的样子在听他说，绝不让对方有片刻怀疑自己知道他现学现卖背后的目的。要是我们想抓住这个人，就不能让他发现我们在怀疑他。因此，查尔斯把他蒙在鼓里。那地质学家说什么，查尔斯都毫无异议地全盘接受。

那天早上的大部分时间，我们都一起待在山上。查尔斯带着他们到处转转，把一切都看了一遍。他装作对那位科学家很客气的样子，对那位爱诗的女士，他则是发自内心地客气，极为客气。不到午饭时间，我们就已经成为非常要好的朋友了。

克雷夫妇二人总是易于相处；虽然他们干些无赖的事，不过，我们不能否认同他们相处很愉快。查尔斯邀请他们一起吃午餐，他们欣然接受。在向艾米莉亚介绍他们时，查尔斯不停地挤眉弄眼。“这二位是福布斯—盖斯克尔教授夫妇，”他说道，使劲使得下巴都快掉了，“亲爱的，他们住在旅店，我带他们在这儿转转，他们一点也不见外，说过来拜访一下，尝尝咱们的冷烤羊肉。”查尔斯经常这么开玩笑。

艾米莉亚带他们到楼上洗手——这对于教授来说绝对有必要，因为他研究石头时手上沾满了泥土。他们一离开，查尔斯就把我拉到书房。

“西摩，”他说，“我们这时最需要避免偏见。我们决不能认为这人就是克雷上校——当然，也不能认为他不是。我们要记住，咱们过去在这两种情况下都犯过错，现在要坚决避免旧错重犯。不管今天是哪种情况，我都会随时做好准备——有必要的话，会叫一名警察来随时待命抓捕他们！”

“计划太妙了！”我低声道，“不过，请允许我提个建议，这两个人到底想怎么给我们下套呢？他们目前没什么阴谋——没什么城堡，也没什么公司合并。”

“西摩，”我内兄说道，一副董事会议事的口吻，“你有点太着急了，梅德赫斯特这么说过你——我是指克雷上校乔装成的梅德赫斯特。首先，咱们才开始接触，他们还没想好要做什么，我们也许不久就会发现他们有份财产要卖，或者有个公司要筹办，再或者有在南非或其他地方开发土地的特许权。其次，在他们的计划在我们手上引爆之前，或者说真相大白之前，我们总是不知道他们葫芦里卖的什么药。在梅德赫斯特侦探带着我们的钱胜利出逃之前，还有什么能比他更容易看穿的吗？‘白石南花’还有小副牧师把艾米莉亚自己的珠宝卖给我们，我们觉得像是捡了个大便宜。事发前，还有比他们更单纯无知的吗？我不会因为没有发现某个人正要针对我们实施不轨图谋，而理所当然地认为他就不是克雷上校。那个无赖诡计太多，有一些掩饰得太好，就像精神上的炸药，直到真正爆炸了，你才会察觉。因此，我会小心行事，就仿佛这种炸药无处不在。不过，最后一点——这一点非常重要——记住我的话，我觉得我已经察觉到了他要耍的套路。他说自己是地质学家，会品鉴矿石。很好。你会发现，要是他没有很快就劝我，说自己发现了一处煤矿，具体位置需要给点酬金才会透露，那么他就会骗我说，长山上有绿宝石，但要很大的一部分股份才会帮我探寻；再者，他会想方设法说些地质学方面的东西来骗我。这家伙的脸上全都一清二楚地写着呢；这一次，不管他有什么借口，我都坚决一个子儿不给，也不会让他从我的手中逃掉！”

我们进去吃午饭，福布斯—盖斯克尔夫妇同我们一起，满脸笑容。不知是不是受了查尔斯“凡事不要想当然”这一提醒的影响——吃饭时，我一直紧盯着我们所怀疑的那个人。我发现他的头发很是怪异。他满头头发的颜色不一，后面在外套领口处耷拉下来的一绺，比其他大部分乌黑的头发颜色稍浅和略白。我仔细地看了看，越是这样，我越相信他戴的是假发。这一点不容置疑。

这也许比克雷上校大多数时候的乔装要逊色些，不过这时，我想到（查尔斯“凡事不要想当然”的原则），我们从未怀疑过克雷上校，除了他乔装成大卫阁下的那次，他那红头发还有络腮胡子，连皮卡迪特夫人都忍不住指着哧哧笑道太假了。不管哪件事，要是我们仔细地审视我们要找的这个人，有点眼力，就本应该能立刻（如梅德赫斯特所说）发现伪装中的破绽。

那位侦探实际上已经向我们透露了太多。我还记得，他说我们怀疑大卫·格兰顿时，应如何去碰掉他的假发。当男仆端上土豆条时，我立刻蹩手蹩脚地要给自己夹一些，这样胳膊肘就能漫不经心地扫到那假发上。不过，这一切都是徒劳。那家伙似乎预料到，或者说察觉到了我的动机，便小心地躲开了，像是已经习惯了维持自己的伪装，避免一切或真或假的意外。

我满脑子想的都是这个新的发现，一吃完饭，就哄伊莎贝尔，让她带着这两位新朋友去家里的花园转转，给他们看看查尔斯那上等的大丽花，而我则赶快告诉查尔斯还有艾米莉亚这一发现，还有这次失败的尝试。

“是假发，”艾米莉亚表示同意，“我一眼就看出来了。十分不错的假发，戴得也十分巧妙。男人注意不到这些，不过女人会留意。西摩，你能发现这一点，值得表扬。”

查尔斯则不太领情。“你个笨蛋，”他说道，这司空见惯的坦率让人不悦，“假设说那就是假发，为什么要试着把它蹭掉去揭露他呢？有什么用吗？如果那真是假发，被我们发现了，这不就行了吗？我们就提防一下，知道自己在同谁打交道。你总不能因为某个人戴假发就把人抓起来啊。法律管不了这事。大多数体面人物有时也戴假发，我知道有位公司创始人戴假发，有位掌管着十四家公司的董事也戴！我们下一步要做的就是，等他来骗我们，然后——把他一举拿下。你放心，他的计划早晚会露出马脚的。”

于是，我们制订了一套绝佳的方案，随时监视他们，以免他们再次溜走，就像上次从岛上逃掉那样。首先，艾米莉亚去请他们到城堡中住下，就说旅店房间太小，住着不舒适。然而，我们觉得，他们肯定会同上一次那样，谢绝好意，因为万一他们发现自己受到了明显的怀疑，便可以神不知鬼不觉地溜掉。万一他们拒绝，只要他们还住在克罗默蒂·阿姆斯旅店，我们就让西塞琳也在那儿住着，报告他们的行踪。同时，白天我们让侍从领班的儿子来监视整个房子，那个小伙子十分机敏，有一股真正的苏格兰人的精明劲儿，为人可靠，不会向任何人透露任何消息。

让我们万万没想到的是，福布斯—盖斯克尔夫人满口答应，接受了邀请。她再三表示感谢，说阿姆斯旅店的管理不行，做的饭菜对她丈夫的肝脏也不好。我们能邀请他们真是太贴心了，没想到我们对素昧平生之人会这么友善。她不停地说，自己从未碰到过比在塞尔登城堡更热忱、更友好的款待了。问题是——她坦然地接受了邀请。

“肯定不是克雷上校，”我对查尔斯说，“克雷上校决不会住在这儿的。他冒充大卫·格兰顿时，住过来是多么顺理成章，即便这样，他也不愿意落入我们的股掌之间：他喜欢在克罗默蒂·阿姆斯旅店的那种自由，还有安全感。”

“西，”我内兄简洁地训诫道，“你真是不可救药，总摆脱不了偏见的影响。他接受邀请，或许是出于自己的某种考虑。等着吧！等到他准备行动时——那时候，一切都会真相大白。”

就这样，在接下来的三周内，福布斯—盖斯克尔夫妇也参加了我们在塞尔登举办的家庭宴会。不得不说，查尔斯对他们极为关心。为了同这两位亲近，他很明显怠慢了其他客人。福布斯—盖斯克尔夫人发现了这一点。“查尔斯爵士，你对我们太热情了，”她说，“怕是我们把你都独占了！”

可查尔斯，同以前一样大胆，微笑着答道：“你也清楚，你同我们在一起的时间却这么短！”听到这话，福布斯—盖斯克尔夫人的面颊又泛起了可爱的红霞。

在这段时间里，教授一直在继续潜心钻研矿石。“真够可以的！”查尔斯对我说，“他演得可真像那么一回事！说到对科学的热爱，还有什么能同眼下这个场景相比？”的确，他从早到晚一心扑在上面。“他迟早会露出马脚的。”查尔斯说道。

同时，有两件小事值得注意。一天，我和教授一同到长山上去，我看着他对着石头敲敲打打，有点受够了他的装模作样。这时，为了打发时间，我问他某个被流水磨平的小石头是什么。他看了看，微微一笑。“要是里面云母再多一些，”他说，“就是附近一带典型的冰川砾石形成的片麻岩。可惜里面云母不太多。”说着，他仔细地打量着那块石头。

“实际上，”我接过话，“这算不上样品，对吧？”

他严厉地瞪了我一眼。“百分之十，”他说道，声音很低，很怪异，“通常是百分之十。”

我抖得厉害。他是不是想让我身败名裂？“你要是胆敢说出来——”我大声喊道，但又打住了。

“你说这话什么意思？”他问道，一脸茫然。

我想到了查尔斯说的话，凡事不要主观臆断，于是谨慎地就此打住。

第二件小事是这样的。一天下午，中午野餐后，我遗憾地说，查尔斯当时可能是香槟喝多了些，在山上摘了一枝白石南花。他倒没出什么洋相，不过心情很不错，兴致很高，说话口无遮拦。他把花枝拿到福布斯—盖斯克尔夫人面前，递给她，有点眉目传情。“人美花美，”他咕哝道，紧紧地盯着她，“白石南花送给‘白石南花’。”他立刻意识到了自己的言行，便立马打住。

福布斯—盖斯克尔夫人的脸上又同以往一样泛起了红晕，结结巴巴地说道：“我——我不太明白。”

查尔斯牵强附会地解释道：“白石南花代表幸运，”他说，“要是——要是哪位男子有幸能送一枝白石南花给你，他肯定会走运。”

她微微一笑，一点也不领情。我觉得她怀疑我们在怀疑她。

不过，这件麻烦事之后，什么都没有发生。

第二天，查尔斯兴高采烈地冲到我面前。“哈，他终于要行动了！”他大声说道，“我就知道。他昨天找到我，手里拿着——你猜是什么？——一块含金的石英，在长山上找到的。”

“不会吧！”我叫道。

“千真万确，”查尔斯说，“他说那儿有一条矿脉，很明显能看出里面有星星点点的金子，也许值得开采一下。要是有人开始说这种话，你也就明白他是什么意思了！而且，他事先把一切都编好了，因为他接下来跟我说，萨瑟兰郡长期以来一直盛产黄金——为什么不是罗斯郡呢？接着他就开始全面对比了这两个地区的地质状况。”

“这就不是儿戏了，”我说，“你打算怎么办？”

“再等等看，”查尔斯答道，“只要他提议分他一些股票，成立企业联合组织进行开矿，或者索取钱财作为他这一发现的报酬——就立刻报警抓他。”

接下来的几天，教授比以前更积极、更热心了。他拿着锤子，将各处石头都仔细观察一番，不断地带回一些小石头，上面还有星星点点的金子，头头是道地谈着“开矿碎石的大概成本”。查尔斯之前早就听过这一套，实际上，他先后帮助起草过几十份售股章程。因此，他并不在意，就等着那戴假发的男子拿出自己的方案。他知道，这一刻很快就会到来，于是就静观其变。不过，为了引诱他采取进一步行动，他装作对此事很感兴趣。

我们都抱着这种想法，听随天意，观察克雷上校要怎么做。一天，我们沿着海岸朝着与海鸥岛相反的方向散步。突然，我们碰到了那位教授，他正挽着阿道弗斯·科德里爵士的胳膊！二人貌似关系不错，谈得很投入。

现在，自从股价暴跌事件以后，阿道弗斯爵士同凡德里夫特一家的关系自然变得略微紧张些。不过，在目前的情况下，这事关能否抓住克雷上校，这点小隔阂先放一放也无妨。于是，查尔斯便设法把教授与阿道弗斯爵士分开，又让艾米莉亚陪教授回城堡，而自己则在后面停住，同我和阿道弗斯爵士一起把问题厘清。

“你认识他吗，科德里？”他问，稍显狐疑。

“认识他吗？当然，我当然认识，”阿道弗斯爵士回答，“他叫玛玛丢克·福布斯—盖斯克尔，在约克郡大学工作，是一位非常杰出的科学家，一流的矿物学家——也许是（除一个人之外）全英国最了不起的。”出于谦虚，他没说出那个例外的人是何方高士。

“你敢确保他的身份吗？”查尔斯变得更加怀疑，便问道，“你以前认识他吗？不会是第二个施莱尔马赫吧？”

“你敢确保他的身份吗？”阿道弗斯爵士应道，“那我知道自己是谁吗？自从在三一学院时，我就认识玛米[31]·盖斯克尔了，在他同福布斯小姐结婚前就认识他了；他夫人来自格伦卢斯，是我妻子的二表妹，为了不让财产流到族外，便把两人的姓氏连起来做双姓来用[32]。我跟他们俩都非常熟。我到这儿的旅馆来，是因为听说玛米在这一带的山丘中游荡，我想他也许要找些什么宝贝——藏在化石中的某些宝贝。”

“可他戴着假发！”查尔斯提醒他。

“肯定，”科德里答道，“他秃顶得厉害——至少前面是这样——所以他戴假发遮掩一下。”

“这太无耻了，”查尔斯叫道，“无耻——把我们耍成这样。”他脸涨得通红，像只雄火鸡。

阿道弗斯爵士毫无顾忌，突然大笑起来。

“哦，我明白了，”他叫道，一下子来了兴致，“你觉得福布斯—盖斯克尔是克雷上校乔装的！哈，我的天，你可真行！”

“至少你无权取笑我，”查尔斯接过话，挺了挺身子，脸更红了，“你曾经引着我进了一个类似的圈套，接着你从中全身而退，非绅士所为。还有，”查尔斯继续道，每个字眼都冒着愈发浓烈的火气，“这家伙，不管他是谁，总想凭自己的一面之词骗我。不管他是不是克雷上校，但他老是骗我，说我这儿的山丘中有含金石英，还试着诱使我参与一个荒唐可笑的投机活动！”

阿道弗斯爵士忍无可忍。“这太过分了，”他大声说道，“我得告诉玛米！”福布斯—盖斯克尔正同艾米莉亚一起坐在岩石的一角，于是他便急急忙忙过去了。

而我和查尔斯则返回家中。半小时后，福布斯—盖斯克尔也火冒三丈地回来了。

“先生，你这是什么意思？”他看到查尔斯便吼道，“有人跟我说，你邀请我和我妻子到你家来，是想监视我们，觉得我是那个臭名远扬的骗子克雷上校！”

“我之前是这么想的，”查尔斯答道，也同样十分光火，“说不准你就是他！不管怎么说，你是个无赖，想骗我一把！”

福布斯—盖斯克尔脸气得发白，转向正在发抖的妻子。“格特鲁德，”他说，“收拾行李，立刻远离这些人！他们假惺惺地装作好客，实则是一场精心策划的羞辱。他们让你我显得极其荒唐可笑。咱们来这儿之前就有人说——说得一点不错——查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士是全苏格兰最抠门、最专横的老浑蛋。咱们还兴高采烈地写信跟朋友们说，事实与他们说的正相反，说他是最热情、最大方、最大度的绅士。现在，我们知道了，他就是个无耻之徒，装成好人样，出于卑鄙的动机邀请陌生人到他家做客，然后无端地羞辱他们。这种人这辈子应该隔三岔五地听听真话，我倍感荣幸，因为我要告诉查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士：他就是个最没有良心的无赖小人。格特鲁德，去收拾行李！我去克罗默蒂·阿姆斯旅店叫马车，带咱们离开这没人情味儿的假城堡，一分钟也不停留。”

“你戴了假发，先生，可是你戴了假发。”查尔斯叫道，激动得快说不出话了。的确，福布斯—盖斯克尔说话时，气得把头转来转去，戴的假发向一边斜得很厉害。戴假发这事就掩饰不住了。

“先生，我是戴了假发，我还能当着无赖的面甩一甩呢！”教授回敬道，说着把假发扯掉，打算重新戴上；并且为了“说到做到”，还在查尔斯面前甩了三次；接着他气得一句话没说，快步走出房间。

等他们走后，当查尔斯气消得刚能听进别人讲的道理时，我就斗胆说道：“这下错不了了！我们搞错了。我们理所当然地认为，一个人要是戴假发，他就一定是骗子——但这不一定正确。我们忘了头上戴假发的不仅仅是克雷上校，忘了别人戴假发也可能纯粹是出于爱面子。实际上，我们又一次受了偏见的左右。”

我直直地盯着他。查尔斯起身。“西摩·温特沃斯，”他高高在上地怒视着我，终于开口了，“你这番说教讲的可真是时候！我想，你是不是压根儿就不明白作为一位私人秘书的身份与职责！”

不过，这件事最离奇的部分是——查尔斯深信，福布斯—盖斯克尔虽然不是克雷上校，但一直哄他说石头中有金子，想骗他，于是再也没有关注这些所谓的发现。于是，福布斯—盖斯克尔和阿道弗斯一起带着这个秘密去了别处。查尔斯把塞尔登城堡这份地产卖掉时（不久后他就卖掉了，因为他莫名其妙地厌恶这个地方），克雷盖拉奇勋爵就从他手中将它买了过来，并成立了现在的“塞尔登黄金城有限公司”。结果，福布斯—盖斯克尔给克雷盖拉奇说，他在某块地产上发现了一条富矿矿脉，要是给他一定的原始股份的未定权益，他就说出具体的位置。这位勋爵立刻抓住了这个机会。查尔斯以射猎松鸡的沼地的价格把它卖掉了，结果现在即便除去推广的费用，黄金城目前的回报也相当可观——而查尔斯又被骗走了一桩金矿的好买卖！

不过，我时刻谨记自己“作为私人秘书的身份与责任”，当时没有向他挑明，这笔损失源于一个固有的成见——实际上，这一切都源于查尔斯那令人费解的偏见：凡是戴假发的男子，不管是谁，都想骗他。

第九章　镀漆公文箱

“西，”我内兄第二年春天说道，“我受够伦敦了！咱们立刻收拾行囊，远走高飞，到一个别人不认识我的地方去吧！”

“去火星还是水星？”我问道，“要知道，在咱们这个特殊的星球上，要让查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士不露锋芒、不为人知，还真有点困难。”

“哦，我会处理好的，”查尔斯应道，“你要是成天到晚都得‘举止得体’，我真想知道，当个百万富翁究竟有什么好处？我要隐姓埋名去旅行。这些骗子一而再，再而三地跟着我，我彻底受够了。”

实际上，那年冬天极其难熬。克雷上校也已有几个月不见踪影了，这倒是真的。就我而言，我必须承认，因为我没有什么损失，我相当怀念他平日里给我们带来的刺激。不过查尔斯早已疑神疑鬼、草木皆兵，他始终秉着“不信任何人，不信任何事”这一原则，生活已经成了他的负担。他已识破克雷上校的成千上万种伪装，不过那些人都不可能是克雷上校，他还深信自己把对方吓跑十几次之多。有时对方扮成肥胖的酒吧侍者、高挑的警察、洗衣婆的儿子、律师的书记员、英格兰银行的小吏，还有收水费的。就像中世纪的圣徒能随时随地看到恶魔一样，查尔斯也能时时刻刻看到变化多端的上校。我和艾米莉亚真的开始担心他还能否像以前那么精明。我们觉得，除非克雷上校少给我们惹点事，否则查尔斯的头脑会逐渐沦落到一位平庸的证券交易所冒险投机者的水平。

因此，当我内兄宣布他打算在随后的这个星期六隐姓埋名，到某个不为人知的地方时，我和艾米莉亚感到一阵轻松，从长期的紧张状态中解脱出来了。尤其是艾米莉亚——因为她不同他一起出去。

“想休息休息，清静清静，”早饭时，他放下《晨报》对我们说，“让我到大西洋班轮的甲板上去吧！没有信函、电报，不谈股票、股份，也没什么《泰晤士报》，也没什么《星期六报》。这些都让人烦透了！”

“世事纷繁无停歇。”我兴高采烈地表示同意。不过很遗憾，没人体会到我引用这句话的精妙之处[33]。

不得不说，为了绝对保密，查尔斯费了不少心思。他让我不要提他的名字，而是以我自己的名义写信订好伊特鲁里亚号开往纽约下一航班最好的特等舱——在船中部的主甲板上。这次的目的地，他只跟艾米莉亚说了，艾米莉亚警告西塞琳，无论如何绝不能将此事告诉其他用人。为了进一步隐姓埋名，查尔斯乔装成彼得·波特先生，并用这个名字在利物浦订了伊特鲁里亚号的船票。

不过，出发的前一天，我同查尔斯一起去伦敦，同他在老宽街亚当斯厅的经纪人会个面。老搭档芬戈摩尔急忙上前迎接我们。我们走进他的私人房间时，一位长相不错的年轻人便站起身来，信步离去。“好哇，芬戈摩尔，”查尔斯说，“刚刚那位就是你的浪荡兄弟吧？我还以为你早就把他打发到中国去了呢！”

“是把他打发走了，查尔斯爵士，”芬戈摩尔一边答道，一边略显紧张地搓着手，“可他压根儿就没去那个地方。他是个游手好闲的青年，喜欢吃喝玩乐，当时去的最远的地方就是巴黎。从那以后，他到处闲逛，但于己于家无益。不过大约三四年前，不知怎的，他‘开窍了’：去了南非，在你的保护区里偷猎，现在又回来了——有钱了，结了婚，有头有脸。他那漂亮的小娇妻让他洗了心革了面。对了，你今早前来有何贵干？”

查尔斯在美国圣达菲还有托皮卡有不少股份，还有些其他重要事项，所以他坚持带一些与他那广布的商业投资相关的各种公文、证件等材料。他说，这次出行纯粹为了休息、转换心情，是一次普通的个人调查之旅——转转纽约、芝加哥、科罗拉多、采矿区等。这是百万富翁式的休假。于是他把这些所有的贵重物品装进了一只黑色的镀漆公文箱，像小孩一样守着，那股小心劲儿真是荒唐。他的视线一刻也不离开那箱子，为了确保箱子完好无损，也扰得我不得安宁。这真是变态。“我们千万要小心，”他说，“西，要小心！尤其是出门在外。想想那个小副牧师是如何从艾米莉亚的珠宝箱中偷走钻石的！我绝不允许这个箱子离开我的视线。就算咱们葬身海底，我也要带着它。”

我们没有葬身海底。“从未让任何旅客丧生”，这正是丘纳德公司感到自豪之处。仅仅为了能让查尔斯在情况危急时抱着自己的公文箱，就让伊特鲁里亚号葬身海底，船长才不会同意。情况刚好相反，我们的行程很愉快，同行的旅客也都非常易于相处，没什么事情发生。查尔斯化名彼得·波特先生，暂时不用担心克雷上校来骗自己。我觉得要是没有那公文箱，查尔斯一定会非常开心。旅行一开始，他就同一对和善的美国医生夫妇交了朋友（就跟以前一样，无所顾忌，那时克雷上校还没出来扰乱他的生活），那夫妇二人准备回肯塔基。伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯医生——一个典型的美国名字——在维也纳学了一年的医学，现在要回到自己的祖国，他满脑子装的都是细菌学以及抗菌剂方面的最新发现。他妻子是位漂亮且风趣的美国人，身材娇小，鼻头上翘，还有美国女性的机智和精明，这让查尔斯为之倾倒。在甲板的条凳上，她在身旁为查尔斯腾出点空儿，还一边露出甜甜的微笑，一边说道：“波特先生，你就坐这儿吧；太阳可真好。”查尔斯很吃这一套，甚是高兴。他发现女性并不总是因为他的财富还有地位才注意他；还有，他作为一位普普通通的波特先生，别人对他的魅力的欣赏不亚于对大名鼎鼎的南非百万富翁查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士的敬仰，这让他感到自豪。

航程从头到尾，查尔斯张口闭口全都是夸肯鲍斯夫人这，夸肯鲍斯夫人那，幸好艾米莉亚没有在甲板上看到这一切。说实话，早在抵达桑迪岬以前，我就受够了查尔斯天天挂在嘴边的那两件东西——夸肯鲍斯夫人，还有那只公文箱。

我们发现，夸肯鲍斯夫人是位业余画家，风和日丽的时候，她会在甲板上给查尔斯画肖像，极尽各种姿态。好像在她看来，查尔斯是位魅力非凡的模特。

那位医生也是不可多得，非常聪明。他对化学有些研究——许多其他的学科（我猜，也包括人类性格）也略有涉猎，因为他跟查尔斯谈了自己的想法，说回去打算用这些想法“让肯塔基那儿的人变得有活力一些”，说得查尔斯对他的这些想法和事业赞不绝口。“西，那个家伙能说到做到！”查尔斯有一天对我说，“他说一不二！这种美国人才是真正的男人。多希望我在南非的工矿里能有上百来号这种人！”

查尔斯的这一愿望变得越来越强烈，他都有点沉醉于其中了。他最近辞掉了克罗地多普矿上的一名主管，正在认真地考虑要不要把这个位置留给那位精明的肯塔基人。就我而言，我倒是觉得这件事同他说过的今后每年要有三个月待在南非的公司有关。我也开始怀疑，他是不是觉得能有位离奇且有趣的美国妇人做伴，在克罗地多普的日子会好过很多。

“不要忘了，”我说，“你要给他这一职位，就得暴露自己的身份。”

“大可不必，”查尔斯回答，“在一切安排妥当之前，我可以暂时隐瞒自己的身份，只需说，我在南非有些股份就行了。”

于是，一天早上，我们快要到班克斯镇时，查尔斯在甲板上向医生夫妇二人小心地说出了自己的想法。他说自己同南半球最大的金融财团有联系，会每年付伊莱休一千五百块让他到矿区代自己做事。

“什么？美元吗？”那女士问道，边问边微笑着，这一笑鼻头就翘得更厉害了，“啊，波特先生，这不够！”

“不是美元，夫人，是英镑，”查尔斯回应道，“英镑，换成美元的话，合七千五百美元。”

“我想，伊莱休肯定会毫不犹豫就接受的。”夸肯鲍斯夫人边说边探询地盯着丈夫。

医生大笑。“先生，你出的价码不错，”他一字一顿，以美国人的方式缓缓地说道，“可是你忽略了一点。我是科学家，不是投机者。我付出了相当大的成本在欧洲最好的大学接受医学训练，我才不会把自己辛辛苦苦获得的成果抛到一边，转身跳到另一个新行当里。再说了，能不能适应这个新行当还是个问题。”

（“彻头彻尾的美国佬。”我在背后小声咕哝了一句。）

查尔斯一再坚持，不过一切都是徒劳。夸肯鲍斯夫人心动了，不过那医生却总是面带狮身人面像一般神秘莫测的笑容，他还反复重申，自己坚信半路改行就如同中途换马、危局易人——不合适。他越是拒绝，说得越头头是道，查尔斯就越想说服他。另外，医生每天都会拿出越来越多让人意想不到的证据，来证明自己在各方面的能力，好像故意要引诱查尔斯。“我不是什么专家，”他说，“我只是抓住重点，抓住核心，其余的就随它去吧。”

他好像真的无所不能，能给骡子钉掌钉，还能组织一场野营聚会。他是位了不起的化学家、无可挑剔的外科医生、品鉴马肉的行家、玩尤克牌的高手，还是讨人喜欢的男中音。如有需要，他还能登台布道。他发明了一种拔塞器，让自己小赚了一笔。当前，他正在翻译一篇波兰语的文章《论氢氰酸在麻风病治疗中的应用》。

不过，当我们抵达纽约时，我们在说服夸肯鲍斯医生方面并没有什么新进展。在码头上，他上前同我们道别，脸上还挂着那副神秘莫测的笑容。查尔斯则一手抓着公文箱，另一只手攥着夸肯鲍斯夫人的小手。

“千万别说这是最后的见面了！”他说道，声音颤抖得厉害。

“恐怕真是最后一次了，波特先生。”那位漂亮的美国妇人答道，说着递了个眼色，“你们住在哪家酒店？”

“莫里山酒店。”查尔斯答道。

“天哪，不是太巧了吗？”夸肯鲍斯夫人应道，“莫里山酒店！巧不巧！伊莱休，咱们也住在那家酒店！”

查尔斯劝他们在回肯塔基州之前，抽出几天时间陪我们一起去乔治湖还有尚普兰湖转转，希望能在那儿说服这位倔强的医生。

于是，我们去了乔治湖，住进了位于铁路终点站的一家很不错的酒店。在酒店与通往泰孔德罗加的路之间有通勤的小型轻载蒸汽船，我们很多时间是在那上面度过的。不知怎的，映在碧绿湖水中的山峦让我想起了卢塞恩，进而又想到了小副牧师。自打我们离开英国以来，我第一次隐隐地感到被恐惧包围。夸肯鲍斯会不会又是克雷上校乔装的，一直跟着我们来到了大洋彼岸？

我忍不住把这一想法跟查尔斯提了提——很奇怪，他却对此嗤之以鼻。他那天一直在向夸肯鲍斯夫人大献殷勤，那位美国小妇人用扇子敲了敲他的指节，叫了他一声“小傻瓜”，他就兴奋得不知所以了。

不过，第二天发生了一件奇怪的事。我们四人一起沿着湖畔散步，湖的四周全是树木，树下覆了一层奇异的三角形的花——夸肯鲍斯夫人称之为延龄草——还有一排排漂亮的蕨类植物，它们是春天里第一批冒出绿色的植物。

我开始诗兴大发。（年轻时，去南非前我写过诗。）我们躺在草地上，身旁是一小股山溪，溪水从上方矗立的树林里沿着满是青苔的石块中间流下来。那位肯塔基人全身舒展地躺在草地上，就在查尔斯的前方。他留了一头奇怪的头发，非常浓密、蓬松。不知为何，这突然让我想到了那位墨西哥先知，他是克雷上校的第一个化身，我们一直记着。就在这时，查尔斯头脑中好像也冒出了同样的想法，因为，说来也怪，他一时兴起，就俯身向前，仔细观察那头发。我看到夸肯鲍斯夫人感到纳闷，还往后退了退。那头发太浓密，不像是真的。我现在还记得，他前额处的发际线十分整齐。这会不会也是假发呢？似乎极有可能。

正当我思量这件事时，查尔斯好像突然下定了决心。他用他那有力的手以迅雷不及掩耳之势一把抓住医生的头发，想使劲把它扯掉。这次他猜错了。接着，医生疼得号叫起来，听得人毛骨悚然，几根头发从头皮上被连根拔起，攥在查尔斯手上，头皮上被拔掉头发的地方还有几滴血。毫无疑问，这浓密、蓬松的头发不是假发，是那位肯塔基人天生的。

接下来的场面，我已无力描述，任何文字都显得苍白。医生起身，与其说是生气，倒不如说是感到震惊；他面色苍白，一副难以置信的神情。“你究竟想干吗？”他问道，生气地瞪着我内兄。查尔斯不停地赔礼道歉，不断地忏悔，主动提出要做些适当的补偿，不管是通过金钱还是其他方式。接着，他便把秘密和盘托出，说自己是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，就是那位知名的百万富翁，有个叫克雷上校的人总是不断地用阴谋诡计骗他，让他深受其苦；那个克雷上校是个狡猾的无赖，在全欧洲不断地跟踪他，一刻也不消停。他又详尽地描述了那个骗子是如何用假发和蜡来乔装的，甚至连最亲近的人都认不出来。接着他又请求夸肯鲍斯医生原谅他，说自己被骗得太多且太惨了，有时也冤枉了一些最正派的人。夸肯鲍斯夫人说怀疑也是正常的——她说得很坦诚：“尤其是伊莱休的头发好像是从前额冒出来的，很引人注意，早就有人发现这一点了。”她还把他的头发撩起来给我们看。不过伊莱休伤了脸面，又气又恼。“你要是想知道，”他说，“不妨问一下我。要想知道一个人的头发是不是真的，进行人身攻击这种方式可不合适。”

“是一时冲动，”查尔斯赔礼道，“本能的冲动！”

“文明人会抑制冲动，”医生回应道，“你在南非住得太久了，波特先生——我是说，查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，不知道咱们面前的这种绅士还配不配得上这一名号。你貌似染上了与你共同生活的南非黑人的行为习惯。”

不得不说，在接下来的两天里，我不敢相信查尔斯竟然会因为其他人而如此情绪低落。他确确实实放下了身段。因为，他意识到自己伤了夸肯鲍斯医生的感情，并且——让我大为惊奇的是——他貌似由衷地对此感到伤心。如果给医生一千英镑能让双方立即握手言和，不计前嫌，我觉得查尔斯肯定会乐于这么做。实际上，他已经通过其他方式向夸肯鲍斯夫人表达了此意——因为他不能说给她钱，以免羞辱了她。夸肯鲍斯夫人也尽自己所能来调解此事，她虽然有些淘气，但心肠不坏；不过伊莱休对此却敬而远之。查尔斯仍继续催他去南非，把价码开到了每年两千英镑，不过医生仍不为所动。“不行，不行，”他答道，“我本来快打算接受你的提议了——可是发生了那件倒霉事，不过也好，这件事也就就此作罢。作为一位美国公民，我拒绝做某位英国贵族的代表，他那调查问题的方式不仅让我丢了些头发，还让我丢了心情。”

我不知道查尔斯是否会因为克罗地多普矿失去一位如此精明的主管而大失所望，还是会因为第一次有人称他为“某位英国贵族”而感到高兴，要知道英国人可不认为殖民地的爵士是什么贵族。

三天后，夸肯鲍斯夫妇二人按照计划要离开湖畔酒店。我们准备自己到湖上游玩一番，这时那位漂亮的小妇人突然进来，说他们要走了。她穿了一身美式旅行衣，干干净净、整整齐齐，十分迷人。查尔斯深情地握住她的手。“真遗憾，”他说，“现在得说再见了，我已尽了全力来说服你丈夫。”

“我比你费的口舌还多，”那妇人答道，她那上翘的鼻子更显得楚楚动人，“因为我不愿意在肯塔基待一辈子！不过，伊莱休这人，对女的软硬都不吃，所以我们只能忍忍吧。”她冲我们甜甜一笑，就再也不见了踪影。

查尔斯那天一整天都郁郁不乐。第二天早上起床，他说打算向西出发做些调查。科罗拉多的白银矿脉会让他沉醉其中。

查尔斯此行连辛普森都没带，我们只能自己收拾旅行皮箱，然后准备出发，乘早班列车去萨拉托加。

查尔斯自始至终一直在小心地看护着他那只公文箱。不过在“行李搬运工”把我们的行李带下去时，有位女服务员懒洋洋地在周围转来转去，想要小费。他把公文箱在中间的桌子上放了一会儿，就自己去收拾其他随身行李了。他的烟盒不见了，就回到卧室找找。我帮他一起找，可是那烟盒就是神秘地消失了。他一时之间不知所措。等我们找到烟盒回到客厅时——看哪！公文箱不见了！查尔斯问了几个服务生，都说没看见。他又在屋子里找来找去——一点影子也没有。

“可是，我在两分钟前明明就把它放在这儿的！”他叫道。不过叫也没用。

“到时候，箱子自己就出来了，”我说，“一切东西到头来都会冒出（翘起）[34]来的——夸肯鲍斯夫人的鼻子也不例外。”

“西摩，”我内兄答道，“你这玩笑开得可真是时候。”

说实在的，查尔斯当时气疯了。他坐电梯下楼到所谓的“办事处”（他们是这么叫的），向经理投诉了此事。那位经理是个纽约人，脸庞轮廓分明，一边微笑一边漠然地说道，客人携带的贵重物品应当按照要求交予酒店保管，酒店会将物品锁到保险箱中，待客人离开时再归还给他们。查尔斯情绪有点激动，说自己被抢了，还说找不到公文箱，所有人都不能离开酒店半步。那位经理相当冷静，一边冒冒失失地剔着牙，一边回应道，这在欧洲那种规模的酒店也许可行，只有大约几百位客人；不过，这是美国的酒店，住着一千多名旅客——每天都有人来有人走——不会因为某个外国人的要求，而采取这种不切实际的措施。

“外国人”这个字眼戳到了查尔斯的痛处。不管在哪儿，没有哪位英国人会承认自己是外国人[35]。“先生，你知道我是谁吗？”查尔斯生气地问，“我是来自伦敦的查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士——英国国会议员。”

“你也可能是英国王子，”那人回敬道，“这与我又有何干？在美国，你同其他人的待遇一样。不过，话又说回来，要是你是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，”他继续道，手里翻着名册，“为什么要登记成彼得·波特先生？”

查尔斯窘得满脸通红。又多了一层麻烦。

那只公文箱一直放在皮箱里，盖子内侧用白色标准字体清清楚楚地写着“查尔斯·凡德里夫特一等勋爵士”。这场意外真把查尔斯害惨了：他丢了宝贵的文件，用了假名字，并且把酒店经理惹得已经毫不在乎他到底有没有找回丢失的财物。实际上，经理见他用“波特”登记，现在又“宣称”自己是查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，已经非常怀疑到底有没有这么一只公文箱；还有，即使有这么一只公文箱，也怀疑里面到底有没有什么贵重的文件。经理虽然没有直说，但已经把意思暗示得很清楚了。

那天早上我们很狼狈。查尔斯在酒店见人就问有没有看到他那只公文箱。大部分房客觉得这问题有辱个人声誉，十分恼火；一位暴躁的弗吉尼亚人掏出左轮手枪，要立刻把问题就地解决。查尔斯给纽约方面发电报，防止股票和息票被别人转卖，但他的经纪人回电说，虽然他们已经尽快冻结了这些票据，不过做得不太情愿，因为他们不知道查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士现在就在美国。查尔斯放出话，找不回丢失的东西他绝不离开酒店。就我而言，我感觉我们在有生之年——甚至在更长一段时间内，得一直待在那个地方了。

那天晚上，我们还是住在湖畔酒店。在清晨的几个小时里，我在床上躺着，琢磨着这件事，突然冒出个想法。这让我非常兴奋，便起身冲进查尔斯的卧室。“查尔斯，查尔斯！”我喊道，“咱们又一次太想当然了。说不定是伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯把你的公文箱拿走了！”

“你个笨蛋，”查尔斯回道，语气很不客气（这个词，他冲我说得越来越频繁了），“你把我吵醒就为了这个？想一想，夸肯鲍斯夫妇在星期二早上离开的乔治湖，可星期三的时候公文箱还在我的手上呢。”

“他们只是嘴上这么说说而已，”我大声说道，“也许他们当时没有走——后来才把公文箱偷走了！”

“咱们明天问问，”查尔斯应道，“不过，说真的，我觉得你不该为这事把我吵醒。那小妇人的人品，我敢用生命担保。”

我们第二天问了问——得到的回复让人感到蹊跷：原来，虽然夸肯鲍斯夫妇星期二离开了湖畔酒店，但他们只是搬到了附近的华盛顿酒店，直到星期三早上才离开，坐同一班火车去了萨拉托加，正是我和查尔斯打算乘坐的那列火车。夸肯鲍斯夫人手里拿了个棕色的小纸质包裹——这样一来，我们不难猜出，那里面就是查尔斯的公文箱，只是包得有些松。

我知道这是怎么一回事了。那位在房间里晃来晃去要小费的女服务员就是——夸肯鲍斯夫人！只需一件围裙，就能让她那漂亮的旅行装束变成女服务员的一身行头。在美国任何一家大酒店里，女服务员在人群中穿梭都大可不必担心被识破。

“咱们跟着他们，一起去萨拉托加，”查尔斯叫道，“马上把账单结清，西摩。”

“好的，”我答道，“你能不能给我点钱？”

查尔斯拍拍口袋，咕哝了句：“所有的钱都在那只公文箱里。”

这件事又耽误了我们一天，一直到后来，我们才从在纽约的代理人那里拿到了一些现金。那位酒店经理，对查尔斯改名换姓、声称失窃早就深表怀疑，便趾高气扬地拒绝接受查尔斯用支票之类的付款，用他的话说，只认“硬通货”。于是，我们只好低三下四地在湖畔酒店继续待着，什么也做不了。

“毫无疑问，”当天晚上我对查尔斯说，“伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯就是克雷上校。”

“我猜也是，”查尔斯顺着我的话咕哝了一句，“我现在碰到的所有人好像都是克雷上校——除了我确信他们就是的时候，这个时候他们又变成了无辜的路人。我都把他的头发揪下来了，谁还能想到是他呢？我甚至都怀疑他了——他在塞尔登跟我们说过，这违背了他的首要原则——可谁又能想得到，他还能把戏接着演下去？”

我又突然灵光一闪。不过，想到上一次说话口无遮拦，这次我说话时适当地谨慎起来。“查尔斯，”我说道，“咱们这次不是又受了偏见的左右了吗？我们之前认为福布斯—盖斯克尔是克雷上校——理由就是他戴了假发。这次我们觉得伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯不是克雷上校——理由仅仅是他没戴假发。问题是，我们怎么知道克雷上校戴不戴假发？有没有这种可能：当他还是梅德赫斯特，那个私人侦探时，他给我们的关于乔装的那些提示，是故意设的一个圈套，目的就是要误导和欺骗我们？有没有可能，他那天在海鸥岛提到的那些方法也同样是为了打算骗我们一把？”

“西，这太明显了，”我内兄评价道，语气极为不满，“我觉得任何一位称职的秘书都应该立刻想到这一点。”

即便现在，在我没告诉查尔斯之前，他自己也一直没明白这是怎么一回事。不过，这一点我没说。我觉得说出来不会有什么好处。于是，我又继续道：“对了，我觉得他乔装成梅德赫斯特时把头发剪短了，那是他自身天生的短发，没有任何修饰。这段时间以来，它足以长得长而密了。他乔装成大卫·格兰顿时，不用说，就把头发剪到中等长度，修了修下巴还有两鬓的胡子，并且全染成红色，纯正的苏格兰人胡子的颜色。咱们再回到他乔装成先知的时候，那时，他的头发和伊莱休基本一样，只不过为了让自己打扮得更像，那时头发梳得更整齐也更蓬松罢了。乔装成小副牧师时，他把头发的颜色染深，又用发油抚平。乔装成凡·莱本斯坦时，他把头发剪得很短，还尽量蓄络腮胡子，并且按照蒂罗尔的时尚染成了黑色。他自始至终从不需要什么假发，考虑到每次事件中间的时间间隔，他自己天生的头发就完全够用了。”

“西，你说得对，”我内兄说道，态度变得极其友好，“我得替你说句公道话，这是咱们目前在追踪上校这件事上得出的最靠谱的想法。”

星期六早上，我们收到一封信，稍微缓解了一下我们当时的紧张情绪。发信人还是我们的死对头——不过语气同以往大为不同，不再是揶揄和嘲讽：

萨拉托加，星期五

查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士：

我现在将公文箱原封不动地归还于你，里面的文件丝毫未动。箱子没有开启过，你一眼就能看出来。

你也许会问，我为什么会有这么奇怪的举动。这一次，我认认真真地把实话告诉你。

我和“白石南花”（温特沃斯先生起的这个绰号很合适，我会继续用下去）同你一起登上伊特鲁里亚号，同以往一样，想从你身上捞点东西。我们同你俩一起登上乔治湖——因为我按照我们以往的计划，诱使你邀请我们，算是“迫牌”，一直打算再耍你一次。按照计划，我们原本没有打算偷你的公文箱，我觉得这种小儿科的把戏不值得我这老将出马。我们一直按照原计划准备，直到后来，你把我的头发拽了下来。我当时很诧异，因为我看到你表现出了某种歉意，还有发自内心的悔恨，以前我根本想不到你会这样。你自己觉得伤害了我的感情，并且你的言行举止比我所了解的以往任何时候都更像位绅士。你不仅道了歉，还主动要求做些补偿。这让我改变了主意。你也许不信，不过我还是就此放弃了之前准备骗你的计划。

我原本也可以接受你的邀请去南非，到那里先把钱拿到手，然后很快就可以脱身。不过，当时我肩负着信任与责任——我是有点无赖，但还没无赖到在这种情形下仍要继续骗你。

暂且不论我这个人其他方面如何，不过我不是什么伪君子。我只是一个普通的骗子而已。我把你的文件完整奉还，想法同澳大利亚的那位绿林好汉一样：他把一位女士自己的手表送还给她，因为她唱歌给他听，让他想起了英格兰。换句话说，他没有将手表从她身上偷走。同样，我发现你这次的表现像个绅士，仅此一次，完全出乎我所料，于是我就打算放弃当时正在酝酿的计划了。不过，这并不是说我今后不会以其他方式来骗你，这还得看你今后的表现。

为什么我让“白石南花”偷走你的公文箱，然后又还回来？仅仅是因为我心情好才这么做的吗？不是。这么做是为了让你知道，我说的这一切都是真的。要是我两手空空就走了，然后再给你写这封信，你肯定不会相信我的话。你肯定会觉得，我这么做只是因为这次又失手了。不过，当我把你的文件拿到手，再主动归还给你时，你肯定就会明白我说的是真的了。

就像信的开头那样，信的结尾我也认认真真地说上几句。我虽然干这一行，但还存有一定的良知。当我看到一位百万富翁有着男子汉的担当时，我要是再利用这一点敲他一杠，那我也就感到无地自容了。

略表悔意，但我依然是个无赖。

克雷上校奉上

收到这封奇怪的信时，查尔斯的第一反应就是冲到楼下去找公文箱。鹰递公司刚刚送过来，他又急匆匆地跑回我们房间，迫不及待地打开并清点文件。当看到文件都在时，他转过身对着我淡然一笑，嘴唇颤抖，说道：“这封信，我觉得比他以往任何一封都更羞辱人。”

不过，就我而言，我真觉得信中的话不无道理。克雷上校是个无赖，这一点不容置疑——他还是个极为恬不知耻的无赖。可是，我相信，即便无赖也有心地善良的一面。

我想，“肩负着信任与责任”这几个字眼戳到了查尔斯的痛处，让他想到了克罗地多普·戈尔康达公司的股价暴跌那件事。不过，我也为之一震，因为它让我想到了那百分之十的佣金。

第十章　纸牌游戏

我们第二天坐伦斯勒—萨拉托加列车离开乔治湖时，查尔斯长叹一声：“西摩，我再也不化名成什么彼得·波特了，我受够这些伪装了。既然我们知道克雷上校现在就在美国，那么再怎么装也没什么用，所以我还是安心地享受我应有的待遇和尊敬吧，这是我这种身份和地位的人该得的。”

“即便在这片共和的土地上，你在大多数情况下也都能享受得到（酒店职员那是算个例外）。”我立刻接过话。

依我之愚见，要是为了能够完全确保摆摆架子就能够享受到劳埃德保险社AI标准的船只[36]，还是让我做一回生而自由的美国公民吧。

于是在接下来的四个月中，我们周游各州，从缅因州到加利福尼亚州，从俄勒冈州到佛罗里达州，用的全是我们的真名。“落实一下做礼拜的事情。”查尔斯这么打趣地说——或者换句话说，就是调查一下铁路、辛迪加、工矿还有畜牧场的经营和控制情况。我们俩什么都打听。经过我们的调查，正如查尔斯进一步指出的，那些骚扰约伯儿子们的士巴人，貌似已经一股脑全都移民到了堪萨斯州还有内布拉斯加州，那几千头牲畜也似乎像克雷上校一样，在打烙印[37]之前从草原上凭空消失了。

不管怎么说，我们很幸运，没有遇到克雷上校的骚扰，想必他定是乘了什么魔毯去了其他某个欢乐地了。

直到阴冷的十月，我们才安全回到纽约，准备返回英国。这么长时间以来，克雷上校没来劫财（查尔斯对此正暗自高兴——不过，我却不这么认为），这对我内兄的身心大有裨益。他现在生龙活虎，兴致颇高，甚至都有点担心克雷上校是不是染上了黄热病——当时黄热病正在新奥尔良市肆虐——或者担心他是不是把自己吃坏了。我们也差点吃坏了身子，胡吃海喝，什么都往肚子里塞，什么蛤蜊汤、淡水龟、软壳蟹、泽西桃、帆背潜鸭、卡托巴酒、酸浆、白兰地鸡尾酒、草莓酥饼、冰激凌、玉米烤饼，还有一种俗称为“僵尸复活”的酒饮。不管怎么说，查尔斯回到纽约时心情很不错。由于担心在这个了不起的城市受到克雷上校的算计，他便欣然接受了他的兄弟温古德的邀请，先在他那儿待上几天，然后再住进在第五大道尽头新建成的宏伟的参议员宫殿；温古德是内华达州的参议员，也是位百万富翁。

“西，在那儿，至少我可以保证自己的安全，”他满腹牢骚，脸上挂着疲惫的笑容，“不管怎样，温古德不会骗我——当然，平时做生意是另一码事。”

鲍斯—纳格特会堂（大家都这么叫）也许是第五大道上最漂亮的理查森风格的上流宅邸。我们在那儿待了一个星期，十分高兴。用绳量给我们的地界，坐落在佳美之处[38]。我们抵达那儿的当天晚上，温古德为我们办了一场小型单身派对。他知道查尔斯这次旅行没有带夫人同行，便猜到了查尔斯希望头一天晚上来个非正式的派对，打打牌，抽抽烟，而不用费神去理会女眷们，虽然她们在场会让晚会添彩不少，但多少也会让男士们放不开手脚。

那天晚上算上我们一共只有七位客人——温古德说，加上他自己刚好八人，这个数字不错。他是位暴发户——暴发户中资历最浅的——传统排外的纽约社交圈称他为“有钱的僭据人”[39]。他开始“发迹”不到十年，因此他像其他美国人一样，急切地想“被文化冲昏头脑”。他作为文学赞助人，还邀请了英国文学界的著名诗人阿尔杰农·克雷亚德先生，他是西部乡村小说中野蔷薇派的领军人物，刚刚抵达纽约。

“你在伦敦肯定闻其大名了吧？”我们在等客人就餐时，他笑着问查尔斯。

“没听说过，”查尔斯不冷不热地回了一句，“我可没那份荣幸。你也知道，我们不是一个圈子的人。”

温古德参议员的脸上掠过一丝奇怪的表情，我发现他完全误解了我内兄的意思。查尔斯想表达的当然是，克雷亚德先生只是伦敦文学界还有波西米亚那个圈子的，而他自己本人则在有钱人和政客这个更高级别的圈子内活动。不过，那位参议员已经习惯了从新富的角度看问题，觉得查尔斯的意思是，大名鼎鼎的克雷亚德先生所在的那个上流团体，他查尔斯还没有资格加入。这自然使得温古德对克雷亚德这位文学之交的敬意又增添了几分。

诗人进来时已经迟到了两分钟。即使我们没见过《海滨杂志》上他本人各时期的肖像，也能一眼就看出他是位真正的诗人：充满激情的双眸，秀美的嘴唇，一缕灰色鬈发搭在宽阔的额头前，一脸和善的笑容在斑白胡须的映衬下更显真挚，可以看到两排整齐洁白的牙齿。诗人在前一天晚上才抵达纽约，其他大部分客人早在第二天下午莲花俱乐部举办的招待会上见过克雷亚德，所以只有我和查尔斯需要引见。他一身普通晚礼服，没有任何纨绔习气，不过扣眼上戴了一朵蓝色小花，不知何名。他透过眼镜打量着查尔斯，远远地鞠了一躬，衬衫的胸部正中央有一大块钻石闪闪发光，至少可以看出，野蔷薇派（世人因为他那首著名的史诗而这么称呼）靠着诗歌发了一笔财。后来，他略微向我们解释，实际上他来纽约是为了处理自己的版税问题。“我那最后一部作品，”他说，“那些穷光蛋只给八百英镑。这谁能受得了？现代诗人要与时俱进，只有给了适当的激励，才能放声歌唱，所以我大老远过来看看这是怎么一回事。大家都明白，只要给钱，诗人就会为你歌唱。”

“跟我一样，”查尔斯说道，找到一个双方的共同点，“我对矿山感兴趣；我同你一样，大老远过来也是为了我的‘特许使用费’问题。”

诗人又把眼镜戴上，把查尔斯浑身上下仔细打量了一番。“哦。”他拖着长调咕哝了一声，一个字也没多说。不过，不知怎的，所有人都觉得查尔斯颜面尽失。吃晚饭时，我看到温古德急急忙忙调换了标记座位的桌签。显然他一开始安排查尔斯紧挨着诗人坐着，现在调整之后，他把诗人放在了一位铁路大王和一名杂志编辑中间。我内兄一句话都没说，这种情况我极少碰到。

诗人就餐期间的举止极为古怪，他总是不合时宜地引诗摘句。

“先生，要烤羊羔还是炖火鸡？”仆人问道。

“玛丽有只小羊羔，”诗人道，“我就学学玛丽吧！”

查尔斯还有参议员觉得这话说得有失身份。

不管怎样，晚餐后，查尔斯喝了一些上好的罗德尔红酒，就又开始高谈阔论起来，变得活跃、八卦。诗人讲了一些伦敦文学界的趣事，引得众人大笑不止——至少有两件事，我从未听说过。查尔斯倍感压力，也分享一些逸事来愉悦众人。他那天心情很好。他平日里不怎么爱开玩笑，不过只要他乐意，就能展示出自己冷幽默的一面，虽然严格地讲不免粗俗，但绝对有意思。就在那天晚上，他喝了几杯温古德的上等香槟——美国最上乘的香槟——就开始添油加醋地描述克雷上校是如何想尽各种办法来骗他的。他说的话可不像我的文字这么坦诚、准确，好多最有意思的细节都跳过了——原因很明显，因为有损他的形象，而对他好几次差点抓住上校时所表现出来的机智则夸大其词。不过，由于查尔斯的虚荣天性，他讲起来有些闪烁其词、添枝加叶，但他讲得还是绝对滑稽——只讲这些事荒唐可笑的一面，而不讲损失惨重的一面，这在他还是头一遭。他环顾在座的诸位，还表示，这四年来克雷上校从他身上骗走的钱财，远比不上由于失手而在伦敦股票交易所一天的损失。他说这话，大概是想对纽约的这些实力派传达这一信息：为了能享受克雷上校追随他而带来的乐趣和刺激，这点小痛小痒的损失，他倒也乐意牺牲。

诗人很高兴。“查尔斯爵士，你是个有血性的汉子，”他说，“崇尚勇气与冒险，我倒想一睹英国人这一优良传统！不过，话又说回来，这家伙身上肯定有些为人称道的地方。我得就这些故事做些笔记，要创作一则冒险故事；这都是些不错的素材。”

“我也不清楚自己到底适不适合做小说的主人公。”查尔斯扬扬自得地小声说道。显然，诗人实际上并不是这个意思。

“我的意思是，让克雷上校做主人公。”诗人冷冷地回敬道。

“啊，你们玩弄笔墨的人都这样，”查尔斯接过话，语气缓和了些，“你们都暗地里同情那些无赖。”

“这也比同情股票交易所那些最见不得人的投机行为要强。”诗人冷冷地反呛了一句。

在场的其他人都不自在地笑了。那位铁路大王扭了扭身子。温古德赶忙转换话题，不过查尔斯不肯善罢甘休。

“不过，你得听听最后的结局，”他说道，“这还不是最糟的。那人最坏的一点，就是他还是个伪君子。他上一次骗完我之后——就在这儿骗的我，就在美国骗的我——他给我写了这么一封信。”他接着讲了一通夸肯鲍斯那件事，中间零零碎碎夹杂着些许纯粹他自己个人的臆想。

当查尔斯提到夸肯鲍斯夫人时，诗人笑了。“已婚女士最不好的一点，”他说，“就是——你不能娶她们；未婚女士最不好的一点就是——她们想嫁给你。”不过，说到那封信时，诗人的眼睛一直盯着我内兄。查尔斯不幸地曲解了信中的内容，这一点我不得不承认。即便这样，信中还是流露出了一些善意。不过，查尔斯最后说道：“因此，那个无赖让自己成了一个爱发牢骚的杂种，一个让人唾弃的伪善者，一个完完全全彻头彻尾的浑球儿。”

“难道你不觉得，”诗人不慌不忙地插话道，很有风度，“他也许说的是真话？你不觉得有一丝悔恨触动了他的灵魂？——你不觉得残存的一些良知让他也诚心地对待一个信任自己的人？我有一种观点：即便最无耻的无赖，内心也总会有好的一面。我发现，他们常常能一直让女性爱自己，并且对自己忠诚。”

“哈！我早就说过！”查尔斯嗤之以鼻，“我早就说过，搞文学的人总是对无赖有一种见不得人的想法。”

“也许你说得对，”诗人冷笑道，“因为你我都是凡人。咱们中间谁要是问心无愧，没有什么罪过，那就先站出来教训教训我吧！”说完他就在一边赌气，闭口不言。

我们起身离桌，拿上雪茄，转身去吸烟室。那个房间是摩尔风格的装潢，富丽堂皇，配的是东方风格的墙幔。温古德参议员在那儿同查尔斯谈些富矿带、大农场，还有一些其他振奋人心的饭后谈资；那位杂志编辑则时而插话问个相关的问题，时而也说个古怪而讽刺的类似事件。很明显，他心中想的是以后要把这些发表出来。只有阿尔杰农·克雷亚德一个人坐在一旁想着心事，一句话不说，一只手托着下巴，眉头紧锁，眼睛盯着火炉中的灰烬。顺便说一句，他手上戴了一个稀奇古怪的戒指，一眼就能认出是埃及人或伊特鲁里亚人造的，上面镶的宝石向外凸起，琢面很大。他只是在打惠斯特桥牌的时候突然冒了一句话。

“霍金斯当伯爵了。”查尔斯说道，说的是伦敦某位相识。

“他何德何能？”参议员问道。

“会造假呗！”诗人刻薄地答道。

“荣耀名誉，这一切太容易。”杂志编辑插话道。

“查尔斯爵士靠耍滑头也弄了两个。”诗人补充道。

夜幕快要降临时，温古德参议员提议玩一玩瑞典扑克，这是一种容易上手的游戏——此时诗人虽说不是怒发冲冠，但也依旧郁郁寡欢。这游戏是根据过去的赌博游戏演化而来的，最近在西方社会非常流行，不过在座的众人，除了那位万事通诗人还有杂志编辑，几乎无人了解。后来才知道，温古德之所以提议玩这个游戏，是因为他当天下午在莲花俱乐部听克雷亚德说，这是他最喜欢的娱乐消遣。不过，他此刻不愿意玩。他说自己没钱，而其他诸位都是富翁，自己为什么要把十几首漂亮的十四行诗赚来的钱拱手让给百万富翁，好让他们在金碧辉煌的百万富翁的宫殿上再添一砖加一瓦呢？此外，他正在写一首颂诗，称赞共和国的简朴。民主党参议员宅邸的简单朴素让他不禁想到了登塔图斯、法比家族，还有卡美卢斯[40]。温古德隐隐地感到他在取笑自己，不过仍然坚持诗人一定要同这些金融家一起玩玩牌。“你可以不叫牌，”他说，“多少次都行。你可以把赌注下得低一些，或者随便碰碰运气，你随意。这个游戏很民主，除了庄家，其他人自己决定下多大的注。你要是不想坐庄，可以不坐。”

“哦，要是你这么坚持，”克雷亚德懒洋洋地，透着一股不情愿，慢悠悠地说，“我就不得不从命了，要不然会扫了你的兴。不过，你可记住，我是诗人，我有神秘的灵感。”

这些纸牌，为了方便辨认，除了牌面上有花色和点数，角上也有花色和点数。一开始，我们的赌注很小。诗人很少下注，每次下注——几英镑——他总输，很奇怪。他想用古西班牙金币或古威尼斯金币下注，费了不少劲才说服他用美元。查尔斯最后隔着牌桌看着他，那时赌注在快速增加，都用现钱。纸币在绿色桌布上厚厚地摞着。“喂，”他低语道，有些挑衅，“你的灵感呢？阿波罗[41]不管你了吗？”

查尔斯能用上这么经典的暗指，这够稀奇的，老实说，我自己都觉得不可思议（后来发现，他看了当晚的《评论家》杂志的一篇评论，现学现卖）。不过，诗人微微一笑。

“没有哇，”他平静地答道，“我现在正在酝酿灵感。灵感来的时候，肯定让你吃不了兜着走。”

接下来的一局，查尔斯坐庄发牌，诗人下注，和之前一样，不让别人看到。他下注时，一副绅士派头。让我们万万没想到的是，他抽出一沓钞票，平和地说道：“现在灵感来了。‘心不在焉’这个词刚好，我押五千。”当然是五千美元，换成英国货币约一千英镑——对一名以写作为生的人来讲，这是个大赌注。

查尔斯笑了笑，摊了牌，诗人也亮了牌——于是赢了一千英镑。

“运气不错嘛！”查尔斯低声说道，虽然输了钱不高兴，但他仍装出一副若无其事的样子。

“灵感嘛！”诗人沉思道，又变得心不在焉起来。

查尔斯再次发牌。虽然诗人的一双死鱼眼在盯着发牌，思绪却不知飞到哪儿去了。他嘴唇翕动着，念念有词。“郊游、水手、行走，”他咕哝着，“凑够三个了。对了，还有杨柳，‘柳’的意思是留。这下就大功告成了。月桂、画眉这两个词押韵押得不好。用‘郊游’试试，你觉得怎么样？”

“下不下注？”查尔斯接过话，口气严厉，把诗人拉回了现实。

诗人一惊。“不下，你们继续。”他回应道，低头看牌，又陷入沉思。我们又看到他双唇在颤抖，听到他念道：“西海边心不在焉的守望者/我比你更拥护共和/多年后，我前来看你/少女的誓言是否仍还铭记/如花似锦的年纪/誓做自由妻——”

“下不下注？”查尔斯再次试探着打断他。

“下，五千，”诗人在半睡半醒中回答，把自己面前的一堆纸币推上前去，嘴上一直没闲着，“来日誓做自由妻。‘来日’，‘来日’，这个词乏味得连五块钱都不值得下。”

查尔斯再次亮牌，诗人又赢了。查尔斯把钱推过去，诗人心不在焉地揽了过来，好像在注视着无际的远方，问谁能借他铅笔还有纸。有几行难得的诗句，他要记下来，否则很可能就忘了。

“这是在打牌，”查尔斯厉声说道，“你能不能只专注一件事？”

诗人望了他一眼，脸上挂着同情的笑容。“早就给你说了，我有灵感，”他说，“诗和灵感形影不离。你的钱我不能想赢多快就赢多快，除非我打牌的时候作作诗。每每我想到好词好句，我都要赌一赌运气。你没发现吗，我靠着‘心不在焉’这个词赢了一千，靠‘如花似锦’又赢了一千。要是我为‘来日’这词下注，我肯定会输。懂不懂我这套规则？”

“要我说，这纯粹是瞎扯，”查尔斯回应道，“不管这些，接着打牌。规则是给蠢货准备的——却是为了迎合智者。靠这种瞎想，你早晚会输。”

诗人继续道：“此生誓做自由妻。”

“下注！”查尔斯厉声喊道，我们都下了注。

“此生，”诗人咕哝道，“此后余生。这个词够妙。我押一万美元，查尔斯爵士，押‘此生’这个词。”

大家都亮了牌，有输有赢，诗人则赢了两千英镑[42]。

“我身上没带这么多钱，”查尔斯说道，语气严肃而恼怒，他输牌时通常都是这种语气，“不过——我明天会把钱给你结清。”

“再来一局？”主人问道，满脸堆笑。

“谢谢，还是算了吧！”查尔斯答道，“克雷亚德先生的灵感来得太是时候了。他的运气太好了，参议员先生，我不玩了。”

就在此时，一名仆人进来了，手托一个托盘，上面有一个信封，里面装了一封短笺。“是给克雷亚德先生的，”他说，“送信人说十分紧急。”

克雷亚德赶忙撕开信封。能看出来他很焦虑，脸立刻就白了。

“抱……抱歉，”他说道，“我……我现在必须马上回去了。我妻子病危——发作得很突然。参议员先生，请原谅。查尔斯爵士，你明天再报仇吧。”

很明显，他说话时有些哽咽。我们觉得他最起码是个重感情的人。他显然有些害怕，再也无法冷静。他在恍惚中同各位握手道别，接着便冲下楼梯找自己的风衣。就在他关上前门的那一刻，又来了一位客人，两人在玄关擦肩而过。

“各位先生，好哇，”他张口道，“咱们被骗了，知道吗？从莲花俱乐部说起，我们接纳为俱乐部名誉会员的那个人，并不是阿尔杰农·克雷亚德。他是位招摇撞骗的骗子。今晚来的电报说，阿尔杰农·克雷亚德在英格兰的家中，现在已经病危。”

查尔斯倒抽了一口长气。“克雷上校，”他叫道，声音很大，“他这次又把我骗了。没时间了，赶紧追，先生们！赶紧追！”

我们之前从未有过如此唾手可得的一个机会，去抓那令人敬畏的骗子，收拾他一顿。我们便一股脑儿三步并作两步奔下楼梯，冲到第五大道上。那位冒牌诗人只在我们前面一百码的距离，并发现事情已经败露了。不过，他是位跑步健将。考虑到年龄还有体重，我跑起来也不慢，在后面狂奔追赶。他在一个拐角转了弯，前方无路可逃，浪费了一些时间，他又发疯似的迅速折回。我想到自己正在追捕的是这么一个名声显赫的罪犯就感到兴奋，便又加了一把劲儿——气喘吁吁地追上了他。他穿了件轻薄的风衣，我用手一把抓住，喊道：“终于抓到你了，克雷上校，你逃不了了！”

他转过身看着我。“哈，记不记得那百分之十！”他一边挣扎一边喊道，“是你干的，对不对？先生，你永远、永远别想抓住我！”说时迟，那时快，他在说话的空当儿，把双臂向后并拢，想让风衣滑掉；风衣是新做的，袖子里面是平滑的丝衬，一下子就滑掉了。他这一下让我猝不及防，脚下也没站稳。我抓着他的外套，外套一掉我便仰面向后倒去，滚进了街上的泥浆里，背摔得很疼。那克雷上校不安地笑了笑，便穿着晚礼服全速逃跑，在街角一转便不见了踪影。

过了一会儿，我才缓过气，从地上爬起来，看看自己的伤势如何。这时，查尔斯还有其他人都已赶到，我向他们说明了事情经过。我对查尔斯的事情如此上心——胳膊摔破了，那件不错的晚礼服也毁了，我的内兄非但没有称赞我几句，反而冷冷地说，既然只差那么一点就能抓住了，我就应该把他抓住的。

“至少，我拿到了他的外套，”我说，“这也许会给我们提供一点线索。”我手里拿着那件外套一瘸一拐、摇摇晃晃地往回走，身上摔得青一块紫一块。

我们开始检查那外套，不过上面没有找到裁缝的名字。衣服后背处裁缝借以标榜自己手艺的带子被小心地撕掉了，取而代之的是一条纯黑的带子，没有任何字迹。我们又搜了搜胸前的口袋，找到了一块手帕，是用最好的细麻纱做的，也没留下什么名字。再看看两侧的口袋——哈，这是什么？我喜出望外，掏出一张纸。是一张短笺——这是一个真正有价值的发现——就是刚刚仆人在参议员家中递给他的那张短笺。

我们一口气读完。

亲爱的保罗，我早就跟你说过，这样太冒险，为什么不听我一劝呢？你就不该冒充现实中的人物。我刚刚碰巧瞧了一眼酒店的自动电报机，打算看看克罗地多普公司今天的行情怎样。你猜我在从英格兰发过来的电报中看到了什么消息？阿尔杰农·克雷亚德先生，就是那位大名鼎鼎的诗人，现在在德文郡家中的床上病死了。现在整个纽约都知晓了此事。就说我病危，立刻回来，一分钟都不要耽误。别回酒店，我正在转移咱们的东西，到玛丽家找我。

你忠心的，

玛格特

“这张短笺非常重要！”查尔斯说道，“它给了我们一条线索。其他的先不管，现在我们知道了两件事：他的真名叫保罗，皮卡迪特夫人的真名叫玛格特。”

我又搜了搜口袋，找到一枚戒指。显然，他发现我在追他时，就把这两样东西塞到了口袋里，在扭扯中忘了这事，或者说根本顾不上了。

我仔细地看了看，这就是他玩瑞典扑克时戴在手上的那枚戒指，中间镶有一枚合成的大宝石，有好几个面，像金字塔一样向中间突起。一共有八个面，有些面上是祖母绿、紫水晶，或绿松石，不过有一面——与佩戴者的眼睛成直角的那一面——根本不是什么珠宝，而是一块非常小的凸面镜。我一下子明白了他这葫芦里卖的什么药。我内兄发牌时，他就漫不经心地把手搭在桌上，当通过镜面折射，看到自己的点数与花色比查尔斯的要好时，就来了“灵感”，便信心十足地为自己的运气下注——或者说为自己的内幕信息下注。同样，我确信他那样子奇怪的眼镜是个高倍的放大镜，在这种把戏中助了他一臂之力。于是，我们又发了一次牌，试了一下——我戴上戒指，即便裸眼也都能每次认出发给我的牌的点数与花色。

“好哇，这跟作弊差不多。”参议员说道，后退了一步。他想向我们表明，即便是在美国的偏远西部地区的投机者也会有个底线。

“说得对，”杂志编辑应和道，“为自己的牌技下注合规合法，为自己的运气下注是没有头脑，为自己的内幕信息下注是——”

“不讲道德。”我提示了一下。

“说得非常好。”杂志编辑接过话。

“骗法很简单，”查尔斯插话道，“换成其他人，我早就识破了。但是他喋喋不休地说着自己的灵感，把我的注意力引开了，这就是那个无赖的障眼法。他用一般骗子的手段来转移你的注意力——他这一招用得太好了，等你发现他的真实意图，一切都无可挽回了。”

我们让纽约警方追寻克雷上校，不过，当然他又同以往一样，已经化作曼哈顿的一缕轻烟，立刻消失得无影无踪，一丝线索都没有。“玛丽家”，我们得到的是个不全的地址。

我们又在纽约等了整整两星期，一点消息都没有，没找到什么“玛丽家”。唯一能表明克雷上校在这个城市的东西，是他按惯例写来的羞辱信。内容如下：

哎，那位一直上当受骗的：

自从咱们在乔治湖见面以后，我就回了伦敦，不过马上又回来了。实际上，我在伦敦有笔买卖要做，现在已经做完了。英国警方的高度戒备又让我像天上伟大的猎户座一样，“缓缓地向西移动”。我又回到美国，是想看看你是否仍有悔恨之心。刚到的那天，我就碰到了温古德参议员，便接受了他的热情邀请，纯粹是想看看我上次给你的信对你的影响有多大。结果，我发现你还是相当冥顽不灵，并且固执地误解我的初衷，于是我决定再给你来个小小的教训。这次差一点就失败了，我承认这个意外事件让我紧张了一把。现在我即将彻底罢手，在萨里郡安顿下来度过余生。我打算再略微骗你一次，事成之后，克雷上校就会像辛辛纳图斯[43]一样，弃甲归田。到时候，你就不必再提心吊胆。我已为余生准备得差不多了，不像你那么贪得无厌。现在我意识到要成为一名好公民，得及早收手，以便给那些更年轻、更有资格的无赖更多的机会。咱们共同经历的愉快冒险，我今后定会常常愉悦地回味一番。既然你拿到了我的外套，还有一枚戒指，一封对我来讲十分重要的信件，咱们就算扯平了，我也就体面地罢手了。

衷心祝愿你的，

诗人库斯伯特·克雷

“这就是他一贯的风格！”查尔斯说道，“说是要再最后骗我一次，算是给我一个警告。即便他这么做了，我为什么要信他的话？他那种无赖说这些话，当然也可能就是为了故意让我放松警惕。”

就我而言，我十分赞同“玛格特”的话。当上校不得不冒充某位知名人士时，我觉得他已经基本黔驴技穷了，最好还是到萨里郡安度余生吧。

不过，杂志编辑把这一切总结成了一句话：“勤劳和能力创造财富，这是瞎扯，千万别信。人生就像打牌，成功源自两个因素——一个是机会，另一个就是作弊。”

第十一章　贝蒂荣识别法

我们从纽约回去的行程糟糕得不行。船长说他本人“了解大西洋里的每一滴水”，还从未遇到它们这般不听话的。船在波涛中来回颠簸，查尔斯则在船舱中翻来覆去，那股闷气总消不掉。快到爱尔兰的海岸时，我顶着大风爬上甲板，又赶忙兴冲冲地下去，告诉我内兄能看到灯塔岛了。查尔斯只是在铺位上翻了个身，哼哼两声。“鬼才信，”他答道，“我想那可能又是克雷上校变的吧！”

不过，在利物浦，阿德菲酒店让他心情好些。我们在路易十五大饭店里吃了顿大餐，就仿佛天底下只有百万富翁才能吃饭一样。然后，我们第二天坐普耳曼卧车回伦敦。

回到家后，我们发现艾米莉亚满眼泪花，家里出了件大事，貌似西塞琳跟她说要辞职不干了。

当查尔斯满脑子想的都是投资，顾不上自己时，就几乎不着家。我那受人尊敬的内兄同其他有钱人一样，潜意识里总会多多少少担心自己死去时会身无分文。为了避免这种不幸——我不得不说，没人替他操这份心——几年前他投了二十万英镑买永续债券，万一戈尔康达公司还有南非都一起倒闭了，他还可以有点储备金作为退路。同样还是由于这种偏执，他不让银行把这股利单邮寄给他，而是非要学那些老妇人还有乡村牧师，每年四次亲自到英格兰银行去领取利息。银行的不少职员都跟他很熟，每个法定季度结算日后的几周内，他总会如众目所盼，如约出现在针线街。

于是，我们到达伦敦的第二天清晨，查尔斯就情绪高昂地对我说：“西，我今天得去城里取一下我的股息。有两个季度没有取了。”

我陪他一起来到银行。甚至门口那个不可一世的侍者也上前替百万富翁开车门。接待我们的职员面带微笑，点头致敬。“取多少？”他例行公事地问道。

“二十万。”查尔斯一脸和气地答道。

那位职员翻开账簿。“已经付过了！”他说道，语气坚定，“先生，冒昧地问一句，您究竟想干吗？”

“付过了！”查尔斯附和了一句，向后一退。

职员隔着柜台盯着他。“是的，查尔斯爵士，”他答道，语气稍显严肃，“您一定还记得，您从我这儿取了一个季度的股息——上一周——就在这个柜台。”

查尔斯两眼直直地盯着他。“把签名给我看看。”他最后慢吞吞、恍恍惚惚地说。我觉得我们又碰到麻烦了。

职员隔着柜台把账簿推到查尔斯面前，查尔斯仔细地看了看笔迹。

“又是克雷上校干的！”他喊道，语气中带着沮丧，转向我，“他肯定乔装成我的样子了。西，我以后准会死在济贫院的。那人甚至把我的储备金都偷走了。”

我立刻明白了这是怎么一回事。“是夸肯鲍斯夫人干的！”我说，“在伊特鲁里亚号上的那些画像！就是为了方便他乔装！你想想，她从不同的角度画了你的脸庞，还有身材。”

“上个季度的呢？”查尔斯声音颤抖地问道。

职员翻开记录，漫不经心地答道：“七月十号取走了。”他说这话的语气，好像这事没什么大不了似的。

接着，我明白克雷上校为什么要千里迢迢地返回英格兰了。

查尔斯显然要晕倒了。“西，带我回家。”他大声叫道，“我毁了，彻底地毁了！他连五十万都不会给我剩。我那些可怜的孩子，今后得在伦敦的大街小巷中靠乞讨为生，没人理没人问了。”

想到艾米莉亚自己名下有价值十五万英镑的地产，所以最后这个意外事件并没有像查尔斯所期待的那样，让我掉几滴同情的眼泪。

我们该问的都问了，和以往一样，又立刻叫来警察去追查此事，不过一点用都没有。那些钱，一旦支付，就再也不可能追回了。无论何种情形，政府都不会掏两次腰包，这是永续债券所能玩弄的一点特权。查尔斯驱车回到梅费尔，垂头丧气，彻底垮掉了。我想，要是克雷上校能亲眼看到他当时的情形，看到这么精明的一个人如此悲痛、迷茫，肯定会感到惋惜。

不过，午饭后，我内兄又逐渐恢复了他那天生的乐天劲儿。他稍稍振作了一下。“西摩，”他对我说，“你肯定听说过包括一系列身体测量和记录罪犯身体数据的贝蒂荣识别法吧？”

“听说过，”我说，“目前而言很不错。不过，它就跟格拉斯夫人的罐炖野兔肉一样，关键在于第一步。‘首先要抓住犯人。’目前，咱们还从未抓住过克雷上校——”

“或者，更确切地说，”查尔斯不近人情地插了一句，“在你追上他的时候，没有抓住他。”

这含沙射影伤人的话我就当没听见，用刚才的语气接着说道：“我们从未抓住过克雷上校。只有当咱们抓到他时，才能用贝蒂荣识别法来记录他的信息。此外，即便咱们抓住过他，并且留意了他的鼻子、下巴、耳朵、额头的外形，但他每次都换一副全新的面孔，自己想变成什么样就能变成什么样。他每次骗咱们，咱们都认不出。贝蒂荣那套方法又有什么用呢？”

“不用担心，西，”我内兄答道，“在纽约，有人跟我说，伦敦的弗兰克·贝德斯莱博士是全英格兰目前最顶尖的贝蒂荣识别法的专家。我要去贝德斯莱那儿一趟，或者，我还是邀请他明天到我这儿共进午餐吧。”

“谁跟你提到的他？”我问，“希望别再是夸肯鲍斯医生，也希望别是阿尔杰农·克雷亚德。”

查尔斯愣了一下，想了想。“不是，不是他们，”他思考片刻后回答道，“是我们在温古德家碰到的那位杂志编辑。”

“他没事，”我说，“至少，我觉得没事。”

于是我们给贝德斯莱博士写了封客气的邀请函，请他第二天下午两点钟到梅费尔来同我们共进午餐，他是这套识别法的专家。

贝德斯莱博士如约前来——他身材短小精悍，眉毛中间向上凸起，双目不大，但炯炯有神。我一眼看去，开始怀疑他是否又是克雷上校巧妙乔装而成的。他说起话来简短且清晰，行为举止一副科学家的风范。他开门见山地告诉我们，除非这方面的专家曾经见过罪犯，否则这套方法几乎派不上用场；不过，如果我们能早点儿向他咨询的话，他或许能帮我们避免一些重大损失。“克雷上校这么精明的人，”他说道，“肯定研究过贝蒂荣识别法的原理，也肯定会采取一切措施不让别人认出自己。所以，鼻子、下巴、胡须、头发之类的，你们都可以抛到一边，这些改变起来都太容易。不过，仍然有一些特征，很有可能保留下来——身高、头型、脖子、身材、手指等；还有说话时的音质，以及虹膜的颜色等等。即便是这些，也能部分伪装或遮掩起来。留的发型、填充物的多少、脖子周围的高领、睫毛周围一道深色的线条等，这些都能改变面部形象，变化能大得让你想不到。”

“这一点我们也知道。”我答道。

“再说一下声音，”贝德斯莱博士继续道，“声音本身最具欺骗性。那人绝对是个出色的模仿者。他或许可以扩大或者缩小喉部。从你们的描述来看，我猜他每一次转换角色，都不得不较大地改变或调整一下自己的声调还有口音。”

“不错，”我说，“他乔装成墨西哥先知时，操着一口西班牙腔。他扮成小副牧师时，又变成了一位有教养的北方的乡下人。冒充大卫·格兰顿时，他一口苏格兰口音，很有绅士风度。乔装成凡·莱本斯坦时，他自然成了德国南部居民，试着用法语进行交流。扮成施莱尔马赫教授时，他又成了德国北部人，英语说得结结巴巴。冒充伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯时，他又是满口明显的肯塔基口音。冒充诗人时，他赶俱乐部的时髦拖着长腔，带着点德文郡世家的遗风。”

“一点不错，”贝德斯莱博士回应道，“果然不出我所料。现在的问题是，你知道他是一个人吗？还是说真的是一帮人？是不是一伙人都用这个名字？不管他如何乔装，你那儿有没有克雷上校本人的照片？”

“一张也没有，”查尔斯答道，“他还是侦探梅德赫斯特的时候，自己拿出过一些照片。不过又马上装到了自己的口袋里，我们之后再也没有拿到过这些照片。”

“你能弄到几张吗？”博士问，“知不知道给他拍照的人叫什么？住在哪儿？”

“很不幸，不知道，”查尔斯应道，“不过尼斯警方给我们看过两张照片，也许我们可以借来用用。”

“要是没有照片，”贝德斯莱博士说道，“我们什么都做不了。要是你能给我两张那个人的清晰照片，不管他怎么乔装，我都能知道是不是同一个人；这样我就能找到些共同的细节，帮助咱们继续调查下去。”

这一切都发生在午餐期间，艾米莉亚的侄女多莉·林格菲尔德碰巧也在场；在我们谈话期间，我刚好注意到她脸上掠过一丝非常内疚的神情。这次我有些怀疑，倒不是怀疑多莉是同克雷上校一伙的；不过我纳闷，她为什么要脸红呢？令我惊讶的是，午饭后，多莉单独把我叫到书房。“西摩叔叔，”她开口道——尽管我跟她没有任何关系，那亲爱的孩子仍叫我叔叔，“要是你想要，我倒是有些克雷上校的照片。”

“你？”我吃惊地叫道，“多莉，你是怎么得到的？”

要不要告诉我，她犹豫了一两分钟，最后低声说：“要是我说出来，你会不会生气？”（多莉刚十九岁，长得十分漂亮。）

“孩子，”我说，“我为什么要生气呢？你可以悄悄地告诉我。”（她的脸都红成那样了，谁还会生她的气呢？）

“那你也不告诉艾米莉亚姑姑？还有伊莎贝尔姑姑？”她心里没底，又试探道。

“绝对不会。”我回答道。（实际上，多莉对我说的事，我向谁都能吐露，就是不能跟艾米莉亚还有伊莎贝尔说。）

“是这样的，大卫·格兰顿先生在塞尔登时——或者说那个流氓冒充大卫·格兰顿的时候，我在这儿暂留了一段时间，你也知道。”多莉继续道，“你——你保证不生我的气？有一天，我用柯达相机拍了一张他和艾米莉亚姑姑的快照！”

“这样，这有什么大不了的？”我问道，一头雾水。我所能想到的，最坏的情况莫过于大卫阁下当时正在同艾米莉亚调情。

多莉的脸更红了。“噢，那你知道伯第·温斯洛吧？”她说道，“他喜欢摄影——并且——并且也喜欢我。他发明了一种方法，他自己说一点都不实用，但它的特别之处在于，它能显示纹理。至少伯第是这么说的，会让事物这么显现出来。他还给了我一些柯达相机用的底片——至少有六七张，于是——我就用这些底片拍了艾米莉亚姑姑。”

“我还是不太明白。”我低声说，打趣地望着她。

“哎，西摩叔叔，”多莉大声说道，“你们男人真笨啊！要是艾米莉亚姑姑知道了，她绝不会原谅我的。你还问我，你自己肯定明白啊。要知道，照片上有那个——那个无赖，还有珍珠粉！”

“哦，这么说，照片上都显示出来了？”我问道。

“显示出来了！我倒也这么觉得！姑姑的脸上就像是有一个个小黑点。她在照片中就是那副模样！”

“克雷上校也在照片上？”

“嗯，他和姑姑说话时我拍下的，两个人都没发现。伯第冲洗的。我有三张大卫·格兰顿的照片，很清楚，拍得非常成功。”

“还有其他人吗？”我看到了希望，又问道。

多莉有点犹豫，脸更红了，她内心挣扎了一下，说道：“有，其他的是和伊莎贝尔姑姑的合影。”

“好孩子，”我抑制住自己作为丈夫的感情，说道，“我可以承受，即便是刚说的那种不幸，我也能承受。”

多莉抬头，两眼乞求似的望着我。“是在伦敦拍的，”她接着说，“就是我上次同姑姑在一起的时候。梅德赫斯特当时在房间里逗留；我拍了两张，他正和伊莎贝尔姑姑说着什么。”

“伊莎贝尔不搽粉。”我带着肯定低声道。

多莉又犹豫了一下，小声地向我提示道：“是没搽粉，不过——她的头发！”

“她头发的颜色，”我说，“有些地方用了些生发剂，你知道的。”

多莉的脸上突然露出淘气而狡黠的笑容。“对，没错，”她继续道，“可是，西摩叔叔，凡是用生发剂——呃——修复过的地方，在照片上都有一种闪亮的金属光泽。”

“亲爱的，把照片拿下来。”我边说边拍拍她的头。为了公正起见，我想最好还是不要吓唬她。

多莉把照片拿了下来。在我看来，这些照片拍得不怎么好，不过还是值得一试。经过进一步交谈，我们发现用一把剪刀就可以解决问题，把每张照片都剪成两半，这样就能抹去艾米莉亚还有伊莎贝尔的一切踪迹。不过，即便这样，我觉得最好还是把查尔斯还有贝德斯莱博士一起叫到书房，同多莉私下谈谈，不要将这些残缺不全的照片公开，以免他们身边的人对此妄加猜测。现在，我们实际上有了五张残缺不全得厉害的克雷上校的照片，从不同的角度拍的，表情和神态十分自然。全欧洲最聪明的骗子居然败在了一个孩子的手上！

贝德斯莱的目光刚落到这些照片上，脸上就出现了一种奇特的表情，说道：“林格菲尔德小姐，这些照片是用赫伯特·温斯洛的方法拍的。”

“不错，”多莉羞怯地承认了，“确实是的。你也知道，他是……我的一个朋友。是他给了我些底片，刚好我的相机能用。”

贝德斯莱直直地盯着这些照片，接着转向查尔斯，说：“最终，这位年轻的小姐无意间追踪到了克雷上校。这些都是这个人真实的照片——他本人就是这样——没有任何伪装！”

“我看着到处是斑点，”查尔斯低声道，“鼻梁那儿有条明显的黑线，脸上也有类似的斑点！”

“一点不错，”贝德斯莱说道，“这些就是纹理上的差别。这些照片就显示了这个人的脸到底有多少是真的——”

“有多少是蜡。”我也斗胆说了一句。

“不是蜡，”那位专家仔细地瞧了瞧，说道，“是一种比蜡更硬的混合物。我猜是杜仲胶和橡胶合成的，容易上色，贴上之后就会变硬，与皮肤贴合得比较平整，耐热耐熔。看这儿，这是一条人造伤疤，填补中空的地方；这一点是多加在鼻尖上的；这些阴影是因为嘴里塞了些填充脸颊的东西，让人看起来更胖些！”

“肯定，”查尔斯大声说道，“肯定是橡胶。这就是为什么在法国，别人管他叫橡皮脸上校！”

“你能用这些照片重新勾勒出他的真实面目吗？”我急切地问道。

贝德斯莱博士仔细地盯着照片。“给我一两个小时的时间，”他说，“再给我一盒水彩。我想，到时候——根据已有的材料进行推断——我就能把伪装剔除，给你们勾勒出他大致的真实形象。”

我们把他领到书房待了几个小时，带了他所需要的材料。到下午茶的时候，他已经根据两张脸中的共同点，画出了第一幅草图。他拿到客厅，我先看了看。那张面孔很奇怪，有点模糊，很像高尔顿先生先后分别将两张底片放在同一张感光纸上十秒钟冲洗出来的“合成照片”。不过，这也让我立刻为之一惊，因为它涵盖了克雷上校众多化身的某些特点。现实中的小副牧师让人想不到墨西哥先知，伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯也不能让人想到凡·莱本斯坦伯爵，或者施莱尔马赫教授。可是，在这张由大卫·格兰顿和梅德赫斯特的照片合成的面孔中，我可以很明显地追寻到那个骗子每一次乔装后的某些踪迹。换句话说，虽然他的乔装打扮能避免同他扮演的其他角色有任何相似之处，但他无法乔装打扮得让别人认不出他自己。他无法完完全全抹掉自己天生的体格以及真实的相貌特点。

除了与先知还有小副牧师有惊人的相似以外，我还隐隐觉得在某个时间某个地点见过用水彩画出的这个人。不是在尼斯，也不是在塞尔登；不是在米兰，也不是在美国。我确信自己曾经在伦敦的某个地方与他同处一室。

查尔斯从我身后看过来，突然一惊。“啊，我知道这个家伙，”他喊道，“西，你想想这个人，他是芬戈摩尔的弟弟——就是没去中国的那个家伙！”

紧接着，我一下子想起来在哪儿见过他了——我们动身去美国前，在伦敦那位经纪人的办公室里见过。

“他的教名是什么？”我问。

“和我们从风衣中搜到的短笺中的名字一模一样，”查尔斯想了一会儿，最后答道，“他叫保罗·芬戈摩尔！”

“你会抓捕他吗？”我问。

“就凭这种证据，我能吗？”

“咱们会让他明白的。”

查尔斯沉思了一阵子。“我们除了能确定他的身份，”他缓缓说道，“没有任何指控他的证据。这下子可能就难办了。”

就在此时，仆人端茶上来。克雷上校冒充大卫·格兰顿时，这个仆人当时也同我们一起在塞尔登。查尔斯很显然想试探一下，看看他能否还记得这张脸，或者是否记得在哪儿见过。“达德利，看这里，”他举起水彩画，问道，“你认不认识这个人？”

达德利盯了一会儿，马上答道：“认识，先生！”

“他是谁？”艾米莉亚问道。我们都觉得他会说“凡·莱本斯坦伯爵”，或者“格兰顿先生”，再或者“梅德赫斯特”。

他没这么说。让我们万万没想到的是，他答道：“夫人，那是西塞琳的男友。”

“西塞琳的男友？”艾米莉亚大吃一惊，重复道，“啊，达德利，你肯定认错了，肯定认错了！”

“不可能，夫人，”达德利肯定地回答，“他常常过来看她。自打我服侍查尔斯爵士以来，他就隔三岔五地过来看她。”

“他什么时候再来？”查尔斯屏住了呼吸，问道。

“先生，他现在就在楼下。”达德利答道，全然不知他给一个体面的家庭扔了一枚炸弹。

查尔斯兴奋地站了起来，用背倚着门。“抓住那人！”他用手指着，厉声向我喝道。

“哪个人？”我问道，完全摸不着头脑，“克雷上校？正在楼下同西塞琳待在一起的那个人？”

“不是，”查尔斯说，语气坚决，“达德利！”

我一只手按在那位仆人的肩上，不明白查尔斯究竟是什么意思。达德利吓得半死，向后退去；要不是查尔斯倚着门，他早就夺门而逃了。

“我——我什么出格的事也没做，查尔斯爵士，”达德利喊道，两眼祈求似的盯着艾米莉亚，一副惊恐可怜的样子，“不是——不是我骗的您。”他看起来也绝对不像能做出这种事的人。

“我知道你没骗我，”查尔斯说，“不过，在抓住克雷上校以前，你不能离开这个房间。不行，艾米莉亚；不行，说什么都没用。他说的全是实话。我现在完全明白是怎么一回事了。那个无赖同西塞琳俩人一直以来都是同谋！他现在正在楼下同西塞琳待在一起。要是我让达德利离开房间，他就会下楼给他们报信。这样，不等我们明白过来，那条泥鳅就又从我们指尖溜走了，他经常这样。他就是保罗·芬戈摩尔，西塞琳的男友。要是咱们现在不立刻抓住他，他今晚就会跑到马德里或者圣彼得堡去了！”

“说得对！”我接过话，“机不可失，时不再来！”

“达德利，”查尔斯极为威严地说，“我们不通知你，不要离开这个房间。艾米莉亚还有多莉，不要让那个人就地捅娄子。要是他不老实，就把他拿住。西摩，贝德斯莱博士，跟我下楼去仆役大厅。达德利，我是不是能在那儿找到这个人？”

“找——找不到，先生，”达德利吓得魂不附体，结结巴巴地说道，“他现在在管家的房间里，先生！”

我们三人一行来到楼下，半路碰到了辛普森，他是查尔斯爵士的贴身男仆兼管家，我们把他也一起拉过去帮忙。到了管家的房间门口，为了小心行事，我们停住脚步。里面传出阵阵声音：一个是西塞琳的声音，另一个声音让我立刻想到了梅德赫斯特、先知、伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯还有阿尔杰农·克雷亚德。他们俩在用法语交谈，时不时地能听到他们压低的笑声。

我们打开门时，那男的正用法语说：“这个老头是不是很滑稽？”

“快要笑死我了。”西塞琳也用法语答道。

我们冲进去，把他们当场抓住。

西塞琳的男友站起身，手里拿着帽子，态度很恭敬。这立刻让我想起了梅德赫斯特的情形，他当时在马维尔家，站着同查尔斯谈论着第一天的安排；还让我想起了那位公正无私的小副牧师极为谦卑的样子。

查尔斯紧紧地按住那个年轻人的肩膀，并示意我也这么做。我仔细看了看那家伙的脸：西塞琳的男友就是保罗·芬戈摩尔，就是我们经纪人的弟弟，绝对错不了。

“保罗·芬戈摩尔，”查尔斯厉声喝道，“也就是库斯伯特·克雷，因你犯的几项偷窃罪和共谋罪我要捉拿你！”

那个年轻人看看四周，大吃一惊，有些慌张。不过，即便这样，他仍然始终保持冷静。“怎么，就凭你们五个对付我一个吗？”他数了数我们的人数，说道，“这儿还有没有王法了？五个有头有脸的无赖来抓捕一个爱冒险的乞丐！嗨，比在纽约还卑鄙！在纽约，只是咱们两个。还记得吗？之前的百分之十那件事！”

“辛普森，抓住他两只手！”查尔斯焦急地喊道，生怕他从手中逃掉。

虽然我们抓住了他的双肩，保罗·芬戈摩尔还是往后退了几步。“不行，你不行，先生，”他高傲地说，“我看你敢碰我！查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士，要抓我，你就派个警察来，我绝不会让一个男仆来抓我！”

“去找警察。”贝德斯莱博士向前走了几步，对辛普森说道。

那犯人上下打量他一番。“哎，原来是贝德斯莱博士！”他舒了一口气，说道，很明显犯人认识他，“要是你完全按照贝蒂荣识别法找到的我，我倒不怎么介意。我愿屈身于科学，但不愿屈身于蠢材。我觉得，这位钻石大王可没长那么多脑子，能想到求助于你。他是我这辈子碰到过的最好骗的老浑蛋。不过，要是你把我追捕到了，我只能认了。”

查尔斯紧紧地抓住他。“西，小心别让他跑了，”他喊道，“他又在耍老花招！别听他在那儿叨叨！”

“小心点，”上校说，“想想伯尔派罗那件事！你凭什么抓我？”

查尔斯满腔怒火。“你在尼斯骗过我，”他说，“在米兰，在纽约，在巴黎，你都骗过我！”

保罗·芬戈摩尔摇摇头。“说这些没用，”他冷静地应道，“看看你在哪儿？那些地方都不在司法管辖区！你要指控我，得有引渡令。”

“那好，在塞尔登，在伦敦，就在这座房子里，还有其他地方，你也骗过我，”查尔斯激动地大声说道，“西，把他抓得紧点。管它合不合法，即便现在这样，也确保别让他再逃掉了！”

此时，辛普森回来了，在附近找到了一名警察，他碰巧看到那名警察在采光井的台阶旁闲逛。看着警察那鬼祟的笑容，我有点怀疑他是不是查尔斯家的某个熟人。

查尔斯正式地把犯人交给了警察。保罗·芬戈摩尔一再让查尔斯说清楚自己到底犯了什么罪。令我非常懊恼的是，查尔斯从他所干的那些坏事中，单单选了购买莱本斯坦城堡那件事，因为它是英国司法管辖范围内最有力的一项罪名——在伦敦作案，并且通过伦敦的银行付的款。“我凭那件事可以抓捕你。”他说道。他说话时，我整个人在发抖，立刻觉得自己最担心的佣金那件事，现在肯定要昭告天下了。

警察把犯人押住，查尔斯仍然死死地抓着他。在走出房间时，犯人转身用德语低声对西塞琳快速说了些什么话。“虽然我好心送了你一本德语字典还有语法书，”他转过身温和地对我们说，“不过，我说的这些话，你肯定还是根本听不懂！”

西塞琳深情地扑向他。“哦，保罗，我亲爱的，”她用英语哭诉道，“我不会那么做，不会！我不会牺牲你来保全自己。要是他们让你坐牢——保罗，保罗，我就同你一起坐牢！”

她说这话时，我想起了阿尔杰农·克雷亚德先生在参议员家中对我们说的话：“即便最无耻的无赖，内心也总会有好的一面。我发现，他们常常能一直让女性爱自己，并且对自己忠诚。”

他的双手还可以自由活动，用手指轻柔地松开了她的双臂。“亲爱的，”他温柔地说道，“可惜英国法律不允许你跟我一起坐牢。要是我坐牢了，”（他此时的声音又变成了我们所碰到的诗人的声音）“‘石壁不足以为囚牢，铁栏不足以为牢笼。[44]’”他身子前倾，轻轻地吻了一下她的额头。

我们带着他出了门。那位警察遵照查尔斯的吩咐，紧紧地抓着犯人，不过因为犯人没有强烈反抗，便坚决不用手铐铐住他。我们叫了辆过路的马车。“去弓街！”查尔斯一边粗鲁地把警察和犯人推搡进马车，一边大声喊道。车夫点点头。我们自己又叫了辆四轮马车，车上坐着我内兄、贝德斯莱博士还有我。“紧跟那辆马车！”查尔斯大声说，“别让它跑出你的视线。跟着它，跟紧点，去弓街！”

我回头看了一眼，看到西塞琳已经在前门台阶上快晕过去了，多莉则满脸泪花，站在旁边扶着她，试着安慰她一下。多莉显然没有想到事情会出现这种结局。

“我的天！”我们在第一个街角转弯时，查尔斯突然警觉地叫了出来，“那辆马车哪儿去了？谁知道那个家伙是不是真警察，我们应该把他押在这辆车上的，就不应该让他脱离咱们的视线。虽然咱们都明白事情真相并非如此，不过那个警察——那个警察也许就是克雷上校的同党！”

于是，我们心急如焚，一路驱车奔向弓街。

第十二章　老贝利街[45]

我们抵达弓街时，长舒了一口气，因为囚犯没有半路跑掉。虚惊一场。他同警察待在一起，欣然允许我们正式提出对他的第一项指控。

我和查尔斯都宣过誓，犯人当然就被立刻送到大牢之中，不许保释：一方面是因为被指控的罪名比较严重，另一方面是因为犯人有过溜逃的前科。我们回到梅费尔——看到令自己一直担惊受怕的那个人被关到了牢狱中，查尔斯十分满意；就我而言，一想到令自己一直担惊受怕的那个人不再逍遥法外，而百分之十的佣金那个微不足道的小插曲即将公开，我一点也高兴不起来。

第二天，来了很多警察，同我和查尔斯长谈了一番。他们不断地催促我们，说至少还有其他两个人也应该受到指控——西塞琳，还有在不同场合被冠以皮卡迪特夫人、白石南花、大卫·格兰顿夫人、伊莱休·夸肯鲍斯夫人等称呼的那个小妇人。他们还说，要是这两个同党也被逮捕的话，我们就可以在起诉书中再增加共谋这一罪状，会让我们多一份胜算。目前，他们抓到了克雷上校，实际上自然想关着他，并且打算一同指控他尽可能多的同党。

不过，这么一来，问题就出现了。查尔斯阴沉着脸，把我叫到一边，去了书房。“西摩，”他开口道，两眼直直地盯着我，“这个问题比较严重。我不愿轻易地指控任何一位女性。至于克雷上校——或者说保罗·芬戈摩尔——他是个寡廉鲜耻的无赖，我不想对他有任何的袒护。不过，可怜的小皮卡迪特夫人——她或许是他法定的妻子，或许暗中受了他的指使。还有，我不清楚能不能认出她来。这是警方拿来的照片，说是克雷上校的头号女共犯。现在，我问问你，她像不像那位聪明、有趣、魅力四射，还经常骗咱们的小女士？”

虽然查尔斯以前对我冷嘲热讽，但我自以为深谙作为一名秘书的职责。他的意思很明显：不想让我认出她。于是，我也就没认出来。“查尔斯，根本不像，”我回答得很坚决，“我压根儿就不认识她。”不过，我没说压根儿不认识保罗·芬戈摩尔——或者说西塞琳的男友——所冒充的克雷上校，因为说这种话显然是秘书职责之外的事。

不过，当时我的脑海里突然想到，先知在尼斯时不经意间提到过，查尔斯的口袋中有封信，很有可能就是皮卡迪特夫人写的。再想想，那么皮卡迪特夫人很有可能手里也有查尔斯的回信，信的内容和措辞查尔斯不愿让艾米莉亚看到。实际上，说句实话，不论“白石南花”以何种伪装出现，查尔斯总会第一眼就拜倒在她的石榴裙下。因此，我觉得，那位精明的小妇人——你想怎么称呼她都行——很可能手里攥着不止一封查尔斯写给她的秘密信件。

“这样一来，”查尔斯用最严厉的口吻继续道，“我无法同意去逮捕‘白石南花’。我……我拒绝指认她。实际上，”他越说语气越重，“我觉得没有任何对她不利的证据。”他稍稍一顿，又继续道：“我并不想包庇犯人。现在说说西塞琳——我们喜欢她，也信任她，可是她辜负了我们的信任，把我们出卖给了这个家伙。毫无疑问，是她从艾米莉亚的首饰盒中把钻石偷走给了他；是她安排我们在莱本斯坦城堡同他碰的面；是她拆了我给克雷盖拉奇勋爵的信，然后又寄给了他。所以，要我说，咱们得把西塞琳抓起来。不能抓‘白石南花’——不抓杰西，不抓那位漂亮的夸肯鲍斯夫人。要让犯了罪的人接受惩罚，对于那无辜的人——或者最坏的情况是，受人误导的人——我们为什么要加以惩罚呢？”

“查尔斯，”我兴奋地大声说道，“我们为你的体贴周到感到骄傲。你是个有情有义的人，要我说，‘白石南花’这么漂亮这么聪明，无论做了什么，都应该原谅她。放心，我绝口不提。我发誓，我不会指认这个妇人就是皮卡迪特夫人的。”

查尔斯默默地抓住我的手。“西摩，”他顿了一顿，感动地说，“我想我绝对可以相信你的……你的……正直与人品。我以前有时对你苛刻了一些，不过，请你原谅。我明白，你已完全知晓自己岗位的全部职责。”

我们再次走出书房，两人的关系几个月以来从未如此亲密。实际上，我希望万一芬戈摩尔把百分之十的佣金那件事告诉查尔斯，今天这段愉快的小插曲能缓和一下那件事的不利影响。我们正一起走进客厅，这时艾米莉亚向我招手，让我到她房间待一会儿。

“西摩，”她对我说，语气中明显充满了惊恐，“有时，我对你不太客气，我也知道，非常抱歉。不过，现在我碰到了一点极为头疼的事，想让你帮我一下。警方指控的阴谋罪，这一点都不错。那个诡计多端的小狐狸精，‘白石南花’，或叫大卫·格兰顿夫人，或者其他什么名字，她绝对要受审——还要关到大牢里面去——再把她那荒唐的头发剪短梳直。不过……亲爱的西摩，我相信，在这一点上，你肯定会帮我的——我不能让他们把西塞琳带走。我不是装作不知她没有过错，她对我忘恩负义，到处骗我，毫无悔意。不过，话又说回来——你也结了婚，我给你说——让一个女人站到证人席，让自己的女仆被诘问、奚落，或者让女仆把知道的事告诉律师，让律师不留情面地盘问，谁能受得了？西摩，我告诉你，这事门儿都没有。女士的日常生活中有一些琐事——只有她的女仆知道——绝不可以公之于众。你尽可能地向查尔斯解释一下，让他明白，要是他非要坚持逮捕西塞琳，我就得站到证人席上——我发誓，到时候，他们这一帮人谁都判不了。我就是这么跟西塞琳说的，向她保证要帮她一把。我跟她说，我是她朋友，要是她帮我，我就帮她，也帮她那位让人恨之入骨的男友。”

我一下子明白这是怎么一回事了。查尔斯和艾米莉亚二人谁都无法面对克雷上校的共犯的诘问。就艾米莉亚而言，原因毫无疑问仅仅在于胭脂、染发之类的事情；不过，这又不是伪造文书，也不是杀人害命，只不过是梳洗化妆上的小秘密，有什么不能坦白的呢？

于是我又找到查尔斯，花了半个小时，尽我所能地向他解释了这些家庭内部小问题。我们最终商定，如果查尔斯尽力保护西塞琳免于逮捕，那艾米莉亚则同意尽其所能来保护皮卡迪特夫人作为报答。

接下来，我们还得过警方这一关——这一关更为棘手。即便他们通情达理，这也并非易事。他们觉得自己抓住了克雷上校，不过能否对他加以指控，这完全取决于查尔斯的指认，还有我的进一步确认。他们越是催促，说有必要逮捕他的那些女性同党，查尔斯就越坚决地宣布，自己不敢确定克雷上校的身份，同时完全拒绝出示任何对那两位女性不利的证据。他说，这个案件比较棘手，他一点儿都不敢确定那名男子的身份。要是他犹豫不决，不愿意指认，那么这个案子就得终止，陪审团也就无法判定克雷上校任何罪名了。

最终警方别无选择，只得让步。他们抓捕了一个重要罪犯，不过发现，一切都取决于目击证人的安全，而要是目击证人受到干扰的话，他则有可能什么都不说。

实际上，在法庭的初步调查还未结束前（犯人按惯例还在关押候审），查尔斯就早已陷入了焦虑，多么希望自己当初没有抓住克雷上校。

“西，我在想，”他对我说，“当时我为什么没有一年给这无赖两千英镑，让他直接滚到澳大利亚，让他永远消失！就我的个人声誉而言，这要比把他押在英国法庭受审划算得多。最糟的是，即便最无可挑剔的人，一旦站到了证人席上，指不定到头来会被说成什么样！”

“查尔斯，对你来说，不必有此顾虑，”我责无旁贷地答道，“也许，只是并购克雷盖拉奇那件事算个例外。”

接着，我们便同警方还有律师一起无休止地“策划这场诉讼”。查尔斯本想在此时全身而退，不过，非常不幸的是，他不得不出庭指证。“你们能不能把事情一次处理完，然后放我走？”查尔斯跟巡官开玩笑道。不过，我心里明白，这正是俗话所说的“嬉笑多真言”。

当然，现在我们明白了这场大阴谋是如何一步步设计的，设计得就像蒂奇伯恩骗局一样缜密[46]。年轻的芬戈摩尔，也就是查尔斯的经纪人的弟弟，他从一开始就知道查尔斯的底细。一开始小打小闹干了一些坏事以后，他便开始针对我内兄精心制订了周密的计划，所有的一切都是他事先故意设计好的。先给西塞琳找了个差事，去当艾米莉亚的女仆——不用说，用的都是些假证明。有了西塞琳的帮助，那骗子对这个家庭的日常习惯更是一清二楚。他掌握了一些信息，后来又以此来骗我们。他针对我们的第一次行动，也就是扮演先知的那次，设计得十分巧妙，让我们觉得自己只是偶然被他选作目标。现在查尔斯才注意到，皮卡迪特夫人在马赛信贷银行询问他银行账号这一细节，是为了故意蒙蔽我们，不让我们一眼看出克雷上校早已完全掌握了我们的这些信息。同样，还是西塞琳帮的忙，他拿到了艾米莉亚的钻石，截获了发给克雷盖拉奇的信函，还在莱本斯坦城堡那件事上骗了我们。不过，这些事，查尔斯决定在法庭上避而不谈，凡是对西塞琳或皮卡迪特夫人不利的事，他对警方都只字不提。

至于西塞琳，在克雷上校被捕以后，她也立即出走了，直到庭审那天我们才见到她。

庭审当天，老贝利街的场面从未如此让人震撼过，法庭被围得水泄不通。查尔斯在律师的陪同下，早早地到场了。他面色苍白，愁眉不展，看起来更像是被告，而非原告。法庭外面站着一位漂亮的小妇人，面色苍白，一脸焦急。周围的人在一旁静静地望着她。“她是谁？”查尔斯问。我们俩虽然看不出，却都能猜得到，她就是“白石南花”。

“她是被告的妻子，”当班的巡官答道，“她要在这儿看丈夫出庭。可怜的人儿，真替她惋惜，这么一位无可挑剔的妇人。”

“看起来确实是这样。”查尔斯说道，不敢正眼看她。

就在此时，她转过身，看着查尔斯的双眼。查尔斯怔了一下，看起来身子有些摇摆。在那双眼睛中，只能隐隐地看到一丝乞求，完全看不到以往轻佻、傲慢、活泼的影子。查尔斯张开嘴要说话，但一个字都未能出口。我想我不会猜错，从口型来看，他准备说：“我会尽力帮他的。”

我们在警方的帮助下挤进法庭。在法庭里，我们看到有位全身素黑的女士坐着，戴了顶挺般配的软帽。过了一会儿，我才意识到——那就是西塞琳。“那个人……又是谁？”查尔斯又问了问离他最近的巡官，想听听他怎么说。

这一次的回答是：“先生，她是被告的妻子。”

查尔斯向后一退，大吃一惊，一脸不解，突然冒了句：“可是……有人给我说……门外有位女士是他的妻子。”

“那也很有可能，”巡官不动声色地答道，“我们碰到过很多这样的。像克雷上校这样的绅士，有众多的化身，你很难想象这么多的身份却执意只娶一位妻子，是不是？”

“哦，明白了，”查尔斯喃喃地说道，语气中流露着震惊，“重婚！”

巡官看起来面无表情。“也不是，”他答道，“只是临时婚姻。”

拉德曼斯法官审理这个案子。“西，真倒霉，是他来审理。”我内兄在我耳边小声道。（查尔斯之所以这么说，是因为不管他在其他方面如何，但他绝不迂腐；大多数受过教育的人说出的英语，都完全能够表达出自己的意思。）“多么希望是爱德华·伊斯爵士，他见过世面，也懂世故，会体谅像我这种身份地位的人。他决不会让这些禽兽般的律师来纠缠我，攻击我。他会支持与自己同一阶层的人。可这位拉德曼斯是你们的现代法官，以所谓的‘讲良心’而自夸，有什么说什么，一点都不遮掩。说实话，我有点怕他，巴不得这一切早点儿结束。”

“哦，没事，你会挺过去的。”我这么说，完全是出于秘书的职责。实际上我却不这么认为。

法官入了席，犯人被带了进来。好像所有人都在注视着他：他衣着整洁朴素，说实话，虽然他是个无赖，但看起来至少像位绅士。他的一举一动都趾高气扬，不像查尔斯那么低三下四。他知道自己已经无处可逃，于是便勇敢地直面指控者。

我们列了两三条罪状，在走了一些法律程序之后，查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士就被带入证人席，去指控芬戈摩尔。

那犯人没有律师。法庭找了位律师来帮他，不过被他拒绝了。法官甚至建议他接受法庭的帮助，不过克雷上校（我们在心里还是这么叫他）拒绝采纳法官的提议。

“法官大人，我本人就是一名律师，”他说道，“这是大约九年前的事了。恕我冒昧，我自己为自己辩护，会比其他博学的同行为我辩护更有力。”

查尔斯很轻松地就结束了本方证人的讯问。他对答如流，迫不及待地指出，庭上的犯人就是曾经先后乔装成理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗牧师、大卫·格兰顿阁下、凡·莱本斯坦伯爵、施莱尔马赫教授、夸肯鲍斯医生等人来骗他的那个人。他对此人的身份有十足的把握，无论在哪儿都绝对能把他认出来。在我看来，他有些过于自信了。要是指认时能略显迟疑，或许会更好。至于那各种各样的骗局，他一五一十一个不落地全说了，银行官员还有其他下级人员都为之做证。总之，他让芬戈摩尔毫无立足之地。

不过，在交互讯问这个环节，局势开始出现了大转折。犯人开始质疑查尔斯的指认，问查尔斯敢认定他就是这个人吗？他递给查尔斯一张照片，劝诱地问道：“是不是这个人乔装成了理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗牧师？”

查尔斯立刻承认，毫不迟疑。

就在此时，一个小牧师站了起来，我之前没有注意到这个人，他站在法庭近中间的位置，毫不起眼，就坐在西塞琳的身旁。

“看看这位先生！”犯人边说边挥手想引起公诉人的注意。

查尔斯转过身，看了看他提到的那个人。他脸色更苍白了。那个人——就外表来看——就是理查德·佩普洛·布拉巴宗牧师本人。

我当然明白其中的把戏。克雷上校所乔装的那小牧师模仿的就是这位真正的牧师。不过，陪审团为之一震，查尔斯也惊呆了好一会儿。

“让陪审员也看看照片。”法官威严地说道。照片在陪审席前传看，法官本人也仔细地看了一看。从他们的面部表情和态度上，我们立刻明白了，他们都认出照片中的人正是面前这位牧师，而非被告席中的犯人——此刻，他正看着查尔斯那狼狈的样子，泰然自若地微笑着。

牧师坐下了。此时，犯人又拿出第二张照片。

“好，现在能不能告诉我这是谁？”他以中央刑事法庭那一贯咄咄逼人的语气问查尔斯。

查尔斯这次略微迟疑得久些，他顿了一顿，答道：“这就是你。当时你来到伦敦，乔装成凡·莱本斯坦伯爵。”

这一点极其关键，因为莱本斯坦诈骗案这个案子，是我们的律师最能充分证明案件在伦敦法院受理范围的依据。

就在查尔斯说话的当儿，一位坐在“白石南花”身旁的先生——我刚才注意到了——用手帕遮着脸，跟小牧师一样，突然站了起来。克雷上校用手优雅地向他一指，冷静地问道：“那这位先生呢？”

查尔斯明显要站不住了。这显然就是冒牌的凡·莱本斯坦伯爵的原型。

那张照片再一次在陪审席间传阅。陪审员的脸上挂着笑容，也挂着质疑。查尔斯已经放弃了。他那过分的自信与肯定已经毁了自己。

接着，克雷上校身子前倾，十分引人注目，又开始交互讯问，说道：“查尔斯爵士，在座的诸位都已经看到了，我们不能盲目地相信你的指认。现在，咱们来看看，你其他的证据到底有多可信。首先，先说说钻石那件事。你企图从一位自称为理查德·布拉巴宗牧师的人手里把它买到手，原因是，你相信那牧师觉得那只是铅玻璃；要是你买，你大概会给他十英镑左右，对不对？你觉得这有诚信吗？”

“我反对这个讯问，”我们的首席律师打断他，“这和原告的证据没有任何关系，这纯粹是揭丑。”

克雷上校全然不顾。“法官大人，”他转而看看四周，说道，“我这么做，是想证明原告不足为信。我想遵循的是法律上广为人知的‘一事假，事事假’这一原则。我想，大人应该允许我动摇对目击证人的信任吧？”

“犯人完全有权这么做，”拉德曼斯一边说着，一边板着脸盯着查尔斯，“刚才我还建议他接受律师的建议或援助，看来我是错了。”

看得出，查尔斯在扭动着身体，克雷上校则振作了起来。他那些巧妙的提问，一步步逼得查尔斯承认，自己虽然知道那些钻石是真品，可仍想以铅玻璃的价格把它们买到手；承认自己作为一位百万富翁，却满心欢喜地算计着从一名穷副牧师手中骗走几千英镑。

“我有权用自己的专业知识为自己牟利。”查尔斯弱弱地咕哝了一句。

“哈，当然，”犯人接过话，“不过，你一方面对生活拮据的副牧师夫妇大谈友谊，大谈爱心；而另一方面，却貌似打算花十英镑——要是可以的话——从他们手中买走价值三千英镑的物品，难道不是吗？”

查尔斯被迫承认这一事实。

犯人接着又说到了大卫·格兰顿那件事。“当你主动要同克雷盖拉奇勋爵合作时，”他问道，“有一条金矿矿脉从你的土地延伸到了克雷盖拉奇勋爵的土地上，你知道还是不知道？他土地里的矿脉比你的面积要大，并且重要得多，你知道还是不知道？”

查尔斯又扭动着身体，我们的律师打断他，不过拉德曼斯法官非常固执，查尔斯只得任其讲下去。

同样，他还提到了戈尔康达股价暴跌事件。查尔斯被一步步逼着羞愧地承认，他作为戈尔康达的董事长，虽然多次向股东及其他相关人士强调，自己不会出售公司的股票，可最后还是把公司股票全部卖出了，原因是他相信施莱尔马赫教授已经使钻石变得一文不值了。他企图通过毁掉公司来拯救自己。查尔斯努力厚着脸皮，想表明生意归生意，是另一码事。“可欺诈就是欺诈。”拉德曼斯接着他的话，一针见血地说道。

“人人都要自保啊。”查尔斯突然迸出这句话。

“那些信任此君的名誉和人品的人却做了牺牲品。”法官冷冷地评论道。

如此这般，我内兄熬了四个小时，最后离开证人席，咬着嘴唇，抹着额头，俨然一副罪人模样。他的人格大为受损。他站在证人席上时，所有人都觉得他是被告，而克雷上校则是原告。别人用他自己提供的证据，指控他想方设法去诱使所谓的大卫·格兰顿将他父亲的财产利益出卖给竞争对手，还指控了其他每项见不得人的勾当；很不幸，这一切都是他那出众、精明的商业头脑在投机活动中惹的祸。我内兄遭受了这些不幸，只有一点让我欣慰——我想他意识到了自己的种种缺点，也许当他发现自己可怜的秘书犯了点小错时，最终会网开一面。

接下来，轮到我站到证人席中。我无意对自己的功劳夸大其词。实际上，考虑到自己的面子，证据陈述之后的那痛苦场面我就不谈了。我所能说的是，在指认相片时，我比查尔斯要谨慎得多，不过自己尤其担心交互问讯的其他环节。特别是在购买莱本斯坦城堡的佣金支票那件事上，我走错的那一步，让我心惊胆战——克雷上校毕恭毕敬地把支票递给我，问我有没有在上面签名。在对我问讯结束时，我看到了查尔斯的眼神。我敢说，他那眼神中有种解脱，好像在说，我最终也没能保全自己，在城堡购买款项百分之十的佣金这件微不足道的小事上栽了跟头。

总之，不得不承认，要是没有警方的佐证，我们对克雷上校的指控根本不成立。不过，警方的诉讼让人拍手称快。既然他们知道了克雷上校的真实身份就是保罗·芬戈摩尔，于是便巧妙地展示了保罗·芬戈摩尔——不管他乔装成小副牧师、先知、大卫·格兰顿，还是其他身份——在伦敦的出现与消失，与克雷上校在其他地方的消失与出现，是如何完全吻合的。此外，他们还试着演示了那犯人是如何乔装成其他不同角色的。不仅如此，贝德斯莱博士根据在弓街的观察，塑了一个半身像，又按照多莉·林格菲尔德的照片增添了一些杜仲胶混合物，警方利用这种方法，证明了那张脸庞能迅速地整形成梅德赫斯特还有大卫·格兰顿的面孔。总的来说，警方的聪明劲儿，还有那训练有素的敏锐劲儿，挽回了查尔斯的过分肯定带来的后果，他们成功地在陪审团面前摆了一份强有力的证据来指控保罗·芬戈摩尔。

庭审持续了三天。第一天过后，我那位令人敬重的内兄就说，自己再也不想出庭指控犯人了。当天晚上吃饭时，百分之十的佣金那件小事他提都没提，只是说所有人——不管是秘书，还是董事长——都肯定会维护自身的利益。我就当他原谅我了。我仍然继续参加庭审，代表自己的雇主关注案件的进展。

克雷上校的辩护，虽说略显乏力，但很机智。他自始至终无非是想证明我和查尔斯认错了人，因而让他蒙冤。芬戈摩尔让小副牧师那位朴实的原型人物——赛普蒂默斯·伯金顿牧师，他家族的一位朋友——出庭做证，说是贝克街的一位摄影师为赛普蒂默斯牧师本人照的相，但查尔斯却一口认定，这张照片就是克雷上校乔装的理查德·布拉巴宗先生的照片。接着，他又说道，凡·莱本斯坦伯爵照片中的那个人的确是尤里斯·凯博尔博士，他是蒂罗尔的音乐教师，住在巴勒姆，并请他出庭做证，碰巧陪审团主席同此人很熟。他一步步让我们明白，除了多莉·林格菲尔德手里的照片是真的，这世上根本没有什么关于克雷上校的照片。我渐渐才明白，要是我们找到了据称是克雷上校乔装成伯爵还有小副牧师的照片——就是梅德赫斯特给我们看过的那几张——并且认为那就是他本人，那么贝德斯莱也肯定会受到误导。总之，犯人申辩说，只有两位目击者直接认出了他，并且其中有一位满口发誓，说认出了犯人的两张照片，但他却有独立证据证明那些照片上的人另有他人！

法官做了总结，言辞刻薄，双方听着都不怎么顺耳。他说，虽说自己毫不掩饰地指出“查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士显然不诚实”，但让陪审团完全不要受这种印象的影响；还说虽然查尔斯是位百万富翁——名声极其不好——但千万别因此事而心存偏见，转而同情犯人。哪怕是最有钱的人——最坏的人——都必须受到法律的保护。此外，这还是个公共问题。如果一个无赖骗了另一个无赖，他也仍要受到惩罚。如果一个杀人犯刺杀或枪杀了另一个杀人犯，他也仍要被处以绞刑。社会一定要确保，即使万恶不赦的盗贼也不能受到别人的侵害。因此，虽然已经证实查尔斯·凡德里夫特爵士身价几百万英镑，却使用下流的手段，试图从被告或者说其他某位穷人手中骗走价值不菲的钻石，卑鄙地企图把克雷盖拉奇勋爵的矿产骗到自己手中，心怀歹意地贿赂儿子去出卖自己的父亲，毫不避讳地用了见不得人的手段来挽回自己的财富，而那些相信他正直廉洁的人的财富却面临被洗劫的风险——即使这样，陪审团也千万不要让这些铁定的事实遮住双眼，而忘了被囚禁的这位犯人（如果他真的是克雷上校）是个寡廉鲜耻的骗子。他们应该关注的仅仅是，如果他们确信这位犯人就是在不同场合乔装成大卫·格兰顿、凡·莱本斯坦、梅德赫斯特，还有施莱尔马赫的那个人，那么陪审团就必然要认定他有罪。

法官也同样就此评价了警方的有力证据，还提到，在如此众多的事件中，犯人没有试着去证明自己不在场。当然，陪审团应当想想，要是他不是克雷上校，那么要去证明自己不在场，这难道不是件轻而易举的事吗？最后，法官总结了犯人身份认定中的一切可疑因素——还有所有的可能因素，剩下的交予陪审团进行裁决。

陪审团最后退席讨论如何裁决。在这段时间，法庭中所有人的目光都落在犯人身上。不过，保罗·芬戈摩尔自己却一动不动地望着大厅的尽头，在那儿两位面色苍白的女士坐在一起，手里拿着手帕，双眼哭得通红。

他站在那里，等待着裁决，面无表情，脸色苍白，准备迎接一切可能的结果。这时，我才意识到，他只身一人，仅仅凭借一己之力还有两位柔弱的女人，这得需要多大的勇气才能在这场不平等的较量中，这么长时间对抗着财富、权威，还有欧洲所有的政府！这时我才体会到，这些年来，他都是一直如此不顾一切地玩这场游戏，最后竟是这个结局！我的心中不免感慨万千。

陪审团缓缓鱼贯而回。当书记员问“你们认为被告有罪，还是无罪？”时，法庭里死一般寂静。

“我们认为他有罪。”

“所有罪名都成立吗？”

“指控的所有罪名都成立。”

后排的那两位妇人不约而同地一下子哭出声来。

拉德曼斯法官对着犯人厉声问道：“你还有什么要申辩的吗？说出来或许会让法庭酌情对你从轻量刑。”

“没有，”犯人答道，声音有些颤抖，“我是罪有应得……不过……我保护了自己身边最亲近的人。我已全力抗争过了。我承认自己的罪行，愿意接受惩罚。我只有一点遗憾：我们俩都不是什么好东西——我是说自己和原告——罪行轻的竟然站到了被告席，而罪行重的却站到了证人席。要说赏罚分明，咱们国家可真是煞费苦心——给他的是圣米迦勒及圣乔治大十字勋章[47]，给我的却是囚衣！”

法官严肃地盯着他。“保罗·芬戈摩尔，”他宣读着判决，口吻有些讽刺，“你选择究其一生钻研如何欺诈他人。如果一开始你的心思全都用于合法目的，至少你可以毫不费力地解决生计问题——运气好点的话，甚至还可能过上一种为人所不齿的舒适生活。可是你宁可走上一条恶行和犯罪的不法之路——你长期以来似乎一直逍遥法外，这一点我不否认。不过，我作为社会的代言人，决不能再允许你对它加以嘲弄，却仍逍遥法外。你已公然违反了社会的法律，并且你的劣迹也已败露。”他说这些话时，语气平和谦逊，但接下来，总会是他最为严厉的时刻。“我判你十四年劳役监禁。”

犯人鞠了一躬，不失他的外在风度。可他的目光却游离到了大厅的尽头，在那儿，两位啜泣的妇人突然放声大哭，不省人事地倒在彼此的肩上，传达员费了好大劲儿才将二人扶出庭外。

我们离庭时，周围只听到一个人说话，那是一个上学的孩子：“要是被判刑的是那个老凡德里夫特才让人高兴呢！这个叫克雷的家伙太聪明了，关到监狱里真可惜！”

话虽这么说，可他还是被关到了那里——关到了那个“僻静清幽之地”以劳代过，我对此感到有点惋惜。

故事的结尾，我再讲一个小插曲。

这件事过后，查尔斯匆匆忙忙离开伦敦赶往戛纳，以逃避周围人那指责的目光。艾米莉亚、伊莎贝尔还有我同他一起过去。一日午后，我们驱车在小镇远处的山中赶路，路两旁尽是桃金娘还有低矮的乳香树。这时，我们看到前方有辆漂亮的四轮敞篷马车，上面坐着两位妇人，身着全黑丧服。我们无意间一直跟到了大松树那儿——就是隔着海湾与昂蒂布遥望的那棵大松树。那两位妇人下了车，坐在一座小山上，悲伤地看着大海还有海上的岛屿。很明显，她们正满心悲痛。她们面色苍白，两眼充满血丝。“真可怜！”艾米莉亚说道，但突然间她的语气变了。

“哎，我的天，”她叫道，“那不是西塞琳吗！”

的确是她——还有“白石南花”！

查尔斯下车，向她们走去。“打扰了，”他一面脱帽致意，一面对皮卡迪特夫人说道，“很高兴见到你。既然最后是我把你的马车钱付了，我能否冒昧地问一句，你这是为谁戴的孝？”

“白石南花”一边往后退了退，一边啜泣着。这时，西塞琳转过身来，气得脸蛋通红，一副贵妇派头。“为了他！”她答道，“为了保罗！为了我们的王！就是因为你而被监禁起来的那个人！他一日不释放，我们俩就一日为他戴孝！”

查尔斯又脱帽致意，退了回来，一句话未说。他向艾米莉亚挥了挥手，同我一道步行回家，回戛纳。他看起来好像十分沮丧。

“你在呆呆地想什么？”我后来大声打趣地问道，想试着让他回过神来。

他转向我，叹了口气，说道：“我在想，要是我坐牢了，艾米莉亚和伊莎贝尔是否也会为我这么做？”

就我而言，根本不用考虑，我心里十分清楚。对于查尔斯，我敢说，虽然他是两个无赖中更有权势的那个，却不是能让女性为之死心塌地的那个。

Chapter VI The Episode of the German Professor

That winter in town my respected brother-in-law had little time on his hands to bother himself about trifes like Colonel Clay. A thunderclap burst upon him.He saw his chief interest in South Africa threatened by a serious, an unexpected, and a crushing danger.

Charles does a little in gold, and a little in land；but his principal operations have always lain in the direction of diamonds. Only once in my life, indeed, have I seen him pay the slightest attention to poetry, and that was when I happened one day to recite the lines：—

Full many a gem of purest ray serene

The dark, unfathomed caves of ocean bear.

He rubbed his hands at once and murmured enthusiastically，“I never thought of that. We might get up an Atlantic Exploration Syndicate, Limited.”So attached is he to diamonds.You may gather, therefore, what a shock it was to that gigantic brain to learn that science was rapidly reaching a point where his favourite gems might become all at once a mere drug in the market.Depreciation is the one bugbear that perpetually torments Sir Charles's soul；that winter he stood within measurable distance of so appalling a calamity.

It happened after this manner.

We were strolling along Piccadilly towards Charles's club one afternoon—he is a prominent member of the Crœsus, in Pall Mall—when, near Burlington House, whom should we happen to knock up against but Sir Adolphus Cordery, the famous mineralogist, and leading spirit of the Royal Society！He nodded to us pleasantly.“Halloa, Vandrift，”he cried, in his peculiarly loud and piercing voice；“you’re the very man I wanted to meet to-day.Good morning, Wentworth.Well, how about diamonds now, Sir Gorgius?You’ll have to sing small.It’s all up with you Midases.Heard about this marvellous new discovery of Schleiermacher’s?It’s calculated to make you diamond kings squirm like an eel in a frying-pan.”

I could see Charles wriggle inside his clothes. He was most uncomfortable.That a man like Cordery should say such things, in so loud a voice, on no matter how little foundation, openly in Piccadilly, was enough in itself to make a sensitive barometer such as Cloetedorp Golcondas go down a point or two.

“Hush, hush！”Charles said solemnly, in that awed tone of voice which he always assumes when Money is blasphemed against.“Please don't talk quite so loud！All London can hear you.”

Sir Adolphus ran his arm through Charles's most amicably. There's nothing Charles hates like having his arm taken.

“Come along with me to the Athenæum，”he went on, in the same stentorian voice，“and I’ll tell you all about it.Most interesting discovery.Makes diamonds cheap as dirt.Calculated to supersede South Africa altogether.”

Charles allowed himself to be dragged along. There was nothing else possible.Sir Adolphus continued, in a somewhat lower key, induced upon him by Charles's mute look of protest.It was a disquieting story.He told it with gleeful unction.It seems that Professor Schleiermacher, of Jena，“the greatest living authority on the chemistry of gems，”he said, had lately invented, or claimed to have invented, a system for artifcially producing diamonds, which had yielded most surprising and unexceptionable results.

Charles's lip curled slightly.“Oh, I know the sort of thing，”he said.“I've heard of it before. Very inferior stones, quite small and worthless, produced at immense cost, and even then not worth looking at.I'm an old bird, you know, Cordery；not to be caught with chaff.Tell me a better one！”

Sir Adolphus produced a small cut gem from his pocket.“How's that for the frst water?”he inquired, passing it across, with a broad smile, to the sceptic.“Made under my own eyes—and quite inexpensively！”

Charles examined it close, stopping short against the railings in St. James's Square to look at it with his pocket-lens.There was no denying the truth.It was a capital small gem of the fnest quality.

“Made under your own eyes?”he exclaimed, still incredulous.“Where, my dear sir?—at Jena?”

The answer was a thunderbolt from a blue sky.“No, here in London；last night as ever was；before myself and Dr. Gray；and about to be exhibited by the President himself at a meeting of Fellows of the Royal Society.”

Charles drew a long breath.“This nonsense must be stopped，”he said frmly—“it must be nipped in the bud. It won't do, my dear friend；we can't have such tampering with important Interests.”

“How do you mean?”Cordery asked, astonished.

Charles gazed at him steadily. I could see by the furtive gleam in my brother-in-law's eye he was distinctly frightened.“Where is the fellow?”he asked.“Did he come himself, or send over a deputy?”

“Here in London，”Sir Adolphus replied.“He's staying at my house；and he says he'll be glad to show his experiments to anybody scientifcally interested in diamonds. We propose to have a demonstration of the process to-night at Lancaster Gate.Will you drop in and see it?”

Would he“drop in”and see it?“Drop in”at such a function！Could he possibly stop away?Charles clutched the enemy's arm with a nervous grip.“Look here, Cordery，”he said, quivering；“this is a question affecting very important Interests. Don't do anything rash.Don't do anything foolish.Remember that Shares may rise or fall on this.”He said“Shares”in a tone of profound respect that I can hardly even indicate.It was the crucial word in the creed of his religion.

“I should think it very probable，”Sir Adolphus replied, with the callous indifference of the mere man of science to fnancial suffering.

Sir Charles was bland, but peremptory.“Now, observe，”he said，“a grave responsibility rests on your shoulders. The Market depends upon you.You must not ask in any number of outsiders to witness these experiments.Have a few mineralogists and experts, if you like；but also take care to invite representatives of the menaced Interests.I will come myself—I'm engaged to dine out, but I can contract an indisposition；and I should advise you to ask Mosenheimer, and, say, young Phipson.They would stand for the mines, as you and the mineralogists would stand for science.Above all, don't blab；for Heaven's sake, let there be no premature gossip.Tell Schleiermacher not to go gassing and boasting of his success all over London.”

“We are keeping the matter a profound secret, at Schleiermacher's own request，”Cordery answered, more seriously.

“Which is why，”Charles said, in his severest tone，“you bawled it out at the very top of your voice in Piccadilly！”

However, before nightfall, everything was arranged to Charles'ssatisfaction；and off we went to Lancaster Gate, with a profound expectation that the German professor would do nothing worth seeing.

He was a remarkable-looking man, once tall, I should say, from his long, thin build, but now bowed and bent with long devotion to study and leaning over a crucible. His hair, prematurely white, hung down upon his forehead, but his eye was keen and his mouth sagacious.He shook hands cordially with the men of science, whom he seemed to know of old, whilst he bowed somewhat distantly to the South African interest.Then he began to talk, in very German-English, helping out the sense now and again, where his vocabulary failed him, by waving his rather dirty and chemical-stained hands demonstratively about him.His nails were a sight, but his fngers, I must say, had the delicate shape of a man's accustomed to minute manipulation.He plunged at once into the thick of the matter, telling us briefy in his equally thick accent that he“now brobosed by his new brocess to make for us some goot and sadisfactory tiamonds.”

He brought out his apparatus, and explained—or, as he said，“eggsblained”—his novel method.“Tiamonds，”he said，“were nozzing but pure crystalline carbon.”He knew how to crystallise it—“zat was all ze secret.”The men of science examined the pots and pans carefully. Then he put in a certain number of raw materials, and went to work with ostentatious openness.There were three distinct processes, and he made two stones by each simultaneously.The remarkable part of his methods, he said, was their rapidity and their cheapness.In three-quarters of an hour（and he smiled sardonically）he could produce a diamond worth at current prices two hundred pounds sterling.“As you shall now see me berform，”he remarked，“viz zis simple abbaradus.”

The materials fizzed and fumed. The Professor stirred them.An unpleasant smell like burnt feathers pervaded the room.The scientifc mencraned their necks in their eagerness, and looked over one another；Vane-Vivian, in particular, was all attention.After three-quarters of an hour, the Professor, still smiling, began to empty the apparatus.He removed a large quantity of dust or powder, which he succinctly described as“by-broducts，”and then took between fnger and thumb from the midst of each pan a small white pebble, not water-worn apparently, but slightly rough and wart-like on the surface.

From one pair of the pannikins he produced two such stones, and held them up before us triumphantly.“Zese，”he said，“are genuine tiamonds, manufactured at a gost of fourteen shillings and siggspence abiece！”Then he tried the second pair.“Zese，”he said, still more gleefully，“are broduced at a gost of eleffen and ninebence！”Finally, he came to the third pair, which he positively brandished before our astonished eyes.“And zese，”he cried, transported，“haff gost me no more zan tree and eightbence！”

They were handed round for inspection. Rough and uncut as they stood, it was, of course, impossible to judge of their value.But one thing was certain.The men of science had been watching close at the frst, and were sure Herr Schleiermacher had not put the stones in；they were keen at the withdrawal, and were equally sure he had taken them honestly out of the pannikins.

“I vill now disdribute zem，”the Professor remarked in a casual tone, as if diamonds were peas, looking round at the company. And he singled out my brother-in-law.“One to Sir Charles！”he said, handing it；“one to Mr.Mosenheimer；one to Mr.Phibson—as representing the tiamond interest.Zen, one each to Sir Atolphus, to Dr.Gray, to Mr.Fane-Fiffan, as representing science.You will haff zem cut and rebort upon zem in due gourse.We meet again at zis blace ze day afder do-morrow.”

Charles gazed at him reproachfully. The profoundest chords of his moral nature were stirred.“Professor，”he said, in a voice of solemn warning，“are you aware that, if you have succeeded, you have destroyed the value of thousands of pounds'worth of precious property?”

The Professor shrugged his shoulders.“Fot is dat to me?”he inquired, with a curious glance of contempt.“I am not a fnancier！I am a man of science. I seek to know；I do not seek to make a fortune.”

“Shocking！”Charles exclaimed.“Shocking！I never before in my life beheld so strange an instance of complete insensibility to the claims of others！”

We separated early. The men of science were coarsely jubilant.The diamond interest exhibited a corresponding depression.If this news were true, they foresaw a slump.Every eye grew dim.It was a terrible business.

Charles walked homeward with the Professor. He sounded him gently as to the sum required, should need arise, to purchase his secrecy.Already Sir Adolphus had bound us all down to temporary silence—as if that were necessary；but Charles wished to know how much Schleiermacher would take to suppress his discovery.The German was immovable.

“No, no！”he replied, with positive petulance.“You do not unterstant. I do not buy and sell.Zis is a chemical fact.We must bublish it for the sake off its seoretical falue.I do not care for wealse.I haff no time to waste in making money.”

“What an awful picture of a misspent life！”Charles observed to me afterwards.

And, indeed, the man seemed to care for nothing on earth but the abstract question—not whether he could make good diamonds or not, but whether he could or could not produce a crystalline form of pure carbon！On the appointed night Charles went back to Lancaster Gate, as I could not fail to remark, with a strange air of complete and painful preoccupation. Never before in his life had I seen him so anxious.

The diamonds were produced, with one surface of each slightly scored by the cutters, so as to show the water. Then a curious result disclosed itself.Strange to say, each of the three diamonds given to the three diamond kings turned out to be a most inferior and valueless stone；while each of the three intrusted to the care of the scientifc investigators turned out to be a fne gem of the purest quality.

I confess it was a sufficiently suspicious conjunction. The three representatives of the diamond interest gazed at each other with inquiring side-glances.Then their eyes fell suddenly：they avoided one another.Had each independently substituted a weak and inferior natural stone for Professor Schleiermacher's manufactured pebbles?It almost seemed so.For a moment, I admit, I was half inclined to suppose it.But next second I changed my mind.Could a man of Sir Charles Vandrift's integrity and high principle stoop for lucre's sake to so mean an expedient?—not to mention the fact that, even if he did, and if Mosenheimer did likewise, the stones submitted to the scientifc men would have amply suffced to establish the reality and success of the experiments！

Still, I must say, Charles looked guiltily across at Mosenheimer, and Mosenheimer at Phipson, while three more uncomfortable or unhappy-faced men could hardly have been found at that precise minute in the City of Westminster.

Then Sir Adolphus spoke—or, rather, he orated. He said, in his loud and grating voice, we had that evening, and on a previous evening, been present at the conception and birth of an Epoch in the History of Science.Professor Schleiermacher was one of those men of whom his nativeSaxony might well be proud；while as a Briton he must say he regretted somewhat that this discovery, like so many others, should have been“Made in Germany.”However, Professor Schleiermacher was a specimen of that noble type of scientifc men to whom gold was merely the rare metal Au, and diamonds merely the element C in the scarcest of its manifold allotropic embodiments.The Professor did not seek to make money out of his discovery.He rose above the sordid greed of capitalists.Content with the glory of having traced the element C to its crystalline origin, he asked no more than the approval of science.However, out of deference to the wishes of those fnancial gentlemen who were oddly concerned in maintaining the present price of C in its crystalline form—in other words, the diamond interest—they had arranged that the secret should be strictly guarded and kept for the present；not one of the few persons admitted to the experiments would publicly divulge the truth about them.This secrecy would be maintained till he himself, and a small committee of the Royal Society, should have time to investigate and verify for themselves the Professor's beautiful and ingenious processes—an investigation and verification which the learned Professor himself both desired and suggested.（Schleiermacher nodded approval.）When that was done, if the process stood the test, further concealment would be absolutely futile.The price of diamonds must fall at once below that of paste, and any protest on the part of the fnancial world would, of course, be useless.The laws of Nature were superior to millionaires.Meanwhile, in deference to the opinion of Sir Charles Vandrift, whose acquaintance with that fascinating side of the subject nobody could deny, they had consented to send no notices to the Press, and to abstain from saying anything about this beautiful and simple process in public.He dwelt with horrid gusto on that epithet“beautiful.”And now, in the name of British mineralogy, he mustcongratulate Professor Schleiermacher, our distinguished guest, on his truly brilliant and crystalline contribution to our knowledge of brilliants and of crystalline science.

Everybody applauded. It was an awkward moment.Sir Charles bit his lip.Mosenheimer looked glum.Young Phipson dropped an expression which I will not transcribe.（I understand this work may circulate among families.）And after a solemn promise of death-like secrecy, the meeting separated.

I noticed that my brother-in-law somewhat ostentatiously avoided Mosenheimer at the door；and that Phipson jumped quickly into his own carriage.“Home！”Charles cried gloomily to the coachman as we took our seats in the brougham. And all the way to Mayfair he leaned back in his seat, with close-set lips, never uttering a syllable.

Before he retired to rest, however, in the privacy of the billiard-room, I ventured to ask him：“Charles, will you unload Golcondas to-morrow?”Which, I need hardly explain, is the slang of the Stock Exchange for getting rid of undesirable securities. It struck me as probable that, in the event of the invention turning out a reality, Cloetedorp A's might become unsaleable within the next few weeks or so.

He eyed me sternly.“Wentworth，”he said，“you're a fool！”（Except on occasions when he is very angry, my respected connection never calls me“Wentworth”；the familiar abbreviation，“Sey”—derived from Seymour—is his usual mode of address to me in private.）“Is it likely I would unload, and wreck the confdence of the public in the Cloetedorp Company at such a moment?As a director—as Chairman—would it be just or right of me?I ask you, sir, could I reconcile it to my conscience?”

“Charles，”I answered，“you are right. Your conduct is noble.You will not save your own personal interests at the expense of those who haveput their trust in you.Such probity is, alas！very rare in fnance！”And I sighed involuntarily；for I had lost in Liberators.

At the same time I thought to myself，“I am not a director. No trust is reposed in me.I have to think frst of dear Isabel and the baby.Before the crash comes I will sell out to-morrow the few shares I hold, through Charles's kindness, in the Cloetedorp Golcondas.”

With his marvellous business instinct, Charles seemed to divine my thought, for he turned round to me sharply.“Look here, Sey，”he remarked, in an acidulous tone，“recollect, you're my brother-in-law. You are also my secretary.The eyes of London will be upon us to-morrow.If you were to sell out, and operators got to know of it, they'd suspect there was something up, and the company would suffer for it.Of course, you can do what you like with your own property.I can't interfere with that.I do not dictate to you.But as Chairman of the Golcondas, I am bound to see that the interests of widows and orphans whose All is invested with me should not suffer at this crisis.”His voice seemed to falter.“Therefore, though I don't like to threaten，”he went on，“I am bound to give you warning：if you sell out those shares of yours, openly or secretly, you are no longer my secretary；you receive forthwith six months'salary in lieu of notice, and—you leave me instantly.”

“Very well, Charles，”I answered, in a submissive voice；though I debated with myself for a moment whether it would be best to stick to the ready money and quit the sinking ship, or to hold fast by my friend, and back Charles's luck against the Professor's science. After a short, sharp struggle within my own mind, I am proud to say, friendship and gratitude won.I felt sure that, whether diamonds went up or down, Charles Vandrift was the sort of man who would come to the top in the end in spite of everything.And I decided to stand by him！

I slept little that night, however. My mind was a whirlwind.At breakfast Charles also looked haggard and moody.He ordered the carriage early, and drove straight into the City.

There was a block in Cheapside. Charles, impatient and nervous, jumped out and walked.I walked beside him.Near Wood Street a man we knew casually stopped us.

“I think I ought to mention to you，”he said, confidentially，“that I have it on the very best authority that Schleiermacher, of Jena—”

“Thank you，”Charles said, crustily，“I know that tale, and—there's not a word of truth in it.”

He brushed on in haste. A yard or two farther a broker paused in front of us.

“Halloa, Sir Charles！”he called out, in a bantering tone.“What's all this about diamonds?Where are Cloetedorps to-day?Is it Golconda, or Queer Street?”

Charles drew himself up very stiff.“I fail to understand you，”he answered, with dignity.

“Why, you were there yourself，”the man cried.“Last night at Sir Adolphus's！Oh yes, it's all over the place；Schleiermacher of Jena has succeeded in making the most perfect diamonds—for sixpence apiece—as good as real—and South Africa's ancient history. In less than six weeks Kimberley, they say, will be a howling desert.Every costermonger in Whitechapel will wear genuine Koh-i-noors for buttons on his coat；every girl in Bermondsey will sport a rivière like Lady Vandrift’s to her favourite music-hall.There’s a slump in Golcondas.Sly, sly, I can see；but we know all about it！”

Charles moved on, disgusted. The man's manners were atrocious.Near the Bank we ran up against a most respectable jobber.

“Ah, Sir Charles，”he said；“you here?Well, this is strange news, isn't it?For my part, I advise you not to take it too seriously. Your stock will go down, of course, like lead this morning.But it'll rise to-morrow, mark my words, and fluctuate every hour till the discovery's proved or disproved for certain.There's a fne time coming for operators, I feel sure.Reports this way and that.Rumours, rumours, rumours.And nobody will know which way to believe till Sir Adolphus has tested it.”

We moved on towards the House. Black care was seated on Sir Charles's shoulders.As we drew nearer and nearer, everybody was discussing the one fact of the moment.The seal of secrecy had proved more potent than publication on the housetops.Some people told us of the exciting news in confdential whispers；some proclaimed it aloud in vulgar exultation.The general opinion was that Cloetedorps were doomed, and that the sooner a man cleared out the less was he likely to lose by it.

Charles strode on like a general；but it was a Napoleon brazening out his retreat from Moscow. His mien was resolute.He disappeared at last into the precincts of an offce, waving me back, not to follow.After a long consultation he came out and rejoined me.

All day long the City rang with Golcondas, Golcondas. Everybody murmured，“Slump, slump in Golcondas.”The brokers had more business to do than they could manage；though, to be sure, almost every one was a seller and no one a buyer.But Charles stood frm as a rock, and so did his brokers.“I don't want to sell，”he said, doggedly.“The whole thing is trumped up.It's a mere piece of jugglery.For my own part, I believe Professor Schleiermacher is deceived, or else is deceiving us.In another week the bubble will have burst, and prices will restore themselves.”His brokers, Finglemores, had only one answer to all inquiries：“Sir Charles has every confidence in the stability of Golcondas, and doesn't wish tosell or to increase the panic.”

All the world said he was splendid, splendid！There he stationed himself on'Change like some granite stack against which the waves roll and break themselves in vain. He took no notice of the slump, but ostentatiously bought up a few shares here and there so as to restore public confdence.

“I would buy more，”he said, freely，“and make my fortune；only, as I was one of those who happened to spend last night at Sir Adolphus's, people might think I had helped to spread the rumour and produce the slump, in order to buy in at panic rates for my own advantage. A chairman, like Cæsar’s wife, should be above suspicion.So I shall only buy up just enough, now and again, to let people see I, at least, have no doubt as to the frm future of Cloetedorps.”

He went home that night, more harassed and ill than I have ever seen him. Next day was as bad.The slump continued, with varying episodes.Now, a rumour would surge up that Sir Adolphus had declared the whole affair a sham, and prices would steady a little；now, another would break out that the diamonds were actually being put upon the market in Berlin by the cart-load, and timid old ladies would wire down to their brokers to realise off-hand at whatever hazard.It was an awful day.I shall never forget it.

The morning after, as if by miracle, things righted themselves of a sudden. While we were wondering what it meant, Charles received a telegram from Sir Adolphus Cordery：—

“The man is a fraud. Not Schleiermacher at all.Just had a wire from Jena saying the Professor knows nothing about him.Sorry unintentionally to have caused you trouble.Come round and see me.”

“Sorry unintentionally to have caused you trouble.”Charles wasbeside himself with anger. Sir Adolphus had upset the share-market for forty-eight mortal hours, half-ruined a round dozen of wealthy operators, convulsed the City, upheaved the House, and now—he apologised for it as one might apologise for being late ten minutes for dinner！Charles jumped into a hansom and rushed round to see him.How had he dared to introduce the impostor to solid men as Professor Schleiermacher?Sir Adolphus shrugged his shoulders.The fellow had come and introduced himself as the great Jena chemist；he had long white hair, and a stoop in the shoulders.What reason had he for doubting his word?（I reflected to myself that on much the same grounds Charles in turn had accepted the Honourable David Granton and Graf von Lebenstein.）Besides, what object could the creature have for this extraordinary deception?Charles knew only too well.It was clear it was done to disturb the diamond market, and we realised, too late, that the man who had done it was—Colonel Clay, in“another of his manifold allotropic embodiments！”Charles had had his wish, and had met his enemy once more in London！

We could see the whole plot. Colonel Clay was polymorphic, like the element carbon！Doubtless, with his extraordinary sleight of hand, he had substituted real diamonds for the shapeless mass that came out of the apparatus, in the interval between handing the pebbles round for inspection, and distributing them piecemeal to the men of science and representatives of the diamond interest.We all watched him closely, of course, when he opened the crucibles；but when once we had satisfed ourselves that something came out, our doubts were set at rest, and we forgot to watch whether he distributed those somethings or not to the recipients.Conjurers always depend upon such momentary distractions or lapses of attention.As usual, too, the Professor had disappeared into space the moment his trick was once well performed.He vanished likesmoke, as the Count and Seer had vanished before, and was never again heard of.

Charles went home more angry than I have ever beheld him. I couldn't imagine why.He seemed as deeply hipped as if he had lost his thousands.I endeavoured to console him.“After all，”I said，“though Golcondas have suffered a temporary loss, it's a comfort to think that you should have stood so frm, and not only stemmed the tide, but also prevented yourself from losing anything at all of your own through panic.I'm sorry, of course, for the widows and orphans；but if Colonel Clay has rigged the market, at least it isn't you who lose by it this time.”

Charles withered me with a fierce scowl of undisguised contempt.“Wentworth，”he said once more，“you are a fool！”Then he relapsed into silence.

“But you declined to sell out，”I said.

He gazed at me fxedly.“Is it likely，”he asked at last，“I would tell you if I meant to sell out?or that I'd sell out openly through Finglemore, my usual broker?Why, all the world would have known, and Golcondas would have been fnished. As it is, I don't desire to tell an ass like you exactly how much I've lost.But I did sell out, and some unknown operator bought in at once, and closed for ready money, and has sold again this morning；and after all that has happened, it will be impossible to track him.He didn't wait for the account：he settled up instantly.And he sold in like manner.I know now what has been done, and how cleverly it has all been disguised and covered；but the most I'm going to tell you to-day is just this—it’s by far the biggest haul Colonel Clay has made out of me.He could retire on it if he liked.My one hope is, it may satisfy him for life；but, then, no man has ever had enough of making money.”

“You sold out！”I exclaimed.“You, the Chairman of the company！You deserted the ship！And how about your trust?How about the widows and orphans confded to you?”

Charles rose and faced me.“Seymour Wentworth，”he said, in his most solemn voice，“you have lived with me for years and had every advantage. You have seen high fnance.Yet you ask me that question！It's my belief you will never, never understand business！”

Chapter VII The Episode of theArrest of the Colonel

How much precisely Charles dropped over the slump in Cloetedorps I never quite knew. But the incident left him dejected, limp, and dispirited.

“Hang it all, Sey，”he said to me in the smoking-room, a few evenings later.“This Colonel Clay is enough to vex the patience of Job—and Job had large losses, too, if I recollect aright, from the Chaldeans and other big operators of the period.”

“Three thousand camels，”I murmured, recalling my dear mother's lessons；“all at one fell swoop；not to mention fve hundred yoke of oxen, carried off by the Sabeans, then a leading firm of speculative cattle-dealers！”

“Ah, well，”Charles meditated aloud, shaking the ash from his cheroot into a Japanese tray—fne antique bronze-work.“There were big transactions in live-stock even then！Still, Job or no Job, the man is too much for me.”

“The diffculty is，”I assented，“you never know where to have him.”

“Yes，”Charles mused；“if he were always the same, like Horniman's tea or a good brand of whisky, it would be easier, of course；you'd stand some chance of spotting him. But when a man turns up smiling every time in a different disguise, which fts him like a skin, and always apparently with the best credentials, why, hang it all, Sey, there's no wrestling with&nbsp；him anyhow.”

“Who could have come to us, for example, better vouched，”I acquiesced，“than the Honourable David?”

“Exactly so，”Charles murmured.“I invited him myself, for my own advantage. And he arrived with all the prestige of the Glen-Ellachie connection.”

“Or the Professor?”I went on.“Introduced to us by the leading mineralogist of England.”

I had touched a sore point. Charles winced and remained silent.

“Then, women again，”he resumed, after a painful pause.“I must meet in society many charming women. I can't everywhere and always be on my guard against every dear soul of them.Yet the moment I relax my attention for one day—or even when I don't relax it—I am bamboozled and led a dance by that arch Mme.Picardet, or that transparently simple little minx, Mrs.Granton.She's the cleverest girl I ever met in my life, that hussy, whatever we're to call her.She's a different person each time；and each time, hang it all, I lose my heart afresh to that different person.”

I glanced round to make sure Amelia was well out of earshot.

“No, Sey，”my respected connection went on, after another long pause, sipping his coffee pensively，“I feel I must be aided in this superhuman task by a professional unraveller of cunning disguises. I shall go to Marvillier's to-morrow—fortunate man, Marvillier—and ask him to supply me with a really good'tec, who will stop in the house and keep an eye upon every living soul that comes near me.He shall scan each nose, each eye, each wig, each whisker.He shall be my watchful half, my unsleeping self；it shall be his business to suspect all living men, all breathing women.The Archbishop of Canterbury shall not escape for a moment his watchful regard；he will take care that royal princesses don'tcollar the spoons or walk off with the jewel-cases.He must see possible Colonel Clays in the guard of every train and the parson of every parish；he must detect the off-chance of a Mme.Picardet in every young girl that takes tea with Amelia, every fat old lady that comes to call upon Isabel.Yes, I have made my mind up.I shall go to-morrow and secure such a man at once at Marvillier's.”

“If you please, Sir Charles，”Césarine interposed, pushing her head through the portière，“her ladyship says, will you and Mr.Wentworth remember that she goes out with you both this evening to Lady Carisbrooke’s?”

“Bless my soul，”Charles cried，“so she does！And it's now past ten！The carriage will be at the door for us in another fve minutes！”

Next morning, accordingly, Charles drove round to Marvillier's. The famous detective listened to his story with glistening eyes；then he rubbed his hands and purred.“Colonel Clay！”he said；“Colonel Clay！That's a very tough customer！The police of Europe are on the look-out for Colonel Clay.He is wanted in London, in Paris, in Berlin.It is le Colonel Caoutchouc here, le Colonel Caoutchouc there；till one begins to ask, at last, is there any Colonel Caoutchouc, or is it a convenient class name invented by the Force to cover a gang of undiscovered sharpers?However, Sir Charles, we will do our best.I will set on the track without delay the best and cleverest detective in England.”

“The very man I want，”Charles said.“What name, Marvillier?”

The principal smiled.“Whatever name you like，”he said.“He isn't particular. Medhurst he's called at home.We call him Joe.I'll send him round to your house this afternoon for certain.”

“Oh no，”Charles said promptly，“you won't；or Colonel Clay himself will come instead of him. I've been sold too often.No casual strangers！I'llwait here and see him.”

“But he isn't in，”Marvillier objected.

Charles was frm as a rock.“Then send and fetch him.”

In half an hour, sure enough, the detective arrived. He was an odd-looking small man, with hair cut short and standing straight up all over his head, like a Parisian waiter.He had quick, sharp eyes, very much like a ferret's；his nose was depressed, his lips thin and bloodless.A scar marked his left cheek—made by a sword-cut, he said, when engaged one day in arresting a desperate French smuggler, disguised as an offcer of Chasseurs d'Afrique.His mien was resolute.Altogether, a quainter or‘cuter little man it has never yet been my lot to set eyes on.He walked in with a brisk step, eyed Charles up and down, and then, without much formality, asked for what he was wanted.

“This is Sir Charles Vandrift, the great diamond king，”Marvillier said, introducing us.

“So I see，”the man answered.

“Then you know me?”Charles asked.

“I wouldn't be worth much，”the detective replied，“if I didn't know everybody. And you're easy enough to know；why, every boy in the street knows you.”

“Plain spoken！”Charles remarked.

“As you like it, sir，”the man answered in a respectful tone.“I endeavour to suit my dress and behaviour on every occasion to the taste of my employers.”

“Your name?”Charles asked, smiling.

“Joseph Medhurst, at your service. What sort of work?Stolen diamonds?Illicit diamond-buying?”

“No，”Charles answered, fxing him with his eye.“Quite another kindof job. You've heard of Colonel Clay?”

Medhurst nodded.“Why, certainly，”he said；and, for the frst time, I detected a lingering trace of American accent.“It's my business to know about him.”

“Well, I want you to catch him，”Charles went on.

Medhurst drew a long breath.“Isn't that rather a large order?”he murmured, surprised.

Charles explained to him exactly the sort of services he required. Medhurst promised to comply.“If the man comes near you, I'll spot him，”he said, after a moment's pause.“I can promise you that much.I'll pierce any disguise.I should know in a minute whether he's got up or not.I'm death on wigs, false moustaches, artificial complexions.I’ll engage to bring the rogue to book if I see him.You may set your mind at rest, that, while I’m about you, Colonel Clay can do nothing without my instantly spotting him.”

“He'll do it，”Marvillier put in.“He'll do it, if he says it. He's my very best hand.Never knew any man like him for unravelling and unmasking the cleverest disguises.”

“Then he'll suit me，”Charles answered，“for I never knew any man like Colonel Clay for assuming and maintaining them.”

It was arranged accordingly that Medhurst should take up his residence in the house for the present, and should be described to the servants as assistant secretary. He came that very day, with a marvellously small portmanteau.But from the moment he arrived, we noticed that Césarine took a violent dislike to him.

Medhurst was a most effcient detective. Charles and I told him all we knew about the various shapes in which Colonel Clay had“materialised，”and he gave us in turn many valuable criticisms and suggestions.Why, when we began to suspect the Honourable David Granton, had we not, as if by accident, tried to knock his red wig off?Why, when the Reverend Richard Peploe Brabazon first discussed the question of the paste diamonds, had we not looked to see if any of Amelia's unique gems were missing?Why, when Professor Schleiermacher made his bow to assembled science at Lancaster Gate, had we not strictly inquired how far he was personally known beforehand to Sir Adolphus Cordery and the other mineralogists?He supplied us also with several good hints about false hair and make-up；such as that Schleiermacher was probably much shorter than he looked, but by imitating a stoop with padding at his back he had produced the illusion of a tall bent man, though in reality no bigger than the little curate or the Graf von Lebenstein.High heels did the rest；while the scientifc keenness we noted in his face was doubtless brought about by a trife of wax at the end of the nose, giving a peculiar tilt that is extremely effective.In short, I must frankly admit, Medhurst made us feel ashamed of ourselves.Sharp as Charles is, we realised at once he was nowhere in observation beside the trained and experienced senses of this professional detective.

The worst of it all was, while Medhurst was with us, by some curious fatality, Colonel Clay stopped away from us. Now and again, to be sure, we ran up against somebody whom Medhurst suspected；but after a short investigation（conducted, I may say, with admirable cleverness），the spy always showed us the doubtful person was really some innocent and well-known character, whose antecedents and surroundings he elucidated most wonderfully.He was a perfect marvel, too, in his faculty of suspicion.He suspected everybody.If an old friend dropped in to talk business with Charles, we found out afterwards that Medhurst had lain concealed all the time behind the curtain, and had taken short-hand notes of the wholeconversation, as well as snap-shot photographs of the supposed sharper, by means of a kodak.If a fat old lady came to call upon Amelia, Medhurst was sure to be lurking under the ottoman in the drawing-room, and carefully observing, with all his eyes, whether or not she was really Mme.Picardet, padded.When Lady Tresco brought her four plain daughters to an“At Home”one night, Medhurst, in evening dress, disguised as a waiter, followed them each round the room with obtrusive ices, to satisfy himself just how much of their complexion was real, and how much was patent rouge and Bloom of Ninon.He doubted whether Simpson, Sir Charles's valet, was not Colonel Clay in plain clothes；and he had half an idea that Césarine herself was our saucy White Heather in an alternative avatar.We pointed out to him in vain that Simpson had often been present in the very same room with David Granton, and that Césarine had dressed Mrs.Brabazon’s hair at Lucerne：this partially satisfed him, but only partially.He remarked that Simpson might double both parts with somebody else unknown；and that as for Césarine, she might well have a twin sister who took her place when she was Mme.Picardet.

Still, in spite of all his care—or because of all his care—Colonel Clay stopped away for whole weeks together. An explanation occurred to us.Was it possible he knew we were guarded and watched?Was he afraid of measuring swords with this trained detective?

If so, how had he found it out?I had an inkling, myself—but, under all the circumstances, I did not mention it to Charles. It was clear that Césarine intensely disliked this new addition to the Vandrift household.She would not stop in the room where the detective was, or show him common politeness.She spoke of him always as“that odious man, Medhurst.”Could she have guessed, what none of the other servants knew, that the man was a spy in search of the Colonel?I was inclinedto believe it.And then it dawned upon me that Césarine had known all about the diamonds and their story；that it was Césarine who took us to see Schloss Lebenstein；that it was Césarine who posted the letter to Lord Craig-Ellachie！If Césarine was in league with Colonel Clay, as I was half inclined to surmise, what more natural than her obvious dislike to the detective who was there to catch her principal?What more simple for her than to warn her fellow-conspirator of the danger that awaited him if he approached this man Medhurst?

However, I was too much frightened by the episode of the cheque to say anything of my nascent suspicions to Charles. I waited rather to see how events would shape themselves.

After a while Medhurst's vigilance grew positively annoying. More than once he came to Charles with reports and shorthand notes distinctly distasteful to my excellent brother-in-law.“The fellow is getting to know too much about us，”Charles said to me one day.“Why, Sey, he spies out everything.Would you believe it, when I had that confdential interview with Brookfeld the other day, about the new issue of Golcondas, the man was under the easy-chair, though I searched the room beforehand to make sure he wasn't there；and he came to me afterwards with full notes of the conversation, to assure me he thought Brookfield—whom I've known for ten years—was too tall by half an inch to be one of Colonel Clay's impersonations.”

“Oh, but, Sir Charles，”Medhurst cried, emerging suddenly from the bookcase，“you must never look upon any one as above suspicion merely because you've known him for ten years or thereabouts. Colonel Clay may have approached you at various times under many disguises.He may have built up this thing gradually.Besides, as to my knowing too much, why, of course, a detective always learns many things about hisemployer's family which he is not supposed to know；but professional honour and professional etiquette, as with doctors and lawyers, compel him to lock them up as absolute secrets in his own bosom.You need never be afraid I will divulge one jot of them.If I did, my occupation would be gone, and my reputation shattered.”

Charles looked at him, appalled.“Do you dare to say，”he burst out，“you've been listening to my talk with my brother-in-law and secretary?”

“Why, of course，”Medhurst answered.“It's my business to listen, and to suspect everybody. If you push me to say so, how do I know Colonel Clay is not—Mr.Wentworth?”

Charles withered him with a look.“In future, Medhurst，”he said，“you must never conceal yourself in a room where I am without my leave and knowledge.”

Medhurst bowed politely.“Oh, as you will, Sir Charles，”he answered；“that's quite at your own wish. Though how can I act as an effcient detective, any way, if you insist upon tying my hands like that, beforehand?”

Again I detected a faint American favour.

After that rebuff, however, Medhurst seemed put upon his mettle. He redoubled his vigilance in every direction.“It's not my fault，”he said plaintively, one day，“if my reputation's so good that, while I'm near you, this rogue won't approach you.If I can't catch him, at least I keep him away from coming near you！”

A few days later, however, he brought Charles some photographs. These he produced with evident pride.The first he showed us was a vignette of a little parson.“Who's that, then?”he inquired, much pleased.

We gazed at it, open-eyed. One word rose to our lips simultaneously：“Brabazon！”

“And how's this for high?”he asked again, producing another—the photograph of a gay young dog in a Tyrolese costume.

We murmured，“Von Lebenstein！”

“And this?”he continued, showing us the portrait of a lady with a most fetching squint.

We answered with one voice，“Little Mrs. Granton！”

Medhurst was naturally proud of this excellent exploit. He replaced them in his pocket-book with an air of just triumph.

“How did you get them?”Charles asked.

Medhurst's look was mysterious.“Sir Charles，”he answered, drawing himself up，“I must ask you to trust me awhile in this matter. Remember, there are people whom you decline to suspect.I have learned that it is always those very people who are most dangerous to capitalists.If I were to give you the names now, you would refuse to believe me.Therefore, I hold them over discreetly for the moment.One thing, however, I say.I know to a certainty where Colonel Clay is at this present speaking.But I will lay my plans deep, and I hope before long to secure him.You shall be present when I do so；and I shall make him confess his personality openly.More than that you cannot reasonably ask.I shall leave it to you, then, whether or not you wish to arrest him.”

Charles was considerably puzzled, not to say piqued, by this curious reticence；he begged hard for names；but Medhurst was adamant.“No, no，”he replied；“we detectives have our own just pride in our profession. If I told you now, you would probably spoil all by some premature action.You are too open and impulsive！I will mention this alone：Colonel Clay will be shortly in Paris, and before long will begin from that city a fresh attempt at defrauding you, which he is now hatching.Mark my words, and see whether or not I have been kept well informed of the fellow'smovements！”

He was perfectly correct. Two days later, as it turned out, Charles received a“confdential”letter from Paris, purporting to come from the head of a second-rate fnancial house with which he had had dealings over the Craig-Ellachie Amalgamation—by this time, I ought to have said, an accomplished union.It was a letter of small importance in itself—a mere matter of detail；but it paved the way, so Medhurst thought, to some later development of more serious character.Here once more the man's singular foresight was justifed.For, in another week, we received a second communication, containing other proposals of a delicate fnancial character, which would have involved the transference of some two thousand pounds to the head of the Parisian frm at an address given.Both these letters Medhurst cleverly compared with those written to Charles before, in the names of Colonel Clay and of Graf von Lebenstein.At frst sight, it is true, the differences between the two seemed quite enormous：the Paris hand was broad and black, large and bold；while the earlier manuscript was small, neat, thin, and gentlemanly.Still, when Medhurst pointed out to us certain persistent twists in the formation of his capitals, and certain curious peculiarities in the relative length of his t's, his l's, his b's, and his h's, we could see for ourselves he was right；both were the work of one hand, writing in the one case with a sharp-pointed nib, very small, and in the other with a quill, very large and freely.

This discovery was most important. We stood now within measurable distance of catching Colonel Clay, and bringing forgery and fraud home to him without hope of evasion.

To make all sure, however, Medhurst communicated with the Paris police, and showed us their answers. Meanwhile, Charles continued to write to the head of the frm, who had given a private address in theRue Jean Jacques, alleging, I must say, a most clever reason why the negotiations at this stage should be confidentially conducted.But one never expected from Colonel Clay anything less than consummate cleverness.In the end, it was arranged that we three were to go over to Paris together, that Medhurst was to undertake, under the guise of being Sir Charles, to pay the two thousand pounds to the pretended fnancier, and that Charles and I, waiting with the police outside the door, should, at a given signal, rush in with our forces and secure the criminal.

We went over accordingly, and spent the night at the Grand, as is Charles's custom. The Bristol, which I prefer, he finds too quiet.Early next morning we took a fiacre and drove to the Rue Jean Jacques.Medhurst had arranged everything in advance with the Paris police, three of whom, in plain clothes, were waiting at the foot of the staircase to assist us.Charles had further provided himself with two thousand pounds, in notes of the Bank of France, in order that the payment might be duly made, and no doubt arise as to the crime having been perpetrated as well as meditated—in the former case, the penalty would be fifteen years；in the latter, three only.He was in very high spirits.The fact that we had tracked the rascal to earth at last, and were within an hour of apprehending him, was in itself enough to raise his courage greatly.We found, as we expected, that the number given in the Rue Jean Jacques was that of an hotel, not a private residence.Medhurst went in frst, and inquired of the landlord whether our man was at home, at the same time informing him of the nature of our errand, and giving him to understand that if we effected the capture by his friendly aid, Sir Charles would see that the expenses incurred on the swindler's bill were met in full, as the price of his assistance.The landlord bowed；he expressed his deep regret, as M.le Colonel—so we heard him call him—was a most amiable person, much liked by the household；but justice, of course, must have its way；and, with a regretful sigh, he undertook to assist us.

The police remained below, but Charles and Medhurst were each provided with a pair of handcuffs. Remembering the Polperro case, however, we determined to use them with the greatest caution.We would only put them on in case of violent resistance.We crept up to the door where the miscreant was housed.Charles handed the notes in an open envelope to Medhurst, who seized them hastily and held them in his hands in readiness for action.We had a sign concerted.Whenever he sneezed—which he could do in the most natural manner—we were to open the door, rush in, and secure the criminal！

He was gone for some minutes. Charles and I waited outside in breathless expectation.Then Medhurst sneezed.We fung the door open at once, and burst in upon the creature.

Medhurst rose as we did so. He pointed with his finger.“This is Colonel Clay！”he said；“keep him well in charge while I go down to the door for the police to arrest him！”

A gentlemanly man, about middle height, with a grizzled beard and a well-assumed military aspect, rose at the same moment. The envelope in which Charles had placed the notes lay on the table before him.He clutched it nervously.“I am at a loss, gentlemen，”he said, in an excited voice，“to account for this interruption.”He spoke with a tremor, yet with all the politeness to which we were accustomed in the little curate and the Honourable David.

“No nonsense！”Charles exclaimed, in his authoritative way.“We know who you are. We have found you out this time.You are Colonel Clay.If you attempt to resist—take care—I will handcuff you！”

The military gentleman gave a start.“Yes, I am Colonel Clay，”heanswered.“On what charge do you arrest me?”

Charles was bursting with wrath. The fellow's coolness seemed never to desert him.“You are Colonel Clay！”he muttered.“You have the unspeakable effrontery to stand there and admit it?”

“Certainly，”the Colonel answered, growing hot in turn.“I have done nothing to be ashamed of. What do you mean by this conduct?How dare you talk of arresting me?”

Charles laid his hand on the man's shoulder.“Come, come, my friend，”he said.“That sort of bluff won't go down with us. You know very well on what charge I arrest you；and here are the police to give effect to it.”

He called out“Entrez！”The police entered the room. Charles explained as well as he could in most doubtful Parisian what they were next to do.The Colonel drew himself up in an indignant attitude.He turned and addressed them in excellent French.

“I am an offcer in the service of her Britannic Majesty，”he said.“On what ground do you venture to interfere with me, messieurs?”

The chief policeman explained. The Colonel turned to Charles.“Your name, sir?”he inquired.

“You know it very well，”Charles answered.“I am Sir Charles Vandrift；and, in spite of your clever disguise, I can instantly recognise you. I know your eyes and ears.I can see the same man who cheated me at Nice, and who insulted me on the island.”

“You Sir Charles Vandrift！”the rogue cried.“No, no, sir, you are a madman！”He looked round at the police.“Take care what you do！”he cried.“This is a raving maniac. I had business just now with Sir Charles Vandrift, who quitted the room as these gentlemen entered.This person is mad, and you, monsieur, I doubt not，”bowing to me，“you are, of course, his keeper.”

“Do not let him deceive you，”I cried to the police, beginning to fear that with his usual incredible cleverness the fellow would even now manage to slip through our fngers.“Arrest him, as you are told. We will take the responsibility.”Though I trembled when I thought of that cheque he held of mine.

The chief of our three policemen came forward and laid his hand on the culprit's shoulder.“I advise you, M. le Colonel，”he said, in an offcial voice，“to come with us quietly for the present.Before the juge d'instruction we can enter at length into all these questions.”

The Colonel, very indignant still—and acting the part marvellously—yielded and went along with them.

“Where's Medhurst?”Charles inquired, glancing round as we reached the door.“I wish he had stopped with us.”

“You are looking for monsieur your friend?”the landlord inquired, with a side bow to the Colonel.“He has gone away in a facre. He asked me to give this note to you.”

He handed us a twisted note. Charles opened and read it.“Invaluable man！”he cried.“Just hear what he says, Sey：‘Having secured Colonel Clay, I am off now again on the track of Mme.Picardet.She was lodging in the same house.She has just driven away；I know to what place；and I am after her to arrest her.In blind haste, MEDHURST.'That's smartness, if you like.Though, poor little woman, I think he might have left her.”

“Does a Mme. Picardet stop here?”I inquired of the landlord, thinking it possible she might have assumed again the same old alias.

He nodded assent.“Oui, oui, oui，”he answered.“She has just driven off, and monsieur your friend has gone posting after her.”

“Splendid man！”Charles cried.“Marvillier was quite right. He is theprince of detectives！”

We hailed a couple of facres, and drove off, in two detachments, to the juge d'instruction. There Colonel Clay continued to brazen it out, and asserted that he was an offcer in the Indian Army, home on six months'leave, and spending some weeks in Paris.He even declared he was known at the Embassy, where he had a cousin an attaché；and he asked that this gentleman should be sent for at once from our Ambassador’s to identify him.The juge d’instruction insisted that this must be done；and Charles waited in very bad humour for the foolish formality.It really seemed as if, after all, when we had actually caught and arrested our man, he was going by some cunning device to escape us.

After a delay of more than an hour, during which Colonel Clay fretted and fumed quite as much as we did, the attaché arrived.To our horror and astonishment, he proceeded to salute the prisoner most affectionately.

“Halloa, Algy！”he cried, grasping his hand；“what's up?What do these ruffans want with you?”

It began to dawn upon us, then, what Medhurst had meant by“suspecting everybody”：the real Colonel Clay was no common adventurer, but a gentleman of birth and high connections！

The Colonel glared at us.“This fellow declares he's Sir Charles Vandrift，”he said sulkily.“Though, in fact, there are two of them. And he accuses me of forgery, fraud, and theft, Bertie.”

The attaché stared hard at us.“This is Sir Charles Vandrift，”he replied, after a moment.“I remember hearing him make a speech once at a City dinner.And what charge have you to prefer, Sir Charles, against my cousin?”

“Your cousin?”Charles cried.“This is Colonel Clay, the notorioussharper！”

The attaché smiled a gentlemanly and superior smile.“This is Colonel Clay，”he answered，“of the Bengal Staff Corps.”

It began to strike us there was something wrong somewhere.

“But he has cheated me, all the same，”Charles said—“at Nice two years ago, and many times since；and this very day he has tricked me out of two thousand pounds in French bank-notes, which he has now about him！”

The Colonel was speechless. But the attaché laughed.“What he has done to-day I don’t know，”he said；“but if it’s as apocryphal as what you say he did two years ago, you’ve a thundering bad case, sir；for he was then in India, and I was out there, visiting him.”

“Where are the two thousand pounds?”Charles cried.“Why, you've got them in your hand！You're holding the envelope！”

The Colonel produced it.“This envelope，”he said，“was left with me by the man with short stiff hair, who came just before you, and who announced himself as Sir Charles Vandrift. He said he was interested in tea in Assam, and wanted me to join the board of directors of some bogus company.These are his papers, I believe，”and he handed them to his cousin.

“Well, I'm glad the notes are safe, anyhow，”Charles murmured, in a tone of relief, beginning to smell a rat.“Will you kindly return them to me?”

The attaché turned out the contents of the envelope.They proved to be prospectuses of bubble companies of the moment, of no importance.

“Medhurst must have put them there，”I cried，“and decamped with the cash.”

Charles gave a groan of horror.“And Medhurst is Colonel Clay！”heexclaimed, clapping his hand to his forehead.

“I beg your pardon, sir，”the Colonel interposed.“I have but one personality, and no aliases.”

It took quite half an hour to explain this imbroglio. But as soon as all was explained, in French and English, to the satisfaction of ourselves and the juge d'instruction, the real Colonel shook hands with us in a most forgiving way, and informed us that he had more than once wondered, when he gave his name at shops in Paris, why it was often received with such grave suspicion.We instructed the police that the true culprit was Medhurst, whom they had seen with their own eyes, and whom we urged them to pursue with all expedition.Meanwhile, Charles and I, accompanied by the Colonel and the attaché—“to see the fun out，”as they said—called at the Bank of France for the purpose of stopping the notes immediately.It was too late, however.They had been presented at once, and cashed in gold, by a pleasant little lady in an American costume, who was afterwards identifed by the hotel-keeper（from our description）as his lodger, Mme.Picardet.It was clear she had taken rooms in the same hotel, to be near the Indian Colonel；and it was she who had received and sent the letters.As for our foe, he had vanished into space, as always.

Two days later we received the usual insulting communication on a sheet of Charles's own dainty note. Last time he wrote it was on Craig-Ellachie paper：this time, like the wanton lapwing, he had got himself another crest.

“MOST PERSPICACIOUS OF MILLIONAIRES！—Said I not well, as Medhurst, that you must distrust everybody?And the one man you never dreamt of distrusting was—Medhurst.Yet see how truthful I was！I told you I knew where Colonel Clay was living—and I did

know, exactly.I promised to take you to Colonel Clay’s rooms, and to get him arrested for you—and I kept my promise.I even exceeded your expectations；for I gave you two Colonel Clays instead of one—and you took the wrong man—that is to say, the real one.This was a neat little trick；but it cost me some trouble.

“First, I found out there was a real Colonel Clay, in the Indian Army.I also found out he chanced to be coming home on leave this season.I might have made more out of him, no doubt；but I disliked annoying him, and preferred to give myself the fun of this peculiar mystification.I therefore waited for him to reach Paris, where the police arrangements suited me better than in London.While I was looking about, and delaying operations for his return, I happened to hear you wanted a detective.So I offered myself as out of work to my old employer, Marvillier, from whom I have had many good jobs in the past；and there you get, in short, the kernel of the Colonel.

“Naturally, after this, I can never go back as a detective to Marvillier’s.But, on the large scale on which I have learned to work since I first had the pleasure of making your delightful acquaintance, this matters little.To say the truth, I begin to feel detective work a cut or two below me.I am now a gentleman of means and leisure.Besides, the extra knowledge of your movements which I have acquired in your house has helped still further to give me various holds upon you.So the fluke will be true to his own pet lamb.To vary the metaphor, you are not fully shorn yet.

“Remember me most kindly to your charming family, give Wentworth my love, and tell Mlle.Césarine I owe her a grudge which I shall never forget.She clearly suspected me.You are much too rich, dear Charles；I relieve your plethora.I bleed you financially.Therefore I

consider myself—Your sincerest friend，

“CLAY-BRABAZON-MEDHURST，

“Fellow of the Royal College of Surgeons.”

Charles was threatened with apoplexy. This blow was severe.“Whom can I trust，”he asked, plaintively，“when the detectives themselves, whom I employ to guard me, turn out to be swindlers?Don't you remember that line in the Latin grammar—something about，‘Who shall watch the watchers?'I think it used to run，‘Quis custodes custodiet ipsos?'”

But I felt this episode had at least disproved my suspicions of poor Césarine.

Chapter XI The Episode of the Bertillon Method

We had a terrible passage home from New York. The Captain told us he“knew every drop of water in the Atlantic personally”；and he had never seen them so uniformly obstreperous.The ship rolled in the trough；Charles rolled in his cabin, and would not be comforted.As we approached the Irish coast, I scrambled up on deck in a violent gale, and retired again somewhat precipitately to announce to my brother-in-law that we had just come in sight of the Fastnet Rock Lighthouse.Charles merely turned over in his berth and groaned.“I don't believe it，”he answered.“I expect it is probably Colonel Clay in another of his manifold disguises！”

At Liverpool, however, the Adelphi consoled him. We dined luxuriously in the Louis Quinze restaurant, as only millionaires can dine, and proceeded next day by Pullman car to London.

We found Amelia dissolved in tears at a domestic cataclysm. It seemed that Césarine had given notice.

Charles was scarcely home again when he began to bethink him of the least among his investments. Like many other wealthy men, my respected connection is troubled more or less, in the background of his consciousness, by a pervading dread that he will die a beggar.To guard against this misfortune—which I am bound to admit nobody else fearsfor him—he invested, several years ago, a sum of two hundred thousand pounds in Consols, to serve as a nest-egg in case of the collapse of Golcondas and South Africa generally.It is part of the same amiable mania, too, that he will not allow the dividend-warrants on this sum to be sent to him by post, but insists, after the fashion of old ladies and country parsons, upon calling personally at the Bank of England four times a year to claim his interest.He is well known by sight to not a few of the clerks；and his appearance in Threadneedle Street is looked forward to with great regularity within a few weeks of each lawful quarter-day.

So, on the morning after our arrival in town, Charles observed to me, cheerfully，“Sey, I must run into the City to-day to claim my dividends. There are two quarters owing.”

I accompanied him in to the Bank. Even that mighty official, the beadle at the door, unfastened the handle of the millionaire's carriage.The clerk who received us smiled and nodded.“How much?”he asked, after the stereotyped fashion.

“Two hundred thousand，”Charles answered, looking affable.

The clerk turned up the books.“Paid！”he said, with decision.“What's your game, sir, if I may ask you?”

“Paid！”Charles echoed, drawing back.

The clerk gazed across at him.“Yes, Sir Charles，”he answered, in a somewhat severe tone.“You must remember you drew a quarter's dividend from myself—last week—at this very counter.”

Charles stared at him fixedly.“Show me the signature，”he said at last, in a slow, dazed fashion. I suspected mischief.

The clerk pushed the book across to him. Charles examined the name close.

“Colonel Clay again！”he cried, turning to me with a despondent air.“He must have dressed the part. I shall die in the workhouse, Sey！That man has stolen away even my nest-egg from me.”

I saw it at a glance.“Mrs. Quackenboss！”I put in.“Those portraits on the Etruria！It was to help him in his make-up！You recollect, she sketched your face and fgure at all possible angles.”

“And last quarter's?”Charles inquired, staggering.

The clerk turned up the entry.“Drawn on the 10th of July，”he answered, carelessly, as if it mattered nothing.

Then I knew why the Colonel had run across to England.

Charles positively reeled.“Take me home, Sey，”he cried.“I am ruined, ruined！He will leave me with not half a million in the world. My poor, poor boys will beg their bread, unheeded, through the streets of London！”

（As Amelia has landed estate settled upon her worth a hundred and ffty thousand pounds, this last contingency affected me less to tears than Charles seemed to think necessary.）

We made all needful inquiries, and put the police upon the quest at once, as always. But no redress was forthcoming.The money, once paid, could not be recovered.It is a playful little privilege of Consols that the Government declines under any circumstances to pay twice over.Charles drove back to Mayfair a crushed and broken man.I think if Colonel Clay himself could have seen him just then, he would have pitied that vast intellect in its grief and bewilderment.

After lunch, however, my brother-in-law's natural buoyancy reasserted itself by degrees. He rallied a little.“Seymour，”he said to me，“you've heard, of course, of the Bertillon system of measuring and registering criminals.”

“I have，”I answered.“And it's excellent as far as it goes. But, likeMrs.Glasse's jugged hare, it all depends upon the initial step.‘First catch your criminal.'Now, we have never caught Colonel Clay—”

“Or, rather，”Charles interposed unkindly，“when you did catch him, you didn't hold him.”

I ignored the unkindly suggestion, and continued in the same voice，“We have never secured Colonel Clay；and until we secure him, we cannot register him by the Bertillon method. Besides, even if we had once caught him and duly noted the shape of his nose, his chin, his ears, his forehead, of what use would that be against a man who turns up with a fresh face each time, and can mould his features into what form he likes, to deceive and foil us?”

“Never mind, Sey，”my brother-in-law said.“I was told in New York that Dr. Frank Beddersley, of London, was the best exponent of the Bertillon system now living in England；and to Beddersley I shall go.Or, rather, I'll invite him here to lunch to-morrow.”

“Who told you of him?”I inquired.“Not Dr. Quackenboss, I hope；nor yet Mr.Algernon Coleyard?”

Charles paused and reflected.“No, neither of them，”he answered, after a short internal deliberation.“It was that magazine editor chap we met at Wrengold's.”

“He's all right，”I said；“or, at least, I think so.”

So we wrote a polite invitation to Dr. Beddersley, who pursued the method professionally, asking him to come and lunch with us at Mayfair at two next day.

Dr. Beddersley came—a dapper little man, with pent-house eyebrows, and keen, small eyes, whom I suspected at sight of being Colonel Clay himself in another of his clever polymorphic embodiments.He was clear and concise.His manner was scientifc.He told us at oncethat though the Bertillon method was of little use till the expert had seen the criminal once, yet if we had consulted him earlier he might probably have saved us some serious disasters.“A man so ingenious as this，”he said，“would no doubt have studied Bertillon's principles himself, and would take every possible means to prevent recognition by them.Therefore, you might almost disregard the nose, the chin, the moustache, the hair, all of which are capable of such easy alteration.But there remain some features which are more likely to persist—height, shape of head, neck, build, and fingers；the timbre of the voice, the colour of the iris.Even these, again, may be partially disguised or concealed；the way the hair is dressed, the amount of padding, a high collar round the throat, a dark line about the eyelashes, may do more to alter the appearance of a face than you could readily credit.”

“So we know，”I answered.

“The voice, again，”Dr. Beddersley continued.“The voice itself may be most fallacious.The man is no doubt a clever mimic.He could, perhaps, compress or enlarge his larynx.And I judge from what you tell me that he took characters each time which compelled him largely to alter and modify his tone and accent.”

“Yes，”I said.“As the Mexican Seer, he had of course a Spanish intonation. As the little curate, he was a cultivated North-countryman.As David Granton, he spoke gentlemanly Scotch.As Von Lebenstein, naturally, he was a South-German, trying to express himself in French.As Professor Schleiermacher, he was a North-German speaking broken English.As Elihu Quackenboss, he had a fne and pronounced Kentucky favour.And as the poet, he drawled after the fashion of the clubs, with lingering remnants of a Devonshire ancestry.”

“Quite so，”Dr. Beddersley answered.“That is just what I shouldexpect.Now, the question is, do you know him to be one man, or is he really a gang?Is he a name for a syndicate?Have you any photographs of Colonel Clay himself in any of his disguises?”

“Not one，”Charles answered.“He produced some himself, when he was Medhurst the detective. But he pocketed them at once；and we never recovered them.”

“Could you get any?”the doctor asked.“Did you note the name and address of the photographer?”

“Unfortunately, no，”Charles replied.“But the police at Nice showed us two. Perhaps we might borrow them.”

“Until we get them，”Dr. Beddersley said，“I don't know that we can do anything.But if you can once give me two distinct photographs of the real man, no matter how much disguised, I could tell you whether they were taken from one person；and, if so, I think I could point out certain details in common which might aid us to go upon.”

All this was at lunch. Amelia's niece, Dolly Lingfeld, was there, as it happened；and I chanced to note a most guilty look stealing over her face all the while we were talking.Suspicious as I had learned to become by this time, however, I did not suspect Dolly of being in league with Colonel Clay；but, I confess, I wondered what her blush could indicate.After lunch, to my surprise, Dolly called me away from the rest into the library.“Uncle Seymour，”she said to me—the dear child calls me Uncle Seymour, though of course I am not in any way related to her—“I have some photographs of Colonel Clay, if you want them.”

“You?”I cried, astonished.“Why, Dolly, how did you get them?”

For a minute or two she showed some little hesitation in telling me. At last she whispered，“You won't be angry if I confess?”（Dolly is just nineteen, and remarkably pretty.）

“My child，”I said，“why should I be angry?You may confde in me implicitly.”（With a blush like that, who on earth could be angry with her?）

“And you won't tell Aunt Amelia or Aunt Isabel?”she inquired somewhat anxiously.

“Not for worlds，”I answered.（As a matter of fact, Amelia and Isabel are the last people in the world to whom I should dream of confiding anything that Dolly might tell me.）

“Well, I was stopping at Seldon, you know, when Mr. David Granton was there，”Dolly went on；“—or, rather, when that scamp pretended he was David Granton；and—and—you won't be angry with me, will you?—one day I took a snap-shot with my kodak at him and Aunt Amelia！”

“Why, what harm was there in that?”I asked, bewildered. The wildest stretch of fancy could hardly conceive that the Honourable David had been firting with Amelia.

Dolly coloured still more deeply.“Oh, you know Bertie Winslow?”she said.“Well, he's interested in photography—and—and also in me. And he's invented a process, which isn't of the slightest practical use, he says；but its peculiarity is, that it reveals textures.At least, that's what Bertie calls it.It makes things come out so.And he gave me some plates of his own for my kodak—half-a-dozen or more, and—I took Aunt Amelia with them.”

“I still fail to see，”I murmured, looking at her comically.

“Oh, Uncle Seymour，”Dolly cried.“How blind you men are！If Aunt Amelia knew she would never forgive me. Why, you must understand.The—the rouge, you know, and the pearl powder！”

“Oh, it comes out, then, in the photograph?”I inquired.

“Comes out！I should think so！It's like little black spots all overauntie's face. Such a guy as she looks in it！”

“And Colonel Clay is in them too?”

“Yes；I took them when he and auntie were talking together, without either of them noticing. And Bertie developed them.I've three of David Granton.Three beauties；most successful.”

“Any other character?”I asked, seeing business ahead.

Dolly hung back, still redder.“Well, the rest are with Aunt Isabel，”she answered, after a struggle.

“My dear child，”I replied, hiding my feelings as a husband，“I will be brave. I will bear up even against that last misfortune！”

Dolly looked up at me pleadingly.“It was here in London，”she went on；“—when I was last with auntie. Medhurst was stopping in the house at the time；and I took him twice, tête-à-tête with Aunt Isabel！”

“Isabel does not paint，”I murmured, stoutly.

Dolly hung back again.“No, but—her hair！”she suggested, in a faint voice.

“Its colour，”I admitted，“is in places assisted by a—well, you know, a restorer.”

Dolly broke into a mischievous sly smile.“Yes, it is，”she continued.“And, oh, Uncle Sey, where the restorer has—er—restored it, you know, it comes out in the photograph with a sort of brilliant iridescent metallic sheen on it！”

“Bring them down, my dear，”I said, gently patting her head with my hand. In the interests of justice, I thought it best not to frighten her.

Dolly brought them down. They seemed to me poor things, yet well worth trying.We found it possible, on further confabulation, by the simple aid of a pair of scissors, so to cut each in two that all trace of Amelia and Isabel was obliterated.Even so, however, I judged it best to call Charlesand Dr.Beddersley to a private consultation in the library with Dolly, and not to submit the mutilated photographs to public inspection by their joint subjects.Here, in fact, we had five patchy portraits of the redoubtable Colonel, taken at various angles, and in characteristic unstudied attitudes.A child had outwitted the cleverest sharper in Europe！

The moment Beddersley's eye fell upon them, a curious look came over his face.“Why, these，”he said，“are taken on Herbert Winslow's method, Miss Lingfeld.”

“Yes，”Dolly admitted timidly.“They are. He's—a friend of mine, don't you know；and—he gave me some plates that just ftted my camera.”

Beddersley gazed at them steadily. Then he turned to Charles.“And this young lady，”he said，“has quite unintentionally and unconsciously succeeded in tracking Colonel Clay to earth at last.They are genuine photographs of the man—as he is—without the disguises！”

“They look to me most blotchy，”Charles murmured.“Great black lines down the nose, and such spots on the cheek, too！”

“Exactly，”Beddersley put in.“Those are differences in texture. They show just how much of the man's face is human fesh—”

“And how much wax，”I ventured.

“Not wax，”the expert answered, gazing close.“This is some harder mixture. I should guess, a composition of gutta-percha and india-rubber, which takes colour well, and hardens when applied, so as to lie quite evenly, and resist heat or melting.Look here；that's an artificial scar, flling up a real hollow；and this is an added bit to the tip of the nose；and those are shadows, due to inserted cheek-pieces, within the mouth, to make the man look fatter！”

“Why, of course，”Charles cried.“India-rubber it must be. That's why in France they call him le Colonel Caoutchouc！”

“Can you reconstruct the real face from them?”I inquired anxiously.

Dr. Beddersley gazed hard at them.“Give me an hour or two，”he said—“and a box of water-colours.I think by that time—putting two and two together—I can eliminate the false and build up for you a tolerably correct idea of what the actual man himself looks like.”

We turned him into the library for a couple of hours, with the materials he needed；and by tea-time he had completed his first rough sketch of the elements common to the two faces. He brought it out to us in the drawing-room.I glanced at it frst.It was a curious countenance, slightly wanting in definiteness, and not unlike those“composite photographs”which Mr.Galton produces by exposing two negatives on the same sensitised paper for ten seconds or so consecutively.Yet it struck me at once as containing something of Colonel Clay in every one of his many representations.The little curate, in real life, did not recall the Seer；nor did Elihu Quackenboss suggest Count von Lebenstein or Professor Schleiermacher.Yet in this compound face, produced only from photographs of David Granton and Medhurst, I could distinctly trace a certain underlying likeness to every one of the forms which the impostor had assumed for us.In other words, though he could make up so as to mask the likeness to his other characters, he could not make up so as to mask the likeness to his own personality.He could not wholly get rid of his native build and his genuine features.

Besides these striking suggestions of the Seer and the curate, however, I felt vaguely conscious of having seen and observed the man himself whom the water-colour represented, at some time, somewhere. It was not at Nice；it was not at Seldon；it was not at Meran；it was not in America.I believed I had been in a room with him somewhere in London.

Charles was looking over my shoulder. He gave a sudden littlestart.“Why, I know that fellow！”he cried.“You recollect him, Sey；he's Finglemore's brother—the chap that didn't go out to China！”

Then I remembered at once where it was that I had seen him—at the broker's in the city, before we sailed for America.

“What Christian name?”I asked.

Charles refected a moment.“The same as the one in the note we got with the dust-coat，”he answered, at last.“The man is Paul Finglemore！”

“You will arrest him?”I asked.

“Can I, on this evidence?”

“We might bring it home to him.”

Charles mused for a moment.“We shall have nothing against him，”he said slowly，“except in so far as we can swear to his identity. And that may be diffcult.”

Just at that moment the footman brought in tea. Charles wondered apparently whether the man, who had been with us at Seldon when Colonel Clay was David Granton, would recollect the face or recognise having seen it.“Look here, Dudley，”he said, holding up the water-colour，“do you know that person?”

Dudley gazed at it a moment.“Certainly, sir，”he answered briskly.

“Who is it?”Amelia asked. We expected him to answer，“Count von Lebenstein，”or“Mr.Granton，”or“Medhurst.”

Instead of that, he replied, to our utter surprise，“That's Césarine’s young man, my lady.”

“Césarine’s young man?”Amelia repeated, taken aback.“Oh, Dudley, surely, you must be mistaken！”

“No, my lady，”Dudley replied, in a tone of conviction.“He comes to see her quite reg'lar；he have come to see her, off and on, from time to time, ever since I've been in Sir Charles's service.”

“When will he be coming again?”Charles asked, breathless.

“He's downstairs now, sir，”Dudley answered, unaware of the bombshell he was finging into the midst of a respectable family.

Charles rose excitedly, and put his back against the door.“Secure that man，”he said to me sharply, pointing with his fnger.

“What man?”I asked, amazed.“Colonel Clay?The young man who's downstairs now with Césarine?”

“No，”Charles answered, with decision；“Dudley！”

I laid my hand on the footman's shoulder, not understanding what Charles meant. Dudley, terrifed, drew back, and would have rushed from the room；but Charles, with his back against the door, prevented him.

“I—I've done nothing to be arrested, Sir Charles，”Dudley cried, in abject terror, looking appealingly at Amelia.“It—it wasn't me as cheated you.”And he certainly didn't look it.

“I daresay not，”Charles answered.“But you don't leave this room till Colonel Clay is in custody. No, Amelia, no；it's no use your speaking to me.What he says is true.I see it all now.This villain and Césarine have long been accomplices！The man’s downstairs with her now.If we let Dudley quit the room he’ll go down and tell them；and before we know where we are, that slippery eel will have wriggled through our fngers, as he always wriggles.He is Paul Finglemore；he is Césarine’s young man；and unless we arrest him now, without one minute’s delay, he’ll be off to Madrid or St.Petersburg by this evening！”

“You are right，”I answered.“It is now or never！”

“Dudley，”Charles said, in his most authoritative voice，“stop here till we tell you you may leave the room. Amelia and Dolly, don't let that man stir from where he's standing.If he does, restrain him.Seymour and Dr.Beddersley, come down with me to the servants'hall.I suppose that'swhere I shall fnd this person, Dudley?”

“N—no, sir，”Dudley stammered out, half beside himself with fright.“He's in the housekeeper's room, sir！”

We went down to the lower regions in a solid phalanx of three. On the way we met Simpson, Sir Charles's valet, and also the butler, whom we pressed into the service.At the door of the housekeeper's room we paused, strategically.Voices came to us from within；one was Césarine’s, the other had a ring that reminded me at once of Medhurst and the Seer, of Elihu Quackenboss and Algernon Coleyard.They were talking together in French；and now and then we caught the sound of stifed laughter.

We opened the door.“Est-il drôle, donc, ce vieux?”the man’s voice was saying.

“C'est à mourir de rire，”Césarine’s voice responded.

We burst in upon them, red-handed.

Césarine’s young man rose, with his hat in his hand, in a respectful attitude.It reminded me at once of Medhurst, as he stood talking his frst day at Marvillier’s to Charles；and also of the little curate, in his humblest moments as the disinterested pastor.

With a sign to me to do likewise, Charles laid his hand firmly on the young man's shoulder. I looked in the fellow's face：there could be no denying it；Césarine’s young man was Paul Finglemore, our broker’s brother.

“Paul Finglemore，”Charles said severely，“otherwise Cuthbert Clay, I arrest you on several charges of theft and conspiracy！”

The young man glanced around him. He was surprised and perturbed；but, even so, his inexhaustible coolness never once deserted him.“What, fve to one?”he said, counting us over.“Has law and order come down to this?Five respectable rascals to arrest one poor beggar of a chevalierd'industrie！Why, it's worse than New York.There, it was only you and me, you know, old Ten per Cent！”

“Hold his hands, Simpson！”Charles cried, trembling lest his enemy should escape him.

Paul Finglemore drew back even while we held his shoulders.“No, not you, sir，”he said to the man, haughtily.“Don't dare to lay your hands upon me！Send for a constable if you wish, Sir Charles Vandrift；but I decline to be taken into custody by a valet！”

“Go for a policeman，”Dr. Beddersley said to Simpson, standing forward.

The prisoner eyed him up and down.“Oh, Dr. Beddersley！”he said, relieved.It was evident he knew him.“If you've tracked me strictly in accordance with Bertillon's methods, I don't mind so much.I will not yield to fools；I yield to science.I didn't think this diamond king had sense enough to apply to you.He's the most gullible old ass I ever met in my life.But if it’s you who have tracked me down, I can only submit to it.”

Charles held to him with a ferce grip.“Mind he doesn't break away, Sey，”he cried.“He's playing his old game！Distrust the man's patter！”

“Take care，”the prisoner put in.“Remember Dr. Polperro！On what charge do you arrest me?”

Charles was bubbling with indignation.“You cheated me at Nice，”he said；“at Meran；at New York；at Paris！”

Paul Finglemore shook his head.“Won't do，”he answered, calmly.“Be sure of your ground. Outside the jurisdiction！You can only do that on an extradition warrant.”

“Well, then, at Seldon, in London, in this house, and elsewhere，”Charles cried out excitedly.“Hold hard to him, Sey；by law or without it, blessed if he isn't going even now to wriggle away from us！”

At that moment Simpson returned with a convenient policeman, whom he had happened to find loitering about near the area steps, and whom I half suspected from his furtive smile of being a particular acquaintance of the household.

Charles gave the man in charge formally. Paul Finglemore insisted that he should specify the nature of the particular accusation.To my great chagrin, Charles selected from his rogueries, as best within the jurisdiction of the English courts, the matter of the payment for the Castle of Lebenstein—made in London, and through a London banker.“I have a warrant on that ground，”he said.I trembled as he spoke.I felt at once that the episode of the commission, the exposure of which I dreaded so much, must now become public.

The policeman took the man in charge. Charles still held to him, grimly.As they were leaving the room the prisoner turned to Césarine, and muttered something rapidly under his breath, in German.“Of which tongue，”he said, turning to us blandly，“in spite of my kind present of a dictionary and grammar, you still doubtless remain in your pristine ignorance！”

Césarine flung herself upon him with wild devotion.“Oh, Paul, darling，”she cried, in English，“I will not, I will not！I will never save myself at your expense.If they send you to prison—Paul, Paul, I will go with you！”

I remembered as she spoke what Mr. Algernon Coleyard had said to us at the Senator's.“Even the worst of rogues have always some good in them.I notice they often succeed to the end in retaining the affection and fdelity of women.”

But the man, his hands still free, unwound her clasping arms with gentle fngers.“My child，”he answered, in a soft tone，“I am sorry to saythe law of England will not permit you to go with me. If it did”（his voice was as the voice of the poet we had met），“‘stone walls would not a prison make, nor iron bars a cage.'”And bending forward, he kissed her forehead tenderly.

We led him out to the door. The policeman, in obedience to Charles's orders, held him tight with his hand, but steadily refused, as the prisoner was not violent, to handcuff him.We hailed a passing hansom.“To Bow Street！”Charles cried, unceremoniously pushing in policeman and prisoner.The driver nodded.We called a four-wheeler ourselves, in which my brother-in-law, Dr.Beddersley and myself took our seats.“Follow the hansom！”Charles cried out.“Don't let him out of your sight.After him, close, to Bow Street！”

I looked back, and saw Césarine, half fainting, on the front door steps, while Dolly, bathed in tears, stood supporting the lady's-maid, and trying to comfort her.It was clear she had not anticipated this end to the adventure.

“Goodness gracious！”Charles screamed out, in a fresh fever of alarm, as we turned the frst corner；“where's that hansom gone to?How do I know the fellow was a policeman at all?We should have taken the man in here. We ought never to have let him get out of our sight.For all we can tell to the contrary, the constable himself—may only be one of Colonel Clay's confederates！”

And we drove in trepidation all the way to Bow Street.

Chapter XII The Episode of the Old Bailey

When we reached Bow Street, we were relieved to find that our prisoner, after all, had not evaded us. It was a false alarm.He was there with the policeman, and he kindly allowed us to make the first formal charge against him.

Of course, on Charles's sworn declaration and my own, the man was at once remanded, bail being refused, owing both to the serious nature of the charge and the slippery character of the prisoner's antecedents. We went back to Mayfair—Charles, well satisfied that the man he dreaded was under lock and key；myself, not too well pleased to think that the man I dreaded was no longer at large, and that the trifing little episode of the ten per cent commission stood so near discovery.

Next day the police came round in force, and had a long consultation with Charles and myself. They strongly urged that two other persons at least should be included in the charge—Césarine and the little woman whom we had variously known as Madame Picardet, White Heather, Mrs.David Granton, and Mrs.Elihu Quackenboss.If these accomplices were arrested, they said, we could include conspiracy as one count in the indictment, which gave us an extra chance of conviction.Now they had got Colonel Clay, in fact, they naturally desired to keep him, and also to indict with him as many as possible of his pals and confederates.

Here, however, a difficulty arose. Charles called me aside with a grave face into the library.“Seymour，”he said, fxing me，“this is a serious business.I will not lightly swear away any woman's character.Colonel Clay himself—or, rather, Paul Finglemore—is an abandoned rogue, whom I do not desire to screen in any degree.But poor little Madame Picardet—she may be his lawful wife, and she may have acted implicitly under his orders.Besides, I don't know whether I could swear to her identity.Here's the photograph the police bring of the woman they believe to be Colonel Clay's chief female accomplice.Now, I ask you, does it in the least degree resemble that clever and amusing and charming little creature, who has so often deceived us?”

In spite of Charles's gibes, I fatter myself I do really understand the whole duty of a secretary. It was clear from his voice he did not wish me to recognise her；which, as it happened, I did not.“Certainly, it doesn't resemble her, Charles，”I answered, with conviction in my voice.“I should never have known her.”But I did not add that I should no more have known Colonel Clay himself in his character of Paul Finglemore, or of Césarine’s young man, as that remark lay clearly outside my secretarial functions.

Still, it flitted across my mind at the time that the Seer had made some casual remarks at Nice about a letter in Charles's pocket, presumably from Madame Picardet；and I refected further that Madame Picardet in turn might possibly hold certain answers of Charles's, couched in such terms as he might reasonably desire to conceal from Amelia. Indeed, I must allow that under whatever disguise White Heather appeared to us, Charles was always that disguise's devoted slave from the frst moment he met it.It occurred to me, therefore, that the clever little woman—call her what you will—might be the holder of more than one indiscreetcommunication.

“Under these circumstances，”Charles went on, in his austerest voice，“I cannot consent to be a party to the arrest of White Heather. I—I decline to identify her.In point of fact”—he grew more emphatic as he went on—“I don't think there is an atom of evidence of any sort against her.Not，”he continued, after a pause，“that I wish in any degree to screen the guilty.Césarine, now—Césarine we have liked and trusted.She has betrayed our trust.She has sold us to this fellow.I have no doubt at all that she gave him the diamonds from Amelia’s rivière；that she took us by arrangement to meet him at Schloss Lebenstein；that she opened and sent to him my letter to Lord Craig-Ellachie.Therefore, I say, we ought to arrest Césarine.But not White Heather—not Jessie；not that pretty Mrs.Quackenboss.Let the guilty suffer；why strike at the innocent—or, at worst, the misguided?”

“Charles，”I exclaimed, with warmth，“your sentiments do you honour. You are a man of feeling.And White Heather, I allow, is pretty enough and clever enough to be forgiven anything.You may rely upon my discretion.I will swear through thick and thin that I do not recognise this woman as Madame Picardet.”

Charles clasped my hand in silence.“Seymour，”he said, after a pause, with marked emotion，“I felt sure I could rely upon your—er—honour and integrity. I have been rough upon you sometimes.But I ask your forgiveness.I see you understand the whole duties of your position.”

We went out again, better friends than we had been for months. I hoped, indeed, this pleasant little incident might help to neutralise the possible ill-effects of the ten per cent disclosure, should Finglemore take it into his head to betray me to my employer.As we emerged into the drawing-room, Amelia beckoned me aside towards her boudoir for a moment.

“Seymour，”she said to me, in a distinctly frightened tone，“I have treated you harshly at times, I know, and I am very sorry for it. But I want you to help me in a most painful diffculty.The police are quite right as to the charge of conspiracy；that designing little minx, White Heather, or Mrs.David Granton, or whatever else we're to call her, ought certainly to be prosecuted—and sent to prison, too—and have her absurd head of hair cut short and combed straight for her.But—and you will help me here, I'm sure, dear Seymour—I cannot allow them to arrest my Césarine.I don’t pretend to say Césarine isn’t guilty；the girl has behaved most ungratefully to me.She has robbed me right and left, and deceived me without compunction.Still—I put it to you as a married man—can any woman afford to go into the witness-box, to be cross-examined and teased by her own maid, or by a brute of a barrister on her maid’s information?I assure you, Seymour, the thing’s not to be dreamt of.There are details of a lady’s life—known only to her maid—which cannot be made public.Explain as much of this as you think well to Charles, and make him understand that if he insists upon arresting Césarine, I shall go into the box—and swear my head off to prevent any one of the gang from being convicted.I have told Césarine as much；I have promised to help her：I have explained that I am her friend, and that if she’ll stand by me, I’ll stand by her, and by this hateful young man of hers.”

I saw in a moment how things went. Neither Charles nor Amelia could face cross-examination on the subject of one of Colonel Clay's accomplices.No doubt, in Amelia's case, it was merely a question of rouge and hair-dye；but what woman would not sooner confess to a forgery or a murder than to those toilet secrets?

I returned to Charles, therefore, and spent half an hour in composing, as well as I might, these little domestic difficulties. In the end, it wasarranged that if Charles did his best to protect Césarine from arrest, Amelia would consent to do her best in return on behalf of Madame Picardet.

We had next the police to tackle—a more difficult business. Still, even they were reasonable.They had caught Colonel Clay, they believed, but their chance of convicting him depended entirely upon Charles's identifcation, with mine to back it.The more they urged the necessity of arresting the female confederates, however, the more stoutly did Charles declare that for his part he could by no means make sure of Colonel Clay himself, while he utterly declined to give evidence of any sort against either of the women.It was a diffcult case, he said, and he felt far from confident even about the man.If his decision faltered, and he failed to identify, the case was closed；no jury could convict with nothing to convict upon.

At last the police gave way. No other course was open to them.They had made an important capture；but they saw that everything depended upon securing their witnesses, and the witnesses, if interfered with, were likely to swear to absolutely nothing.

Indeed, as it turned out, before the preliminary investigation at Bow Street was completed（with the usual remands），Charles had been thrown into such a state of agitation that he wished he had never caught the Colonel at all.

“I wonder, Sey，”he said to me，“why I didn't offer the rascal two thousand a year to go right off to Australia, and be rid of him for ever！It would have been cheaper for my reputation than keeping him about in courts of law in England. The worst of it is, when once the best of men gets into a witness-box, there's no saying with what shreds and tatters of a character he may at last come out of it！”

“In your case, Charles，”I answered, dutifully，“there can be no such doubt；except, perhaps, as regards the Craig-Ellachie Consolidated.”

Then came the endless bother of“getting up the case”with the police and the lawyers. Charles would have retired from it altogether by that time, but, most unfortunately, he was bound over to prosecute.“You couldn't take a lump sum to let me off?”he said, jokingly, to the inspector.But I knew in my heart it was one of the“true words spoken in jest”that the proverb tells of.

Of course we could see now the whole building-up of the great intrigue. It had been worked out as carefully as the Tichborne swindle.Young Finglemore, as the brother of Charles's broker, knew from the outset all about his affairs；and, after a gentle course of preliminary roguery, he laid his plans deep for a campaign against my brother-in-law.Everything had been deliberately designed beforehand.A place had been found for Césarine as Amelia’s maid—needless to say, by means of forged testimonials.Through her aid the swindler had succeeded in learning still more of the family ways and habits, and had acquired a knowledge of certain facts which he proceeded forthwith to use against us.His frst attack, as the Seer, had been cleverly designed so as to give us the idea that we were a mere casual prey；and it did not escape Charles’s notice now that the detail of getting Madame Picardet to inquire at the Crédit Marseillais about his bank had been solemnly gone through on purpose to blind us to the obvious truth that Colonel Clay was already in full possession of all such facts about us.It was by Césarine’s aid, again, that he became possessed of Amelia’s diamonds, that he received the letter addressed to Lord Craig-Ellachie, and that he managed to dupe us over the Schloss Lebenstein business.Nevertheless, all these things Charles determined to conceal in court；he did not give the police a single fact thatwould turn against either Césarine or Madame Picardet.

As for Césarine, of course, she left the house immediately after the arrest of the Colonel, and we heard of her no more till the day of the trial.

When that great day came, I never saw a more striking sight than the Old Bailey presented. It was crammed to overflowing.Charles arrived early, accompanied by his solicitor.He was so white and troubled that he looked much more like prisoner than prosecutor.Outside the court a pretty little woman stood, pale and anxious.A respectful crowd stared at her silently.“Who is that?”Charles asked.Though we could both of us guess, rather than see, it was White Heather.

“That's the prisoner's wife，”the inspector on duty replied.“She's waiting to see him enter. I'm sorry for her, poor thing.She's a perfect lady.”

“So she seems，”Charles answered, scarcely daring to face her.

At that moment she turned. Her eyes fell upon his.Charles paused for a second and looked faltering.There was in those eyes just the faintest gleam of pleading recognition, but not a trace of the old saucy, defiant vivacity.Charles framed his lips to words, but without uttering a sound.Unless I greatly mistake, the words he framed on his lips were these：“I will do my best for him.”

We pushed our way in, assisted by the police. Inside the court we saw a lady seated, in a quiet black dress, with a becoming bonnet.A moment passed before I knew—it was Césarine.“Who is—that person?”Charles asked once more of the nearest inspector, desiring to see in what way he would describe her.

And once more the answer came，“That's the prisoner's wife, sir.”

Charles started back, surprised.“But—I was told—a lady outside was Mrs. Paul Finglemore，”he broke in, much puzzled.

“Very likely，”the inspector replied, unmoved.“We have plenty that way. When a gentleman has as many aliases as Colonel Clay, you can hardly expect him to be over particular about having only one wife between them, can you?”

“Ah, I see，”Charles muttered, in a shocked voice.“Bigamy！”

The inspector looked stony.“Well, not exactly that，”he replied，“occasional marriage.”

Mr. Justice Rhadamanth tried the case.“I'm sorry it's him, Sey，”my brother-in-law whispered in my ear.（He said him, not he, because, whatever else Charles is, he is not a pedant；the English language as it is spoken by most educated men is quite good enough for his purpose.）“I only wish it had been Sir Edward Easy.Easy's a man of the world, and a man of society；he would feel for a person in my position.He wouldn't allow these beasts of lawyers to badger and pester me.He would back his order.But Rhadamanth is one of your modern sort of judges, who make a merit of being what they call‘conscientious，'and won’t hush up anything.I admit I’m afraid of him.I shall be glad when it’s over.”

“Oh, you'll pull through all right，”I said in my capacity of secretary. But I didn't think it.

The judge took his seat. The prisoner was brought in.Every eye seemed bent upon him.He was neatly and plainly dressed, and, rogue though he was, I must honestly confess he looked at least a gentleman.His manner was defant, not abject like Charles's.He knew he was at bay, and he turned like a man to face his accusers.

We had two or three counts on the charge, and, after some formal business, Sir Charles Vandrift was put into the box to bear witness against Finglemore.

Prisoner was unrepresented. Counsel had been offered him, but herefused their aid.The judge even advised him to accept their help；but Colonel Clay, as we all called him mentally still, declined to avail himself of the judge's suggestion.

“I am a barrister myself, my lord，”he said—“called some nine years ago. I can conduct my own defence, I venture to think, better than any of these my learned brethren.”

Charles went through his examination-in-chief quite swimmingly. He answered with promptitude.He identified the prisoner without the slightest hesitation as the man who had swindled him under the various disguises of the Reverend Richard Peploe Brabazon, the Honourable David Granton, Count von Lebenstein, Professor Schleiermacher, Dr.Quackenboss, and others.He had not the slightest doubt of the man's identity.He could swear to him anywhere.I thought, for my own part, he was a trife too cocksure.A certain amount of hesitation would have been better policy.As to the various swindles, he detailed them in full, his evidence to be supplemented by that of bank officials and other subordinates.In short, he left Finglemore not a leg to stand upon.

When it came to the cross-examination, however, matters began to assume quite a different complexion. The prisoner set out by questioning Sir Charles's identifcations.Was he sure of his man?He handed Charles a photograph.“Is that the person who represented himself as the Reverend Richard Peploe Brabazon?”he asked persuasively.

Charles admitted it without a moment's delay.

Just at that moment, a little parson, whom I had not noticed till then, rose up, unobtrusively, near the middle of the court, where he was seated beside Césarine.

“Look at that gentleman！”the prisoner said, waving one hand, and pouncing upon the prosecutor.

Charles turned and looked at the person indicated. His face grew still whiter.It was—to all outer appearance—the Reverend Richard Brabazon in propriâ personâ.

Of course I saw the trick. This was the real parson upon whose outer man Colonel Clay had modelled his little curate.But the jury was shaken.And so was Charles for a moment.

“Let the jurors see the photograph，”the judge said, authoritatively. It was passed round the jury-box, and the judge also examined it.We could see at once, by their faces and attitudes, they all recognised it as the portrait of the clergyman before them—not of the prisoner in the dock, who stood there smiling blandly at Charles's discomfture.

The clergyman sat down. At the same moment the prisoner produced a second photograph.

“Now, can you tell me who that is?”he asked Charles, in the regular brow-beating Old Bailey voice.

With somewhat more hesitation, Charles answered, after a pause：“That is yourself as you appeared in London when you came in the disguise of the Graf von Lebenstein.”

This was a crucial point, for the Lebenstein fraud was the one count on which our lawyers relied to prove their case most fully, within the jurisdiction.

Even while Charles spoke, a gentleman whom I had noticed before, sitting beside White Heather, with a handkerchief to his face, rose as abruptly as the parson. Colonel Clay indicated him with a graceful movement of his hand.“And this gentleman?”he asked calmly.

Charles was fairly staggered. It was the obvious original of the false Von Lebenstein.

The photograph went round the box once more. The jury smiledincredulously.Charles had given himself away.His overweening confdence and certainty had ruined him.

Then Colonel Clay, leaning forward, and looking quite engaging, began a new line of cross-examination.“We have seen, Sir Charles，”he said，“that we cannot implicitly trust your identifications. Now let us see how far we can trust your other evidence.First, then, about those diamonds.You tried to buy them, did you not, from a person who represented himself as the Reverend Richard Brabazon, because you believed he thought they were paste；and if you could, you would have given him 10 pounds or so for them.Do you think that was honest?”

“I object to this line of cross-examination，”our leading counsel interposed.“It does not bear on the prosecutor's evidence. It is purely recriminatory.”

Colonel Clay was all bland deference.“I wish, my lord，”he said, turning round，“to show that the prosecutor is a person unworthy of credence in any way. I desire to proceed upon the well-known legal maxim of falsus in uno, falsus in omnibus.I believe I am permitted to shake the witness's credit?”

“The prisoner is entirely within his rights，”Rhadamanth answered, looking severely at Charles.“And I was wrong in suggesting that he needed the advice or assistance of counsel.”

Charles wriggled visibly. Colonel Clay perked up.Bit by bit, with dexterous questions, Charles was made to acknowledge that he wanted to buy diamonds at the price of paste, knowing them to be real；and, a millionaire himself, would gladly have diddled a poor curate out of a couple of thousand.

“I was entitled to take advantage of my special knowledge，”Charles murmured feebly.

“Oh, certainly，”the prisoner answered.“But, while professing friendship and affection for a clergyman and his wife, in straitened circumstances, you were prepared, it seems, to take three thousand pounds'worth of goods off their hands for ten pounds, if you could have got them at that price. Is not that so?”

Charles was compelled to admit it.

The prisoner went onto the David Granton incident.“When you offered to amalgamate with Lord Craig-Ellachie，”he asked，“had you or had you not heard that a gold-bearing reef ran straight from your concession into Lord Craig-Ellachie's, and that his portion of the reef was by far the larger and more important?”

Charles wriggled again, and our counsel interposed；but Rhadamanth was adamant. Charles had to allow it.

And so, too, with the incident of the Slump in Golcondas. Unwillingly, shamefacedly, by torturing steps, Charles was compelled to confess that he had sold out Golcondas—he, the Chairman of the company, after repeated declarations to shareholders and others that he would do no such thing—because he thought Professor Schleiermacher had made diamonds worthless.He had endeavoured to save himself by ruining his company.Charles tried to brazen it out with remarks to the effect that business was business.“And fraud is fraud，”Rhadamanth added, in his pungent way.

“A man must protect himself，”Charles burst out.

“At the expense of those who have put their trust in his honour and integrity，”the judge commented coldly.

After four mortal hours of it, all to the same effect, my respected brother-in-law left the witness-box at last, wiping his brow and biting his lip, with the very air of a culprit. His character had received a most seriousblow.While he stood in the witness-box all the world had felt it was he who was the accused and Colonel Clay who was the prosecutor.He was convicted on his own evidence of having tried to induce the supposed David Granton to sell his father's interests into an enemy's hands, and of every other shady trick into which his well-known business acuteness had unfortunately hurried him during the course of his adventures.I had but one consolation in my brother-in-law's misfortunes—and that was the thought that a due sense of his own shortcomings might possibly make him more lenient in the end to the trivial misdemeanours of a poor beggar of a secretary！

I was the next in the box. I do not desire to enlarge upon my own achievements.I will draw a decent veil, indeed, over the painful scene that ensued when I fnished my evidence.I can only say I was more cautious than Charles in my recognition of the photographs；but I found myself particularly worried and harried over other parts of my cross-examination.Especially was I shaken about that misguided step I took in the matter of the cheque for the Lebenstein commission—a cheque which Colonel Clay handed to me with the utmost politeness, requesting to know whether or not it bore my signature.I caught Charles's eye at the end of the episode, and I venture to say the expression it wore was one of relief that I too had tripped over a trifing question of ten per cent on the purchase money of the castle.

Altogether, I must admit, if it had not been for the police evidence, we would have failed to make a case against our man at all. But the police, I confess, had got up their part of the prosecution admirably.Now that they knew Colonel Clay to be really Paul Finglemore, they showed with great cleverness how Paul Finglemore's disappearances and reappearances in London exactly tallied with Colonel Clay's appearancesand disappearances elsewhere, under the guise of the little curate, the Seer, David Granton, and the rest of them.Furthermore, they showed experimentally how the prisoner at the bar might have got himself up in the various characters；and, by means of a wax bust, modelled by Dr.Beddersley from observations at Bow Street, and aided by additions in the gutta-percha composition after Dolly Lingfield's photographs, they succeeded in proving that the face as it stood could be readily transformed into the faces of Medhurst and David Granton.Altogether, their cleverness and trained acumen made up on the whole for Charles's over-certainty, and they succeeded in putting before the jury a strong case of their own against Paul Finglemore.

The trial occupied three days. After the first of the three, my respected brother-in-law preferred, as he said, not to prejudice the case against the prisoner by appearing in court again.He did not even allude to the little matter of the ten per cent commission further than to say at dinner that evening that all men were bound to protect their own interests—as secretaries or as principals.This I took for forgiveness；and I continued diligently to attend the trial, and watch the case in my employer's interest.

The defence was ingenious, even if somewhat halting. It consisted simply of an attempt to prove throughout that Charles and I had made our prisoner the victim of a mistaken identity.Finglemore put into the box the ingenuous original of the little curate—the Reverend Septimus Porkington, as it turned out, a friend of his family；and he showed that it was the Reverend Septimus himself who had sat to a photographer in Baker Street for the portrait which Charles too hastily identified as that of Colonel Clay in his personifcation of Mr.Richard Brabazon.He further elicited the fact that the portrait of the Count von Lebenstein wasreally taken from Dr.Julius Keppel, a Tyrolese music-master, residing at Balham, whom he put into the box, and who was well known, as it chanced, to the foreman of the jury.Gradually he made it clear to us that no portraits existed of Colonel Clay at all, except Dolly Lingfield's—so it dawned upon me by degrees that even Dr.Beddersley could only have been misled if we had succeeded in finding for him the alleged photographs of Colonel Clay as the count and the curate, which had been shown us by Medhurst.Altogether, the prisoner based his defence upon the fact that no more than two witnesses directly identified him；while one of those two had positively sworn that he recognised as the prisoner's two portraits which turned out, by independent evidence, to be taken from other people！

The judge summed up in a caustic way which was pleasant to neither party. He asked the jury to dismiss from their minds entirely the impression created by what he frankly described as“Sir Charles Vandrift's obvious dishonesty.”They must not allow the fact that he was a millionaire—and a particularly shady one—to prejudice their feelings in favour of the prisoner.Even the richest—and vilest—of men must be protected.Besides, this was a public question.If a rogue cheated a rogue, he must still be punished.If a murderer stabbed or shot a murderer, he must still be hung for it.Society must see that the worst of thieves were not preyed upon by others.Therefore, the proved facts that Sir Charles Vandrift, with all his millions, had meanly tried to cheat the prisoner, or some other poor person, out of valuable diamonds—had basely tried to juggle Lord Craig-Ellachie's mines into his own hands—had vilely tried to bribe a son to betray his father—had directly tried, by underhand means, to save his own money, at the risk of destroying the wealth of others who trusted to his probity—these proved facts must not blind themto the truth that the prisoner at the bar（if he were really Colonel Clay）was an abandoned swindler.To that point alone they must confne their attention；and if they were convinced that the prisoner was shown to be the self-same man who appeared on various occasions as David Granton, as Von Lebenstein, as Medhurst, as Schleiermacher, they must fnd him guilty.

As to that point, also, the judge commented on the obvious strength of the police case, and the fact that the prisoner had not attempted in any one out of so many instances to prove an alibi. Surely, if he were not Colonel Clay, the jury should ask themselves, must it not have been simple and easy for him to do so?Finally, the judge summed up all the elements of doubt in the identifcation—and all the elements of probability；and left it to the jury to draw their own conclusions.

They retired at the end to consider their verdict. While they were absent every eye in court was fxed on the prisoner.But Paul Finglemore himself looked steadily towards the further end of the hall, where two pale-faced women sat together, with handkerchiefs in their hands, and eyes red with weeping.

Only then, as he stood there, awaiting the verdict, with a fxed white face, prepared for everything, did I begin to realise with what courage and pluck that one lone man had sustained so long an unequal contest against wealth, authority, and all the Governments of Europe, aided but by his own skill and two feeble women！Only then did I feel he had played his reckless game through all those years with this ever before him！I found it hard to picture.

The jury filed slowly back. There was dead silence in court as the clerk put the question，“Do you fnd the prisoner at the bar guilty or not guilty?”

“We fnd him guilty.”

“On all the counts?”

“On all the counts of the indictment.”

The women at the back burst into tears, unanimously.

Mr. Justice Rhadamanth addressed the prisoner.“Have you anything to urge，”he asked in a very stern tone，“in mitigation of whatever sentence the Court may see ft to pass upon you?”

“Nothing，”the prisoner answered, just faltering slightly.“I have brought it upon myself—but—I have protected the lives of those nearest and dearest to me. I have fought hard for my own hand.I admit my crime, and will face my punishment.I only regret that, since we were both of us rogues—myself and the prosecutor—the lesser rogue should have stood here in the dock, and the greater in the witness-box.Our country takes care to decorate each according to his deserts—to him, the Grand Cross of St.Michael and St.George；to me, the Broad Arrow！”

The judge gazed at him severely.“Paul Finglemore，”he said, passing sentence in his sardonic way，“you have chosen to dedicate to the service of fraud abilities and attainments which, if turned from the outset into a legitimate channel, would no doubt have suffced to secure you without excessive effort a subsistence one degree above starvation—possibly even, with good luck, a sordid and squalid competence. You have preferred to embark them on a lawless life of vice and crime—and I will not deny that you seem to have had a good run for your money.Society, however, whose mouthpiece I am, cannot allow you any longer to mock it with impunity.You have broken its laws openly, and you have been found out.”He assumed the tone of bland condescension which always heralds his severest moments.“I sentence you to Fourteen Years'Imprisonment, with Hard Labour.”

The prisoner bowed, without losing his apparent composure. But his eyes strayed away again to the far end of the hall, where the two weeping women, with a sudden sharp cry, fell at once in a faint on one another's shoulders, and were with diffculty removed from court by the ushers.

As we left the room, I heard but one comment all round, thus voiced by a school-boy：“I'd a jolly sight rather it had been old Vandrift. This Clay chap's too clever by half to waste on a prison！”

But he went there, none the less—in that“cool sequestered vale of life”to recover equilibrium；though I myself half regretted it.

I will add but one more little parting episode.

When all was over, Charles rushed off to Cannes, to get away from the impertinent stare of London. Amelia and Isabel and I went with him.We were driving one afternoon on the hills beyond the town, among the myrtle and lentisk scrub, when we noticed in front of us a nice victoria, containing two ladies in very deep mourning.We followed it, unintentionally, as far as Le Grand Pin—that big pine tree that looks across the bay towards Antibes.There, the ladies descended and sat down on a knoll, gazing out disconsolately towards the sea and the islands.It was evident they were suffering very deep grief.Their faces were pale and their eyes bloodshot.“Poor things！”Amelia said.Then her tone altered suddenly.

“Why, good gracious，”she cried，“if it isn't Césarine！”

So it was—with White Heather！

Charles got down and drew near them.“I beg your pardon，”he said, raising his hat, and addressing Madame Picardet：“I believe I have had the pleasure of meeting you. And since I have doubtless paid in the end for your victoria, may I venture to inquire for whom you are in mourning?”

White Heather drew back, sobbing；but Césarine turned to him, feryred, with the mien of a lady.“For him！”she answered；“for Paul！for our king, whom you have imprisoned！As long as he remains there, we have both of us decided to wear mourning for ever！”

Charles raised his hat again, and drew back without one word. He waved his hand to Amelia and walked home with me to Cannes.He seemed deeply dejected.

“A penny for your thoughts！”I exclaimed, at last, in a jocular tone, trying feebly to rouse him.

He turned to me, and sighed.“I was wondering，”he answered，“if I had gone to prison, would Amelia and Isabel have done as much for me?”

For myself, I did not wonder. I knew pretty well.For Charles, you will admit, though the bigger rogue of the two, is scarcely the kind of rogue to inspire a woman with profound affection.

[1]维多克，一个声震欧美的传奇人物，被誉为侦探之王；罗伯特·胡丁被誉为现代魔术之父；卡廖斯特罗，意大利的江湖骗子，魔术师兼冒险家，在欧洲各地卖假药，在各大城市算命行骗。

[2]英国旧时货币单位。

[3]伦敦的上流住宅区。

[4]波兰钢琴家、作曲家、政治家、外交家，是19世纪末20世纪初杰出的世界级钢琴大师之一，1919年曾出任波兰总理，并兼任外交部部长。

[5]中名可以用于纪念某个人，此处“奥沙利文”是其母亲的姓氏。

[6]Clay，音译为“克雷”，有“泥土、黏土”之意。

[7]英国政治家，曾任首相。

[8]磅、盎司、本尼威特均为英美重量单位，1磅约为453.6克，1盎司约为28.35克，1本尼威特约等于1.6克。

[9]南非开普省城市，世界闻名的钻石产地。

[10]《天方夜谭》中的故事，水手辛巴达曾经进行七次航海旅行，在第二次冒险中落入一山谷，谷中满是钻石。

[11]英国的一份体育报纸，最初印在粉红色的纸上，故得此名。

[12]南非一省名。

[13]荷兰西部城市。

[14]荷兰一古老小镇。

[15]普耳曼（Pullman）是一种豪华卧车，因设计者乔治·普耳曼（1831—1897）而得名。

[16]1基尼=1.05英镑。

[17]“schloss”一词为德语，并不能按照英语语法规则，通过加“es”的后缀变成复数，而原文中作者在“schloss”一词后面加“es”变成复数，从英语语法上看是错误的，但英语的读者能意会到作者想要表达的意思，即表示复数。

[18]伯恩·琼斯是位唯美主义绘画大师，曾在给友人的信中说：“我在我的作品中创造一个美丽而浪漫的梦境，它不曾存在过，将来也不会存在。那光线比任何现实中的光线都要美，那片大陆不存在于任何人的记忆中，形式庄严而美丽，你能想象吗……”

[19]伦敦为世界的几个主要的金融中心之一，而针线街则被称为“中心的中心”。这里有许多英国著名的金融机构，包括英格兰银行等就坐落在这里。

[20]卡佩尔厅为当时英国的股票交易场所；金伯利为南非中部城市，出产钻石。

[21]扫罗和大卫均为《圣经》中的人物。《圣经》中说：“扫罗杀死千千，大卫杀死万万。”

[22]克伦威尔是英国军人、政治家和宗教领袖，曾作为英格兰的护国公实行独裁统治。

[23]布尔人是南非荷兰殖民者或荷兰殖民者的后裔。

[24]伦敦有名的绅士俱乐部。

[25]过去旧制英镑辅币为先令和便士。1英镑=20先令，1先令=12便士。

[26]德国地名。

[27]世界最大、最著名、最古老的钻石之一。

[28]西方谚语：恺撒之妻，不容置疑。

[29]约伯，《圣经》中人物，乌斯地的义人，家里有五百对牛、七千只羊、五百头母驴、三千匹骆驼，还有众多奴仆。一天，示巴人突然把他的牛和驴抢走了；天降大火，把羊群还有仆人都烧死了；迦勒底人抢走了骆驼，用刀杀了仆人；房屋倒塌将他的子女压死。

[30]马歇尔（A.R.Marshall），19世纪晚期英国诗人，常为《体育时报》写一些幽默、滑稽的小诗，多斯·柴德多斯（Doss Chiderdoss）为他的笔名。

[31]玛米（Marmy），玛玛丢克（Marmaduke）的昵称。

[32]在英国传统中，使用双姓（通常以连字符连接）主要是为了避免某个姓氏消失，同时也与家族财产的继承有关系。

[33]引自英国浪漫主义诗人华兹华斯的诗篇The World Is Too Much with Us。

[34]原文为“Everything turns up in the end—including Mrs.Quackenboss’s nose”。“turn up”此处为双关，既有“出现”之意，也有“向上翘起”之意。

[35]19世纪维多利亚时代的大英帝国步入了鼎盛时期，殖民地遍布全球，领土面积占世界陆地总面积的四分之一，被称为日不落帝国。

[36]劳埃德保险社是位于英国伦敦的保险商协会。根据劳埃德保险社的规定，船体技术状况分类中A为最好。

[37]给牲畜打烙印，用于表示归属。

[38]改编自《圣经·旧约》的“诗篇”（Psalms）第16章，“用绳量给我的地界，坐落在佳美之处”（The lines are fallen unto me in pleasant places）。

[39]纽约社交圈认为虽然温古德有钱，但是不属于上流社会的圈子。

[40]登塔图斯（Dentatus），罗马共和国平民英雄，三次任共和国执政官，曾多次实施建造规模浩大的公共工程；法比家族（the Fabii），罗马共和国早期著名的贵族家族，出过很多执政官；卡美卢斯（Camillus），被誉为“罗马第二创建者”，五次当选罗马独裁官。此处为讽刺议员的奢华铺张。

[41]希腊神话中，阿波罗被认为是音乐家、诗人、射手的保护神和预言之神。

[42]前文提到，1英镑约合5美元，2，000英镑即10，000美元。

[43]古罗马共和国时期的英雄。公元前458年，罗马军队遭到意大利埃奎人的包围，退隐务农的他临危受命担任罗马独裁官，以保卫罗马。退敌16天后，他辞职返回农庄。

[44]引自英国17世纪的诗人理查德·洛弗莱斯（Richard Lovelace）在英国内战期间坐牢时，写给他情人的一首诗To Althea, from Prison。

[45]英国中央刑事法院所在地。

[46]1854年英国贵族罗杰·蒂奇伯恩爵士在海上遇难，但他母亲坚信儿子仍然在世，于是在全球各地刊登广告悬赏征求儿子的消息。第二年，一位名叫亚瑟·奥尔顿的男子声称自己就是遇难的罗杰·蒂奇伯恩爵士，被别人从海上救起。后来，亚瑟·奥尔顿企图获得部分家产，但被亲戚识破。

[47]英国荣誉制度中的一种骑士勋章，一般授予对英联邦或外交事务做出贡献的人士。

1

这是个诡异、酷热的夏天。间谍罗森伯格夫妇在这个夏天坐上了电椅。而我不知道自己在纽约做什么。我对于处决这种事情懵懵懂懂，但一想到全身通电而死就感到反胃，偏偏报纸上全是这事儿。在每个街角，每个散发着霉臭、花生味的地铁出入口，这些标题都瞪大眼睛盯着我。按说这本和我无关，但我就是忍不住地想，被电流窜遍神经活活烧死会是种什么感觉。

我想世上最恐怖的事情，莫过于此吧。

纽约真是够糟的。那随风潜入夜的隐约带有乡间湿气的清新气味，才刚早上九点，就已宛如美梦余韵般蒸腾得无影无踪。高楼构筑的花岗岩峡谷底下是海市蜃楼般的灰蒙一片，暑气逼人的街道在烈日下泛着热浪。车顶被晒得嘶嘶作响，晃得人眼花。干燥的、煤灰般的尘土吹入我的眼中，直下我的喉咙。

收音机和办公室里总在说罗森伯格夫妇的事，弄得我想忘也忘不掉。那感觉就像第一次看见尸体，过了好几个礼拜，那尸体的头——或者该说留在尸身上的残余物——仍不时浮现在我眼前，从我早餐的鸡蛋和培根后面冒出来，从巴迪·威拉德的脸后面冒出来，这家伙正是害我见到那具尸体的罪魁祸首。之后没多久，我就觉得自己走到哪里都带着一颗用绳子拴着的死人头颅，像带着一个黑乎乎的、没有鼻子的、酸臭的气球。

我知道那个夏天自己有些不对劲，因为我满脑子都是罗森伯格夫妇的事；要不就是成天想着自己怎么那么蠢，买了那些穿着不舒服又很昂贵的衣服，只好让它们像死鱼一样无精打采地挂在衣橱里；我也搞不明白，麦迪逊大道上的光滑大理石和玻璃橱窗，是怎么把我在大学期间兴高采列地积累的小小成就消弭于无形的。

我本该享受着人生的大好时光才对啊。

我本该是全美成千上万大学女生羡慕的对象，她们一心向往的就是穿着和我一样的七号漆面皮鞋四处游走。这双鞋是我趁午餐的时候跑到布鲁明戴尔百货商店买的，当时还买了一条黑色的漆面皮带和一个黑色的漆面手袋来配它。当我的照片登上了我们十二人所任职的杂志社的杂志时，人人都以为我一定乐得晕头转向。照片中的我穿着仿银丝质料的紧身胸衣，下半身是一条云朵般的白纱大蓬裙，在某个名为“星光屋顶”的地方喝着马丁尼，身旁环绕着数位年轻男子。他们虽然没什么名气，却有着美国人那种十足的好身材，都是专为这次拍摄雇来或者借调来的。

人们会说，瞧瞧，美国真是无奇不有。一个在穷乡僻壤住了十九年，穷到连本杂志都买不起的乡下姑娘，居然拿了奖学金念大学，还一会儿得这个奖，一会儿得那个奖，最后竟把纽约当作私家车一样，驾驭起来得心应手。

其实，我什么都驾驭不了，甚至连自己都掌控不好。我就像一辆麻木的无轨电车，一路从所住的旅馆颠簸到办公室再到派对，然后又从派对颠簸回旅馆再到办公室。我想我本该像大多数其他女孩那样兴奋，但我自己就是没这种感觉。我只感到一种极度的静与空，如同处于暴风眼中一般，在周遭的纷扰喧闹中，迟钝地前进。

我们总共十二个人住在这家旅馆。

我们全都赢得了一个时尚杂志举办的竞赛，有的写了散文，有的写了小说，有的写了诗歌，还有的写了时尚广告文案，奖品就是在纽约市见习一个月。开销全由杂志社支付，此外还有各种免费福利，比如芭蕾舞的门票，时装秀和顶级发型沙龙的招待券，有机会依照个人喜好和该领域的成功人士见面，还有针对个人肤质的化妆建议，等等。

我手头还有一套他们送的化妆品，适合棕眼褐发的女孩：内有一支带小刷子的长方形褐色睫毛膏，一小盘只容指尖放入的蓝色眼影，三支唇膏，颜色从大红到粉色渐变。这些全装在一个内盖镶了面镜子的镀金小盒里。我还有一个白色塑料墨镜盒，上面缀着彩色贝壳、金属圆片和绿色的塑料海星。

我明白之所以有源源不断的礼物，是因为这形同给赞助商免费打广告，即使如此，我也无法愤世嫉俗。这些天上掉下来的礼物，我可是收得心花怒放。虽然我把礼物收起来了好一阵子，但一等我恢复正常，又将它们一一拿出来摆在屋子各处。现在我仍时不时地抹抹那几支唇膏，上周我还把墨镜盒上的塑料海星割下来给小宝宝玩。

就这样，我们十二人住在同一家旅馆同一个侧翼的同一个楼层的单人房里，一间紧挨着一间，这让我想起大学宿舍。这不是一家普通意义上的旅馆——我指的是那种男女混住在同一楼层的旅馆。

这家叫“亚马逊”的旅馆只接待女客。她们多和我年纪相仿，家境殷实，她们的父母希望自己的宝贝女儿住在不会被男人勾引和欺骗的地方。她们读的全是像凯蒂·吉布斯这类的高级秘书学校，得戴着帽子、穿着长筒袜、戴着手套去上课；要不，她们就是刚从这类学校毕业，担任着各级主管的秘书，留在纽约只是为了等待嫁给事业有成的男人的机会。

在我看来，这些女孩实在无聊。我看见她们在楼顶天台，打着呵欠涂着指甲，晒着日光浴保养在百慕大群岛晒出的小麦色肌肤，看起来真的无聊透顶。我和其中一个聊过，她说她厌倦了游艇，厌倦了搭飞机飞来飞去，厌倦了在圣诞节到瑞士滑雪，厌倦了巴西男人。

我受够了那样的女孩。我已嫉妒到说不出话来。十九年来，除了这趟纽约之行，我不曾踏出过新英格兰地区。这是我的第一个大好机会，但我却只是坐看机会像流水般从我指间哗哗流逝。

我想，我的麻烦之一是朵琳。

我以前不曾认识像朵琳这样的女孩。她来自南方一所上流女校，一头闪亮的白发，像是棉花糖一样蓬松醒目，圈住她的整张脸；一对蓝眸澄澈如玛瑙珠子，又硬又亮，坚不可摧；嘴边永远带着一抹嘲讽的微笑。我说的不是那种惹人讨厌的冷笑，而是一种顽皮而神秘的嘲笑，仿佛她身边尽是蠢蛋，只要她愿意，她随时都能嘲弄他们一番。

朵琳第一眼就注意上了我，让我觉得我比其他人机灵得多，而她这个人也确实有趣得很。开会时，她总是挨着我坐，来访的名流说话时，她会压低声音和我耳语些诙谐的嘲讽。

她说她的学校很注重时尚。所有女孩都有和服装相同材质面料的手包，所以她们每换一套衣服都有与之相配的手包。这种对细节的讲究让我印象深刻。它展现出一种神奇炫目的生活方式，带着刻意而精致的颓废气息，像磁铁般深深吸引着我。

朵琳只会因为一件事情对着我吼，那就是我总是努力如期完成工作。

“你那么拼命干吗呀？”朵琳穿着一件蜜桃色的丝绸晨袍，懒洋洋地窝在我的床上，手里拿着锉刀打磨着被尼古丁熏得微黄的长指甲，而我则忙着在打字机上敲出一位畅销小说家的采访稿。

这是朵琳的又一个与众不同之处——我们穿的是上过浆的夏季棉质睡衣和夹棉家居服，或者是可以充当海滩浴袍的毛巾布长袍，可朵琳穿的要么是半透明的尼龙长衫或是蕾丝长衫，要么是会因静电而贴在身上的肉色晨袍。她身上有一股好闻的轻微的汗味，让人想到香蕨木的扇形叶片，这种叶子摘下一些在指间揉碎，就会散发一股麝香味。

“你知道的，老杰·茜根本不在意你的稿子是明天交还是周一交。”朵琳点了根烟，袅袅烟雾从鼻孔逐渐散开，遮住了她的眼睛。“杰·茜长得丑死了。”她冷冷地说，“我打赌她那老伴在亲近她之前得把灯全关了，免得吐出来。”

杰·茜是我的上司，不管朵琳怎么说，我还是很喜欢她。她不是时尚杂志圈里那种扑闪着假睫毛、珠光宝气、虚情假意的人。杰·茜有脑子，所以相貌丑点也不打紧。她会几种语言，而且对这一行里的优秀作家了如指掌。

我试着想象杰·茜脱下严谨的办公室套装，摘下午宴帽子，和她的肥老公上床的模样，可我就是做不到。对我来说，想象别人上床难如登天。

杰·茜想教我些东西，所有我认识的老太太都想教我点东西，但是我突然觉得她们根本没什么好教给我的。我罩上打字机的盖子，咔一声合上。

朵琳咧嘴一笑。“聪明。”

有人敲门。

“谁啊？”我懒得起身。

“是我，贝琪。你要去舞会吗？”

“大概会吧。”我还是没有起身开门。

从堪萨斯被请来纽约的贝琪梳着轻盈弹跳的金色马尾辫，脸上带着电影《赌徒甜心》里女主人公的甜美笑容。记得有一次，我们俩被某电视剧制作人叫进办公室，这个下颏泛着青色胡楂、穿着细条纹西装的制作人问我们有没有什么点子可以拿出来做节目。然后贝琪就开始大谈堪萨斯的雌雄株玉米，她说起那该死的玉米真是情绪激昂，听得制作人眼泛泪光，不过他说，真是可惜，这些都用不上。

后来，美容部编辑说服贝琪剪了短发，让她做了封面模特。现在我仍不时看见她在“魁北克的太太穿B．H．Wragge(1)”的广告中展露迷人的笑脸。

贝琪总爱邀我陪她和她的女伴一起做这做那，好像这样是在以某种方式拯救我。但她从来不找朵琳。朵琳私底下都叫她“牛仔傻大妞”。

“你要跟我们一起搭出租车吗？”贝琪在门外问。

朵琳摇了摇头。

“没关系，贝琪。”我说，“我和朵琳一起去。”

“好吧。”我听见贝琪脚步轻快地走向长廊另一头。

“我们去看看吧，受够了就走。”朵琳说着把烟蒂按熄在我床头阅读灯的灯座上。“然后我们进城去玩。这里办的派对让我想起那些在学校体育馆办的老式舞会。他们为什么总爱围着耶鲁的学生转？耶鲁的都很蠢哎！”

巴迪·威拉德就是上的耶鲁，我现在一想，发现他的毛病就是蠢。对，他是拼命学出了好成绩，还曾经和科德角一个叫格拉迪斯的可怕的女招待交往过，但他没有哪怕一丁点儿直觉。而朵琳有直觉。她说的每一件事，好像都说出了我偷偷藏在骨头里的每一个想法。

戏剧开演前的交通高峰把我们困住了。我们的出租车前面是贝琪的车，后面是另外四个女孩的车。每辆车都寸步难行。

朵琳看起来真美。她穿着一件无肩带的白色蕾丝晚装，拉链底下的紧身胸衣勾勒出纤细的腰身，玲珑有致，甚是惹眼。脸上淡白色的蜜粉衬得肌肤泛出古铜色的光泽，身上的香味浓得好像混合了一整间香水店的芬芳。

我穿着一件花了四十美元买的黑色山东绸紧身小礼服。一知道自己成为纽约之行的幸运儿之一，我就动用了部分奖学金疯狂采购，这件小礼服就是其中的战利品。它的剪裁怪得很，里面完全穿不下任何款式的文胸，不过无所谓，反正我瘦得跟个小男孩一样，身材几乎没有曲线。而且，在这炎炎夏夜，我喜欢这种几近赤裸的感觉。

可是，这城市让我小麦色的皮肤褪了色，使我看起来黄得像个中国人。照理说我应该为穿着和奇怪的肤色感到紧张不安，但和朵琳在一起让我忘掉了这些担忧。我觉得自己无比睿智，无所畏惧。有个男人向我们走来，他穿着蓝色格纹衫、黑色斜纹棉布裤，脚上是一双雕有图案的牛仔皮靴。先前他就站在路边一间酒吧外的条纹遮阳篷下，瞧着我们的出租车。我没有产生一丝绮想，因为我清楚地知道他是为朵琳而来。他穿过拥堵的车阵，往我们敞开的车窗上一靠，魅力十足。

“冒昧相问，值此良宵，两位漂亮姑娘为何独自搭车？”

他咧着一口大白牙，露出牙膏广告般的笑容。

“我们正要去参加派对。”我脱口而出，因为身旁的朵琳突然沉默得像根柱子，恹恹地拨弄着白色蕾丝的皮包罩套。

“听起来挺没劲的。”男人说，“何不跟我到那边的酒吧喝两杯？我还有几个朋友在那儿等着呢。”

他朝遮阳篷底下那几个衣着随意、姿态慵懒的男人点点头。一见他回头瞧了一眼，一直看着他的几个人轰地笑了。

那笑声本该让我警觉，那是一种低沉的、自以为是的窃笑。偏偏此时车阵出现移动的迹象，我知道如果继续坐在车里，不出两秒我就会后悔没有把握良机看看纽约的另一面，这可是杂志社悉心安排的行程里见不到的。

“怎么样，朵琳？”我问。

“怎么样，朵琳？”那男人也说，维持着他那大大的笑容。直到今天我也想不起他不笑的时候是个什么模样。我想他一定无时无刻不在笑。对他来说，那样的笑容必定是再自然不过的吧。

“那，好吧。”朵琳对我说。我打开车门，就在我俩下车时，出租车刚好徐徐开动。我们迈步走向酒吧。

突然传来一阵刺耳的刹车声，紧跟着是沉闷的砰砰的撞击声。

“喂！”我们那辆车的司机怒气冲冲地从窗口探出头，脸色铁青，“搞什么鬼啊！”

他的车停得太突然，后面那辆出租车猛地撞了上来，里面的四个姑娘被震得东倒西歪，正挣扎着爬起来。

四周喇叭声和喊叫声不绝于耳，和我们搭讪的那个男人哈哈大笑。他把我和朵琳留在路边，折返回去给司机塞了张钞票。然后，我们看见载着杂志社女孩的车鱼贯驶离，就像载满伴娘的婚礼车队。

“来吧，弗兰基。”那男人对着他的一个朋友说道。一个侏儒一样的矮个儿立刻迈步出列，跟着我们走进酒吧。

我真受不了弗兰基这类的男人。我只穿袜子都有五英尺十英寸高，所以和小个子男人在一起时，为了让自己看起来矮一些，我要稍稍弯腰驼背，把屁股往下撅，搞得一边高一边低，就像个又笨又残的跑龙套的。

有那么一会儿，我奢望会按照身高来配对，这样我就能跟最初前来搭讪的那个男人凑对，因为他起码有六英尺高。但是他看也不看我一眼，就与朵琳走在一起。我只好假装没瞧见贴在我肘边的那个弗兰基，紧挨着朵琳坐下。

酒吧里灯光昏暗，除了朵琳，我几乎什么也看不清。她的白发白衣衬得她整个人也是白的，看起来银光闪闪。我想她肯定是反射了酒吧里霓虹灯的光。我觉得自己融入了重重阴影中，变成了一张底片，而底片中的人我此生从未见过。

“那么，喝点什么呢？”那个男人带着大大的笑容问道。

“我想来杯老式的鸡尾酒。”朵琳对我说。

点酒我不在行。我连威士忌和杜松子酒都分不清，没一次点到自己真正喜欢的口味。巴迪·威拉德和我认识的其他大学生要么穷到买不起烈酒，要么根本不屑于喝酒。真想不到有那么多大学生不抽烟不喝酒，而这种人全让我给遇上了。巴迪·威拉德买的最烈的东西，就是一瓶杜本内葡萄酒，而此举不过是为了证明学医的他也有审美品位罢了。

“我来杯伏特加吧。”我说。

那男人深深地望了我一眼，问：“加点什么吗？”

“纯的就好。”我说，“我都喝纯的。”

我怕如果我说要加冰块、杜松子酒或其他什么，听起来会很蠢。我曾经看过一个伏特加广告，满满一杯伏特加置于随风飘舞的雪花中，在蓝色的灯光下澄净如水，所以我觉得来点纯的准没错。我的梦想就是有一天能点到一杯甘醇的美酒。

侍者走上前来，那个男人为我们四人点了酒水。他一身牧场上的打扮，却于这间充满都市感的酒吧中怡然自得，我猜他很有可能是个名人。

朵琳一言不发，只玩着她的软木杯垫，最后点了根烟。那男人似乎并不介意，只盯着她看，那样子就像动物园里的游客盯着白色的巨型金刚鹦鹉，等着它开口说人话。

酒送来了。我的伏特加果然像广告里那样澄澈纯净。

“你是做什么的？”我问那个男人，试图打破从四面八方涌来的浓密如丛林野草的沉默，“我是说，你在纽约做什么？”

他好像颇费了番力气才慢慢地将目光从朵琳的肩膀移开。“我是个DJ。”他说，“你可能听说过我。我叫伦尼·谢泼德。”

“我知道你。”朵琳突然开口。

“我很高兴你知道，甜心！”那男人说着突然大笑起来，“这样就方便多了。我的名气还真是大。”

接着伦尼·谢泼德意味深长地看了弗兰基一眼。

“那个，你们从哪儿来？”弗兰基猛地坐直了，问我，“叫什么名字？”

“这位是朵琳。”伦尼的手滑向朵琳裸露的胳膊，揽往了她。

我很惊讶，朵琳明知他的一举一动，却没有半点反应。她依然坐在那里，朦胧得好像一个身穿白裳、头顶漂白金发的黑人女子，在一片昏暗之中优雅地啜饮着。

“我叫艾莉·希金巴腾，”我说，“来自芝加哥。”瞎掰完这句我觉得安全多了。我可不希望今晚我所说或所做的一切会跟来自波士顿的我、真名实姓的我，扯上任何关系。

“好吧，艾莉，我们跳支舞如何？”

一想到要和这个脚蹬橘色小羊皮矮子乐增高鞋，上穿廉价T恤，外搭松垮蓝色运动外套的矮冬瓜跳舞，我就觉得可笑。要说有什么是我瞧不起的，那就是穿蓝衣服的男人。黑色或灰色，哪怕棕色都行，可蓝色只会让我发笑。

“我没心情。”我冷冷地转过身，猛地把椅子拉近朵琳和伦尼。

这两人看起来好像彼此已相识多年。每当朵琳用细长的银勺舀起杯底的大块水果凑近唇边，伦尼就呼呼地作势欲咬，像是条狗似的，要抢勺子上的水果。朵琳咯咯直笑，不停地舀起水果来吃。

我想，最终，伏特加是我要找的那款酒。它的滋味难以名状，跟任何东西的味道都不一样。喝下一口，直冲胃部，就像卖艺的人吞下了一柄剑，令我全身力量倍增，感觉自己像神一样。

“我还是走吧。”弗兰基说着，站起身。

我看不太清他的模样，这里太昏暗了，但我第一次听清了他那又尖又蠢的嗓音。没人理会他。

“喂，伦尼，你欠我东西。记住，伦尼，你欠我东西，能记住吗，伦尼？”

我觉得这很奇怪，弗兰基在我们两个完全陌生的人跟前提醒伦尼欠他东西。但他就是杵在那儿翻来覆去地说，直到伦尼伸手从口袋里抽出一大卷绿色的钞票，抽了一张递给他。我觉得那应该是十美元。

“闭嘴，滚吧。”

一时之间，我觉得伦尼这话也是对我说的。然后我听见朵琳来了句：“艾莉不去的话，我也不去。”我不得不佩服朵琳，把我的假名叫得那么顺口。

“噢，艾莉会去的。对吗，艾莉？”伦尼边说边对我使眼色。

“我当然会去。”我答道。弗兰基已经消失在夜色中，我只能跟朵琳牢牢拴在一起。我还想借此机会大开眼界呢。

我喜欢观察别人身处紧要关头时的反应。如果遇上车祸或街头打架，甚至是泡在实验室玻璃罐里的婴儿标本，我都会停下来看个仔细，把一切铭记于心。

要不是用这种办法，我不可能学到那么多东西。所以就算因此受到惊吓，或者恶心作呕，我也不动声色，反而假装自己一贯见多识广。

(1) 美国一服装品牌。

2

说什么我也不愿错失去伦尼家的机会。

他家的房子完全就像是一个牧场小屋，只是位于纽约市中心的公寓楼里。伦尼说他打掉了几堵隔墙，好让空间宽敞一些，然后在墙上钉了松木板，装了个特别的马蹄形松木吧台。我猜，地板也是松木的。

地上铺着一张张大幅的白色熊皮，唯一的家具是许多铺有印度毯子的矮床。墙上挂的不是画，而是一对对鹿角、水牛角和一个兔头标本。伦尼伸出拇指戳了戳这只看起来温顺的小灰兔的口鼻和硬硬的大长耳。

“在拉斯维加斯开车时碾到的。”

他走到房间另一头，牛仔靴踏出子弹出膛般的回声。

“音效来了。”他说，脚步声越来越小，直至他消失在远处的一扇门后。

忽然，房间的各个角落都响起音乐声。乐声乍歇之时，传来伦尼的声音：“我是您的午夜DJ，伦尼·谢泼德，为您带来的是流行音乐排行榜。本周榜单第十名，正是最近常常听到的那个黄毛小丫头所唱的那首……独一无二的《向日葵》！”

我生在堪萨斯，我长在堪萨斯，
等我结婚时，要嫁在堪萨斯……

“他可真会玩儿！”朵琳道，“你说呢？”

“可不是。”我说。

“对了，艾莉，帮我个忙。”她现在好像真把我当作了艾莉。

“没问题。”我说。

“别走，好吗？如果他搞什么花样，我怕没机会脱身。你瞧见他那身肌肉了吧？”朵琳咯咯笑着说。

伦尼突然从后面的房间冒出来。“我花了两万块搞的这间屋子里的录音设备呢。”他悠哉地走到吧台边，摆出三个玻璃杯、一个银色冰桶和一个大水壶，开始把好几种不同瓶子里的酒混在一起调酒。

……忠贞女孩，誓言等待——
向日葵之州的向日葵姑娘。

“很棒吧？”伦尼走了过来，端着三只酒杯。杯子外壁凝出汗滴一样的大水珠。他把杯子递给我们时，杯中的冰块叮当作响。音乐声戛然而止，我们听到伦尼的声音在宣布榜单第九名。

“什么都比不上听自己说话的感觉。”伦尼看着我说，“弗兰基闪人了，应该再给你找个伴。我给朋友打个电话。”

“没关系。”我说，“你不必麻烦了。”我想总不能说得那么直白，要求找个比弗兰基大上几号的人来吧。

伦尼看起来松了口气。“只要你不介意就好。我可不想怠慢了朵琳的朋友。”他对朵琳咧嘴一笑，露出满口白牙。“可以吗，甜心？”

他朝朵琳伸出一只手，无须言语，两人默契地跳起了吉特巴舞，他们的手里还握着酒杯。

我盘腿坐在一张矮床上，摆出一副既诚恳又冷淡的样子，我见过一些生意人在欣赏阿尔及利亚肚皮舞时就是这副模样。可是，当我往挂有兔子标本的墙上一靠，矮床却开始往房间中间滑动。我只好转而席地坐在熊皮上，背靠着矮床。

我的酒杯湿答答的，越喝越没劲，每抿一口，我都越来越觉得如饮死水。酒杯中间画有一条带黄色圆点的粉线。我喝到粉线下方约一英寸处，歇了一会儿，待我想再喝下一口时，融化的冰块让水面又涨到了粉线的位置。

伦尼的声音在屋里隆隆回响：“为什么，哦，为什么，我要离开怀俄明？”

就连两首曲子中间的空当，他和朵琳两人也没有停下舞步。我觉得自己收缩成了一个小黑点，陷在红红白白的地毯和松木板之间，像是地板上的一个洞。

看着别人成双成对、浓情蜜意，心里真不是滋味，尤其当你是房间里唯一多出来的那个人时。

这感觉就像乘着一列驶离巴黎的特快火车，你坐在最后一节车厢里，眼看巴黎变得越来越小，而你却觉得，是你自己变得越来越小，越来越孤单，以百万英里的时速远离这城市的灯火与繁华。

伦尼和朵琳不时撞在一起亲吻，然后各自旋转开，长饮一番后，再回到彼此的怀抱。我想我大可以在熊皮上先睡一觉，等朵琳想回旅馆时再起来。

就在这时，伦尼突然惨叫了一声。我连忙坐起身。朵琳正咬着伦尼的左耳垂不放。

“松嘴，贱人！”

伦尼弯下腰，朵琳便飞上了他的肩头，她手中的玻璃酒杯甩了出去，在空中画出一道长长的大弧线，砸在松木板上，发出铿啷的钝响。伦尼还在哀号着转圈，快到我都看不清朵琳的脸。

通常，你会注意的是别人眼睛的颜色，而我现下注意到的却是朵琳的乳房。她趴在伦尼的肩上疯狂转圈，双腿乱踢，放声尖叫，两颗如同饱满的褐色香瓜般的双乳从衣服中挣出来，悬垂微颤。然后，两人大笑着慢了下来，伦尼正试图隔着裙子去咬朵琳的屁股。此时，我决定走人，省得看见接下来将要发生的事情。我双手撑着楼梯栏杆，半走半滑到楼下。

踉跄地走到人行道上，我才意识到伦尼家开了空调。人行道上积蓄了一天的污浊的热浪迎面袭来，像是要让我饱尝今日最后的一场羞辱。我真不知道自己是在世界的哪个角落。

忽然，我有了搭出租车去派对的念头，但一转念又放弃了。舞会到这时已经散场了不说，我可不想一个人站在空空荡荡的大舞池，面对一地的五彩纸屑、烟蒂和皱巴巴的鸡尾酒纸巾。

我小心翼翼地走向最近的街角，指尖一路划过左侧的屋墙，免得摔倒。我看了看街名，从皮包里拿出纽约街道地图。我这里到旅馆正好是四十三个街区后转弯再走五个街区。

走路一向难不倒我。确定方向我就出发了，边走边低声数着走过的街区。回到旅馆大堂，我已醉意全消，只是双脚微肿，不过这全是我咎由自取，谁叫我懒得穿丝袜。

大厅空荡荡的，只有值夜班的人在亮着灯的小隔间里打盹，与那许多钥匙圈和沉默的电话机为伴。

我溜进自助电梯，按下我房间所在的楼层。电梯门像无声的手风琴，悄然闭合。我的耳朵感觉怪怪的，然后我看到一个人高马大、眼睛满是污垢的女人呆滞地盯着我的脸。当然，那只能是我自己。看到自己满脸细纹的憔悴模样，我吓了一跳。

走廊上连个鬼影都没有。我径直回房。房间里烟雾弥漫。起初我以为这无端冒出来的烟是对我的谴责，但随即想起先前朵琳在我房间抽过烟。我按下窗户上的抽风机的按钮。旅馆为了不让客人打开窗户、探出身子，把窗户都封死了，不知为什么这让我很恼火。

站在窗户左侧，把脸贴在木制窗框上，可以看见闹市区，看见黑暗中像绿色火星式怪蜂窝一样的联合国总部，看见马路上移动着的红红白白的光点，看见几座我不知道名字的桥上的灯火。

寂静让我情绪低沉。因为这不是万籁俱静的静，而是我自己的静。

我很清楚，车流喧嚣，车里和那些大楼亮着灯的窗后的人都在制造声音，就连河水都会潺潺作响，但我什么也听不见。这城市如海报般平铺在我窗前，闪闪发光，但想到它所带给我的一切，我倒宁愿它根本不存在。

床头那部瓷白色的电话能把我与外界联系起来，但此时它一声不响，静默如死人头颅。我使劲回想曾经把电话号码给过谁，好列出会给我打电话的人的名单，可想来想去，只能想到曾把电话号码给了巴迪·威拉德的母亲，由她交给她在联合国担任同声传译的朋友。

我轻轻地干笑了一声。

我能想象得出来威拉德太太要介绍给我的同声传译员是什么样的人。她一直都希望我能够嫁给巴迪。那年夏天，巴迪在纽约州北部的什么地方治疗肺结核，她甚至安排我去那里当女护工，免得巴迪太孤单。她和巴迪都无法理解我为什么不去疗养院，宁可去纽约市。

梳妆台上的镜子有点变形，且太过银亮，镜子里我的脸像是映在用牙医的水银做的球上一样。我想直接爬上床睡觉，但总觉得这样就像把一张书写潦草的脏兮兮的信纸塞进一个清爽干净的信封，所以我决定洗个热水澡。

人生肯定有很多事情是热水澡无法解决的，不过我知道的没几件。每次我难过得要死，紧张得睡不着觉，或者爱上一个整周也见不着面的人，我都会消沉到难以自持，然后我会告诉自己：“我要洗个热水澡。”

我在浴缸里沉思。水必须极烫，烫到几乎无法在水里立足。然后你一寸寸地没入水中，直到热水没过脖颈。

我记得我泡过的每一个浴缸上方的屋顶，记得那些屋顶的材质、裂缝、颜色、水渍和灯具。每个浴缸我也都记得：狮身鹰首式样支腿的老式浴缸，棺材形的现代浴缸，还有那个造型华美、可以俯瞰室内荷塘的粉色大理石浴缸。我甚至记得不同水龙头的形状和大小，以及各式各样的皂托。

泡在热水中的我，才是最真实的我。

躺在这个女士旅馆十七楼的浴缸里，高高在上，底下是喧闹熙攘的纽约。泡了近一个小时后，我觉得自己又恢复了纯净。我不相信洗礼或约旦河圣水一类的东西，但我想，热水浴之于我，就像圣水之于虔诚的教徒吧。

我喃喃低语：“朵琳消融了，伦尼·谢泼德消融了，弗兰基消融了，纽约消融了，一切都消融了，再也不重要了。我不认识他们，我从来也不认识他们，我很纯净。那些饮下的烈酒，那些眼见的腻吻，那些回旅馆途中落于我皮肤上的尘土，皆化作纯净之物。”

我在澄净的热水中待得越久，就觉得自己越纯净。当我最终踏出浴缸，用旅馆里柔软洁白的大浴巾包裹住自己时，感觉整个人纯净甜美，犹如新生儿一般。

不知睡了多久，我被敲门声吵醒。起初我没在意，因为敲门的人一直喊着：“艾莉，艾莉，艾莉，让我进去。”我不认识什么艾莉。然后另一种敲门声压过了刚刚那种沉闷的砰砰声，这是一种尖锐的嗒嗒声，还有另一个清脆得多的声音响起：“格林伍德小姐，你的朋友要找你。”我明白了，门外的是朵琳。

我把腿晃到地上，头晕目眩地花了一分钟才在黑乎乎的房内站稳身子。我很恼火朵琳吵醒了我。经过这么悲惨的一个夜晚，好不容易能睡个好觉摆脱出来，她却非得把我弄醒，毁了这一切。我心想，如果我装睡不理会，说不定敲门声会消失，还我个清静。但我等了一会儿，那声音就是不罢休。

“艾莉，艾莉，艾莉。”第一个声音咕哝不停，这时另一个声音也坚持不懈地嘶嘶响起：“格林伍德小姐，格林伍德小姐，格林伍德小姐。”两个不同的声音搞得我像是人格分裂了一样。

我打开房间的门，眯眼望向亮晃晃的走廊。感觉当下既非黑夜也非白天，而是某种可怕的第三种中间界，突然闯入黑夜与白天之间，绵延无休。

朵琳无力地靠在门框上。我一开门，她就瘫倒在我怀里。我看不见她的脸，因为她的头垂在胸口，硬邦邦的金发露出黑色发根，如草裙舞的流苏般垂下。

我认出那个身材矮胖、唇上有髭、穿着黑制服的女人是夜班服务员，常窝在这层楼狭促的工作间里熨烫客人的日常衣物和晚宴礼服。我不明白她是怎么认识朵琳的，还有她为什么不直接把朵琳悄无声息地送回房，而要帮她叫醒我。

她见朵琳靠在我的怀里，除了偶尔打个酒嗝外还算安静，就转身大步走回工作间，继续与她那台古老的胜家牌缝纫机和白色的烫衣板为伴了。她那种像老派欧洲移民一般严肃、勤劳、充满道德感的样子，让我想起了来自奥地利的祖母，我突然产生一股想要追上她的冲动，告诉她我和朵琳毫无瓜葛。

“让我躺下来，让我躺下来。”朵琳喃喃不停，“让我躺下来，让我躺下来。”

我觉得，如果把朵琳搀过门槛，让她进入我的房间躺在我的床上，我就再也摆脱不了她了。

她的身子温软如枕，靠在我的手臂上，将全身的重量都丢给我，一双细高跟鞋在脚下笨重地拖着。她这么重，我根本无法带着她穿过长长的走廊。

为今之计，我只能把她丢在门外的地毯上，然后关门落锁，上床睡觉。等她醒来，什么都不会记得，只会以为自己醉倒在我房门口，而在屋里睡觉的我对此一无所知。然后她就会自己爬起来，乖乖地回房睡觉。

我正要轻轻地把朵琳放在走廊的绿色地毯上，可她低吟着往前一扑，脱离我的手臂，一股褐色的呕吐物从她嘴里喷出，在我脚边聚成一摊。

突然之间，朵琳变得更重了。她的头冲着那摊呕吐物垂下，几绺金发浸入其中，活像沼泽地里的树根。我这才意识到她睡着了。我往后退。我自己也快睡着了。

那晚我做了一个和朵琳有关的决定。我决定，今后眼看着她，耳听着她，但内心里，我要和她分道扬镳，彻底分道扬镳，只把贝琪和她天真纯洁的朋友当作我真正的友人。本性上，我和贝琪才是一类人。

我默默退回房间，关上门，考虑了一下，没有上锁。我终究狠不下这个心。

翌日早晨，我在阴霾闷热的天气中醒来。我穿好衣服，用冷水拍了拍脸，涂了点口红，慢慢地打开房门。我想，我还是期待看见朵琳的躯体躺在那摊秽物里，像我龌龊本性的一个丑陋而具体的证明。

走廊上空无一人。地毯从这头延展到那头，干干净净，鲜绿如常。只有一片不规则的模糊污迹留在我的房门口，仿佛有人不小心在那儿洒了杯水，但又轻轻地把它弄干了。

3

在《淑女生活》的宴会桌上，摆着对半切好、中间填满蟹肉和蛋黄酱的黄绿色鳄梨，还有一盘盘烤得半熟的嫩牛排和鸡肉冷盘，不时端上的雕花玻璃碗里盛满了黑色的鱼子酱。刚好那天早上我没时间到旅馆的自助餐厅吃早饭，只喝了杯煮过头的咖啡，苦得要死，这会儿正饥肠辘辘。

来纽约之前，我还没在像样的餐馆吃过饭。我和巴迪·威拉德之类的朋友去的豪沃·强森餐厅当然不能算数，那里只能点点炸薯条、奶酪汉堡和香草刨冰。也不知道为什么，我就是热爱食物胜过一切。而且不管怎么吃，我都不发胖，十年来体重始终不变，只有一次例外。

我喜欢满是黄油、奶酪和酸奶油的食物。在纽约，我们和杂志社的同事以及来访的名人一起吃了很多免费的午餐，所以我养成了一个习惯：拿到手写的大菜单后，一定要把这些连一小碟豌豆配菜都开价五六十美分的菜单浏览一遍，挑出最丰盛、最昂贵的菜品，点它一大串。

带我们出去的这种应酬通常可以报销，所以我点得心安理得。我很上道，总是吃得很快，免得那些为了减肥只敢点主厨沙拉或葡萄柚汁的人久等。我在纽约遇到的每个人几乎都在拼命减肥。

“我谨代表《淑女生活》欢迎各位才貌双全、青春洋溢的女士，本社能够认识诸位，实在深感荣幸。”发福又秃头的主持人对着衣襟上的小麦克风呼哧呼哧地说道，“今天的宴会，是《淑女生活》的‘食品检测厨房’部门专为欢迎各位而准备的，聊表诚意。”

现场响起淑女特有的优雅而疏落的掌声。随后大家于铺有亚麻桌巾的大桌前纷纷落座。

杂志社共有十一个女孩赴宴，指导我们的编辑也大多一同出席。《淑女生活》“食品检测厨房”部门的员工一律穿着洁白的卫生罩衫，头罩发网，脸上是标准的蜜桃派色的无瑕妆容。

我们这群女孩也只来了十一人，因为朵琳不见了。出于某种原因，他们把她的座位安排在我旁边，而那张椅子就那么空着。我帮她把席位卡保留了下来——所谓席位卡，就是一小面镜子，顶端以花体写着“朵琳”，镜边上一圈霜状雏菊，框住中间银色的镜面，那里会照出朵琳的脸。

朵琳那天和伦尼·谢泼德在一起。她现在一有空就和伦尼·谢泼德腻在一起。

《淑女生活》是一本大型女性杂志，以豪华全彩的跨页美食图为特色，每月还推出不同的主题和场所。杂志社主办的这场午宴开始前一小时，工作人员先带着我们参观了好几间光可鉴人的厨房，让我们见识了在强光下拍摄不断融化的苹果派冰激凌有多难，他们不得不用牙签从后面撑住冰激凌，要是化得太厉害了就得赶紧换。

眼见每间厨房里的食物都堆积如山，我觉得头晕眼花。倒不是因为在家没吃饱，而是我的祖母通常只会煮便宜的大骨肉和肉糜。她还有个习惯，在我们叉起第一口食物送到嘴边时，总是会说：“但愿你们喜欢吃，这东西一磅可要四十一美分呢。”这么一来，我觉得自己吃下去的不是星期日烤肉，而是一分一分的硬币了。

当大家都站在各自的椅子后面听欢迎辞时，我低下头偷偷地觑着一碗碗的鱼子酱。有一碗就刚好摆在我和朵琳的空位之间。

我盘算着，对面的女孩应该够不着这碗鱼子酱，因为餐桌中间堆满了小山一样的杏仁味水果造型软糖，而我右侧的贝琪总是那么客气，如果我把鱼子酱挪到我手肘边的面包碟旁，让她拿不到，她肯定不好意思要我分给她。况且，有一碗鱼子酱就摆在她邻座女孩的右侧不远处，她可以吃那一碗。

我和祖父之间有个常说的笑话。我的祖父在家乡附近的乡村俱乐部当领班，每周一休假，所以每个周日祖母都会开车去接他回家，弟弟和我交替陪着祖母。不论是谁去，祖父总会把我们当作俱乐部的常客，为我们端上周日大餐。他喜欢介绍我吃些特别的珍馐美味，所以我九岁时就养成了对冷奶油浓汤、鱼子酱和鳀鱼泥的狂热的爱好。

这个常说的笑话就是，祖父保证在我的婚宴上我可以吃鱼子酱吃到饱。之所以说它是个笑话是因为我压根没想过结婚，而且就算我哪天真的结婚了，祖父也无力提供那么多的鱼子酱，除非他洗劫乡村俱乐部的厨房，偷走一整个手提箱的鱼子酱。

在水杯、银器和骨瓷餐具的觥筹交错声的掩护下，我用鸡肉片铺满盘子，然后像在面包片上抹花生酱一样，在鸡肉上面厚厚地盖上一层鱼子酱。接着，我用手拿起一片片鸡肉，把鱼子酱分毫不漏地卷在里面，放进嘴里。

我多次为各种汤匙的用法绞尽脑汁，后来却发现，即使在餐桌上举止不当，只要表现出倨傲的态度，仿佛自己做得无可挑剔，那么你就没事了，没有人会认为你举止失仪或没有教养。人们只会觉得你独树一帜，聪明有趣。

这一招是我从一位著名诗人那儿学到的。那天，杰·茜带我与他共进午餐。在那间满是喷泉和吊灯的高级餐厅里，其他男士都身着深色西装和洁白的衬衫，唯独他上身穿着一件难看、笨重、带斑点的棕色斜纹软呢夹克，里面搭配红蓝格子的敞领运动衫，下身穿一条灰色裤子。

这位大诗人一边徒手抓起一片一片沙拉当中的菜叶子吃着，一边跟我谈论着自然与艺术的对立。看着那苍白而又粗短的手指，拈着湿淋淋的生菜，一片接一片，在沙拉碗和嘴巴之间来来回回，我简直挪不开眼睛。可是，这番粗野之举并未在餐厅里引来讪笑或私语，这位诗人把用手抓沙拉吃变成了一件再自然而合理不过的事。

我的座位附近没有《淑女生活》的工作人员，或是我们杂志的编辑，亲切友好的贝琪似乎对鱼子酱没有兴趣，所以我的信心愈发足了。吃完了第一盘冷鸡肉卷鱼子酱，我又如法炮制了第二盘。接着又消灭了鳄梨和蟹肉沙拉。

鳄梨是我最喜欢的水果。以前每个周日，祖父都会带一颗鳄梨给我，藏在公文包的下层，上面盖着六件脏衬衫和周日版漫画。他还教我吃鳄梨的法子：用炖锅把葡萄果酱和法式沙拉酱熬煮成深红色的酱汁，再把酱汁盛入鳄梨的中空部分。我对那酱汁产生了一种乡愁似的思念。相较之下，鳄梨蟹肉沙拉尝起来已是索然无味。

“皮草秀好看吗？”我问贝琪，此时我已不再担心有人跟我抢鱼子酱了。盘子上残留着最后几粒咸咸的黑色鱼卵，我用汤匙刮了下来，舔个干净。

“很棒。”贝琪笑答，“他们还教我们如何用貂尾和金链子制作多用途的围巾。那种金链子在伍尔沃斯百货商店就可以买到一模一样的，只要一美元九十八美分。皮草秀一结束，希尔达就直奔批发皮草的仓储商店用超低折扣价买了一堆貂尾。然后她又去了伍尔沃斯买金链子。坐在来这儿的公交车上，她就把貂尾和金链子缝成围巾了。”

我觑了眼希尔达。她坐在贝琪的另一侧，果然披着条看起来很贵的貂尾围巾，用一根垂着的金链子系着。

我并不太了解希尔达。她足有六英尺高，绿色的大眼睛，眼角上斜，厚厚的红唇，带着斯拉夫人特有的茫然表情。她会做帽子，跟着时尚编辑见习，所以她与拿笔杆的朵琳、贝琪和我这类姑娘比较疏远，即便有时我们只是写写健康和美容方面的内容，那也是专栏。我不知道希尔达是不是文盲，但她做的帽子很棒。她就读于纽约的一所制帽专科学校，每天见习时戴来的新帽子全出自她的巧手，以稻草、皮毛、缎带或颜色难以捉摸的薄纱制成。

“真厉害。”我说，“厉害。”我开始想念起朵琳来。她要是在这儿，一定会跟我咬耳朵，毒舌揶揄希尔达那条宝贝围巾，逗我开心。

我变得情绪低落。早上杰·茜已经撕下了我的假面具，现在之前那些令人难受的自我怀疑都一一应验，事实再也无法隐瞒。十九年来，我不断追逐着一个又一个的好成绩、奖项、奖学金，而今我想要放慢脚步，彻底退出这样的人生竞赛。

“你怎么没和我们一起去看皮草秀？”贝琪问。我隐约觉得她是在问第二遍，就在一分钟前她才问过我同样的问题，只是我没有认真听。“你和朵琳出去了吗？”

“没有。”我答道，“我想去看皮草秀的，但是杰·茜打电话来，要我去趟办公室。”其实我压根没打算去看秀，但是我努力说服自己，我是想去的，这样一来，就能让杰·茜做的事真正伤害到我。

我跟贝琪说，早上我躺在床上就想着去看皮草秀的事。但我没告诉她，早前朵琳来我房间，说：“干吗去看那傻帽的秀啊，伦尼和我要去科尼岛，你干吗不一起来？伦尼会给你安排一个棒小伙子。反正这顿午宴和下午的电影首映已经把一天给毁了，没人会在意我们的。”

一时之间，我还真有点动心。皮草秀听起来当然很无聊，而且我向来对皮草没兴趣。可是，最终我还是决定赖床，赖到心满意足，再去中央公园，在有鸭子戏水的池塘附近的光秃荒野中，找片杂草最长的地方，躺上一天。

我告诉朵琳，我不去皮草秀，不去午宴和首映会，但我也不去科尼岛，我只想躺在床上。朵琳走了之后，我在想，为什么我不再像以前一样为该做的事勇往直前。想到这里，我顿生悲情倦意。然后我又想，为什么我不能像朵琳一样，不顾一切去做不该做的事。这个念头让我更加悲颓且疲惫。

我不知道当时是几点了，只听得外面走廊满是女孩们喧闹叫喊的声音，她们正准备出发去看皮草秀。不久，走廊归于宁静。我躺在床上，凝视着空荡荡的白色天花板，阒寂愈发膨胀，似乎要胀破我的耳膜。此时，电话响了。

我定定地瞅着电话不动。听筒在骨白色的电话机上微颤，我看都看得出来，它是真的在响。我想，大概是自己在舞会或派对上把电话号码给过谁，之后又忘了个一干二净。我拿起听筒，开口说话，声音沙哑但还听得下去。

“喂？”

“我是杰·茜。”杰·茜果决无情的声音传来，“你今天是不是刚好要来办公室？”

我倒回床上，我真不明白，为什么杰·茜会认为我要去办公室。我们都领到了那种油印卡纸，这样就能清楚所有的活动，我们很多上午和下午都不会在办公室，而是去城里参加各种各样的活动。当然，有些活动并非非去不可。

停了好一会儿，我才小心翼翼地回了一句：“我今天打算去看皮草秀。”我当然不想去看什么秀，但是除此之外找不出什么好借口。

“我跟她讲了，我想去看皮草秀。”我对贝琪说，“可她还是要我去办公室，说要和我谈谈，还有些活儿要我做。”

“哦——哦！”贝琪很是同情。她一定看见我的泪珠簌簌滚落，滴落在我面前那盘蛋白糖饼和白兰地冰激凌里，因为她把她那份没动过的甜点推给了我。我吃完了自己那份后，开始心不在焉地吃她的那份。在她面前掉眼泪，我觉得有点不好意思，但这些泪水都是货真价实的。杰·茜对我说了一些很可怕的事情。

约莫十点钟的时候，我没精打采地走进办公室。杰·茜起身，绕过她的桌子，关上门。我坐在我办公桌前的旋转椅上，面向她。她坐在她桌子后方的旋转椅上，面向我。她背后的窗边摆满了盆栽，一架子又一架子，欣欣向荣，像个热带花园。

“埃斯特，这里的工作你不感兴趣？”

“啊，有兴趣，我有兴趣的。”我说，“我对这份工作很感兴趣。”我很想喊着说出这几句话，仿佛这样会更有说服力，但我还是忍住了。

这十几年我一直告诉自己，我的人生理想就是疯狂地学习、读书、写作和工作。事实似乎确实如此，我样样做到最好，门门功课拿A，一路所向披靡地跨进大学的门槛。

我是镇公报的校内通讯记者，一份文学刊物的编辑，还担任备受肯定的校园惩戒会的秘书——这个机构负责处理学生在校内外的违规和惩处事宜。有位享誉诗界的女教授力荐我到东部最大的大学的研究生院深造，还允诺我全额奖学金。如今，我正跟随这家知性时尚杂志社里最好的编辑学习。但我像匹拉货的蠢驴，除了犹疑畏怯，我还干了什么？

“我对这里的每件事都很有兴趣。”这话从我嘴里蹦出来，好似一堆木头做的硬币，落在杰·茜的桌面上，空洞而单调。

“很高兴听你这么说。”杰·茜的语气略显尖刻，“你要明白，如果你卷起袖子好好干，在杂志社的这一个月你能学到很多东西。之前坐你位子的那个女孩，完全不理会那些时尚秀展，从这间办公室离开后，直接进了《时代》杂志社。”

“天！”我的声音还是死气沉沉的，“速度真快！”

“当然了。你还有一年才毕业。”杰·茜的语气略有缓和，“你毕业后想做什么？”

我心里一直希望能拿到一大笔奖学金读研究生，或者争取公费留学欧洲，然后成为教授，再出几本诗集；或是出几本诗集，然后当个编辑什么的。这些计划我早已有之，张口就能说出。

“我不太确定。”我听到自己这么说。当我听见自己这么说时，吓了一大跳，因为话一出口我就知道确实如此。

这话听起来很真实，而我也承认这一点。就像有个很难形容的人在你家门口徘徊良久，有一天突然上前说他才是你的生父，你俩长得极像，那一刻你知道他果真是你的父亲，而那个你叫了一辈子父亲的人，其实是个冒牌货。

“我不太确定。”

“这样下去，你会一事无成。”杰·茜沉吟片刻，“你会哪几种语言？”

“哦，我懂一点法语，我还一直想学德语来着。”我跟人说想学德语，说了有五年。

我的母亲小时候来了美国，结果一战期间因为说德语，在学校被同学扔石头。我的父亲在我九岁时去世了，他来自普鲁士王国黑色心脏地带的一个令人躁郁癫狂的小村庄，也说德语。我最小的弟弟德语说得像母语一样流利，此时正在柏林参加国际生活体验营。

我没说出口的是，每当我拿起德语字典或德语书籍时，那些密密麻麻、如带刺铁丝般的字母一跃入眼帘，我的脑袋就像蚌壳一样，闭得严丝合缝。

“我一直想进入出版业。”我设法找回一些线索，好让我像从前一样推销有术。“我想，毕业后我会去应聘一些出版社。”

“你应该学好法语和德语。”杰·茜毫不留情，“或者还要再学几门外语，西班牙语和意大利语——俄语最好也要学。每年六月都有数以百计想要成为编辑的女孩涌入纽约，你得比那些平庸之辈多点本事才行。最好多学几种语言。”

我没胆子告诉杰·茜，大学的最后一年我根本挤不出时间来学外语。我选修了一门教人如何独立思考的优等生荣誉课程，一门研究托尔斯泰和陀思妥耶夫斯基的课，还有一门高级诗歌创作研讨课，其他时间都要花在写詹姆斯·乔伊斯作品的晦涩主题的论文上。我还没选定论文主题，因为我还没读过乔伊斯的那本《芬尼根守灵夜》，但是教授对我的论文寄予厚望，还答应给我些提示，帮助我理解这部大作里那对双胞胎所代表的意象。

“我会尽我所能。”我告诉杰·茜，“也许会去报一个他们开设的那种适合双重需要的基础德语速成班。”当时我觉得自己还真可以这么做，因为我有办法说服班主任为我破例，她一向把我当成某种有趣的试验品。

物理和化学是我大学里的必修课。我已经修完了植物学，而且成绩优异，一整学年下来，我没有答错一道题。有一阵子我甚至心血来潮，想当一名植物学家，研究非洲的野生禾本科植物或者南美的雨林。因为研究冷门领域中的奇怪主题，比去意大利研究艺术或去英国研究英语文学，更容易获得大笔补助，毕竟前者少了很多竞争。

植物学挺好的，因为我喜欢切碎叶片，把它们放在显微镜下观察，也喜欢画出面包上的霉菌和蕨类植物繁殖周期中出现的奇异心形叶子。对我来说，这些东西都很真实。

至于物理，上课的第一天就要了我的命。

曼基先生，矮小黝黑，嗓门很高，口齿不清，穿着紧绷的蓝色西装，手里拿着颗小木球，站在教室的前端。他先把小木球放在一条带凹槽的陡斜滑道上，让它一滚到底，说若以a为加速度，以t为时间，然后，他突然开始龙飞凤舞地书写，黑板上一堆的字母、数字和等号看得我只想死。

我把物理课本带回宿舍。这本大部头以吸墨性良好的油印纸装订而成——足足四百页全是图表和公式，一张插图或照片都没有——封面和封底是砖红色的硬皮。这本教材是曼基先生的大作，专门用来跟大学女生讲解物理学，如果我们能读得懂，他就打算正式出版。

好吧，我研读公式，乖乖听课，盯着那些球滚下滑道，期待下课铃声。就这么撑到期末，多数女生都不及格，我得了全A。我听见曼基先生对一群抱怨物理太难的女生说：“不难，应该不会太难。有个女生从头到尾都拿了A。”“是谁？快说。”她们追问，但他摇摇头，什么也没说，只对我露出“你知我知”的迷人微笑。

这让我萌生了逃掉下学期化学课的念头。拼死拼活拿了物理课的全A，我算是学怕了，拿起物理书我就反胃，我受不了它把一切都浓缩成字母和数字。黑板上出现的不是缤纷各异的叶片形状，叶片呼吸气孔的放大图，叶红素和叶黄素之类可爱的词汇，而是曼基先生特有的红色粉笔书写的蛇蝎公式，每个字母都面目可憎、艰涩难辨。

我知道，化学会更要命，因为我在化学实验室见过一张列了九十几种化学元素的巨大周期表，表里的金、银、钴、铝等美好的词汇皆被缩写成不同的丑陋的符号。若再为这些东西绞尽脑汁，我肯定会发疯，彻底垮掉。上学期的物理课，我耗尽全部的意志力才勉强撑过去。

于是，我心生一计，去找班主任。

我的借口是，我需要时间选修一门莎士比亚的课程，毕竟我的专业是英语。班主任和我都知道，化学我也能拿全A，既然如此，参加考试有什么意义？何不让我抛开分数和学分，只需旁听就好？这是有荣誉感的人才会想到的荣誉问题，因为内容重于形式嘛，明知会拿A，成绩只是个没有意义的形式罢了，对吧？我的这番论点又借着学校的一条新政而更具说服力：我这届之后的大二学生取消了选修理科的要求，也就是说，我们这届是旧规定的最后受害者。

曼基先生完全同意我的说法。我那么喜欢上他的课，甘愿放弃学分和全A的功利考量，只求旁听课程，体会化学之美，他对此一定极为满足。我真是天才，才能想出把学分用来修莎士比亚，但依然坚持旁听化学课的妙招。看似多此一举，却恰恰让人觉得我对化学无法割舍。

当然，要不是我的物理成绩先拿到A，这一招也不会奏效。如果班主任知道我有多害怕多沮丧，冥思苦想到狗急跳墙，差点要出绝招了——比如找医生开证明，说我不适合上化学课，一见公式我就头晕之类的——她一定一秒都不愿听我废话，不管三七二十一要逼我修这门课。

如我所愿，教务委员会批准了我的请求。事后班主任告诉我，有好几位教授深为感动，将之视为我智识成熟的一大表现。

想到接下来半年的日子，我就忍不住要发笑。我一周上五次化学课，雷打不动。曼基先生站在朽旧摇晃的阶梯大教室的底部，把试管里的东西倒来倒去，生出红红蓝蓝的火焰和黄色的烟雾。我当他的声音是远处的蚊子叫，摒除在耳外，往椅背上一靠，欣赏着绚烂缤纷的火焰，写下一页页的十九行诗和十四行诗。

曼基先生不时看我一眼，见我奋笔疾书，便抛来一个赞赏有加的笑容。我猜他必定以为我抄下了所有公式，不像其他女生一样是为了考试，乃是被他的课堂所深深吸引而情不自禁的缘故。

4

我不知道当我身处杰·茜的办公室时，脑海中怎么会浮现成功逃避化学课这件陈年往事。

在杰·茜和我说话的当口，我看见曼基先生仿佛是从魔术师的帽子里变出来的一样，从她的脑后腾空而起，手里拿着他的小木球和试管。在复活节假期前一天，他的试管里冒出了大量的黄烟，还散发出一股臭鸡蛋的气味，把全班女生和他自己都逗得大笑不已。

我觉得对不起曼基先生，很想诚心诚意地跪下来恳求他原谅我这个大骗子。

杰·茜递给我一叠小说手稿，语气缓和了许多。接下来的整个早上，我都在读那些小说，并把感想用打字机打在部门间联系专用的粉色备忘纸上，然后拿到贝琪所属的编辑部，好让她明天一来就可以看到。杰·茜不时插进话来，和我聊几句工作实务或者八卦。

那天，杰·茜要和一男一女两位著名作家共进午餐。男作家刚刚出售了六篇短篇小说的版权给《纽约客》杂志，还有六篇给了杰·茜。我很惊讶，从不知道杂志社也会六篇六篇地买进小说，而想到六篇小说所带来的收入，我就更不淡定了。杰·茜说这顿饭她得吃得很小心，因为桌上的女作家也写小说，但是作品从来未曾刊行在《纽约客》上，过去的五年里杰·茜也只采用过她的一篇小说。席间，杰·茜得小心翼翼，不可拜高踩低，既要恭维那位知名的男作家，又得留心不能伤害了名气稍逊的女作家。

当法式壁钟上的小天使上下挥动翅膀，把手上的镀金小喇叭举到唇边，一连吹出十二个短促的音符时，杰·茜终于对我说差不多了，我可以去参加杂志社安排的《淑女生活》杂志社的午宴和电影首映会活动了，还有，她希望明天一早就能在办公室看到我。

说完，她在淡紫色的衬衫外披上西装，戴上一顶缀有人造紫丁花的帽子，迅速地在鼻翼补了点粉，扶了扶厚重的眼镜。她模样看上去很糟糕，却又显得非常睿智。离开办公室时，她用戴着淡紫色手套的手拍了拍我的肩。

“别让纽约这个鬼地方把你给毁了。”

我静静地在转椅里坐了几分钟，脑子里想的全是杰·茜。我试图想象如果我成了名编辑伊·吉，拥有一间办公室，摆满盆栽橡胶树和非洲堇，秘书每天早上负责浇水，那会是什么感觉。真希望有个像杰·茜一样的母亲，这样我就知道该何去何从了。

我的亲生母亲没什么用。自打我父亲去世，她靠着教速记和打字养活一家人。私底下她讨厌这份工作，也恨我的父亲，他因为不相信保险业务员，死后没给我们留下任何保险理赔的遗产。尽管如此，她总是念叨着，要我大学毕业后学速记，让我除了大学文凭之外还有一技之长。“就连耶稣的门徒也会搭帐篷。”她说，“他们也得过日子，是人都一样。”

《淑女生活》的女招待收走我面前的两个空冰激凌杯，并放下了一碗温水，我在水里洗了洗手指，然后用还算干净的亚麻餐巾仔细地擦干净。接着，我折好餐巾，放在双唇之间，精准一抿，将餐巾展回桌上，我看见一个模糊的粉红唇印绽放在餐巾正中，宛若一颗小小的心。

我想起这一路走来，真是漫长又艰辛。

第一次见到洗指钵，是在我的奖学金女赞助人家里。学校奖学金办公室里那个满脸雀斑的小个子女人告诉我，按照学校的惯例，只要提供奖学金的人还健在，我们这些得奖者就要给他们写信致谢。

我拿到的是费罗米娜·吉尼亚设立的奖学金，她是位富有的小说家，二十世纪初就读于这所大学。她的第一部小说被改编成默片，由贝蒂·戴维斯主演，另外改编的广播剧到现在仍在播放。如今她还健在，而且就住在我祖父工作的乡村俱乐部附近的一栋大宅子里。

于是，我给费罗米娜·吉尼亚写了封长信，用炭黑色的墨水写在印有凸印的红色校名的灰色的信纸上。我告诉她骑车上山看到的秋叶是多么美丽；告诉她比起住在家里每日乘公交车往返去城里的学校读书，住在校园里是多么舒服惬意；告诉她知识的大门正在为我敞开，也许有朝一日我也能如她一般写出伟大的作品。

我曾在镇图书馆读过吉尼亚夫人的一本书——不知何故，我们大学图书馆竟没收藏她的作品——这书里从头到尾全是冗长悬疑的问句：“伊芙琳会发现格拉迪斯以前就认识罗杰吗？赫克特急切地思忖着。”“既然唐纳德知道艾尔茜这孩子被罗尔默夫人带到偏僻的乡下农场藏了起来，他怎么还能娶她呢？葛莉谢尔达对着月光下凄凉的枕头问道。”这些书帮费罗米娜·吉尼亚赚进了数百万美元，可她后来告诉我，大学时期的她其实很笨。

吉尼亚夫人给我回了信，邀我到她家吃午饭。就是在那里，我第一次见到洗指钵。

钵里漂浮着几朵樱花，我以为这是某种日式饭后清汤，就喝得一滴也不剩，包括那脆爽的小花。吉尼亚夫人当时什么也没说。直到很久以后，我跟一个在大学里认识的初入社交界的上流年轻女孩聊起那顿饭，才知道自己出了多大的糗。

走出《淑女生活》灯火通明的办公室，我们才发现街上因为下雨而灰蒙蒙的，冒着烟气。那不是洗净尘埃的绵绵细雨，而是我想象中巴西才会有的雨。一滴滴如咖啡杯托大小的雨珠从天而降，打在火热的人行道上，嘶嘶声一片，黑亮的混凝土路面蒸腾起团团水汽。

站在《淑女生活》那道活像玻璃打蛋器的旋转门前，我独自在中央公园消磨一下午的小算盘就这样落空了。我冲过温暖的雨水，钻进出租车昏暗、微颤的洞穴中，同车的还有贝琪、希尔达和艾米莉·安·奥芬巴克。艾米莉个头娇小，举止拘谨，红头发在脑后盘成髻，在新泽西州的提涅克住着她的丈夫和三个孩子。

电影乏善可陈。主演之一是个长得很像琼·艾丽森的金发美女，但我肯定不是她；另一个黑发女主角长得很性感，像伊丽莎白·泰勒，可惜也是冒牌货；还有两个虎背熊腰、榆木脑袋的男性角色，名字叫瑞克和吉尔之类的。

这是一部跟足球有关的彩色爱情片。

我讨厌彩色电影。里面的每个人好像每个场景都非得换一件大红大紫的新衣服，把自己搞得像晾衣架一样，背景也总是大绿的森林、大黄的麦田、大蓝的海洋，向四面八方无尽绵延，一英里又一英里。

电影的大部分场景都发生在足球场的看台上，两个女孩穿着时髦，翻领上有卷心菜大小的橙色菊花，又是挥手又是加油；要不就是在舞池里，打扮得像《乱世佳人》里的风格，和男伴翩翩起舞。可一旦走进化妆室，两人就恶语相向。

最后我算是看明白了，那个金发美女终将赢得足球小子的青睐，而性感的黑发女孩却一无所获。因为那个叫吉尔的家伙只想玩玩，压根不想结婚，他已经买好飞往欧洲的单程票，正收拾行李准备离开。

电影看到这里，我开始觉得怪怪的。我看向四周，看着那一排排全神贯注的小脑袋，它们的正面都笼罩着同一片银光，后面覆盖着同一片阴影，看起来活像一堆中了月魔咒语的蠢人。

我觉得自己快吐了。不知道是因为电影太烂看到我胃疼，还是因为吃了太多的鱼子酱。

“我要回旅馆了。”在半黑的电影院里我对贝琪耳语。

贝琪正盯着银幕，看得如痴如醉。“你不舒服吗？”她几乎没动嘴唇地低声问我。

“对。”我答道，“我难受死了。”

“我也不舒服。我和你一起回去。”

我们起身离开座位，一路说着“借过”“借过”“借过”经过整排的人，他们不得不挪开雨靴和雨伞，好让我们通过。尽管引来沿途抱怨和嘘声一片，但能踩的脚我一个也不放过，因为只有这样才能转移我想吐的注意力，那种翻涌的感觉强烈到像一颗快速膨胀的气球，我已无暇他顾。

走到街上时，温热的雨水还在纷纷扬扬地落下。

贝琪看起来有点吓人，红润的两颊忽变苍白，一脸发青地冒着汗。路边停着几辆黄格子的出租车，每次当你犹豫着要不要打车的时候，总能看见它们。我们浑身发软地坐上一辆，回旅馆的路上我吐了一次，贝琪吐了两次。

出租车司机弯拐得很急，后座上的我俩被甩得东倒西歪。每次谁想吐时，就默不作声地弯腰，假装捡东西，另一个则哼着歌曲假装看向窗外。

即便这样打掩护，还是被司机看穿了。

“喂！”他闯过一个刚刚变红的信号灯，抗议道，“不许吐在我车里，要吐到街上去吐。”

我们没应他，而他估摸着我们快到了，也没真把我们赶下去，车子很快停在了旅馆大门口。

我们没敢等司机提出加价的要求，赶紧塞了一堆硬币到他手里，并往呕吐物上盖了几张纸巾，就慌忙跑过大厅，冲进空无一人的电梯。幸好，这个时间是全天最清静的时候。电梯里面，贝琪又觉得难受，我便托住她的头；然后又轮到我难受了，她来托住我的头。

通常大吐过后，人会立马舒服很多。我们彼此拥抱，互道晚安，然后走向长廊两头各自的房间，准备好好躺一躺。一起吐过的人最容易结为患难之交，此言不虚。

可是等我关上房门，脱掉外衣，爬上床后，却觉得更难受了，好像非得去趟厕所不可。我费力套上那件有蓝色矢车菊图案的白色睡袍，踉踉跄跄地走向公用厕所。

贝琪已经在里面了，我听见她在门后痛苦地呻吟。所以我急忙绕过转角，走向另一侧的厕所。好远啊，我要死在半路上了。

我坐在马桶上，头抵在洗脸池的边缘，觉得吐出来的不只是晚餐，还有我的五脏六腑。恶心感像巨浪般，一波波席卷而至。每一波消退时，我虚脱得像湿透的叶片不停地颤抖，很快下一波又汹涌而至。我如同身处刑讯室，折射着冷光的白瓷砖，从脚下，从头顶，从四面八方逼近，要把我挤成碎片。

不知在厕所里待了多久，我起身拔掉水槽的塞子，打开水龙头。冷水哗哗地流出来，经过的人会以为我在里面洗衣服。确定自己安全了，我伸开四肢躺在地上，一动不动。

好像不再是夏天了。我能感觉到冬天的寒意让我从牙齿冷到骨头缝里，浑身发颤，垫在头下的旅馆里的大白毛巾也仿佛冻成了一个雪堆。

是谁在拍打厕所的门？这样用力，真是没礼貌。他们完全可以学我，绕过拐角，去另一个厕所，这样我就清静了。可那个人就是砰砰敲个不停，求我开门，让他们进去。我觉得那个声音很熟，听起来像是艾米莉·安·奥芬巴克。

“等一下。”我费力挤出的声音浓滞得像糖浆。

我强打精神，爬了起来，第十次按下冲水马桶，把水槽冲洗干净，卷好毛巾，不让呕吐物的痕迹过于明显，然后打开门，走了出去。

我知道，要是我此时看向艾米莉·安或其他人，肯定会撑不住的，所以我只敢盯着走廊尽头一扇摇摇晃晃的窗户，无力地向前迈出一只脚。

接下来，一只鞋子出现在我眼前。

大号的黑皮鞋，正对着我，有褶痕，又旧又黯，鞋头布满扇形小气孔。鞋子好像立在什么绿色坚硬的物体表面上，这东西把我的右颧骨压得生疼。

我躺着不动，等着出现什么线索，告诉我接下来该怎么做。鞋子左侧不远的白色地面上，有许多蓝色的矢车菊，看得我直想哭——这是我身上睡袍的袖口，袖口尽头苍白如鳕鱼的，正是我的左手。

“她没事了。”

我的头上响起冰冷而理性的声音。起初我没觉得那声音有什么不对，可再一想，便觉得不对劲。这是男人的声音，而这间旅馆不论白天黑夜都不准男人入内。

“还有多少人？”这个声音继续说道。

我用心听着。身下的地板很坚实，不错。反正已经砸在地上了，想到自己不会再往下坠，我顿时感觉安心了。

“十一个吧。”一个女人的声音答道。我猜她就是那只黑鞋的主人。“应该有十一个，但是有一个不在，所以目前只有十个。”

“好，你扶这个到床上去，我来照顾剩下的。”

我的右耳听到渐行渐隐的咚咚声，远处有开门声，有人说话，有人呻吟，然后门又关上了。

两只手伸入我的腋下，那个女声说：“来，来，好孩子，我们快到了。”我感到我被扶起来，一扇扇门从身边经过，最后我们来到一扇敞开的门边，走了进去。

我床上的被单已经打开，那女人扶我躺下，拉起被单盖到我的下巴，然后坐在床边的扶手椅上休息了一会儿，不停地拿一只丰满的粉色手掌给自己扇着风。她戴着镀金边的眼镜和白色护士帽。

“你是谁？”我的声音听起来很虚弱。

“我是旅馆的护士。”

“我怎么了？”

“食物中毒。”她简洁地说，“你们所有人都中毒了。我从没见过这样的事。这个病，那个倒的。你们这些小姐到底都吃了什么？”

“其他人也都病了吗？”我抱着一丝希望。

“你们所有人。”她别有意味地肯定，“个个都跟病猫似的喊着要妈妈。”

整个房间都温柔地绕着我转，连桌椅和墙壁都仿佛同情我突然生病一样，变得轻飘飘的。

“医生给你打了一针。”护士走到门口，“好好睡一觉吧。”

房门如一张白纸取代了她站立的位置，接着，一张更大的白纸又取代了房门的位置。我飘向那张大白纸，微笑着沉沉入睡。

有人端着只白色的杯子站在我的枕边。

“喝了吧。”声音响起。

我摇摇头，枕头窸窣作响，像团干草。

“喝了会舒服些。”

一只厚厚的白瓷杯送到我的鼻下。在不知道是黄昏还是晨晓的薄光中，我打量着面前清澄的琥珀色液体，上面浮着一层油脂，闻起来有一股淡淡的鸡肉香。

我的眼睛试探地看向杯子后面的裙子。“贝琪。”我叫道。

“什么贝琪。是我。”

我抬起眼帘，窗格子前衬出朵琳头部的剪影，窗外的光线照亮她的发梢，形成一圈金色的光晕。她背对着光，我看不清她的表情，但可以感觉她的指尖传来一种老练的温柔。她可能是贝琪，或我的母亲，或一个散发着蕨类植物清香的护士。

我低头抿了口肉汤，我想我的嘴一定是沙子做的。我再呷了一口，一口接一口，直到杯子见底。

我觉得自己被净化了，神圣得似要迎接新生。

朵琳把杯子放在窗台上，坐进扶手椅。我很惊讶地发现，她这个老烟民居然没掏出烟来抽。

“知道吗，你差点儿就没命了。”她终于开了口。

“我猜都是鱼子酱的问题。”

“才不是鱼子酱！是蟹肉。他们化验过了，里面全是肉毒胺。”

我的眼前浮现出《淑女生活》的巨大厨房，洁白神圣，漫无边际。一个个填满蟹肉和蛋黄酱的鳄梨，在强光之下很是上镜：厚厚的蛋黄酱里伸出鲜美诱人、粉色斑驳的蟹钳肉，盛在淡黄色的鳄梨杯中，边缘镶着一圈鳄绿色的果皮。

全是毒。

“谁化的验？”我想象着医生从某人的肚子里抽出点东西，拿到旅馆的实验室里分析化验。

“《淑女生活》的那些老家伙。你们一个接一个跟保龄球似的倒下去，马上就有人给办公室打了电话，办公室又打给了《淑女生活》，有人就来把中午那顿大餐剩下的所有东西拿去化验了个遍。哈！”

“哈！”我空洞地应和着。朵琳又回到了我身边，真不错。

“他们送来了礼物赔罪。”她补充道，“就在走廊外面的大纸箱里。”

“怎么这么快？”

“特快专递啊，不然你以为呢？难道要等你们四处嚷嚷，说吃了《淑女生活》的大餐后中毒？他们可担不起。万一你们刚好认识某个精明的律师，一纸诉状，他们就得赔得分文不剩。”

“礼物是什么？”我忽然想，如果礼物够好，我就不介意食物中毒一事了，因为一番折腾下来，我竟然感觉纯净如新。

“箱子还没打开呢，姑娘们全都病倒了。我得一个个送汤去，因为只有我还站着。这不，第一碗汤给了你。”

“看看礼物是什么吧。”我恳求道，又想起了一件事，“我也有礼物要给你。”

朵琳走出去，我听到她窸窸窣窣忙了一阵子，又听到撕纸的声音，最后她拿着本厚厚的书回来了，光亮的封面上印着许多人名。

“《年度最佳短篇小说三十篇》。”她把书搁在我腿上，“外面纸箱里还有十一本。我想他们是希望你们病中有书可看，不至于太无聊。”她顿了一下，“你给我的礼物呢？”

我从手提包里摸出一面镜子递给她，上面有朵琳的名字和雏菊图案。朵琳看着我，我也看着她，我俩忍不住扑哧一声都笑了。

“你要的话，我的汤也给你。”她说，“他们搞错了，在托盘里放了十二碗。之前伦尼和我等雨停的时候吃了太多热狗，现在我是一口东西也吃不下了。”

“拿来。”我说，“饿死我了。”

5

次日早上七点，电话铃响了。

睡得昏天黑地的我慢慢清醒过来。梳妆镜上已经插了一封来自杰·茜的电报，她为坏掉的蟹肉表示遗憾，让我不用急着上班，好好休息一天，彻底恢复再说。既然如此，我想象不出会是谁打的电话。

我伸手拽过听筒，放在枕头上，听筒说话的那头搁在我的锁骨上，听声的那头靠在我肩膀上。

“你好？”

一个男人的声音传来：“是埃斯特·格林伍德小姐吗？”我听出他略带外国口音。

“当然。”我答道。

“我是康斯坦丁……”

我没听清他的姓氏，只听到很多“斯”和“克”的音。我不认得什么康斯坦丁，但不忍心直言。

接着，我想起了威拉德太太和她要介绍给我的那位同声传译员。

“哦，你好！”我大声说道，连忙起身，双手拿起电话。

我从来都不相信威拉德太太真的会介绍一个名叫康斯坦丁的人给我认识。

我喜欢名字有趣的男人。之前我认识一个叫苏格拉底的，个子挺高，虽然其貌不扬但颇有学识，是好莱坞某个著名希腊裔电影制作人的儿子，只可惜他是天主教徒，我们俩之间没戏。除了他，我在波士顿工商管理学院还认识一个叫阿提拉的白俄罗斯人。

聊了几句，我明白过来，康斯坦丁想约我今天见个面。

“下午想不想来看看联合国总部？”

“我能看到联合国总部。”我带着点小兴奋，笑着说。

他似乎有点窘。

“从我房间窗户就可以看到啦。”我想是不是我的英文说得太快了。

静默了一会儿。

他终于开口：“或许参观完后，你能赏脸吃顿便饭。”

觉察到这是威拉德太太惯用的口气，我的一颗心沉入谷底。威拉德太太一开口就是，请你吃顿便饭。我想起这位仁兄初来美国时曾到威拉德太太的家中做客——她信奉这样一种做法：你把家门向外国人敞开，等你出国时，他们也向你敞开家门。

现在我明白了，威拉德太太只不过是把她在俄罗斯做客的机会换成我在纽约的一顿便饭而已。

“好啊，我们吃顿饭吧。”我冷冷地说，“你几点到？”

“大概两点，我开车去接你。是亚马逊女士宾馆，对吧？”

“对。”

“好，我知道在哪儿。”

一时之间，我觉得他话里有话，可转念一想，可能只是住在这间旅馆里的某些女孩正好在联合国总部当秘书，而他又曾经约过其中的一个。我让他先挂电话，然后我也挂断，闷闷不乐地躺下。

我的老毛病又犯了，幻想着一个男人对我一见钟情的浪漫画面，其实不过是我无中生有、自作多情。人家只是略尽地主之谊，带我逛逛联合国总部，然后再吃块三明治罢了！

我努力打起精神。

也许威拉德太太介绍的同声传译员又矮又丑，到头来一样被我瞧不起，就像我瞧不起巴迪·威拉德一样。这么一想，我心满意足了。因为我的确瞧不起巴迪·威拉德，虽然在他离开肺结核疗养院后，所有人依然认为我会嫁给他，但我知道，就算天下的男人都死光了，我也不会选他。

巴迪·威拉德是个伪君子。

当然，起初我不知道他是个伪君子时，还觉得他是我所见过的最好的男孩。我在远处暗恋了他五年，他连瞧都没瞧我一眼。然后他开始注意到我，而我也依然爱慕他，那真是一段美好的时光。可就在他越来越关注我的时候，我却偶然发现他虚伪得可怕。最后变成了现在这个样子：他想娶我，我却恨透了他。

最糟糕的是我不能对他实话实说，因为没等我来得及说，他就得了肺结核。所以我只好事事迁就他，等他康复后能承受我的大实话的时机到来。

我决定不去楼下的自助餐厅吃早饭，因为要下楼就得穿戴整齐。既然我要赖床一个早上，还费那个劲干什么？我本可以打电话到楼下，让人送份早餐上来，可要是那样的话就得付小费给送餐的人，我一直都不知道该给多少合适。来纽约之后，我已经有过几次给小费的不愉快经历了。

我入住亚马逊宾馆那天，有个穿服务生制服、矮小、秃顶的男人又是帮我把行李提进电梯，又是帮我打开房门。一冲进房间，我只顾着欣赏窗外的风景，过了一会儿才意识到他还在房里。他拧开洗脸台上的冷热水龙头，说“这是热水，这是冷水”，还打开收音机告诉我纽约每个电台的名称，搞得我很不舒服，只好背对着他，坚定地说：“谢谢你帮我提行李。”

“谢谢谢谢谢谢。哼！”他讽刺的语调听起来真是恶心。我还没来得及转身看他有什么不对劲的，他就粗鲁地甩上门，走了。

后来，我跟朵琳说起他的怪异举止，她才告诉我：“你这傻瓜，他在跟你要小费呢。”

我问该给多少，她说至少二十五美分，如果行李太重就给三十五美分。其实我本来要自己把行李提到房间里的，只是那个服务生实在太积极了，我才让他帮忙的。我还以为这种服务包含在房费里。

我讨厌花钱请人做我自己轻松就可以办到的事，这让我很不舒服。

朵琳说小费一般是消费金额的百分之十。可是我手头总是没有刚好的零钱，我总不能傻兮兮地给人家五十美分，再跟他解释：“你的小费是十五美分，请找给我三十五美分。”

第一次在纽约搭出租车，我给了司机十美分小费。车费是一美元，所以我想十美分刚刚好。递给他十分硬币时，我面带微笑，还颇有些得意。可他盯着掌心里的硬币看了又看，搞得我担心是不是不小心拿错了，给了他加拿大的硬币。见我要下车时，他开始嚷嚷：“小姐，你要吃饭，我也要吃饭，大家都要吃饭啊！”那嗓门奇大，吓得我撒腿就跑。幸好，他被红灯拦了下来，否则恐怕他会一路开车跟着我，吼得我尴尬万分。

我跟朵琳问起这件事，她说小费很有可能自她上次来纽约之后从百分之十涨到了百分之十五。要不然就是那个出租车司机太贪心。

我伸手去拿《淑女生活》的人送来的书。

刚一打开，一张卡片掉了出来。卡片正面是一只穿着花睡衣的狮子狗，苦着张脸坐在狗篮里。打开卡片，那只狮子狗在狗篮里微笑着睡着了。卡片上方有一条刺绣横幅，写着：“多多休息，才能早日康复。”卡片底部有人用淡紫色的墨水留言：“祝早日康复！《淑女生活》全体好友敬上。”

我草草翻阅着一篇篇小说，直到最后看到一个关于无花果树的故事。

一片绿草地上，一个犹太男子的家和一座修女院毗邻而居，两所房子中间长着一棵无花果。犹太男子和一个黝黑美丽的修女因采摘成熟的无花果，常常在树下见面。有一天，两人发现枝头鸟巢里有颗即将孵化的小蛋，就在他们看着雏鸟啄壳而出时，两人的手背碰到了一起。那天起，修女就再也不来和犹太男子一起摘无花果了，取而代之的是修女院厨房里那个长相凶恶、信奉天主教的女仆。两人每次摘完果子后，她还要清点数目，确定犹太男子摘的没她多，把男的给气坏了。

好美的故事，尤其是那棵冬天覆盖着皑皑白雪、春天缀满绿色果实的无花果树。读到最后一页，我十分不舍，真想像翻越篱笆围墙一样爬进字里行间，安眠在美丽、翠绿的大无花果树下。

在我看来，巴迪·威拉德和我就好比故事里的犹太男子和修女，虽然他不是犹太人，我也不是天主教徒，而都是一神派的信徒。我们在想象的无花果树下相遇，可惜见到的不是雏鸟破壳，而是婴儿诞生，一桩坏事接踵而至，令我们分道扬镳。

我躺在旅馆的白色大床上，孤独，虚弱，觉得自己身处阿迪伦达克山区的疗养院，感觉糟透了。巴迪的信中说，他正在读一位诗人的诗，这位诗人还是名医生，并且他还发现某位已故的俄罗斯著名短篇小说家也是医生。所以，或许医生和作家这两种身份本就相得益彰。

现在的巴迪·威拉德变了很多，跟过去两年我们逐渐熟悉时的论调大不相同。我记得有一天，他笑着问我：“埃斯特，你知道诗是什么吗？”

“不知道，是什么？”我说。

“一粒尘埃。”他对自己有这样的深度颇为得意，而我只是盯着他的金发、蓝眼和白牙——他的牙又长又坚固——应了一声：“大概是吧。”

直到一年后，我身处纽约市中心，才想到当时可以怎么反驳他。

我常在心里和巴迪·威拉德进行假想的对话。他比我大两岁，很有科学条理，所以总能证明自己说得对。跟他在一起时，我必须时刻绷紧神经，以免被他说得哑口无言。

我在心里想象跟他的交谈多是以我俩真正的对话为开头，但是结尾的部分，我不再呆坐着说“大概是吧”，而是对他展开了尖锐的反驳。

这会儿，我躺在床上，想象着巴迪说：“埃斯特，你知道诗是什么吗？”

“不知道，是什么？”我说。

“一粒尘埃。”

就在他得意地扬起嘴角时，我会说：“那么被你解剖的尸体是尘埃，被你治愈的病人也是尘埃。他们是尘中之尘，埃中之埃。我觉得一首好诗远比一百个低到尘埃里的人加起来还要历久弥新。”

被我这么一顶，巴迪肯定会语塞，因为我说的都是实话。人，不过是尘埃做成的，在我看来，医治尘埃如何能比得上写诗？一首好诗，可以让人铭记，可以让人在伤心、病痛或失眠的时候反复吟咏。

问题在于，我把巴迪·威拉德说过的每句话都奉为至高无上的真理。我想起他第一次吻我的那晚。那是在耶鲁大三学生的舞会后。

巴迪邀请我去参加那舞会的方式非常奇怪。

那年圣诞假期，他突然跑到我家，一身白色的翻领厚毛衣，帅得我挪不开眼。他说：“哪天我去学校看你，怎么样？”

我非常吃惊。我们平时在学校念书，只有周末回家去教堂做礼拜时才能远远地打个招呼。我实在不明白，他怎么会想到跑来找我——他的解释是，他把我家和他家之间的这两英里路程当作越野练习。

诚然，我们的母亲是好友，她们一起上学，都嫁给了各自的教授，还定居在同一个城镇，但是巴迪总是秋天拿着奖学金去上预备学校，或者夏天在蒙大拿处理松树的疱状锈病赚钱。总之，就算我们的母亲是同窗好友，对我们之间的感情也没什么用。

那次突然造访过后，巴迪便没了音讯。直到三月初一个明媚的星期六早晨，我在学校宿舍为下周一关于十字军东征的历史考试做准备，正当我埋首于隐士彼得和穷汉瓦尔特的史料中时，走廊上的电话响了。

一般情况下，大家是轮流负责接电话的。但是鉴于整层楼只有我一个新生，高年级的学姐们多半要我去接。我等了一会儿，看有没有人先我一步，但随即想到大家可能都去打壁球或度周末了，所以只得自己去接电话。

“埃斯特，是你吗？”楼下值班的女孩在电话里问道。我说是，她便接着说：“楼下有位男士找你。”

我听了大吃一惊，因为那年相亲认识的男孩中，没有一个再打电话约过我。我就是运气不好。现在我都痛恨相亲了：每周六晚上，手心冒汗、小鹿乱撞地下楼，让某位学姐介绍她阿姨的闺密的儿子给我，结果却发现对方长得像个白蘑菇，还有一对招风耳，要不就是大龅牙，或者腿脚不便。我可不认为我只配得上这种人。虽然我是个书呆子，只知道埋头苦读，但起码我好手好脚啊。

唉，可我还是梳了头，抹了点口红，拿上历史书下楼去了——如果来找我的人太烂，我就借口说我正要去图书馆。来的人居然是巴迪·威拉德。他穿着卡其色的拉链夹克，蓝色粗棉裤，磨损的灰色球鞋，倚着寄信的桌子对着我笑。

“我只是来跟你打个招呼。”他说。

我觉得太反常了，他竟然大老远从耶鲁来到这里——而且据他说，为了省钱，他还是一路搭便车来的——就为了跟我打个招呼。

“嗨。”我说，“我们去外面门廊坐坐吧。”

我想去门廊，因为值班的学姐很八卦，她正好奇地打量着我，那样子显然认为巴迪会喜欢我绝对是犯了重大错误。

我们并排坐在两张藤制摇椅上。阳光明媚，宁静无风，甚至有点儿热了。

“我待不了几分钟。”巴迪说。

“哦，别这样，留下来吃午饭吧。”我说。

“呃，不行。我是陪琼来参加大二舞会的。”

我觉得自己是天下头号大笨蛋。

“琼还好吗？”我冷冷地问道。

琼·吉林和我们来自同一个镇，我们上同一个教堂，她比我高一届。她可是个风云人物——班长，主修物理，校曲棍球冠军。她鹅卵石色的眼睛盯住你便不放，一口墓碑形状的牙齿闪闪发亮，说话时带着喘息声，这一切都让我觉得浑身难受。此外，她的体形壮硕如牛。我开始觉得巴迪品味真差。

“哦，说到她。”他说，“早在两个月前，她就要我参加这个舞会，她妈妈还问我妈妈，我愿不愿意当她的舞伴。我能怎么办？”

“既然你不想陪她去，为什么要答应呢？”我刻薄地问。

“我喜欢琼啊。她从不在意你有没有为她花钱，而且她喜欢户外活动。上次她来耶鲁参加周末宿舍开放日，我们一起骑车去东岩玩，她是唯一不用我帮忙推车上山的女孩。琼很不错。”

我嫉妒得浑身发冷。耶鲁是我宿舍楼里所有学姐周末最爱去的地方，而我从没去过。我决定对巴迪·威拉德死心。没有了期望，自然就不会失望。

“你该去找琼了。”我以一种实事求是的口吻说道，“我的约会对象随时会出现，他不会乐意看见我和你坐在一起。”

“约会对象？”巴迪一脸惊讶，“他是谁？”

“有两个。”我答道，“隐士彼得和穷汉瓦尔特。”

巴迪一言不发，所以我接着说：“这是他们的绰号。”

我随即又补上一句：“他们来自达特茅斯。”

我猜巴迪从来都没有好好读过历史，因为他惊得张口结舌。他从藤制摇椅上愤而起身，还多此一举地猛推了它一把，然后把一个印有耶鲁校徽的浅蓝色信封扔在我大腿上。

“我本来打算，如果你不在，就把信留下。信里有个问题，你写信回答我吧。我不想现在问你。”

巴迪走后，我打开了信，信中他邀请我参加耶鲁的大三舞会。

我欣喜若狂，尖叫了好几声，一边冲进宿舍楼，一边喊着：“我要去我要去我要去！”从门廊外的耀眼日光中走进宿舍楼的我一时不能适应，只觉得眼前一片漆黑，什么也看不清，但我发现自己已经抱住了值班的学姐。当她听明白有人邀请我去参加耶鲁的大三舞会，立刻对我刮目相看。

奇怪的是，这件事之后，宿舍楼里的情况也有所改观。同一层的学姐开始和我说话，有时还很主动地接电话，再也没人在我的门前冷嘲热讽，说有些书呆子只知道读书，白白浪费了大学的黄金时光。

然而，到了舞会那天，巴迪从头到尾待我如普通朋友或家里的表妹。

跳舞时，我们之间隔着有一英里远。直到《友谊地久天长》的乐声响起，他突然把下巴靠在我的头顶，似乎很疲惫。半夜三点，我们顶着寒风，在漆黑的夜里慢慢走了五英里，从舞会返回我借住的人家。我睡的是客厅里五十美分一晚的沙发，虽然太短，好歹能省点钱；大部分有正式床铺的房间要两美元才租得到。

我闷闷不乐，无精打采，幻想尽数破灭。

我原本想着那周末巴迪会爱上我，这样接下来一年我都不必发愁如何打发周六晚上的时光。快到我借住的地方时，巴迪说：“咱们去化学实验室吧。”

我惊讶万分。“化学实验室？”

“对。”巴迪拉起我的手，“化学实验室后面的景色很美。”

果然，实验室后面有一个小山包，站在上面可以看见纽黑文市的零星灯火。

巴迪忙着在崎岖的地面上站稳脚跟，我假装欣赏夜景。他突然俯身吻我，我睁大双眼，想将错落的灯火印入脑海，这样我就永远不会忘记这一刻。

良久，巴迪从我唇边退开。“哦！”他说。

“哦什么？”我惊讶地问。这个干吻了无激情，而且因为在冷风里走了五英里，我俩的嘴唇都干裂了，真是郁闷。

“哦，吻你的感觉真棒。”

我很知时宜地不发一语。

“我猜，你和不少男生约会过。”巴迪说。

“呃，算是吧。”我觉得我的表现很像是这一年的每周都和不同男生约会才有的样子。

“唉，可我得花很多时间读书。”

“我也是。”我急忙说，“总得保住奖学金嘛。”

“不过，我应该可以想办法，每三个礼拜和你见一面。”

“好啊。”我快要乐晕了，迫不及待想回到学校，把这事昭告天下。

在屋前的台阶上，巴迪又吻了我。第二年秋天，他拿到了医学院的奖学金，我没再去耶鲁，改去医学院看他。就是在医学院，我发现这些年他是如何愚弄了我，发现了他是一个多么可怕的伪君子。

在目睹婴儿诞生的那一天，我发现了真相。

6

我一直求巴迪带我看看医院里有趣的东西。在一个周五，我翘掉了所有的课，去医学院和他度个长周末，而他让我大饱眼福。

首先，我穿上白大褂，坐在高凳上，看着巴迪和他的朋友解剖四具尸体。这些尸体没有半点人形，所以我一点都不怕。他们全都硬邦邦的，皮肤像皮革，泛着紫黑色，还散发着一股陈年泡菜缸的味道。

之后，巴迪带我去了一个大厅，那里的大玻璃罐里装着还没出生就夭折的胎儿。第一个罐里的胎儿头颅又大又白，低垂在只有青蛙大小的蜷曲的身体上。第二个罐子里的胎儿稍大一些；第三个罐子里的更大；最后一个罐子里的几乎和正常婴儿一般大小，他似乎在看着我，露出一抹贪心的微笑。

我很自豪自己能这么冷静地看着这些令人毛骨悚然的东西。只有一次我吓得跳起来，当时为了看清巴迪解剖一具尸体的肺部，我把胳膊肘靠在这具尸体的肚子上。过了一两分钟，手肘传来烧灼感，我突然想到这具尸体还是温的，不会没死透吧？这个念头吓得我低声惊叫了一下，赶紧跳下凳子。巴迪解释说，烧灼感来自浸泡尸体的药水，我才又坐回凳子上。

午饭前一小时，巴迪带我去听了场关于镰状细胞贫血症的讲座，其中还讲到一些让人听了很低落的重疾。几个病人坐着轮椅被推上讲台，被问了几个问题，又被推回去，接着放彩色幻灯片。

我记得有张幻灯片上是个笑得很灿烂的美丽女孩，她脸上有颗黑痣。“这颗痣出现二十天后，她就死了。”医生说。现场静默了一分钟，随即下课铃响起，所以我到现在都不知道那颗痣是什么，那女孩又是怎么死的。

下午，我们去看接生婴儿。

我们先来到医院走廊上一个专门放亚麻用品的橱柜旁，巴迪从里面拿出一个白色口罩给我戴上，还取了些纱布。

一个高高胖胖的医学生，身材壮得像席尼·格林史崔(1)，一直在旁边闲逛，看着巴迪拿纱布一圈一圈缠住我的头，直到我的头发被完全盖住，只有双眼露在白色口罩外面。

这个医学生露出惹人嫌的窃笑。“你妈还会爱你。”他说。

我没马上反应过来他在侮辱我，因为我满脑子都在想这家伙胖成这样真不幸，尤其还是个年轻人，哪个女人受得了贴着他的大肚腩亲他啊。等我回过神，想对这个自以为是的家伙狠狠回敬一句“只有当妈的才会爱肥仔”时，他已经走了。

巴迪正在察看墙上的一个奇怪木牌，上面有一排孔洞，洞口大小从一枚银币到餐盘不等。

“很好，很好。”他对我说，“这会儿正好有人要生了。”

产房门口站了一个清瘦且驼背的医学生，巴迪认识他。

“嗨，威尔。”巴迪说，“谁负责接生？”

“我。”威尔沉郁地答道。我注意到他高耸而苍白的额头上冒出一颗颗小汗珠。“我负责。这是我第一次接生。”

巴迪告诉我，威尔现在三年级了，必须接生八个婴儿才能毕业。

接着，他注意到走廊远处一阵忙乱，走来几个穿着柠檬绿的衣袍、戴着手术帽的男医生和几名护士，他们步伐凌乱地推着一辆担架车，上面躺着一个巨大的白色隆起物。

“其实你不该看的。”威尔在我耳边嘟囔，“看了你就永远不想生孩子了。他们真不该让女人看这个，否则人类会绝种。”

巴迪和我笑了。他们握了握手，我们三人走进产房。

看到产妇被抬上分娩台，我震惊得说不出话来。分娩台就像恐怖的刑台，一头是指向空中的金属镫，另一头是各种我不认识的工具、电线和管子。

巴迪带着我站在窗户旁，产妇就在几英尺外，我们看得一清二楚。

产妇的肚子隆起老高，我完全看不见她的脸和上半身。她整个人好像蜘蛛，只剩一个硕大的肚子，以及踏在高耸脚镫上的两条丑陋的小细腿。整个分娩过程，她都在发出野兽似的嘶喊。

稍后巴迪告诉我，产妇用了麻药，不会记得这些痛苦。她处于半昏迷的状态，诅咒呻吟完全是无意识的，她根本不知道自己在做什么。

我猜，这种药一定是男人发明的。这个女人承受着极度的痛苦，每一丝她都感受得到，否则她怎会哀号得如此凄惨。可是转头一回到家，她又要开始制造下一个宝宝，因为这药让她忘了分娩有多么痛。然而，在她心里的某个秘密角落，那痛苦犹如一道没有出路的漆黑长廊，等着开启的时机，然后将她再次吞噬。

负责指导威尔的主治医生一直对产妇说：“往下用力，杜莫利罗太太，用力啊，好样的，用力。”终于，在她两腿之间，那片刮了毛还被消毒药水染红的缝隙间，一团黑乎乎的东西冒了出来。

“那是胎儿的头。”巴迪在产妇的哀吟声中悄声对我说。

但是不知为何，胎儿的头被卡住了，主治医生告诉威尔，他必须在产妇下身剪一刀。剪刀在产妇的肌肤上大嘴一合，就像剪布一样简单，鲜血立刻汩汩而下——红得刺目鲜亮。下一瞬间，婴儿忽的一下就落在了威尔的手中，浑身发蓝，冥王星的那种蓝，裹着一层白白的东西，还挂着些血丝。威尔不停地说：“我抓不住他了，我抓不住他了，我抓不住他了。”声音充满惊恐。

“不，你能抓住。”医生说着，从威尔手里接过婴儿，开始按摩，蓝紫色逐渐消退，婴儿开始扯着嗓子哇哇号哭。我看出是个男孩。

婴儿才缓过来，就一泡尿滋在医生的脸上。稍后我问巴迪怎么会这样，他说这类事虽不常见，但还是有可能发生的。

婴儿一出生，产房里的人就分成两组：护士忙着给婴儿的小手腕戴上金属铭牌，用棉花棒给他擦眼睛，再裹好襁褓放进帆布小床里；医生和威尔则开始用针和长线缝合产妇的切口。

我好像听到有人说：“是个男孩，杜莫利罗太太。”但女人没有回应，连头都没抬。

“嗯，感觉如何？”巴迪和我穿过绿意盎然的中庭，一起回他的宿舍路上，他带着满足的表情问我。

“很棒。”我说，“这种事我天天看也没问题。”

我不想开口问他女人还有没有其他的生产方式。我莫名地觉得，最重要的是清醒地看着婴儿从自己的肚子里生出来，确定那是你的宝贝。既然横竖都得受罪，不如清醒着承受。

我常在脑海中想象着这样的画面：当一切痛苦都结束后，刚刚饱受分娩的折磨的我在产台上用手肘撑起身子，尽管面色惨白，素颜朝天，但嘴角忍不住笑意，脸上洋溢着幸福的笑容，长发垂到腰际，伸手轻抚我的第一个小宝贝，看他微微蠕动，轻唤他的名字。

“婴儿身上为什么糊着一层白乎乎的东西？”我问了个问题好让谈话继续下去。巴迪说那是保护婴儿皮肤的蜡状物。

巴迪的宿舍让我觉得像是修士的房间，光秃秃的墙，光秃秃的床，光秃秃的地板，桌上堆满了格雷的《解剖学》和其他令人望而生畏的大部头书。回到屋，巴迪点了根蜡烛，开了瓶杜本内红葡萄酒，我们俩并肩斜靠在床上。巴迪啜饮着红酒，我则拿起随身带来的诗集，开始朗诵《我未曾去到的远方》等诗篇。

巴迪说，诗一定有奇妙之处，才会使像我这样的女孩不可自拔。所以，每次见面时我都念几首诗给他听，再说说我对这些诗的感受。这是巴迪的主意。他总是把我们的周末安排得满满当当，这样我们就不会后悔虚掷了光阴。巴迪的父亲是老师，我想巴迪也很适合当老师，因为他常常对我解说事理，让我接触各种新知。

我念完一首诗后，他突然开口：“埃斯特，你见过男人吗？”

从他的语气里，我听出他指的不是一般意义上的男人，而是裸体的男人。

“没有。”我说，“只见过雕像。”

“那，你想不想看看我？”

我不知道该怎么回答。这阵子，我的母亲和外婆开始不停地暗示我，说巴迪·威拉德是多俊朗的好孩子，出身也是清清楚楚的好人家，又说教会里的人都认为他是模范青年，对父母、长辈恭爱有加，而且体格健壮，才貌双全。

真的，听来听去都是巴迪多好，多正派，多值得女孩为他守身如玉。所以，我想，巴迪做什么都无害吧。

“嗯，好吧，我想看。”我说。

我看着巴迪拉下斜纹棉布裤的拉链，脱下裤子，放在椅子上，然后脱下了内裤，内裤看着上去是某种尼龙网眼布材质的。

“这种内裤很凉快。”他解释道，“我妈说洗起来也容易。”

然后，他就这么赤条条地站在我面前，我也就这么直愣愣地瞅着。我唯一能想到的竟是火鸡脖子和火鸡胗，真是令人非常沮丧。

我的沉默不语似乎伤了巴迪的心。“我想你该习惯这样的我。”他说，“现在，让我看看你吧。”

那一刻，我忽然觉得，在巴迪面前脱光衣服，就像在学校里拍的站姿全身照，你不得不裸体站在相机前，心里很清楚，这些正面或侧面的全裸照片将会出现在学校的体操档案里，按照身体的挺拔程度被评为A、B、C或D。

“那什么，改天吧。”我说。

“好吧。”巴迪穿上衣服。

我们亲吻和拥抱了一会儿，我感觉好了一些。饮尽剩下的红酒，我盘腿坐在巴迪的床尾，向他要了把梳子，把头发梳向前盖住脸，不让巴迪看。我突然问他：“你和别人好过吗，巴迪？”

也不知怎么鬼使神差，反正这话就这么从我嘴里冒了出来。我从没想过巴迪·威拉德会跟别的女孩在一起过，所以我希望他会说：“没有，我一直洁身自好，等着新婚之夜把完整的自己留给像你这样纯洁的女孩。”

但是巴迪不发一语，反而红了脸。

“喂，到底有没有？”

“你所谓的和别人好过是什么意思？”巴迪问我，声音空洞。

“你知道的，就是你和别人上过床吗？”我继续一下一下有节奏地梳着头，盖住靠近巴迪的侧脸，略带静电的发丝拂上我滚烫的双颊，我只想大喊：“别，别说，不要告诉我，什么都别说。”但我忍住了，静静地梳着头。

“呃，对，我有过。”巴迪终于回答。

我差点儿跌下床。从巴迪·威拉德吻我，还说我一定和许多男生约会过的第一夜起，他就让我觉得，我比他更懂得性，比他更有恋爱经验。他对我的一切亲昵举动，如亲吻、拥抱、爱抚，都是因为我让他情难自禁，他完全不知道这到底是怎么回事。

现在，我看穿了他，他只是在一直假装单纯而已。

“说说看。”我缓缓地梳着头，感觉每梳一下，梳齿都戳入脸颊。“她是谁？”

见我没有生气，巴迪似乎松了一口气，甚至有点如释重负，终于有人可以让他倾诉他是如何被女人引诱失了身。

当然是别人引诱了巴迪，他既没有挑起这个头，所以也算不得他的错。那个人就是鳕鱼角旅馆的女服务生，去年夏天巴迪在那里兼职当杂工。巴迪发现她看他的眼神怪怪的，还总是趁厨房一片混乱的时候用胸部蹭他。有一天，他终于挑明了，问她有什么问题吗，结果对方直视着他，说：“我想吃了你。”

“要加点西芹吗？”巴迪笑得天真无邪。

“不用。”她答道，“找个晚上吧。”

就这样，巴迪失去了纯洁，不再是处男了。

一开始，我以为他和那个女服务生只睡过一次，但为了确定，我还是问了他次数，结果他说他记不清了，反正接下来的那个夏天每周都有两三次。我心里一算，三乘以十，足足三十次。太过分了，说什么都没用了。

从此之后，我心里有个东西冻结了。

回到学校后，我开始到处问大四学姐，如果正在交往的男生突然告诉她们，他一个夏天就和某个当服务生的荡妇睡了三十次，热恋之中猛然受此打击，她们会怎么做。学姐们却说，多数男人都是这副德行，除非你们的关系已经确定，或者订下婚约，否则你还真没资格指责他们。

其实，我在意的不是巴迪跟别人上过床。我的意思是，男欢女爱的故事我也读过不少，如果今天这事不是发生在巴迪身上，而是随便哪个男生，我可能只会问问最精彩的细节，然后自己也找个男生上床，平衡一下心理，这事就算过去了。

我不能忍受的是巴迪的虚伪。他弄得我好像情场老手，自己装出一副清纯的模样，而实际上，他一直都和放荡的女服务生有一腿，这简直像是在当面嘲笑我。

“你妈怎么看这个女服务生？”那个周末我问他。

巴迪和他妈妈亲得不得了，整天把他妈妈对男女关系的金句挂在嘴边。我知道威拉德太太视贞操如命，不论男女。我第一次上她家吃晚餐时，她用怪异又锐利的探寻目光打量我，我知道她想看出来我是不是个处女。

不出所料，巴迪被我问得不好意思起来。“妈妈跟我问起过格拉迪斯。”他承认。

“那你说什么了？”

“我说格拉迪斯未婚，白人，二十一岁。”

现在我知道巴迪绝不会为了我对他妈妈说这么粗鲁的话。他总是引述他妈妈的名言：“男人要的是伴儿，女人要的是无限的安全感。”还有，“男人像箭，射向未来，女人是弓，助力男人。”诸如此类，真是烦人。

每次我不服气，巴迪就会说，他妈现在依然能和他爸同享乐趣，对他们这个年纪的人来说实属难得，所以可见她深谙婚姻之道和男女真谛。

好了，我已经下定决心，一劳永逸甩了巴迪·威拉德。不是因为他和女服务生上床，而是他没胆子对所有人承认这件事，也没种面对自己的本性。这时，走廊上的电话响了，有人用一种了然一切的淡然口吻说：“找你的，埃斯特，波士顿的电话。”

我立刻觉得大事不妙，因为整个波士顿我只认得巴迪一人，而他从未给我打过长途，因为这比写信贵多了。有一次，他有急事要告诉我，就跑到医学院门口到处打听有没有人周末开车到我的学校。结果当然不失所望，于是他把信托付给对方，不仅我当天就拿到了信，他连邮票都省了。

果然是巴迪的电话。他告诉我，每年秋季的胸部X光检查显示他得了肺结核，他即将拿着医学院给肺结核学生的专门补助，去阿迪伦达克的疗养院养病。他接着说，自那次周末过后，我就没给他写过信，他希望我们两人间没出什么问题。他还问我，能不能每周至少写一封信给他，圣诞假期再去疗养院看看他？

我从来没听过巴迪的语气如此不安。他向来自诩身强体壮，还总是说我的鼻塞和呼吸困难是心理压力造成的身体问题。我觉得身为医生，他对疾病的态度有点怪，或许他该改行当心理医生更合适。当然，这话我可没有说出口。

我向巴迪表达了听闻他感染肺结核的遗憾之情，也答应给他写信。可是当我挂上电话，心里可一丝遗憾也没有，只觉得如释重负。

我想，对巴迪这样过着双重人生、觉得自己高人一等的人来说，得肺结核就是他的报应。现在可方便了，我不必在校园里昭告众人我已经和巴迪分手，也不必再接受一轮又一轮无聊的相亲安排了。

我只告诉大家巴迪得了肺结核，而我们也算是订婚了。从此，每当我周六晚上留在宿舍用功时，大家都对我特别好，因为她们觉得我很坚强，以刻苦学习来隐藏一颗破碎的心。

(1) 著名默片演员。

7

的确，康斯坦丁的个头实在太矮了，可他自有英俊之处——浅褐色的头发，深蓝色的眼睛，生动鲜活吸引人的表情。他皮肤是古铜色，一口白牙，很接近美国人了，可我一眼就能看出他不是。他有我见过的美国人所不具备的东西，那就是直觉。

才刚认识，康斯坦丁就猜出我不是威拉德太太的什么后辈。我不时挑挑眉毛，干笑几声，很快，我俩就公然痛批起威拉德太太。我心想：“这个康斯坦丁不会介意我个子太高，不懂几门外语，没去过欧洲。他一眼就能看透我是怎样的人。”

康斯坦丁开着他的绿色老式敞篷车带我去联合国大楼。棕色的皮革座椅虽然开裂了，坐着却很舒服，敞篷顶也打开了。他告诉我，他古铜色的肌肤是打网球晒的。我们并肩坐在敞篷车里，沿着马路飞驰，阳光沐浴在身上，他拉起我的手紧握了一下，瞬间我的幸福感爆发。自从九岁那年的夏天，和父亲在炎热的白沙滩上奔跑，我就再也没有感受过这样的快乐——那之后不久，父亲就去世了。

到了联合国大楼，康斯坦丁带我坐进一间肃穆豪华的旁听室，旁边是一个未施脂粉、严肃冷峻、肌肉发达的俄国女孩。她和康斯坦丁一样，也是同声传译员。此时，我突然想到，真是奇怪，以前怎么从没意识到我只在九岁之前感受过单纯的快乐。

父亲去世后——母亲节衣缩食，让我参加女童子军，学钢琴、水彩画和舞蹈，参加帆船夏令营，最后还供我上大学，让我能够一早在雾霭中扬帆，能够吃着黑底巧克力派(1)，每天的新点子像爆竹一样噼里啪啦往外冒——我再没有真正地开心过。

我直盯着那个俄国女孩。她穿着灰色双排扣套装，用母语连珠炮似的说出一个又一个我听不懂的习惯用语。康斯坦丁说，英语和俄语的习语翻译是同声传译中最难的部分，因为它们之中没有相对应的习语。我无比希望能够附身于她，余生就用来说出一个个习语。这或许不会让我快乐多少，但至少会让我积攒的象征才能的小石头再多上那么一颗。

然后，康斯坦丁和俄国女译员以及一群在贴有标签的麦克风后争论的肤色或黑或白或黄的男人，似乎都在离我远去。我看见他们的嘴一开一合，却听不到任何声音，好像他们正坐在即将起航的船的甲板上，独留我一人搁浅于广漠无垠的寂静中。

我开始细数自己不会做的事情。

从烹饪开始。

我的外婆和母亲都烧得一手好菜，所以我把做菜的事都交给她们了。她们一直想教我做一两道菜，但我总是随便看上两眼，应付两句：“好，好，我会了。”祖传的烹饪秘诀犹如耳边风，过脑即忘，煮出的每道菜的味道也可想而知，于是再也无人要我掌勺做菜。

我想起乔蒂，她是我大一时最好的朋友，也是当时我唯一的女性朋友。有一天早上，她在家炒蛋给我吃。那炒蛋尝起来别有风味，我问她里面是不是加了特别的调料，她说只有奶酪和蒜盐。我又问是谁教她的，她说没人教，自个儿琢磨的。不过本来嘛，她就是个务实的人，学的又是社会学。

我也不会速记。

这意味着我大学毕业后找不到好工作。妈妈一直告诉我，没人会雇一个不具备其他技能的英语系毕业生。但是，如果英语系毕业，又会速记，那就另当别论了，人人都抢着要。许多前程似锦的年轻男人会找上门来，口述一封封精彩的求职信，让她誊抄。

问题在于，我就是不喜欢伺候男人，不论是以何种方式。我想口述我自己精彩的信件，让别人为我誊抄。再说，妈妈给我看的书里那些小小的速记符号，简直跟用t等于时间、用s等于距离之类的东西一样讨厌。

我做不来的事情还有很多。

我的舞跳得很糟。唱歌老是跑调。平衡感又差——每次体育课上要伸平双臂头顶书走平衡木时，我总会跌下来。我最想参加的两项活动是骑马和滑雪，但因为花费太高，所以我也不会。我不会说德语，看不懂希伯来文，不会写中文。我甚至不知道眼前这几位肤色各异的联合国翻译员所属的古老遥远的国家在地图上的哪个角落。

我坐在联合国大楼的核心位置，身处隔音环境，一边是会打网球还会同声传译的康斯坦丁，另一边是深谙大量习语的俄国女孩，我平生第一次惊恐地发现自己一无是处。问题是，我向来一无是处，只是未曾自觉罢了。

我擅长的一件事就是拿奖学金，拿各种奖，而这样的日子快到头了。

我觉得自己就像一匹失去了跑道的赛马，或者一个要穿着西装走上华尔街的大学足球运动员，他的昔日荣光都化作壁炉上的小小金杯，杯身上烙印的日期就像墓碑上镌刻的生卒年。

我看见我的人生伸展出许多枝丫，就像那则短篇小说里的绿色无花果树。

每条枝丫的顶端都挂着一颗饱满的紫色无花果，那是美好的未来在向我招手和眨眼。这一颗果实是相夫教子、家庭和美，那一颗是扬名诗坛，下一颗是杰出教授，另一颗是著名编辑伊·吉，又一颗是游历欧洲、非洲和南美，再一颗是康斯坦丁、苏格拉底、阿提拉等一群名字怪异、职业另类的爱人，还有一颗是奥运女子划船赛冠军。除了这些，还有许多其他我看不清的果实。

我看见自己坐在这株无花果树的枝丫上，饿得要死，只因下不了决心采下哪颗果子。每一颗我都想要，可是选择一颗就代表着失去其他颗。当我干坐着犹豫不决时，果子开始干瘪发黑，一颗接一颗地掉落在我脚下。

康斯坦丁挑选的餐厅弥漫着草药、香料和酸奶油的气味。来到纽约的这段时间，我还没来过这样的餐厅。我找的都是“汉堡天堂”那类地方，供应巨无霸汉堡和今日例汤，四款花哨的蛋糕摆在一尘不染的柜台上，对面是亮晃晃的一溜长镜子。

餐厅位于一个类似地窖的地方，要走下七级昏暗的台阶才能进入。

贴在烟黑色墙上的旅游海报，宛如一扇扇观景窗台，眺望着瑞士的湖泊、日本的山峦和非洲的大草原。厚重的蜡烛杯布满尘埃，彩色烛泪仿佛哭泣了几百年般层层堆积，红叠着蓝，蓝又叠着绿，围成立体精致的花边。蜡烛在桌上投下光晕，桌边一张张容颜浮现，脸色绯红恰似烛焰。

我不知道自己吃的是什么，但是第一口下去，我立刻觉得好多了。我突然想到，刚才之所以会幻想出无花果树和肥厚果实的萎缩凋零，全是腹中空空给闹的。

康斯坦丁不停地往我们的杯里添酒，这种希腊甜酒尝起来有股松树皮的清香。我发现自己不停地说想学德语，想去欧洲，想当一个像玛姬·希金斯一样优秀的战地记者。

等到酸奶和草莓果酱上桌时，我感觉超好，当下决定要让康斯坦丁引诱我。

自从巴迪·威拉德告诉我他跟女服务员的事，我就在想，我也该出去找个人上床。跟巴迪·威拉德做爱不算，因为这样他睡过的人还是比我多一个。我得另找他人。

我只跟一个男孩聊过床笫之事。那是个长着鹰钩鼻的南方人，在耶鲁读书，有一个周末他来我们学校找女友，却发现就在前一天她已经跟一个出租车司机私奔了。那女孩和我住同一栋宿舍楼，恰巧当晚楼里只剩我一人，所以安慰他的任务非我莫属了。

我们找了家附近的咖啡店，窝在椅背高耸的隐秘雅座里，木墙上刻着好几百个的人名。我们喝了一杯又一杯的黑咖啡，直言不讳地畅谈与性有关的论题。

这个名叫艾瑞克的男生，说我们学校里某些女生的行为真是令人作呕。深夜一点宵禁前，她们经常站在门廊的灯光下，或没遮没拦的矮树丛里，与男友狂热地耳鬓厮磨，路过的人看得一清二楚。艾瑞克尖刻地说，人类经过百万年的进化，结果却成了什么？还是禽兽。

接着，艾瑞克说起他第一次和女人上床的事。

那时他去了南方一所预科学校念书，这所大学的特色是培养素质全面的绅士。学校有条不成文的规定，每个人毕业前必须了解一个女人。艾瑞克说，是《圣经》上的那种“了解”。

所以某个周六，艾瑞克和几位同班同学搭公交车到最近的城市，去了一家颇有名声的妓院。接待艾瑞克的妓女甚至连裙子都没脱。那是个肥胖的中年女人，染了一头红发，嘴唇厚得让人起疑，皮肤呈鼠灰色。她不乐意关灯，所以艾瑞克只好在沾满蝇粪的二十五瓦灯泡下享用了她。男女之事根本不像大家所说的那样刺激，他只觉得像上厕所一样无聊。

我说，如果你爱她，做爱也许就不会无聊了。但是艾瑞克说，一想到自己所爱的女人跟其他人一样，也会做出此等苟且之事，什么好感都没了。所以，如果他爱某个人，他绝不会和她上床。实在有需要，他宁可去找妓女，也不让自己爱的女人沾染这种龌龊之事。

那时，我突然起了个念头，或许艾瑞克是个上床的好对象，因为他有经验，而且他说起这事时，也不像一般男生那样猥琐或愚蠢。可是紧接着，艾瑞克给我写了封信，说他很有可能爱上我了，因我聪明愤世，却又一脸和气，与他的姐姐惊人的相似。于是我知道没戏了，他永远不可能跟我上床。于是我回信说，真可惜，我就快和青梅竹马的恋人结婚了。

在纽约搭上一个同声传译员，这主意我越想越觉得不错。康斯坦丁各方面看起来都成熟而又体贴，而且这里也没有我认识的人可供他事后吹嘘——那些大学男生最爱和舍友或篮球队友吹嘘自己如何跟女孩车震。再说，跟威拉德太太介绍给我认识的男人上床，简直是一大讽刺，要怪就怪她好了，想来真是解恨。

所以，当康斯坦丁问我是否想去他的公寓欣赏俄国特有的巴拉莱卡琴(2)唱片时，我暗自偷笑。我的母亲总是告诫我，晚上和男人约会时，无论如何都不能跟他回家，因为这种举动只有一种含义。

“我非常喜欢巴拉莱卡奏出的音乐。”我说。

康斯坦丁的公寓有个阳台，俯瞰下方的河流，听到黑暗中传来拖船的声音，我不禁心动，胸中柔情似水，非常确定自己接下来要做什么。

我知道这样可能会怀孕，可这个念头模模糊糊遥不可及，丝毫干扰不了我的决定。就像我母亲从《读者文摘》里剪下来并寄到学校给我看的那篇文章所言，没有百分百安全的避孕措施。这篇名为《捍卫贞操》的文章的作者是个已经结婚生子的女律师。

文章列举各种理由，力陈女孩不该和除丈夫以外的男人上床，即使是丈夫，也必须在婚后才能发生关系。

它的主要观点是，男人的世界跟女人不同，男人的情感也与女人迥异，唯有婚姻是妥善融合两个世界和两类情感的解药。我母亲说，女孩总要等到为时已晚才能明白个中道理，所以最好听取专家的意见，譬如一个已婚的女人。

这位女律师说，最好的男人愿意为妻子守贞，而即便他们已非纯洁之身，他们仍希望自己是妻子的性爱启蒙者。当然，他们会千方百计哄着女孩上床，答应日后娶她为妻，可是一旦她同意，他们就会看轻她，认为她既然能跟他们上床，也能跟别的男人睡觉。于是，他们便会选择结束，而女孩悲惨的一生就此开始。

这位女专家的结论是，防患于未然，安全总比伤心好。况且，没有什么方法可以确保不怀孕，一旦未婚先孕，你的人生就彻底毁了。

依我看，这篇文章没有考虑到的，恰恰是女孩的感受。

如果女孩纯洁，又嫁与同样纯洁的男子，这当然很好。可万一两人婚后，男人才像巴迪·威拉德一样，突然承认自己早已和别人上过床，一切又当如何？女人就得守身如玉，男人却可以过着一面纯洁一面放荡的双重生活，这样的观点我无法苟同。

最后，我拿定了主意，既然要找到一个聪明强壮、到二十一岁仍保有童男之身的人实非易事，我何不干脆抛开贞操的负累，找个同样有过性经验的人结婚就好。他要是让我的日子过得不舒服，我也可以让他不好过。

我十九岁的时候，贞操可是个大事。

在我看来，世界并非分为天主教徒和新教徒、共和党和民主党、白人和黑人，甚至也不是以男人和女人来划分的，而是分作跟人上过床的和没跟人上过床的。贞操，似乎是人与人之间唯一真正重要的差异。

我觉得，当我跨越这条界限的那一天，我定会发生惊人的改变。

我觉得，这变化可能与我去一趟欧洲发生的变化相同。回到家中，凑近镜子，我会看到眼眸深处有一座小小的白色阿尔卑斯山。而明天照镜子的时候，我应该会看到一个玩偶大小的康斯坦丁安坐在我的眼眸里，对着我微笑。

我们在康斯坦丁家的阳台待了差不多一个小时，慵懒地分坐在两张躺椅上，两人之间堆放着巴拉莱卡琴唱片，留声机里乐声不断。乳白色的氤氲灯光笼罩着我们，分不清是来自街灯、半月、车灯还是星光。可是康斯坦丁就只握着我的手，毫无诱惑我的意图。

我问他是否订了婚，或者有没有交往的女孩，心想也许这是他没有行动的症结所在。但他都否认了，他说不想受这种关系的羁绊。

终于，一股浓浓的睡意袭来，先前饮过的带有松树皮清香的希腊甜酒顺着血管把倦意带遍全身。

“我要进屋躺一会儿。”我说。

我若无其事地晃进房间，弯腰脱掉鞋子。干净的床铺就像一张安稳的小船，在我面前轻摆。我伸展四肢，阖上眼睛。然后，我听见康斯坦丁叹了口气，从阳台进来。他的鞋子咚咚落在地板上，接着他在我身侧躺下。

我借着一缕垂下的头发遮掩，偷偷打量着他。

他仰面躺着，双手枕在头下，盯着天花板。浆过的白衬衫袖子卷到肘部，在昏暗的夜色中折射出诡异的白光，而古铜的肤色现在看起来几乎是黑的。我想，他肯定是我平生所见的男人中最帅的一个。

我又想，假如我的五官更立体些，或者能把政治谈得头头是道，或者是个有名的作家，康斯坦丁没准儿会有兴趣和我上床。

但随后我又想，没准他刚喜欢上我，就沦为我眼中的凡间俗物；等他爱上我，我会不停地对他吹毛求疵，就像我对待巴迪·威拉德和在他之前的那些中意我的男生那样。

同样的事情一再地发生。

我远远地看着一个男人，觉得他完美无瑕，可当他一靠近，我立刻觉得他完全不合适。

这正是我永远不想结婚的理由之一。我最不想要的就是无限的安全感，不想成为男人射向未来之箭的起点。我想要变化与刺激，想让自己像国庆日的璀璨烟火一样，射向四面八方。

我被雨声吵醒。

四周一片漆黑。过了一会儿，我才分辨出陌生窗户的模糊轮廓。不时有一道光束划过墙壁，像一根鬼魅的手指在探究着什么，然后一切又消失于无形。

然后，我听见了呼吸的声音。

起初，我以为是我自己，食物中毒后躺在黑暗的旅馆房间里，发出呼哧呼哧的喘息。可是我屏住呼吸，那个声音还在。

身侧有只绿眼睛发着幽光，像个罗盘一样被分成数等份。我慢慢伸出手，抓住它一提，没想到连带着抓起一只手臂。手臂的主人正在沉睡，所以手臂死沉死沉的，却也挺暖和。

康斯坦丁的手表正指向三点钟。

他和衣而卧，身上的衬衫、长裤和袜子仍是我坠入梦乡时的那一套。等眼睛适应了黑暗之后，我渐渐分辨出他苍白的眼皮，挺直的鼻梁，说话宽容、漂亮有型的嘴。可它们看来又如此虚无缥缈，仿佛雾中的一幅画。我倾身靠近他，细细地端详了好一会儿。我还从来没在男人身边睡着过。

我试着想象成为康斯坦丁太太的感觉。

这意味着我得早上七点起床，给他煎好蛋和培根，准备好面包片和咖啡。他出门上班后，我穿着睡袍，别着发卷，忙着洗盘子、铺床。等他在外面度过充满活力的美好一天后，他期待着回家吃上一顿丰盛的晚餐，然后我只好整晚不停地洗更多的盘子，倒在床上时已然精疲力竭。

对于一个十五年寒窗苦读门门功课全A的女孩来说，这种枯燥的生活无异于虚度光阴，但我知道婚姻就是这么回事，因为巴迪·威拉德的母亲即便身为私立学校的老师，还嫁给了大学教授，也逃不脱从早到晚洒扫烹煮这些事。

有一次我去找巴迪，威拉德太太正用威拉德先生旧西装上拆下的毛线织毯子。她已经织了好几个礼拜，而我也很喜欢穗带上棕绿蓝三色交织的图案。照我的想法，毯子织好后一定要挂在墙上好好欣赏，可威拉德太太竟把它当作厨房的地垫来用。没几天它就变得又脏又丑，跟便宜小店里零售价不到一美元的垫子毫无二致。

我知道，男人在婚前会为女人献上玫瑰、热吻和烛光晚餐，可婚礼结束后，他私心里真正想要的，却是女人臣服于他的脚下，如同威拉德太太厨房里的垫脚布一样。

母亲不是早就告诉过我吗？她刚刚和我父亲离开雷诺(3)——我父亲之前结过婚，他得在雷诺办理离婚手续——踏上蜜月之旅时，我父亲就欢呼着对她说：“终于解脱了，现在我们总算可以放下伪装，做回自己。”从那天起，母亲就一日也不得安宁了。

我还记得，有一次巴迪·威拉德用了然一切、不怀好意的口吻说，等我有了孩子之后，感觉就会不同，不会再想写什么诗了。所以，我开始觉得结婚生子的过程有如洗脑，婚后你会像活在秘密极权国度里的奴隶一样麻木。

我低头凝视康斯坦丁，犹如看着深井底部一颗遥不可及的闪亮水晶。忽然，他睁开眼直直地看向我，眼里满是爱意。我默然无语。我看着他眨眨眼睛认出了我，他眼中隐约的柔情一闪而过，就像按下了快门，大大的瞳孔亮如漆皮，却无法再探及他的心底。

康斯坦丁起身坐好，打了个呵欠。“几点了？”

“三点。”我淡淡地说，“我该回去了。明天一早还要上班呢。”

“我开车送你。”

我们背对彼此，分坐在床的两侧笨拙地穿着鞋。床头灯发出刺目的白光，着实讨厌。我察觉到康斯坦丁转过身来，问我：“你的头发一直都是这样吗？”

“什么样？”

他并不回答，只是伸出手指穿过我的头发，像梳子一样缓缓地从发根捋至发梢。一道小小的电流击过我的身体，我僵住了。从小我就喜欢别人帮我梳头的感觉，这让我平静和放松，直欲睡去。

“啊，我知道了。”康斯坦丁说，“你刚洗过头。”

然后，他弯腰系好网球鞋带。

一小时后，我躺在旅馆的房间里，倾听雨声。听起来不像雨声，倒像是水龙头倾泻。左腿胫骨中段的旧伤开始隐隐作痛，反正七点前是睡不着了。七点一到，收音机闹钟就会用苏沙(4)激越的演奏吵醒我。

每逢雨天，我的断腿旧伤似乎就想起了自己的存在，那是种钝钝的痛。

于是我想：“是巴迪·威拉德令我摔断了腿。”

转念又一想：“不，是我自己弄断的。我故意这么做，这是卑鄙者的自惩。”

(1) 这种巧克力派之所以叫黑底派，是因其底部有一层加有巧克力的黑色蛋粉。

(2) 巴拉莱卡琴（Balalaika），俄罗斯的一种弦乐器，琴腹呈三角形，有三根弦。

(3) 雷诺（Reno），位于美国内华达州西部，素有“离婚城市”之名。只需在该市住满三个月，就可依法实现离婚之目的。

(4) 苏沙，即约翰·菲利普·苏沙（John Philip Sousa），美国著名作曲家、指挥家。

8

威拉德先生开车送我去阿迪伦达克的疗养院。

这是圣诞节后的第一天，头顶上是灰蒙蒙的天，大雪纷飞。我觉得肚子好撑，郁闷而又失望。每年的这一天我都有这种感觉，松枝，蜡烛，系着金银丝带的礼物，烧着桦木的壁炉，圣诞火鸡，圣诞颂歌和钢琴音乐，不管许诺过什么，都从来没有实现过。

每逢圣诞节，我都差点盼着自己是个天主教徒了。

这趟路程，先是威拉德先生开，然后换我开。我不知道我们都聊了些什么，四周乡野覆盖着厚重的积雪，让我们更觉凄冷。茂密的冷杉从灰暗的山丘蔓延到路边，深浓的墨绿连绵，看起来黑沉沉的。我只觉得心情越来越阴郁。

我真想叫威拉德先生自己去疗养院，让我搭便车回家。

可是一抬眼看见威拉德先生的脸——修剪成孩子气的平头的银色头发，澄澈的蓝眸，红润的脸颊，带着纯真而信任的表情，宛如婚礼上洒了糖霜的甜美蛋糕——我知道我开不了这口，我必须把这次探访进行到底。

及至中午，灰霾略退，我们将车停在一处结冰的岔道上，共享威拉德太太给我们准备的午餐：金枪鱼三明治，燕麦曲奇，苹果，还有装在保温瓶里的黑咖啡。

威拉德先生慈祥地看着我，然后清了清喉咙，拂掉腿上的食物碎屑。我看得出来，他有正事要说。他生性害羞，有一次他进行一个重要的经济主题演讲，我听到他在开口前就像现在这样清喉咙。

“娜莉和我一直想要个女儿。”

我一时胡思乱想起来，以为威拉德先生要宣布威拉德太太怀了个女宝宝。他接着说：“可是，我觉得，没有女儿会比你更好。”

威拉德先生一定以为我的泪水是听闻他把我当女儿看待喜极而泣。“好啦，好啦。”他拍拍我的肩膀，又清了清喉咙，“我想我们心意相通。”

然后他打开了他那侧的车门，下车绕过车子，走到我身边，他呼出的气在灰蒙蒙的天色中盘旋成缕缕白烟。我移到他空出来的座位上，他发动车子，我们继续前进。

我不确定自己对巴迪住的疗养院有什么期望。

我想，我期望的是一座小山丘之上的一栋小木屋，住在里面的青年男女面泛酡红，十分迷人，但是双眼因肺痨而红热，裹着厚厚的毯子躺在露天阳台上。

“肺结核就像在肺里埋了颗炸弹。”我在学校时，巴迪曾经写信告诉我，“你只能静静地躺着，祈祷它不会爆炸。”

我很难想象巴迪静静躺着的模样。他的全部人生哲学就是分秒必争，活出精彩。就连夏天里我们去海边，他也绝不会像我在阳光下躺下来打个盹，而是要么跑来跑去，要么打打球，要么来两个伏地挺身，充分利用时间。

威拉德先生和我在接待室里等候下午休息治疗的结束。

整个疗养院似乎以红褐色为基调。暗沉的木构件，焦褐色的皮椅，霉菌或湿气将原本可能洁白无瑕的墙壁侵染得面目全非。地板上铺了棕色的亚麻油毡，已显斑驳。

一张低矮的咖啡桌，深色的胶合板桌面已经被圆形和半圆形的污渍噬咬，上面放了几本破旧的《时代》和《生活》杂志。我拿起离我最近的一本，随手翻到中间，艾森豪威尔总统的脸映入眼帘，微笑，秃头，神情茫然，活像罐子里的胚胎标本。

过了一会儿，我隐隐听到漏水的声音。起初我以为是墙壁吸饱了湿气开始渗水，不过随即发现声音来自房间角落的一个小小喷泉。

一截粗糙的管子喷出几英寸高的喷泉，手状的水柱喷起又落下，参差的水花淹没在一石槽泛黄的水中。石槽上铺了公共厕所常见的白色六角形瓷砖。

蜂鸣声响起，远处的门开了又合上。巴迪走了进来。

“嗨，老爸。”

巴迪抱了抱他父亲，随即快速地带着一种可怕的容光焕发的样子走向我，朝我伸出手来。我握了握他的手——又潮又肥。

威拉德先生和我坐在同一张皮沙发上，巴迪坐在我们对面一张扶手摇椅的边缘。他一直在笑，嘴角仿佛吊了两根看不见的铁丝。

我万万没料到巴迪会变胖。每每想到住在疗养院的他，我的眼前总是浮现深陷的脸颊，镶在凹陷眼窝中的灼红双眼。

然而此刻，巴迪身上原本凹陷的地方突然全都凸起，紧身白色尼龙衬衫下绷着个水桶腰，脸颊圆胖红润好像杏仁果，就连笑声听起来都饱满丰盈。

巴迪与我目光交汇。“饮食造成的。”他说，“他们让我们天天吃饱了就躺下休息。但是现在散步时间我可以出去了，所以别担心，几周后我就会瘦下来。”他倏然起身，笑得像个开心的东道主。“想不想看看我的房间？”

我跟着巴迪，威拉德先生跟在我后面，穿过一道嵌着毛玻璃的双推门，走进一条红褐色的昏暗长廊。这里弥漫着地板蜡、来苏尔消毒液和一种像捣碎了的栀子花的隐约气味。

巴迪用力推开一扇棕色的门，我们鱼贯走入这个狭窄的房间。

一张笨重的床占据了大半的空间，床上铺着白底蓝纹薄床单。旁边的床头柜上有一个水罐和一个玻璃水杯，装着粉色消毒剂的瓶中有一个温度计探出它银色的末端。还有一张桌子挤在床尾和衣橱门之间，上面满是书籍、纸张和陶罐半成品——已经烧制好，也上了色，但没上釉。

“嗯。”威拉德先生呼了口气说，“看起来蛮舒适的。”

巴迪笑笑。

“这是什么？”我拿起一个形似莲叶的陶制烟灰缸，底色是暗绿的，上面用黄色仔细绘出了叶脉。巴迪不抽烟。

“那是烟灰缸。”巴迪说，“给你的。”

我放下烟灰缸。“我不抽烟。”

“我知道。”巴迪说，“但我还以为你会喜欢。”

“好啦。”威拉德先生抿了抿薄如纸片的嘴唇，“我想我该上路了，留你们两个年轻人……”

“好的，老爸。那你慢走。”

我十分吃惊。我以为威拉德先生会留下来过夜，第二天再开车带我回去。“我也一起走吧？”

“不用，不用。”威拉德先生从皮夹中抽出几张钞票递给巴迪，“一定要给埃斯特买个舒服的火车位子。她可能会待上个一两天。”巴迪把他父亲送到门口。

我觉得自己被威拉德先生抛弃了，我猜他肯定早就计划好了这一切。但巴迪说不是这样，他父亲只是见不得人生病，尤其是他的儿子生病，因为他认为所有的疾病都来自意志之病。威拉德先生这辈子就没病过一天。

我坐在巴迪的床沿，因为没其他地方可坐。

巴迪有条不紊地翻查桌上的那叠纸，然后递给我一本薄薄的灰皮杂志。“翻到十一页。”

杂志是在缅因州的什么地方印的，里头全是蜡纸油印的诗歌和叙述的段落，用星号区隔开来。在第十一页上是一首名为《佛罗里达黎明》的诗，随着我快速浏览，意象不断涌现：西瓜色的晨曦，玳瑁绿的棕榈，有凹槽的仿佛希腊建筑缩影的贝壳。

“不错。”其实我觉得很烂。

“谁写的？”巴迪带着奇怪的傻笑问道。

我的视线落到这页的右下角。巴·斯·威拉德。

“我不知道。”但我随即改口，“我当然知道啦，巴迪。你写的。”

巴迪蹭到我身边。

我往后挪了挪。我对结核病所知甚少，但总觉得此病很是凶险，传染人于无影无形之间。而此时巴迪很有可能正置身于自己的结核病菌的致命笼罩之下。

“别担心。”巴迪笑着说，“我不是阳性。”

“阳性？”

“就是你不会被我传染。”

巴迪停下来喘了口气，就像爬了个陡坡中间停下来喘息一样。“我想问你个问题。”他新养成了一个让人不安的坏习惯，就是用目光直刺入我的眼睛，好像这样真的可以穿透我的脑子，更好地分析里头的思绪似的。

“我本想写信问你的。”

我脑中闪过一个淡蓝色的信封，背面的信封口上印有耶鲁大学的徽章。

“但是后来我决定，等你上这儿来时我亲自问问你，这样更妥当。”他顿了顿，“嗯，你难道不想知道我要问什么吗？”

“什么？”我低声问道，预感不妙。

巴迪贴着我坐下，一手揽住我的腰，一手把我耳旁的头发拂开。我一动不动。他附在我耳边悄声问道：“你愿意做巴迪·威拉德太太吗？”

我差点爆笑出来。

在我远远地暗恋巴迪的那五六年间，他若是这么问我，不论什么时候，我想我都必定惊喜若狂。

巴迪看出了我的迟疑。

“呃，我知道我现在身体不太好。”他连忙说，“我还在服用对氨基水杨酸，可能还要切除一两根肋骨，但明年秋天我应该可以回医学院念书。最迟不会超过后年春天……”

“我要告诉你一件事，巴迪。”

“我知道了。”巴迪僵硬地说，“你有别人了。”

“不，不是这样的。”

“那是怎样？”

“我一辈子都不打算结婚。”

“你疯了吧。”巴迪精神一振，“你迟早会改主意的。”

“不会，我心意已决。”

巴迪对我后面的话不予理会，仍是一脸开心。

“你记得吗？”我问他，“有一次在短剧之夜后，你和我一起搭便车回校？”

“我记得。”

“记得当时你问我喜欢住在乡村还是城市吗？”

“你说……”

“我说，我既想住在乡村，也想住在城市。”

巴迪点点头。

“然后你就笑了，”我突然加重语气，“说我完全符合神经官能症的症状。而且那周心理学课上的问卷里就有这道题吧？”

巴迪的笑容渐渐消失了。

“呵，你说得对，我是有点神经质。我永远没办法在乡村或城市中安定下来。”

“你可以住在城乡之间嘛。”巴迪很积极地出主意，“这样你就可以有时进城，有时下乡。”

“那——神经官能症和住在哪里有什么关系？”

巴迪没说话。

“说啊？”我轻叱一声，心想不能太宠着这些病人，把他们惯坏了是最糟糕的。

“没什么关系。”巴迪用一种苍白无力的声音答道。

“神经官能症，哈！”我不屑地放声一笑，“如果神经官能症是同时想获得两种相互不容的东西，那么我就是个十足的神经病。我接下来的人生都要在两种不相容的东西间飞来飞去。”

巴迪把手覆在我的手上。

“让我和你一起飞。”

我站在毗斯迦山滑雪坡顶往下望。我实在没必要来这里，这辈子我还没滑过雪。不过话说回来，当此美景，有机会我自然要好好欣赏一番。

在我的左手边，缆车将滑雪者一一运到积雪的山顶。正午的太阳下，积雪稍融，加上人来人往不断踩踏，峰顶的地面变得坚硬光滑如玻璃一般。冷空气刺激着我的肺部和鼻腔，让我陷入一种幻想的空灵中。

四面八方都有滑雪者从让人昏眩的陡坡飞身而下，他们一身或红或蓝或白的夹克，有如美国国旗上飞逝而过的星星点点。一片寂静之中，从滑雪道底部的一座仿原木小屋中，传出流行歌曲的旋律：

向下凝望着少女峰，
从我俩的度假小屋……

轻快又响亮的乐声，像是冰雪荒原上一条看不见的小溪，悠悠淌过我的身旁。一个不经意的华丽动作，就能让我冲下陡坡，直冲向滑雪场边观众群中的一个卡其色小点——那是巴迪·威拉德。

整个早上，巴迪都在教我滑雪。

首先，巴迪跟村里的一个朋友借了滑雪板和滑雪杖，又跟某个脚只比我大一号的医生太太借了雪地靴，再跟一个实习护士借了红色的滑雪外套。面对众人的极力劝阻，他的执意成行着实令人惊叹。

见此，我想起巴迪在医学院时曾得过一个奖，表彰他说服死者亲属捐出遗体供科学解剖研究最多，无论医学院是否需要。我忘了这个奖项的名称，但我可以想见巴迪穿着白大褂，从一侧口袋中突出的听诊器活像他身上的器官，他面露微笑深深鞠躬，说服那些沉默无语的家属签下解剖同意书，而后者往往还没从失去亲人的震惊中回过神来。

接下来，巴迪从他的主治医生那里借了辆车，这医生自己也得过肺结核，因而很能体谅他。我们驾车出发时，正赶上散步的铃声，回荡在不见天日的疗养院长廊上。

巴迪同样没滑过雪，但他说基本原理很简单，而且他经常观察滑雪教练教学生，所以我需要知道的一切诀窍他都能传授给我。

头半个小时，我乖乖服从他的指令，走之字形爬上一个小坡，然后滑雪杖用力一撑，径直滑下坡来。巴迪对我的进步似乎颇为满意。

“很好，埃斯特。”在我第二十次爬上同一道小坡时，他发表了意见，“现在你试着上索道吧。”

我在滑道上停了下来，脸红气喘。

“但是，巴迪，我还不会之字滑行啊。从山顶往下滑的人都知道怎么滑之字。”

“哦，那你上到一半就好了，这样你下滑的冲力就不会太大。”

巴迪陪我走到索道边上，教我怎么让绳索穿过手掌，然后要我十指紧扣，抓牢绳索上坡。

我完全没想到说不。

粗糙扎人的绳索像条蛇般缠绕在我指间，我紧紧抓住，一路上行。

可这绳索一路摇摇晃晃，拖着我飞快地上山，我只能力保平衡，根本不敢半路松手。我前后都有滑雪者，一旦松手跃下，很可能会被撞翻，再被一堆滑雪板和滑雪杖打中。为了不惹麻烦，我默默地继续上行。

可到了山顶，我后悔了。

巴迪认出我来，我穿着红夹克在山顶犹疑畏缩。他的双臂在空中猛挥，像卡其色的风车。我看见他比画着手势，要我从迂回前行的滑雪者当中空出的一条小路滑下来。我摆好姿势，却心中不安，喉咙发干，从我脚边到他脚边那条顺滑雪白的小径渐至模糊一片。

一个滑雪者从左边切过这条小径，另一个从右边过来。巴迪的手臂继续似有似无地挥着，好像滑雪场的另一端伸出的触角。整个滑雪场挤满人群，有如蠢动的微生物，像细菌一类，或是弯曲明亮的感叹号。

我的目光从人潮涌动的滑雪场底部往上移动。

天空像一个巨大的灰眼回望着我。雾气弥漫中，太阳从四面八方洒下苍白寂寥的光，穿过白雪覆盖的绵延山峦，汇聚在我的脚下。

心里有个声音喋喋不休，要我别做傻事——要保护自己，卸掉滑雪板，走下山去，雪坡侧边的低矮松枝正好做个掩护——像只郁郁寡欢的蚊子一样逃开吧。滑下去会要了我的命，这个念头在我的脑海中冷冷地滋长，长成了一棵树，或一朵花。

我目测自己和巴迪间的距离。

现在，他的双臂交抱在胸前，跟身后的横条篱笆融为一体——一样的无知无觉，一样的棕褐色，一样的微不足道。

我慢慢走到山顶边缘，把滑雪杖的尖头插入雪里，用力一撑，整个人便飞了起来。我知道，此时不论是技术还是迟来的理智，都无法让我停下了。

我笔直往下冲。

之前悠然的风此刻扑面袭来，灌进我的嘴里，吹得我的头发与地面平行。我在下坠，但白色的太阳并没有显得更高。它依然高挂在绵延的山峦之上，是无知无觉的枢纽，没有了它，世界将不复存在。

我的体内有个响应的小点，直向着太阳飞去。迎面涌来的景致——空气、山峦、树木、人群——让我的肺部乍然膨胀。我想：“原来这就是快乐的感觉。”

我急速下冲，冲过之字形前进的新手和专业的滑雪者，冲过年复一年的伪装、微笑和妥协，冲入我的过往。

两侧的人和树不停后退，就像隧道两侧的黑墙不断飞逝，我冲向尽头那不动的亮点——那是井底的水晶，是蜷缩在母亲肚中的白皙可爱的胎儿。

我咬了满嘴的冰碴，牙齿嘎吱作响，沁凉的雪水渗入我的喉咙。

巴迪的脸出现在我上方，又近又大，像一颗脱轨的星球。他的后面冒出其他人的脸孔。他的后方，黑色的小点挤满在一片雪白之上。仿佛有个乏味的仙女婆婆挥了挥她的魔杖，旧世界一点一点地回归原位。

“你滑得很好。”熟悉的声音传入我耳中，“可惜有人闯进你的滑道。”

人们帮我解开滑雪板上的固定装置，捡回两根滑雪杖，它们歪七扭八地插在滑道两侧的雪堤上。小屋的篱笆被我压在身下，硌着我的背。

巴迪弯腰脱掉我的靴子，以及塞在里面的好几双白色毛袜。他的胖手覆住我的左脚掌，一寸一寸地往上移到我的脚踝，轻轻握住，细细摩挲，好像在探寻私藏的武器。

苍穹高处的白色太阳冷冷地照着大地。我好想用它来砥砺磨炼自己，直到自己变得像刀锋一样圣洁而纤薄，只余精华。

“我要起来。”我说，“我还要滑。”

“不，你不能起来。”

巴迪的脸上浮现出一种怪异而满足的表情。

“不，你不能起来，”他带着裁决般的微笑重复，“你的腿断了两处，得打几个月的石膏。”

9

“我真高兴他们快死了。”

希尔达像猫儿一样拱起四肢打了个哈欠，把头埋入臂弯，继续趴在会议桌上睡觉。一缕胆汁绿的稻草装饰在她的眉毛上，有如一只热带鸟。

胆汁绿，这是他们秋天主推的颜色，希尔达一如往常，领先流行风潮半年。胆汁绿配黑色，胆汁绿配白色，胆汁绿配它的近亲尼罗绿。

时尚文案，徒有其表，在我的脑中有如鱼儿吐出的泡泡，升上水面，噗一声幻灭。

我真高兴他们快死了。

我暗道倒霉，走到旅馆自助餐厅时正好碰上希尔达。昨夜睡得晚，我脑袋发木，想不出个借口回房间，比如忘了戴手套、手帕、伞或笔记本之类的，给我的惩罚就是一路漫长死寂的同行，从亚马逊宾馆的毛玻璃大门到位于麦迪逊大道的铺着草莓色大理石的公司入口。

希尔达一路上都迈着模特步。

“帽子不错，你自己做的吗？”

我有点希望希尔达转过身来对我说：“听你的声音像是生病了。”但她只是伸了伸天鹅般的脖子，又缩了回去。

“是啊。”

头天晚上我看了一出女主人公被阴魂附体的戏，每次阴魂借女主人公之口说话时，声音听起来都深邃空洞，不辨男女。嗯，希尔达的声音就像那个阴魂。

她注视着自己在商店闪亮橱窗中的影像，似乎时时刻刻都要确定自己仍存在着。我们之间的沉默如此滞重，我想我也有部分责任。

所以我就说：“罗森伯格夫妇的事真可怕，对吧？”今天深夜，这对间谍夫妻就要坐上电椅。

“是啊！”希尔达说。听闻此言，我终于觉得在她纷乱如翻绳游戏的心思中，探触到一道人性的光辉。直到我们坐在一早就阴暗如坟墓的会议室，等候其他人的到来时，她才说完了她那句“是啊”的意思。

“世上竟有这种人，太可怕了！”

她打了个哈欠，浅橘色的嘴张成了一个巨大的黑洞。我呆呆地望着她面孔后面的大黑洞，直到她的两片嘴唇一碰一开，附体的阴魂从藏身之处开口说话：“我真高兴他们快死了。”

“来，笑一个。”

我坐在杰·茜办公室那张粉红天鹅绒的双人座椅上，拿着一朵纸玫瑰，面向杂志社的摄影师。我是见习的十二人中最后一个拍照的。我试着躲在厕所里，可惜没用，贝琪从门下缝隙窥见了我的脚。

我不想拍照，因为我快哭了。我不知道自己为何想哭，只知道如果有人跟我说话，或者靠我太近盯着我看，我的眼泪就会夺眶而出，哽咽之声也会忍不住飘出喉咙，而且一旦开始，我就会哭上一个礼拜。我能感觉到泪水在体内充盈，随时要泼溅出来，就像一杯盛得太满又摇摇晃晃的水。

这是最后一批照片，然后杂志就要送去印刷，而我们也将踏上归途，各自返回塔尔萨、比洛克西、提涅克、库斯湾等任何所来之处。照相时我们要拿个小道具，暗示将来想做什么。

贝琪拿的是一根玉米，代表她想嫁给农夫；希尔达拿的是一个光秃秃的、没有五官的制帽用的假人头，说明她想设计帽子；朵琳拿的是一件绣金纱丽，意思是她想去印度当社工（她私下告诉我，其实她根本不想当社工，只是想摸摸纱丽）。

他们问我以后想做什么，我说我不知道。

“哦，你心里肯定有数。”摄影师说。

“她啊——”杰·茜幽默了一把，“她什么都想做。”

我说，我想当诗人。

于是大家到处找寻适合我拿的道具。

杰·茜建议拿本诗集，遭到了摄影师的反对，说这样太直白了，最好是能激发诗性的东西。最后，杰·茜从她最新款的帽子上取下了一株长茎纸玫瑰。

摄影师鼓捣着他的白热聚光灯，说：“让大家看看写诗让你有多快乐。”

我的视线穿过杰·茜办公室里雕着橡胶树叶的窗楣，望向远方的蓝天。几朵大到夸张的云彩从右飘到左，我紧盯着最大的云朵，恍惚觉得当它飘逝无踪时，我也能幸运地随之而去。

我觉得让我的嘴唇保持在水平位置很有必要。

“笑一笑嘛。”

终于，我乖乖地扬起嘴角，像腹语师手中操纵的木偶。

“喂。”摄影师抗议道，突然有了预感一般，“你怎么好像要哭似的？”

我忍不住了。

把脸埋在杰·茜粉红天鹅绒双人座的椅背上，如释重负般，我将整个早上潜藏于胸臆间的情绪都发泄了出来，泪水苦咸，泣声凄怆。

我抬起头时，摄影师已经不见了。杰·茜也无影无踪。我四肢无力，有种被人抛弃的感觉，仿佛自己是某种可怕动物蜕下的皮。摆脱这可怕的东西是一种解脱，可它离开时似乎也带走了我的灵魂，以及一切它可以掠夺的东西。

我在皮包里翻找那个镀金小盒子——里头有睫毛膏、睫毛刷、眼影、三支口红和一面小镜子。镜子里回望着我的那张花脸像是被人痛打了一顿，隔着囚牢的铁栅望出来一般，肿胀不堪。这张脸很需要肥皂、清水和基督徒的宽容。

我开始小心翼翼地往脸上涂涂抹抹。

杰·茜如一阵微风，时机恰好、步履轻盈地飘回我的身边，手里抱着一沓稿纸。

“这些东西会让你开心起来。”她说，“祝你阅读愉快。”

每天早上，稿件如雪片般涌进小说编辑室，让原本就落满灰尘的积稿雪上加霜。在全美各地，人们在书房、阁楼和教室里偷偷写作。假设每分钟就有人完成一篇作品，那五分钟就有五篇稿子堆在小说编辑的桌面上。一小时就有六十篇，在地上堆成一片。一年下来……

我的嘴角泛起微笑，想象着有一篇新鲜出炉的稿件浮现于半空，右上角署着埃斯特·格林伍德的大名。我已经申请了一个知名作家开设的夏季写作班，希望这个月在杂志社的见习结束后就能去上课。申请时要先寄一篇小说稿过去，这位名家看过之后再通知你是否够资格参加他的课程。

当然，课程的规模很小，能够获得资格的人不多。我很早就把稿子寄去了，还没收到回音，但我有信心，回到家就会看到桌上躺着录取信。

我决定到时要把在这个班上写的小说寄几篇给杰·茜，用上笔名，让她大吃一惊。我想着有一天，小说编辑会亲自到杰·茜的办公室，把这几篇小说拍在她的桌上，说：“这些是上乘之作。”杰·茜深有同感，全部采用，并邀请作者共进午餐，她将会发现作者就是我。

“说真的。”朵琳说，“这个不一样。”

“说说看他长什么样。”我冷冷地说。

“他是秘鲁人。”

“秘鲁人又矮又壮。”我说，“像阿兹特克人一样丑。”

“不，不，不，亲爱的。我已经见过他了。”

我们一起坐在床上，身边是一堆乱七八糟的棉质裙子、抽了丝的尼龙长袜和灰突突的内衣。朵琳已经劝了我十分钟，要我跟伦尼朋友的朋友去乡村俱乐部跳舞。她一个劲儿地保证，这个男的和伦尼上次的那个朋友不一样。可我明天早上要搭八点的火车回家，现在该整理行李了。

况且，我还有点想在纽约的街头独自逛上整晚，这个城市的神秘和华美也许终将感染我。

但我还是放弃了这个念头。

最后这几天，我越来越拿不定主意该做些什么。好不容易下定决心做一件事，比如打包装箱，我只会把那些昂贵但肮脏的衣服从柜子和壁橱里拖出来，摊得椅子、床铺、地板哪哪儿都是，然后坐在那里干瞪眼，完全不知所措。它们似乎都有独立而执拗的个性，拒绝被清洗、折叠、收纳。

“都是这些衣服害的。”我告诉朵琳，“我受不了回来之后还得面对这堆东西。”

“这简单。”

朵琳开始优雅地抓起衣服，一次一件，衬裙，长筒袜，以及那件精致的、内部塞满弹簧的无肩带文胸——这是我始终没勇气穿上的报春花内衣公司的赠品——就这样，一件接着一件，这些剪裁奇怪、可每件价格都高达四十美元的衣服……

“哎，那件留下，我要穿。”

朵琳从她手头那堆衣服里抽出一件黑色的，扔到我腿上，然后把剩下的衣服揉滚成软沓沓的一大团，塞进床下，眼不见心不烦。

朵琳敲了敲绿色大门上的金色门环。

门内传来拖行的脚步声，一个男人的笑声戛然而止。一个穿着衬衫、留着平头的金发高个男孩缓缓地开了条门缝，探头一望。

“宝贝！”他喊道。

朵琳整个人被他拢入臂弯，我想这一定是伦尼的朋友。

我穿着黑色紧身小礼服，披着带流苏的黑色披肩，安静地站在门口。心中虽然比以往更为忐忑，却也没抱什么希望。“我就是个看客。”我对自己说道。我眼看着朵琳从金发男孩的怀中转移到另一个男人的手上，后者同样是高个儿，但肤色黝黑，头发稍长，穿着一身完美的洁白西装，配着浅蓝色的衬衫，黄色缎面领带上别着一个闪亮的领带夹。

我目不转睛地盯着那个领带夹。

它似乎闪耀出一道炫丽的白光，令整个房间都熠熠生辉。但那道白光又迅速隐藏了去，只剩下金色底托上的一滴露珠。

我向前迈出一步。

“那是钻石。”有人开口，众人哄堂大笑。

我用指甲轻敲钻石光滑的表面。

“她第一次见到钻石吧。”

“送给她吧，马可。”

马可弯腰将领带夹放在我的掌心。

上面的钻石璀璨夺目，随光影起舞，宛如天堂冰晶。我迅速将它放进我那只镶有假黑玉珠的晚宴包里，然后抬头看看四周，众人的脸庞空洞如餐盘，似乎连呼吸都没有。

“幸好，”一只干硬的手攥住我的上臂，“我今晚就是这位小姐的护花使者。”马可眼里的火花尽熄，转为幽黑，“或许，我应该提供一些小小的服务……”

有人笑起来。

“……相当于一颗钻石的服务。”

圈住我上臂的那只手一紧。

“啊！”

马可松开手。我低头一看手臂，上面赫然一个紫色的大拇指印。马可望着我，指指我的手臂内侧：“看那儿。”

四个隐约可见的掐痕。

“明白我有多当真了吧。”

马可若有似无的浅笑让我想起在纽约布隆克斯动物园逗弄过的一条蛇。当我用手指轻敲牢固的玻璃笼舍，那蛇就张开它那有如机械装置的大嘴，看起来好像在笑。然后，它开始不停地攻击那扇透明的玻璃窗，攻击再攻击，直到我离开方休。

我从没见过憎恶女人的人。

但我看得出来，马可恨女人。那晚，满俱乐部里都是模特和小电视明星，他却只盯着我，既非出于善意，也不是因为好奇，而是因为凑巧我被分配给了他。就像一副每张都一样的纸牌中的一张，被发给了他而已。

俱乐部里有个男人走向麦克风，开始摇晃代表南美洲音乐的豆荚状的拨浪鼓。

马可要来拉我的手，但我紧握手中的第四杯代基里鸡尾酒，硬是不动。我以前没喝过代基里，之所以喝它，只是因为马可为我买了这种酒。我很感激他没问我要喝什么，所以酒端上来之后，我二话没说，拿起来猛喝。

马可看着我。

“不要。”我说。

“不要，什么意思？”

“这种音乐我不会跳。”

“别傻了。”

“我要坐在这里把酒喝完。”

马可对着我弯下身子，皮笑肉不笑地伸手一扫，我的酒杯就飞落到了盆栽棕榈树上。然后，他一把抓起我的手，力道之大让我别无选择，不随着他下舞池，就等着被他扯断手臂吧。

“这是探戈。”马可拉着我走进跳舞的人群中，“我就爱探戈。”

“我不会跳。”

“你不必跳，我带着你就行了。”

马可环住我的腰，猛地朝他怀里一拽，我整个人便贴在他白亮的西装上，然后他说：“想象溺水的感觉。”

我闭上眼睛，音乐像暴雨般袭来。马可的脚往前一伸，抵住我的脚，我自然往后一退。整个人像是牢牢贴在他身上，四肢相随，亦步亦趋，完全没有自己的意志和知觉。跳了一会儿，我想：“原来跳舞用不着两个人都会，一个人会跳就够了。”我任自己如风中之树一样摇曳俯仰。

“我说什么来着？”马可的气息让我的耳朵发烫，“你跳得像一个完美的舞者。”

我开始明白为什么憎恶女人的人能将女人玩弄于股掌之间。这种男人就像神：刀枪不入，力大无穷。他们下到凡间，然后又消失，永远不可捉摸。

南美乐曲结束后，音乐暂歇。

马可带着我穿过落地窗走入花园，舞池的窗口溢出灯光和人声，但几码之外，光影被一片漆黑天地所阻隔，再难传远。在星星的微光下，树木和花草散发出冷香。没有月亮的踪影。

黄杨树篱的门在我们身后合上，一片空寂无人的高尔夫球场向着几簇高低起伏的树丛延伸，一切都给我熟悉的荒凉之感——乡村俱乐部，舞会，和只有一只蟋蟀的草坪。

我不知自己身在何处，但肯定是纽约郊区的某个富人区。

马可拿出一根细长的雪茄和一个子弹形状的银质打火机。他用嘴叼住雪茄，低头凑近打火机的小小火焰。火光下，他的脸呈现强烈的明暗光景，看起来疏离陌生，满是苦怨，像个难民。

我看着他。

“你爱着谁？”我问。

马可沉默了有一分钟之久，只是张口吐出氤氲的蓝色烟圈。

“太棒了！”他大笑起来。

烟圈扩散，渐至模糊，在夜色中苍白如幽灵。

他接着说：“我爱上了我表妹。”

我毫不意外。

“那你怎么不娶她？”

“不可能。”

“为什么？”

马可耸耸肩。“她是我亲表妹，她要当修女。”

“她好看吗？”

“没人比得上她。”

“她知道你爱她吗？”

“当然。”

我打住了。在我看来，他们之间的障碍非常不真实。

“既然你爱她，”我说，“将来你也会爱上别人。”

马可把雪茄往地上一掷。

我突然被轻轻撞了一下，跌在地上。泥土陷入我的指间。等我起身到一半，马可伸出双手抓住我的肩头，又把我摔回地上。

“我的衣服……”

“你的衣服！”泥浆顺着我的肩胛骨渗流。“你的衣服！”马可逼近我，满脸阴沉，几颗唾沫星子喷在我的嘴上。“你的衣服是黑的，烂泥也是黑的。”

说完，他猛扑向我，仿佛要用他的身体把我碾碎，一起埋入烂泥。

“发生了。”我心想，“发生了。如果我躺在这儿一动不动，就会发生的。”

马可咬住我的肩带，把我的紧身衣扯到腰际。我看见我赤裸的肌肤微微发光，宛如一方苍白的薄纱，阻隔着两个死对头。

“贱人！”

他在我耳边喘着粗气说出这两个字。

“贱人！”

尘埃落定，让我把这场战役看个清楚。

我开始扭动身体，又踢又咬。

马可把我压在地上。

“贱人！”

我用尖锐的鞋跟狠戳他的腿。他转头摸索伤口。

我攥紧拳头，朝他的鼻子猛地一击，感觉像打在了战舰的钢板上。马可坐起身。我开始哭泣。

马可抽出一条白手帕捂住鼻子，血像墨汁一样在白布上扩散开来。

我吮吸着自己的指关节，尝到了咸咸的味道。

“我要去找朵琳。”

马可望向高尔夫球场的那一头。

“我要找朵琳。我要回家。”

“贱人。全都是贱人。”马可像是自言自语，“听话的，不听话的，都一样贱。”

我捅捅马可的肩膀。

“朵琳人呢？”

马可哼了一声，说：“去停车场找啊。每辆车的后座都别放过。”

说完，他转过身来。

“还我钻石。”

我爬起来，摸黑找回披肩，准备离开。马可跳起来，拦住我，然后有意用手揩了揩鼻下的血渍，在我的脸上来回蹭出两道血痕。“这血足以赎回我的钻石了。还给我。”

“我不知道它丢哪儿去了。”

其实我一清二楚，钻石就在我的晚宴包里。马可扑倒我时，晚宴包像夜鸟投林，被抛入了无尽的黑暗中。我开始盘算，或许应该先引开他，再独自回来寻找。

我不知道那样大小的钻石值多少钱，无论多少，一定很值钱。

马可双手抓住我的肩膀。

“告诉我。”他咬牙切齿地说出每一个字，“告诉我，否则我拧断你的脖子。”

忽然之间，我什么都不在意了。

“就在我那个镶有假黑玉珠的晚宴包里。”我说，“在烂泥里面。”

我走了，听任马可手脚并用，在黑暗中寻找另一个更小的黑暗，这微小的黑暗将钻石的光芒隐藏，令他那愤怒的双眼看不到钻石。

朵琳不在舞池，也不在停车场。一路上我始终躲在阴暗里，免得被人发现我的衣服和高跟鞋上沾满了杂草，我还用黑披肩遮住肩膀和裸露的胸部。

幸好，舞会已接近尾声，宾客成群离去，走向停车场。我一辆接着一辆问，终于问到有辆车仍有空位，愿意捎上我到曼哈顿区的中心。

在暗夜与黎明交错的暧昧时刻，亚马逊宾馆的露天屋顶空无一人。

我穿着有矢车菊枝蔓图案的浴袍，像个小偷似的，悄无声息地走到屋顶短墙边。墙高及肩，所以我从靠墙倚放的一堆折叠椅中抽出一把，打开，爬上摇摇晃晃的椅子。

一阵强风吹起我的头发。脚下的城市，灯火已入眠，黑乎乎的建筑，仿佛在开追悼会。

这是我的最后一晚。

我抓起带来的那捆衣服，揪住一截白色的布料，一件无肩带的弹性衬裙——其实它早已被穿得弹性全无——猛地被我扯出。我挥舞着衬裙，犹如挥舞着求和的白旗，一下，两下……顺着风，我松开了手。

白色的薄裳没入夜色，缓缓下落，不知最后会飘落到哪条街上或哪个屋顶。

我继续从那捆衣服里扯出其他东西。

这次风力不够，一袭状似蝙蝠的黑影落到了对面公寓楼顶的露天花园。

我将衣服一件一件尽付于夜风。灰暗的布片颤颤悠悠，宛如爱人的骨灰随风飘逝，落在此处、彼处，落在纽约市的黑暗的中心，具体落在哪里我真的不得而知。

10

镜中的脸，活像是生了病的印第安人。

我把粉饼盒丢进手提包，望向火车窗外。就像处于一个巨大的垃圾场，康涅狄格州的沼泽和荒地飞快地闪过，这是一个衰败的与世隔绝的碎片。

这世界真是一个大杂烩！

我低头看了看身上这套陌生的衣裙。

绿色的紧腰宽裙，裙面布满黑色、白色和铁青色的小图案，裙身蓬松如灯罩；缀满圆孔的白色衬衫没有袖子，取而代之的是肩部松软的波浪褶边，宛如新生天使的翅膀。

那晚我将所有的衣服都抛入纽约的夜空，却忘了给自己留下一件白天能穿的衣裳，所以贝琪把这身衬衫和裙子给我，换走了我那件有矢车菊图案的浴袍。

我苍白的影子——白色的翅膀，褐色的马尾辫——一切有如幽魂般浮现在窗外的景致里。

“牛仔傻大妞。”我喊了一声。

对面看杂志的女人抬起头来。

直到出发前一刻，我也不想把凝固在脸上的那两道交错的血渍洗掉。它们看起来颇为动人，相当醒目，我甚至想留着它们，就像随身携带死去爱人的遗物，直到它们自然淡去。

当然，如果我笑或者脸部肌肉动得太厉害，血渍就会很快脱落，所以我尽量绷着脸，不得不说话时就从牙缝里挤出几个字，绝不动到嘴巴。

我真搞不懂，人们为什么要把目光落在我身上。

比我怪的人多的是。

灰色皮箱放在我头顶上方的行李架上，里头很空，只放了一本《年度最佳短篇小说三十篇》，一个白色的塑料墨镜盒，和朵琳临行前送的两打鳄梨。

鳄梨尚未成熟，所以很耐放。每当我提起和放下箱子，或哪怕只是拎着它走动时，就会听见它们在箱子里滚来滚去，发出一种微弱而特别的隆隆声。

“一二八线公路到了！”列车员喊道。

人工种植的野生松树、枫树和橡树缓缓停止滑动，在火车窗框中定格成一幅丑陋的画。我走过长长的走道，行李箱一路颠簸作响。

从开着空调的车厢下到车站月台，郊区的气息立刻如慈母般包围了我。那气息闻起来是由草坪洒水器、休旅车、网球拍、宠物狗和婴儿的味道交织而成的。

夏日的静谧如同死亡一样抚慰了一切。

母亲就在那辆灰色的雪佛兰车旁等着我。

“天啊，宝贝，你的脸怎么了？”

“不小心划到了。”我简单地说。把行李箱塞进后座，我也坐了进去。我可不想坐在她旁边，免得被她一路盯着回家。

椅子皮面光滑洁净。

母亲坐到驾驶位上，往我腿上丢了几封信，转回身。

车子低颤着启动。

“我想该让你早点儿知道。”她说。从她脖子的姿势看，我就知道是坏消息。“你没被写作班录取。”

我整个人如泄了气的皮球。

整个六月，如深渊般沉闷的夏天，写作班就像一座光明与安全的桥，是我的盼头。现在，我看到它摇摇晃晃地消失了，一具白衣绿裙的尸体骤然落下深渊。

我的嘴艰涩地闭上。

早料到会是这个结果。

我的脊柱抵着椅背，整个人偷偷往下滑，直到鼻子与车窗下沿齐平，看着窗外波士顿郊区的房舍飞逝而过。房子越来越眼熟，我越缩越低。

我觉得，要紧的是，千万别被人认出来。

包了软垫的灰色车顶在头上罩得严严实实，犹如囚车。窗外的房子钉着清一色的护墙板，白得闪闪发亮，各幢之间种着修剪整齐的绿色植被。房子一幢幢在眼前掠过，好像一个巨大而密不可逃的牢笼的栅栏。

我还从来没在郊区度过夏天。

婴儿车轮子发出女高音般尖厉的声音，刺痛我的耳朵。阳光从百叶窗间隙透进来，整个卧室充满硫黄色的光。我不知道自己睡了多久，只觉得累到虚脱。

旁边的那张床已经空了，还未收拾。

七点时我听见母亲起床，匆促地套上衣服，蹑手蹑脚地走出卧室。然后，楼下传来橙汁机的嗡嗡声，咖啡和培根的香味从门缝底下飘进来。再然后，水槽上的龙头被拧开，一阵叮当作响，是母亲把洗净擦干的餐盘放回碗柜。

接着，前门打开，关上。车门打开，关上，引擎隆隆发动，吱嘎碾过沙砾，慢慢远去了。

母亲在市立大学教很多女生速记和打字，要到下午三四点钟才回家。

婴儿车轮子又发出尖厉的声音，似乎有人在我的窗下来回推着婴儿。

我从床上滑到地毯上，手脚并用，偷偷爬到窗边，看看外面究竟是谁。

我们家不大，外面也钉着白色的护墙板，周围种着一小块绿色草坪，就位于两条宁静的郊区街道的交会处。所以尽管有一排小枫树环绕在房子四周，但是人行道上经过的任何人只要一抬头，就能透过二楼的窗户饱览屋内的风光。

我之所以知道这个，全都拜隔壁的讨人嫌的欧肯丹太太所赐。

老太婆欧肯丹是个退休护士，刚嫁给第三任丈夫的她——两任前夫死因蹊跷——成天躲在自家上了浆的窗帘后面窥探别人。

她曾经两次给我的母亲打过电话告我的密。一次说我在屋前的路灯下坐了一小时，还跟一个开着蓝色普利茅斯的男人亲嘴；另一次提醒我最好放下卧室的百叶窗，因为有一天晚上她出门遛她那只苏格兰小猎犬时，刚好瞧见我半裸着身子准备睡觉。

我小心翼翼地把眼睛凑向窗台。

一个身高不及五英尺的女人，挺着个又丑又凸的大肚子，正推着一辆老旧的黑色婴儿车走在街上。两三个身高不一的孩子跟在她的裙摆下蹒跚而行，全都面色苍白，脸上脏兮兮的，裸露在外的膝盖也脏兮兮的。

女人的脸上洋溢着安详沉静而近于圣洁的微笑。她幸福地仰着头，整个葫芦般的身形像鸭蛋上隆起个麻雀蛋。她对着阳光粲然一笑。

这女人我很熟。

她是朵朵·康威。

朵朵·康威是天主教徒，读完哥伦比亚大学伯纳德女子学院后，嫁给了同是哥大毕业且同是天主教徒的建筑师。他们就住在这条街的另一头，房子很大却乱七八糟，门前是一排长得病歪歪的松树，房子四周散落着代表郊区童年的各色物品——儿童踏板车、三轮脚踏车、娃娃推车、玩具消防车、棒球棍、羽毛球网、棒球的三柱门、仓鼠笼子和小可卡犬玩偶。

不由自主地，我开始注意起朵朵。

她家的房子和左邻右舍的都不一样，大小不同（她家大很多），颜色也特别（二楼的护墙板是深褐色的，一楼则是灰泥墙，上面布满灰色和紫色的状似高尔夫球的圆石），而且周围的松树完全遮挡了视线。这在家家户户草坪相连，篱笆高度只及腰的街坊邻里看来，真是离群寡居的模样。

朵朵的六个孩子——毋庸置疑第七个也即将诞生——全是吃家乐氏的脆米花、花生酱棉花糖三明治、香草冰激凌和一加仑一加仑的护滋牌牛奶长大的，用奶量大到本地的牛奶商愿意给她折扣价。

虽然朵朵家中人口频添，落人话柄，但是大家还是很喜欢她。周围年长的人通常生两个，比如我母亲；年轻一点家境又宽裕的，会生四个。没人像朵朵这样往第七个迈进，就算六个都已嫌多。不过，话锋一转，大伙总是说，当然啦，朵朵是天主教徒嘛。

我看着朵朵推着她家的小康威走来走去，这么做好像就是为了惹毛我。我讨厌小孩。

脚下的地板突然嘎吱一响，我赶紧低头缩腰，与此同时，朵朵·康威不知是出于本能还是听力超强，以她的细脖子为轴，把脸缓缓转向我这一侧。

我觉得她的目光穿透了白色的护墙板和粉红玫瑰壁纸，把蜷伏在银色暖气片后面的我给挖了出来。

我爬回床上，拉过被单，盖住脑袋。可即便如此，仍阻挡不了光线。于是我把头埋进枕头下的漆黑世界，假装已经入夜。我找不到起床的理由。我没有任何期待。

过了一会儿，我听见楼下门厅传来电话铃声。我用枕头塞住耳朵。坚持了五分钟，我把头从枕头拱出的洞里抬起来。铃声已经停了。

几乎同时，铃声再度响起。

不知是哪路亲戚朋友，还是八竿子打不着的什么人，嗅出了我返家的消息，我边诅咒这该死的来电，边光着脚走下了楼。门厅桌上的那个黑乎乎的东西，歇斯底里地发出一声又一声颤音，活像只神经质的鸟。我拿起话筒。“喂。”我故意低声说话。

“喂，埃斯特，你怎么了？喉咙发炎了？”

是我的老友乔蒂从剑桥打来的。

乔蒂这个暑假在学校的合作商店带薪实习，并且修了一门开在午餐时段的社会学课程。她和另外两个跟我同校的女孩向哈佛法学院的四个学生转租了一间大公寓，我本打算写作班一开课，就搬去和她们同住。

乔蒂打电话问我何时过去。

“我不去了。”我说，“我没被录取。”

她沉默了片刻。

“他是笨蛋。”乔蒂说，“有眼无珠，不识好歹。”

“我也这么想。”在我自己听来我的声音陌生而空洞。

“你还是来吧，可以修其他课啊。”

我一下子想到了德语和变态心理学。反正我把在纽约见习的薪水几乎都存下来了，刚好负担得起。

但是那个空洞的声音却说：“还是别把我算在内了。”

“好吧。”乔蒂说，“有个女生想跟我们合租，如果有人要退出的话……”

“好，去找她吧。”

挂上电话的那一刻，我知道我应该答应乔蒂过去的。一整个早上听着朵朵·康威的婴儿车辗来辗去，我一定会发疯。而且，我早就决定，不和母亲住在同一个屋檐下超过一个礼拜。

我伸手想重拾话筒。

手才伸出去几英寸，就缩了回来，颓然下垂。我强迫它再次伸向话筒，但它还是半途停下，仿佛撞上了一扇玻璃。

我漫无目的地走进饭厅。

餐桌上立着两封信。一封长方形的正式信函是暑期学校寄来的；另一封薄薄的蓝色信笺是巴迪·威拉德用剩下的耶鲁信纸写的，上面有他工整清晰的笔迹。

我用刀裁开暑期学校的信。

信里说，我未被写作班录取，可以选择其他课程，但最迟必须于这个早上致电录取办公室，以免耽误注册。另外，各门课程都已接近满员。

我拨通了录取办公室的电话，听到自己僵尸般的声音说，埃斯特·格林伍德小姐取消了前往暑期学校的一切安排。

接着，我打开巴迪·威拉德的信。

信里写道，他很可能爱上了一个同患肺结核的护士，但他妈妈七月在疗养院所在的阿迪伦达克山区租了个小木屋，如果我能同去住上一阵，他或许就会发现自己对那护士只是一时迷恋而已。

我抓过一支铅笔，划掉巴迪写的内容，翻过信纸，在背面写上我已经和一位同声传译官订婚，再也不想见到巴迪，因为我不希望自己孩子的父亲是个伪君子。

我把信纸塞回信封，用透明胶带封口，把收信地址改成巴迪的，邮票不贴了——信里的话值得他到付三分钱邮资。

事毕，我决定要利用这个暑假写本小说。

借此可以修理很多人。

我走进厨房，往一杯生肉糜里打了枚生蛋，搅搅吃了。然后我在房子通往车库那条装有纱窗的通道上支起了一张牌桌。

一大丛摇曳的桑橙挡住了前方的街景，两侧各有屋墙和车库墙作掩护，后面的一片白桦树和一排黄杨树篱让我免受欧肯丹太太的窥视。

我数出三百五十张母亲藏在客厅壁橱中一堆旧毡帽、衣服刷和羊毛围巾下面的高级可改写打字纸。

回到通道，我把第一张洁白的纸放入我那台老旧的便携式打字机，卷好。

另一个疏离的自我，看着自己坐在通道里，周围是两堵钉有白色护板的墙、一丛桑橙树、一片白桦树和一排黄杨树篱，小小的我有如身处娃娃屋里的娃娃。

一股柔情盈满心中。我的女主角就是我自己，只是会加以伪装。她的名字叫依莲。依莲，我伸出指头数了数，和埃斯特一样，都是六个字母，看样子是个好兆头。

依莲穿着母亲的黄色旧睡袍，坐在通道里，等着发生点什么。这是个闷热的七月清晨，汗珠一滴滴从背上滑落，如同小虫慢慢爬过。

我往椅背上一靠，看着自己写的东西。

挺生动的，把汗珠比作虫子这句我尤为得意。只是隐约觉得，很久以前似乎在哪儿读过类似的话。

我就这么呆坐了一个小时，绞尽脑汁想着接下来要做什么。在我的脑海中，那个穿着母亲黄色旧睡袍的娃娃也和我一样，赤足呆坐，茫然凝望。

“怎么了，亲爱的？还不想换衣服吗？”

母亲很小心，从来不强迫我做任何事，只是好声好气地和我讲道理，像两个理智成熟的大人在打交道。

“快下午三点了呢。”

“我在写小说。”我说，“没那闲工夫换来换去的。”

我躺在通道的沙发上，闭着眼。我能听见母亲把牌桌上的打字机和纸张收走，摆上晚餐的银餐具，但是我一动没动。

惰性如糖浆，从依莲的四肢缓缓渗出。她心想：得疟疾就是这个感觉吧。

无论如何，一天能写出一页已属万幸。

然后，我意识到了问题出在哪儿。

我需要历练。

没谈过恋爱，没生过小孩，连死亡也未曾目睹，我能写出什么人生？我认识一个女孩，刚得了个短篇小说奖，人家的故事写的是在非洲俾格米族中的奇遇。这样的经历我怎么比得上？

晚餐结束前，母亲终于说服我，利用晚上时间跟她学速记。我想，这也算一石二鸟吧，既不耽误我写小说，又能学点一技之长。当然，还省了一大笔学费。

当天晚上，母亲就从地下室翻出了一块旧黑板，支在了通道里。她站在黑板前，用白粉笔在上面潦草地写出一些小小的花体字，我就坐在椅子上看着。

一开始，我觉得很有希望。

我想，用不了多久，我就能学会速记。等学校奖学金办公室那个雀斑女士问起，作为领奖学金的女孩，为何我没有在七八月打工赚钱的时候，我就可以告诉她，我利用这段时间上了免费的速记课，这样一毕业我就能养活自己了。

唯一的问题是，当我试图想象自己开始上班，敏捷地速记下一行行信息时，脑子里竟变得一片空白。那些需要速记的工作我一个都不想做。我就那么坐着，看着白粉笔写出的花体字模糊成一片无意义的符号。

我跟母亲说头疼得很，便上床去睡觉了。

过了一小时，门一点点地开了，母亲蹑手蹑脚进了卧室。我听见她窸窸窣窣脱衣服的声音。听见她爬上床。然后她的呼吸渐渐变得缓慢而均匀。

在透过闭合的百叶窗进入室内的昏黄的街灯光芒下，我看见她头上的发卷像刺刀一样闪闪发光。

我决定把小说先放一放，等我去趟欧洲、谈场恋爱再说。至于速记，我一个字也不要学了。如果我坚决不学，就永远也用不到它。

这个暑假就用来读读《芬尼根守灵夜》，写写论文吧。

这样一来，等九月底开学时，我就能好整以暇地享受大学的最后一年，免得像大部分成绩优异的毕业生那样，成日里刻苦用功，把自己搞得蓬头垢面，要靠咖啡和苯丙胺提神，直到论文完成的那一刻方歇。

我又想，不妨推迟一年毕业，去当个陶艺学徒。

要么，想办法去德国当女招待，把德语学会了再回来。

计划一个接一个在脑海中窜来窜去，像一窝狂躁的兔子。

我看见我的人生就像路边一根根以电线相连的电话线杆子，我数着一、二、三……数到第十九根，不论我怎么努力，后面一根杆子也见不到，徒留一截电线在空中飘荡。

房间渐呈蓝色，不知道夜晚跑哪儿去了。母亲的轮廓从一截模糊的木头变为沉睡的中年妇人，嘴巴微张，鼾声从她喉咙冒上来。猪哼似的鼾声真是恼人，有那么片刻，我觉得唯一能阻止这种噪音的方法，只有抓住发出鼾声的那根肉柱，用两手狠狠扭断。

我假装睡觉，直到母亲离开家去学校。可眼睛就算闭着，也挡不住光。眼皮的毛细血管交织成两片刺眼的红帘，像血淋淋的伤口挂在我眼前。我钻入床垫和床架之间，让床垫像墓碑一样压着我，我躲在下面，又黑又安全，只可惜床垫不够重。

还得再来一吨重的东西压着我，我才睡得着。

江河奔腾，流过夏娃与亚当的家，从凸出的河岸，到凹入的海湾。江河宽阔，复始循环，把我们带回霍斯堡和郊外……

《芬尼根守灵夜》真厚，把我的肚子硌出一道令人不快的凹痕。

江河奔腾，流过夏娃与亚当的家……

我在想，第一个词“江河奔腾”之所以首字母小写，可能是为了表示没有任何事物真正拥有全新的开端，一切只是承载过往，延续而来。“夏娃与亚当的家”，指的就是亚当和夏娃。当然，也有可能另有所指。

也许指的是都柏林的某间酒馆。

我的视线在一锅字母杂烩汤里逡巡，落在页面中间那串长长的单词上。

bababadalgharaghtakamminarronnkonnbronntonnerron-ntuonnthunntrovarrhounawnskawntoohoohoordenenthurnuk!

我数了数，正好一百个字母。我想，其中必有深意。

为什么是一百个字母？

揣度犹疑之间，我大声念出这个单词。

听起来就像一块沉重的木制品滚下楼梯，砰砰砰，一级级下落。我提起书页，在眼前缓缓翻动，那些字依稀熟悉，但又像哈哈镜里的脸一样扭曲，且稍纵即逝，未曾在我脑中平滑的镜面上留下丝毫痕迹。

我斜眼看着书页。

看着看着，字母慢慢变成了倒钩和羊角，一个个分离开来，傻兮兮地上下跳动，然后结合成不可思议、难以理解的形状，像是阿拉伯文或者中文。

我决定把论文抛到一边。

同时，也放弃整套优等生课程，只做个英文系的普通学生。我去查了校方对英文系普通学生的要求。

必修课还真多，我上过的一半都不到。其中一门是十八世纪文学，但我想到十八世纪就觉得讨厌。那时的作家都自命不凡，总是写那种严格遵守韵律要求的两行诗，而且极端热衷理性，所以我没选这门课。我们优等生就是有更多的选课自由，所以我的时间多半用来研究狄兰·托马斯(1)。

我有个朋友也是优等生，她就有办法一个字不读莎士比亚，却是研究T.S.艾略特《四首四重奏》的真正专家。

我明白了从选课自由的优等生变成选课诸多限制的普通生，根本不可能，而且也很丢人，所以我去查了母亲任教的那所市立大学英文系的要求。

那里更惨。

你需要懂古英语和英语语言史，还得把从《贝奥武甫》到当代文学的所有代表性作品都读过。

这着实让我大吃一惊。我向来瞧不起我母亲的那所学校，因为它不仅男女同校，而且只有那些拿不到奖学金进东海岸名校的学生才会就读。

现在我才发现，这所学校里最笨的学生都比我懂得多。估计他们连校门都不会让我进，更不用说让他们像我的学校那样，提供给我一大笔奖学金了。

我想我最好先工作一年，把事情想清楚再说。或者我可以私底下学习十八世纪文学。

可我不会速记，能做什么呢？

当个女招待或者打字员。

随便哪个，想想都觉得无法忍受。

“你要我多开点安眠药给你？”

“对。”

“可我上周开给你的，药效已经很强了。”

“现在没有什么效果了。”

特雷莎那双黑色的大眼睛若有所思地望着我。我听见她的三个孩子在诊察室窗外的花园里玩耍。我的姨妈莉比嫁给了一个意大利人，特雷莎就是我姨妈的小姑子，也是我们的家庭医生。

我喜欢特雷莎。她性情温柔又直觉敏感。

我觉得这一定是因为她是意大利人。

出现了片刻沉默。

“问题出在哪儿？”特雷莎问。

“我睡不着，也看不进书。”我试图以一种冷静沉着的语气说话，但那个僵尸又出现了，扼住了我的喉咙，我只好无奈地双手一摊。

“我有个建议。”特雷莎从处方笺上撕下一张纸，写上一个名字和地址，“你最好去看看我认识的这个医生，他比我更能帮助你。”

我费力地看了半天，但我读不出那个名字。

“戈登大夫。”特雷莎说，“他是精神科医生。”

(1) 狄兰•托马斯（Dylan Thomas，1914-1953），英国作家、诗人，一九四六年发表人生中最重要的一部诗集《死亡和出场》，评论界普遍认为他是继奥登以后英国的又一位重要诗人。

11

戈登大夫的候诊室里肃穆安静，一片米黄。

墙是米黄色，地毯是米黄色，软座椅和沙发也是米黄色。墙上没有镜子或画作，只挂着不同医学院颁发的证书，以拉丁文写着戈登大夫的名字。茶几上、咖啡桌上、书报桌上都放有陶瓷花盆，种着卷绕的浅绿色蕨类和尖叶的深绿色观赏植物。

起初，我不知道为什么这间屋子让人这么有安全感，后来才发现是因为没有窗户。

空调冷得我直哆嗦。

我还穿着跟贝琪换来的那身白衣绿褶裙，衣裙有点松垮垮的，因为回到家的这三个礼拜一直没洗。汗湿过的棉布散发出一股酸臭但透着友好的气息。

我也三个礼拜没洗头。

七夜没睡。

母亲说我一定睡着过，人不可能那么久没睡。但就算我真的睡着过，也一定是睁着眼睡的，因为我一直盯着床边时钟的秒针、分针、时针，看着绿色的夜光指针一圈一圈地做着圆周运动，七个夜晚里夜夜如是，一秒、一分、一时都未曾错过。

我不洗衣服、不洗头，因为做这些事感觉很蠢。

我看见白昼像一个个明亮的白盒子在我面前展开，将一个个盒子分隔开来的，是宛如黑影的睡眠。只是于我，将白盒子切分开来的长长黑影突然断裂了，眼前只有灼灼白昼，日日相连，仿佛一条白亮广袤又无尽苍凉的大路。

今日洗了，明日又得洗，真是蠢透了。

只是想想都累得慌。

凡事我只想一次搞定，彻底解决。

戈登大夫转着手中的银色铅笔。

“你母亲说你情绪低落。”

我蜷缩在凹陷的皮椅中，隔着一张光可鉴人的大桌子和戈登大夫对视。

戈登大夫等着我的回答，手中的铅笔轻轻敲在整洁的绿色记事簿上——咄，咄，咄。

他的睫毛又长又密，看起来好像假的，有如黑色的塑料芦苇围绕着两汪冰冷的绿潭。

戈登大夫的五官堪称完美，算得上是美男子。

可我进门的那一刹那，就已经讨厌他了。

在我的想象中，应该是个其貌不扬但直觉敏锐的和蔼男人，抬头看我并用一种鼓励的口吻对我说“啊！”，仿佛他能见我所不能，如此我就知道该怎么告诉他我有多害怕，感觉像是整个人被塞进了一个黑袋子，越陷越深，没有空气，没有出路。

然后，他会往椅背上一靠，把双手指尖顶成一个小尖塔，跟我解释为什么我睡不着觉、看不进书、吃不下饭，为什么我看别人做什么都觉得愚蠢至极，既然人终归是要死的。

再然后，我想，他就能帮我一步步地找回自我。

但是，戈登大夫跟我想象的完全不一样。他年轻俊美，我一眼就看出他颇为自负。

戈登大夫的桌上摆了个银色的相框，半对着他，半对着我坐的皮椅。相框里是张家庭合照，两个金发孩子的头顶上露出一个美丽的黑发女人，笑意盈盈，没准儿是他的姐妹。

我猜两个孩子或许是一男一女，不过也有可能两个都是男孩或两个都是女孩，太小的孩子总是难以分辨。我觉得照片最下方有一只狗——某种艾尔谷狗或者金毛猎犬——不过，没准只是女人裙子上的一个图案。

不知怎的，这张照片让我很恼火。

我看不出有什么理由让照片半对着我，除非戈登大夫自我进门就想向我表明，他家有娇妻，千万不要对他存有什么非分之想。

然后我想，这位戈登大夫有那么漂亮的妻子，那么漂亮的孩子，那么漂亮的狗，他们就像是圣诞卡片上的天使一样环绕着他，这样的医生怎么能帮我脱离苦海呢？

“你试着说说觉得哪里不对劲。”

我满腹狐疑地把这话翻来覆去地想了好几遍，就怕它像被海水冲刷过的鹅卵石突然伸出一只利爪，变成别的什么。

我觉得哪里不对劲？

这话听起来好像是没什么事情不对劲，是我觉得它们不对劲。

我用平淡无趣的声音——好表明他的外貌和全家福丝毫没有令我动心——告诉戈登大夫我无法睡觉、无法吃饭、无法看书，但没说关于写字的事，其实这是最令我困扰的。

那天早上，我想写信给人在西弗吉尼亚的朵琳，问她我能否去和她同住，在她学校找个端盘子之类的兼职。

可是，当我提起笔，我的手写出的字竟如孩童般拙劣，粗大扭曲，几行字从左上角一路歪到右下角，几乎要斜成对角线，好像放在纸上的线圈，被人吹得歪七扭八。

我知道我不能把这样的信寄出去，所以把它撕成碎片，放进手提包，塞在万用化妆盒边上，没准精神科医生会想看看。

但是戈登大夫没说要看，因为我压根儿没提，我挺得意自己的这点小聪明。我打算只跟他说我想说的，该说的说，该瞒的瞒，这样我就能控制他对我的看法，而他还以为他有多厉害呢。

我说话的时候，戈登大夫一直低着头，像在祈祷。整个房间除了我平淡无趣的声音，就只有他的铅笔在绿色记事簿的同一个位置敲个不停发出的声音——咄，咄，咄——有如一根停在原地的拐杖。

我说完了，戈登大夫抬起头。“你说你上的哪所大学？”我被问得一头雾水，但还是告诉了他。搞不懂念哪所学校和我的病有什么关系。“哈！”戈登大夫往椅背一靠，带着怀旧的笑容望向我肩膀的上方。

我以为他要跟我说说诊断结果，这让我觉得先前对他的判断有点太过武断且不友善了。不料，他只是说：“我还清楚地记得贵校。二战期间我就在那儿。那儿有一个陆军妇女队，是不是？或是一个海军妇女辅援队？”

我说我不知道。

“对，是陆军妇女队，我想起来了。我在那儿当医生，后来被派到海外。天啊，那儿的女孩子可真多啊。”

戈登大夫笑了起来。

接着，他如行云流水般地站起身，绕过桌角走向我。我不晓得他要干什么，也跟着站起来。

戈登大夫伸手握住我垂在身侧的右手，摇了摇。

“那下周见了。”

浓密起伏的榆树连成了一条林荫隧道，遮蔽了联邦大道两侧的红黄砖房。一辆电车沿着细长的银色轨道驶向波士顿。我等电车通过，穿过马路，走向停在对面路边的灰色雪佛兰。

我看见挡风玻璃后母亲一脸忧虑地看着我，面色发黄，像一片柠檬。

“如何？医生怎么说？”

我拉上车门，但没关好，推开，再关一次，门发出砰的一声。

“他说下周见。”

母亲叹了口气。

戈登大夫的诊金一小时要二十五美元。

“嗨，你叫什么名字？”

“艾莉·希金巴腾。”

一名水兵和我并肩而行。我微微笑了。

我想，波士顿公园里的水兵一定跟鸽子一样多。他们似乎是从远处那栋暗褐色的征兵处走出来的。房子外侧的布告栏和内侧的墙面都贴满了“加入海军”的蓝白色海报。

“艾莉，你从哪儿来？”

“芝加哥。”

我没去过芝加哥，不过认识一两个芝加哥大学的男生。那个城市感觉是那种不墨守成规却又迷惘彷徨的人待的地方。

“你离家真远。”

水兵伸手搂住我的腰，我们就这样在公园里逛了好久。他隔着我的绿色宽褶裙抚摸我的臀部，我神秘地笑着，尽量不说出任何会泄露出我就是波士顿人的话，也不让他发现我随时有遇见熟人的可能性，比如威拉德太太，或者我母亲的朋友——她们或许在比肯山喝完下午茶，或许逛完飞琳地下商场的名品折扣店，正要穿过公园。

我想，如果我能去芝加哥，或许就可以把名字永远改成艾莉·希金巴腾，这样就不会有人知道我放弃了东部著名女校的奖学金，跑到纽约瞎混了一个月，还拒绝了一个十足完美的医学院学生，他可是终有一天会成为美国医学会的会员，赚得盆满钵满的。

芝加哥人会接受本来的我。

我就是艾莉·希金巴腾，一个孤儿。人们会喜欢我甜美、文静的个性，不会逼我读书，要我就詹姆斯·乔伊斯作品里的双胞胎写出长长的论文。或许有一天，我会嫁给一个外刚内柔的汽车修理工，像朵朵·康威那样生一窝孩子。

但愿我真想这么做。

“你退伍后要做什么？”我突然问道。

这是我和那水兵说的最长的一句话，他吓了一跳，伸手推推头上纸杯蛋糕状的白色水兵帽，挠了挠头。

“呃，不知道呢，艾莉。”他说，“可能用退伍津贴去上大学吧。”

我沉吟片刻，然后给出一个建议：“有没有想过开间汽车修理厂？”

“没有。”水兵回答，“从没想过。”

我用眼角打量着他，这小伙子肯定还不到十六岁。

“你知道我多大了吗？”我带着指责的语气问。

水兵冲我咧嘴一笑。“不知道，也不在乎。”

我突然发现他长得真帅气，有北欧人的轮廓，模样也清纯。自我心思变得单纯之后，吸引的似乎也是清纯英俊的男人了。

“好吧，我三十了。”我说完，等着他的反应。

“哇，艾莉，真看不出来。”水兵捏了捏我的臀部。

然后他匆匆往左右一瞥。“我说，艾莉，我们走去纪念碑下的台阶吧，如果可以，我想在那儿吻你。”

就在那时，我发现有个穿着结实的棕色平底鞋的褐色身影正大步穿过公园，朝我的方向走来。距离尚远，看不清她硬币大小的脸上的五官，但我知道那肯定是威拉德太太。

“请问到地铁的路怎么走？”我大声询问水兵。

“啊？”

“去鹿岛监狱的地铁怎么走？”

等威拉德太太走近了，我得装作只是跟水兵问个路，根本不认识他。

“把你的手拿开。”我咬着牙低声说。

“喂，艾莉，怎么回事？”

那女人走近了，与我擦肩而过，目不斜视，头也不点。当然，这不是威拉德太太，她此刻正在阿迪伦达克山区的小木屋里吧。

我恨恨地盯着那女人远去的背影。

“我说，艾莉……”

“我以为是我认识的人。”我说，“芝加哥孤儿院里的一个恶毒女人。”

水兵再次伸手搂住我。

“你是说你无父无母，艾莉？”

“是的。”一滴泪来得恰逢其时，在我脸上划出一小道灼热的泪痕。

“艾莉，别哭啊。这个女人是不是对你很坏？”

“她……她坏透了。”

说着，我泪如雨下。在一株美国榆树的树荫下，水兵搂着我，用他白净的亚麻大手帕拭干我的眼泪，我则暗自恨着那个穿褐色衣服的坏女人。不论她知不知道，她都要为我转错弯、走错路，为我之后发生的一切不幸负责。

“嗯，埃斯特，这周感觉如何？”

铅笔在戈登大夫的手中真像一颗细长的银色子弹。

“老样子。”

“老样子？”他蹙了蹙一条眉毛，好像难以置信。

所以我又说了一遍，用的是完全一样的平板单调的声音，只是带了些怒气，谁让他如此愚钝，根本不能理解十四天睡不着、读不进、写不出、咽不下是什么感觉。

戈登大夫对此似乎无动于衷。

我从提包里翻出写给朵琳的那封信的碎片，一把撒在戈登大夫纤尘不染的绿色记事簿上，散落的碎片犹如夏日草原上的雏菊花瓣，静默无语。

“你——”我问他，“对此有何想法？”

我以为戈登大夫会立即看看我的字有多糟糕，可他只是说：“我想和你母亲谈谈，不介意吧？”

“不介意。”但我一点也不喜欢这个主意。我猜他大概会让母亲把我关起来。我把给朵琳的信纸碎片一一捡拾干净，这样戈登大夫就没法把它们拼凑起来，发现我的逃跑计划。接着，我一言不发，离开他的办公室。

我看着母亲的身影越变越小，消失在戈登大夫所在的办公楼的门口。然后，又看着她的身影越来越大，回到车上。

“如何？”我看出她哭过。

母亲没看我，径直发动了车子。

车子驶过如深海般蔽日的榆树凉荫，她终于开口：“戈登大夫觉得你的治疗丝毫没有进展，建议你去他位于沃尔顿的私人诊所接受电击治疗。”

我升起一股强烈的好奇心，好像刚刚听到了一则恐怖的头条新闻，和自己全无关系。

“他的意思是，要我住在那里？”

“不是。”母亲答道，下巴簌簌颤抖。

我想她一定在说谎。

“你跟我说实话。”我对她说，“要不我这辈子都不理你了。”

“我什么时候没跟你说实话了？”母亲说着，眼泪忽然夺眶而出。

七楼跳窗自杀者获救

男子乔治·博鲁希爬上水泥停车场上方七楼高的一处狭窄窗沿，在大量围观群众注视下，僵持两小时之久，最后终于接受查尔斯街警署的威尔·克尔马丁警官从临窗伸出的援手，安然脱险。

我买了一袋十美分的花生喂鸽子，随手掰开一个丢进嘴里。花生索然无味，像在啃一片老树皮。

我把报纸贴近眼睛，想看清乔治·博鲁希的长相。聚光灯下，他的脸就像四分之三个月亮，背景是模糊的墙砖和黑色的天空。我觉得他有重要的信息要告诉我，不管是什么，很可能就写在他的脸上。

可是当我盯着乔治·博鲁希肮脏、布满皱纹的脸，他的脸却化成深浅不一的灰点组成的规则图案。

黑黢黢的报纸上的一段话并没有解释为什么博鲁希先生会爬上窗沿，也没交代克尔马丁警官做了什么才得以把他拉回窗子里。

跳楼的麻烦在于，万一没有选对楼层，你很可能着地之后还活着。我想，七楼这样的高度一定很保险。

我把报纸折起来，塞进公园长椅的板条之间。这种我母亲所谓的八卦小报，上面满是当地的凶杀、自杀、斗殴、抢劫这类新闻，几乎每一页都有一个半裸女子，酥胸呼之欲出，并露出长筒丝袜的上缘，十分撩人。

我不知道为什么以前从来没买过这种报纸，这是我现在唯一看得进的东西。穿插在照片之间的文字寥寥可数，段落短小到没机会搔首弄姿、一展魅力。我家只有《基督教科学箴言报》，周一到周六，每天早上五点，它都会出现在门前的台阶上。它从不报道自杀、性犯罪和坠机之类的事件，就仿佛从来都不会发生这样的事情。

一只白色大天鹅带着一群天鹅宝宝向我的长椅游来，绕过树木成荫、遍布鸭子的小岛，游回拱桥下的阴暗处。我眼中的一切都变得亮晃晃的，极小极小。

那感觉就像透过一个无法打开的门上的钥匙孔，我看见我和身高只到我膝盖的弟弟，拿着兔耳朵形状的气球，爬上一条浮在漂满花生壳的水面上的天鹅船，争抢靠边的座位。我的嘴里有清新的薄荷味。如果在牙医诊所表现得很乖，母亲就会买票让我们坐一回天鹅船。

我绕着公园闲逛——走过小桥，走过蓝绿色的纪念碑，走过排列成美国国旗样式的花圃，走过公园入口，那儿有个橙白条纹的帆布照相亭，拍一次收费二十五美分——我一路读着每一棵树的名称。

我最喜欢的一棵叫“哭泣的学者”，我想它一定原产于日本，只有日本人才明白什么是精神。

如果搞砸事情，他们会切腹谢罪。

我试着想象切腹的过程。一定要有一把锋利无比的刀子。不，很可能需要两把。然后坐下，盘腿，两手各执一刀，双手交叉，刀子对准肚子两侧。人必须裸身，否则衣服会卡住刀子。

转瞬间，刀子戳入腹中，弧形拉动，后悔已来不及——切腹者将两刀向上下各划出半圈，合成一个完整的圆。接着，一块圆盘似的肚皮松垮下来，内脏流出，切腹者死去。

这种死法需要极大的勇气。

我的问题在于讨厌见血。

我想我干脆在公园待上一整晚算了。

明天早上，朵朵·康威就要开车载上我和母亲去戈登大夫位于沃尔顿的私人诊所了，现在开溜为时未晚。我数了数钱包里的钱，只有一张一美元的钞票，还有其他硬币，加起来也不过七十九美分。

不知道到芝加哥要多少钱，我也不敢到银行取出我所有的钱，因为我怕戈登大夫早就通知了银行职员，若我有异常举动必须加以阻拦。

我忽然想到搭便车，但我连从波士顿到芝加哥有几条路都搞不清。在地图上找到方向并不难，可一旦我身处现实之中，就完全没有了方向感。每次我想借助太阳分辨东西南北时，就碰到正午或阴天，太阳完全用不上；到了晚上，除了北斗七星和仙后座的五星座椅以外，我别的星星都不认识，巴迪·威拉德常对此感到泄气。

我决定走到公交总站，打听到芝加哥的票价。然后再去银行，只取出买车票的钱，这样就不会惹人生疑。

我不紧不慢地穿过车站的玻璃门，浏览着架子上花花绿绿的旅游传单和时刻表，突然想到下午已经过半，镇上的银行就快关门了，看来得等明天才能取钱了。

沃尔顿诊所跟我约的时间是明早十点。

就在这时，扩音器嘶啦一声开始广播，宣布外头停车场的一辆公交车即将启程，并一一通报了沿途站名。扩音器里的声音照例啪啪作响，你根本一个字都听不清楚，但就在静电干扰声中，我听见一个熟悉的站名，就像一整个弦乐团在调音时，你清晰地听到钢琴弹奏出的音。

那一站离我家只有两个街区。

我疾步走入七月末午后尘埃滚滚的热浪之中，汗流浃背，满口飞沙，像来不及赶赴一场艰难的面试，终于在那辆红色公交车引擎发动的时候上了车。

我把票钱递给司机，身后车门的铰链转动，车门悄然合上。

12

戈登大夫的私人诊所矗立在一座绿茵小丘之上，通向小丘的悠长而隐蔽的车道铺着圆蛤碎壳，一片白色。房子很大，黄色护墙板和四面回廊在太阳照耀下闪闪发光，但绿草青丘却不见有人漫步。

顶着袭人的暑气，母亲和我走向诊所。蝉声聒噪，像半空中开了台割草机，其实它们远远躲在诊所后面的一棵铜红山毛榉树上，反倒令这四周的空寂愈发无边。

一个护士站在门口迎接我们。

“请在客厅稍候，戈登医生马上就来。”

诊所里看似一切正常，反令我心中忐忑，因为我知道里面一定关着一屋子的疯子。窗户上看不见铁栏杆，也听不到让人不安的狂躁叫声，阳光被均匀地分割成长椭圆形，投射在陈旧但柔软的红地毯上，空气中弥漫着刚刚割完草的宜人清香。

我在客厅入口停下脚步。

恍惚之间，我以为这是我曾去过的缅因州海边小岛上某个宾馆的休息室。耀眼的白光自落地窗照进来，远处的角落有一架大钢琴，人们穿着夏装，或坐在牌桌边，或坐在歪斜的藤制扶手椅上——在脏乱破败的海边风景区常看到的那种椅子。

然后，我才发现这些人都一动不动。

我更仔细观察，试图从他们僵硬的姿势上找到一点线索。渐渐地，我分辨出男女，有些男孩女孩跟我一样年轻，所有人脸上的表情都如出一辙，好像已经在架子上闲置了很久，不见天日，覆上了一层灰白的微尘。

接着，我注意到有些人其实在动，只是动作细微堪比小鸟，初看之下难以察觉。

一个面色发灰的男人正数着手中的一沓扑克牌，一、二、三、四……我以为他肯定是在检查这副牌是否完整，没想到他数完后又从头数起。他旁边的胖女人在玩一串木珠子，她把所有珠子拢到线绳的一头，然后，嗒嗒嗒，让它们落回另一头。

一个女孩在钢琴前翻阅着琴谱，发现我在看她，竟然愤愤地低下头，将琴谱一撕两半。

母亲碰了碰我的胳膊，我跟着她走进房间。

我俩坐下，没有说话，身下是凹凸不平的沙发，稍稍一动就嘎吱作响。

我的视线越过客厅里的人，落在半透明窗帘后的那片盎然绿意上，感觉自己像是坐在一家大百货商店的橱窗里，四周的人都不是真的，而是店里的假人，描画得与人相像，神态也装得与活人一样。

我跟在穿着黑色外套的戈登大夫后面走上楼。

在楼下大厅时，我想问他电击治疗是怎么回事，可我张开嘴时却一个字也说不出来，只能睁大眼睛看着他那张带着笑容、满是自信的熟悉脸庞，像一只盘子飘浮在我面前。

石榴色的地毯铺到楼梯的顶端，换成了钉在地板上的朴素的褐色油毡，沿着走廊一路延伸，两侧是一扇扇紧闭的白色大门。我跟着戈登大夫往前走，远处的一扇门打开，我听到一个女人在呼叫。

冷不防，一个护士从我们前面的走廊转角冒出来，拖了一个穿着蓝色浴袍、蓬着一头及腰长发的女人。戈登大夫往后一退，我也赶紧贴墙而立。

女人一边被护士紧紧拖着，一边挥舞着手臂挣扎，嘴里不停嚷嚷：“我要跳窗，我要跳窗，我要跳窗。”

矮壮结实的护士穿着正面脏污的制服，拿斜视的眼睛直盯着我，两只圆圆的镜片厚到居然显现出四只眼睛。我尽力分辨哪只眼睛是真的，哪只是假的；真眼中哪只是斜视，哪只是直视。她却突然凑近我，居心叵测地咧着大嘴，笑得嘶嘶作响，好像在向我保证一般地说：“她以为可以跳窗，可她根本办不到，因为窗户都上了铁条！”

戈登大夫领我走进位于后方的一个空荡荡的房间。我发现这里的窗户果然都安了铁栏杆，房门、橱门和柜子的抽屉，一切能打开关上的东西都配了锁孔，以便上锁。

我躺到床上。

斜眼护士进来，解下我的手表，丢进她的口袋。然后她又开始扯我头发上的发夹。

戈登大夫打开上锁的柜子，拖出一张带滚轮的桌子，推到我的床头后面，桌上摆着一台机器。护士开始把一种难闻的油脂涂在我的太阳穴上。

她俯身涂抹我靠墙那侧的太阳穴时，丰满的胸脯像云朵或枕头一样蒙住我的脸，一股淡淡的药臭味从她身上散发出来。

“别担心。”她低头又对我笑，“每个人第一次都怕得要死。”

我想回赠一个笑脸，但皮肤僵得像羊皮纸。

戈登大夫把两个金属片贴在我的头两侧，用一条皮带固定住，皮带嵌入我的前额，然后再让我咬住一条电线。

我闭上眼睛。

短暂的安静，仿佛深吸了一口气。

然后，有个东西欺身而近，抓住我，用力摇撼，如世界末日来临。吱——它发出尖锐的声音，空中蓝光乍现，噼啪爆裂，每一次闪光就是一次剧烈的撞击，直痛得我魂飞魄散、骨碎血溅，好像树木被闪电劈裂。

我到底犯了什么滔天大罪？

我坐在藤椅里，端着小鸡尾酒杯装着的番茄汁。表又回到我的手腕上，但看起来怪怪的，原来是戴倒了。我察觉到，发夹在我头发里的位置也不是我熟悉的地方。

“感觉怎么样？”

我的脑海中浮现起一盏旧的金属落地灯，它是我父亲书房里为数不多的遗物之一。上面有一个钟形铜座托着灯泡，一条虎皮色的破损电线从铜座垂下，接入墙上的插座中。

一天，我打算把这盏灯从母亲的床头挪到房间另一头，放在我的书桌旁。电线足够长，所以我没拔插头，直接用双手紧握住落地灯柱和毛糙的破电线。

突然，灯柱里跳出一道蓝光，把我震得牙齿打战，我想松开手，可是手被吸住了，我放声尖叫。或者该说尖叫声冲破我的喉咙，因为我完全认不得那声音，只听见它在空中颤抖，像灵魂被残暴地驱离了肉体。

双手猝然挣脱，我往后一仰，倒在母亲的床上。右手掌正中有一个像被铅笔芯戳中的小黑坑。

“感觉怎么样？”

“还好。”

才不好呢，我感觉糟透了。

“你说你读的哪所大学？”

我说出校名。

“啊！”戈登大夫的脸缓缓绽开一个简直算得上热情的笑容，“二战期间那里有个陆军妇女队，是吧？”

母亲的指关节是骨白色，好像在等我的这段时间关节上的皮肤都脱落了。她望向我身后的戈登大夫，神色一松，后者必定是跟她点了个头或露出了个笑容。

“再做几次电击治疗，格林伍德太太。”我听见戈登大夫说，“我想，你就会看见她大有进展。”

那个女孩依旧坐在钢琴凳上，撕破的琴谱像只死鸟落在她的脚边。她瞪着我，我也瞪着她。她眯起眼，对我吐出舌头。

母亲跟着戈登大夫走到门口，我磨磨蹭蹭跟在后面，他们俩一转身，我就转头对着那女孩，捏着耳朵做鬼脸。她缩回舌头，变回了石头脸。

我走到户外的阳光下。

朵朵·康威的黑色旅行车像一只黑豹，等候在光影斑驳的树荫下。

这辆旅行车原本是个富有的名媛预订的，车身全黑，没有一点儿杂色，连内饰皮革也是黑的。结果车子一到，名媛看了之后好不沮丧，说这根本就是辆灵车，其他人也这么觉得，所以没人接手。于是，康威夫妇狠狠杀价，省了好几百美元，把车开回了家。

坐在前排的我，夹在母亲和朵朵之间，浑身无力，倍感压抑。每次想集中精神，心思就像溜冰似的，滑入广袤虚无之中，在那里自顾旋转。

“我受够戈登大夫了。”下车后，看着朵朵的黑色旅行车消失在松树后面，我对母亲说，“你给他打电话，说我下周不会去了。”

母亲微笑着道：“我就知道我的宝贝不是那样的。”

我看着她，问：“哪样？”

“那些可怕的人。医院里的那些行尸走肉。”她顿了顿，“我知道，你会下决心恢复正常的。”

新晋女星，昏迷68小时，终告不治

我在皮包里摸索了半天——纸片，化妆盒，花生壳，硬币，装着十九片吉列剃须刀片的蓝色盒子——终于找到那天下午在公园橙白条纹照相亭里拍的快照。

我把我的照片置于报纸上那张不治身亡的女星照片旁。她的照片有点模糊，但是两张照片看起来真像啊，嘴巴像，鼻子也像。唯一不像的是眼睛。快照里我的眼睛是睁着的，报纸照片中她的眼睛是闭着的。可我知道，如果用手指撑开她的眼睛，它们会如同快照里我的眼睛一样，死气沉沉、黝黑空洞地望向我。

我把快照塞回皮包。

“我就坐在公园的长椅上，晒着太阳，看着那边钟楼上的时钟，多待五分钟吧。”我心里想，“然后，我就找个地方动手。”

我召唤出脑海中小小的声音合奏。

你对工作提不起兴趣吗，埃斯特？

你知道吗，埃斯特，你有神经官能症的典型初期症状。

这样你会一事无成，这样你会一事无成，这样你会一事无成。

某个炎热的夏夜，我曾花了一个小时亲吻一个全身多毛、形似猿猴的耶鲁大学法学院的学生，因为我同情他长得这样丑。我亲完后，他竟告诉我：“宝贝，我知道你是哪种女人了。你到了四十岁会是个假正经的老古板。”

大学里教创意写作的教授在我那篇题为《大周末》的小说上，挥笔写下“矫揉造作！”的评语。

我不知道这词什么意思，所以去查了字典。

矫揉造作：不自然，虚假。

这样你会一事无成。

我已经二十一个晚上睡不着觉了。

我想，这世上最美的东西就是影子，上百万个影子，或移动或固守一方。影子在柜子抽屉、衣橱、皮箱里，影子在屋子、树木、石头底下；影子在眼眸、微笑背后，在地球上笼罩着黑夜的那一面，影子绵延万里。

我低头看着右小腿，两片肉色的创可贴在上面交叉成十字。

那天早上，我终于动手。

我把自己反锁在浴室里，放了一整浴缸的温水，拿出一片吉列剃须刀片。

有人向某位年迈的罗马哲学家之类的智者求教，问他会选择什么死法，哲学家说他要泡在温水里切开自己的血管。我想，这倒容易，躺在浴缸中，看着手腕冒出的红色血花开在澄净的水中，我沉入绚烂如罂粟的红色水底，永远睡去。

然而事到临头，我却发现手腕的皮肤如此苍白无助，我下不了手。仿佛我要杀的东西不在这层皮肤之下，也不是我拇指底下跳动的微弱蓝色脉搏，而是在某个更幽深、更隐秘、更难以企及的地方。

其实只需要两个动作。先割一只手腕，然后换另一只。如果把刀片换手的动作加进去，也就三个动作。然后，踏进浴缸，躺下。

我走到浴柜前，如果割腕时看着镜子，应该就像看着书中或戏里的人吧。

可是镜中人麻木无力，笨得什么也做不了。

我转念一想，或许该先弄出点血练习练习。于是我坐在浴缸边，把右脚踝架在左膝上，然后举起右手的刀片，让它像断头台的铡刀般自由落在我的小腿肚上。

没什么感觉。随后，是一股来自深处的细微震颤，伤口涌出一道鲜明的红色细流。血越聚颜色越暗，像个水果，滚落脚踝，流进黑色的漆皮鞋中。

我想进浴缸，但又想到刚才那番磨蹭耗尽了早上的大好时光，眼看妈妈就要到家，会在我完成一切前发现我。

于是，我给伤口贴上创可贴，将吉列刀片收好，搭十一点半的公交车去了波士顿。

“抱歉，姑娘，地铁到不了鹿岛监狱，因为它在岛上。”

“不，它不在岛上。以前那儿是岛，但是经过填海造地，岛已经和内陆相连了。”

“可是没有地铁。”

“我非去不可。”

“喂。”票亭里的胖男人隔着铁栅栏看着我，“别哭啊，姑娘。那里有你什么人？亲戚？”

夜色被人工照明设备点亮，火车在斯戈雷广场下的蜿蜒隧道中隆隆进出，四周人群你推我搡着追赶火车。我能感觉到泪水就要从我死死闭住的眼角涌出。

“是我的父亲。”

胖男人看了一下票亭内墙上的图表，说：“这么着吧，你先乘旁边的那路车，在‘东高地’下，转乘前往‘海角’的公交车。”他又笑道：“它会直接把你送到监狱门口。”

“喂，你！”小屋里一个穿着蓝色制服的小伙子朝我挥手。

我也对他挥挥手，然后继续往前走。

“喂，你！”

我止住脚步，慢慢地走向小屋，它就像个坐落在废弃沙堆上的圆形客厅。

“喂，你不能再往前走了。那里是监狱重地，禁止入内。”

“我以为沙滩沿岸都可以走。”我说，“只要不超过潮水线。”

小伙子想了一下，然后说：“这片海滩不行。”

他长了张讨人喜欢的充满青春气息的脸。

“你这地方真不错。”我说，“像个小房子。”

他回头看了眼铺着编织小地毯、挂着印花棉布窗帘的房间，笑了。

“我们还有咖啡壶。”

“我以前住在附近。”

“没开玩笑吧？我也是这个镇土生土长的呢。”

我的视线越过沙滩，望向停车场和铁栅门。门后有一条穿海破浪的窄路，通往昔日的小岛。

监狱的红砖建筑看起来挺友善，像是一所海滨大学的校舍。我看见左边山坡的草坪上有些小白点和稍大些的小粉点在移动，问警卫那是什么，他说：“猪和鸡嘛。”

我不禁浮想联翩。要是当初我明白事理，留在这个老镇，说不准会在学校里认识这个狱警，跟他结婚，现在已经有了一堆孩子。住在海边，守着孩子，喂喂小猪小鸡，穿着被祖母称作耐洗外套的衣服，坐在铺着鲜亮油毡的厨房里，陷在宽大的扶手椅当中，一壶一壶地喝着咖啡，这样也不错。

“怎样才能进监狱？”

“要有通行证。”

“不，怎样才能被关进去？”

“哦。”警卫笑了，“偷车啊，或者抢劫商店。”

“里头有杀人犯吗？”

“没有。杀人犯关在大型州立监狱。”

“里面还关着哪些人？”

“呃，冬天一到，波士顿的老流浪汉就会来。他们故意朝窗户扔砖头，等着被逮入狱，这样冬天就不必挨饿受冻了。监狱里有电视可看，三餐吃得饱，周末还有篮球赛。”

“不错嘛。”

“如果喜欢这种生活，的确不错。”警卫说。

我跟他道别，转身离开，只回头望了一眼。他仍站在岗亭门口，见我回头，他举手敬了个礼。

我坐着的树干沉重如铅，气味像是沥青。居高临下的山丘顶上矗立着粗壮的灰色圆柱水塔，下方的沙洲蜿蜒入海，涨潮时就会淹没不见。

我清楚记得这片沙洲。有一种奇特的贝壳只长在这片沙洲的内凹处，海滩的其他地方都寻不着。

这种贝壳厚而光滑，拇指关节大小，通常是白色的，但偶有粉红色或蜜桃色，长得很像一种不大不小的海螺。

“妈咪，那个女生还坐在那儿。”

我懒懒地抬起头，看见一个全身是沙的小孩被一个女人拖上岸，女人身形纤瘦，眼神锐利，穿着红色短裤和红白圆点的颈背系带背心。

我没想到，这个海滩挤满了消夏的人。我离开的这十年，一栋栋花哨的度假小屋如雨后春笋般出现在海角的平坦沙地上，或蓝或粉或浅绿，像一簇食之无味的蘑菇。银色的飞机和雪茄状的飞船已被喷气机取代，它从海湾对面的机场隆隆起飞，急速掠过一片屋顶。

我是海滩上唯一穿裙子和高跟鞋的人，想必很是惹眼。过了一会儿，我把漆皮鞋脱了，因为它们老是陷进沙子里。想到我死了之后，这双鞋子会静静地放在这截银色的木头上，鞋尖指向大海，有如某种灵魂罗盘，我就倍感开怀。

我用手指摸了摸皮包里的那盒剃须刀片。

随即想到自己真是蠢透了。有了刀片，可是这里没有温水供我浸泡。

我想到租个房间，所有避暑胜地肯定都有旅店。可是我没有行李，会让人生疑。而且，旅店里总是有其他房客等着用浴室，如果有人砰砰敲门，我就没时间动手，再迈入浴缸等死。

沙洲顶端的海鸥落在高跷一样的木头上，发出猫一般喵喵的叫声。接着它们振翅飞起，一只接一只，身披灰羽，在我头顶盘旋、哀鸣。

“我说，女士，你最好不要坐在那儿，快涨潮了。”

那个小男孩蹲在离我几英尺的地方，捡起一颗紫色的圆石子，往海里一抛，扑通一声，海水就吞没了它。他在沙滩上到处翻找，我听见干燥的石头发出钱币般的撞击声。

他横扔出一块扁平的石子打水漂，石子在暗绿色的水面上弹了七次才消失无踪。

“你怎么不回家？”我问。

男孩又扔出一块石子，这次的比较重，只弹了两下就沉入水里。

“不想回去。”

“你妈妈该找你了。”

“才没有。”他的声音听起来有点担心了。

“如果你回家，我就给你糖吃。”

男孩立刻往前凑。“什么样的糖？”

用不着打开皮包，我也知道里头只有花生壳。

“我给你钱去买糖。”

“亚——瑟！”

真的有个女人出现在沙洲上，她滑了一跤，嘴里嘀嘀咕咕，显然是对刚才那一跤心怀怨恨，因为她发出响亮急迫的叫喊声时，嘴唇还一上一下地动着。

“亚——瑟！”

她用一只手遮在眼睛上方，好像这样有助于她在渐浓的海边夜色中分辨出我们在哪儿。

我能感觉到，随着母亲催得越急，小男孩的兴致就越低。他开始假装不认识我，踢了几脚石头，像是要找什么东西，缓缓走远了。

我打了个冷战。

裸足之下的石块笨重而冰冷，令我特别想念放在海滩上的那双黑皮鞋。海浪退去，然后又往前涌，像手轻抚触摸着我的脚。

寒湿之气仿佛来自海底，在那样的海底，有种白鱼，目不能视，却以自身发出的亮光穿越酷寒的极地。在那海底，我还看见鲨鱼的牙齿和鲸鱼的耳骨散落各处，有如墓碑。

我等着，等着大海替我做出决定。

第二道浪花在我脚边拍碎，点点白沫轻吻我的赤足。寒意攫住双踝，剧痛难当。

我的肉体畏缩了，因为胆怯，不敢面对这样的死法。

我拾起皮包，走过森寒的石头，回到紫罗兰色的天光之下，我的鞋子守候的地方。

13

“肯定是他妈杀死他的。”

我看着乔蒂介绍我认识的男孩的嘴，他的双唇厚而红嫩，丝绸般的白金色头发紧贴着一张娃娃脸。他叫卡尔，我猜这一定是什么名字的简称，但除了加利福尼亚，我想不出这个全名会是什么。

“你怎么能肯定是她杀了他？”我问。

卡尔应该很聪明才是，乔蒂在电话上还说他很可爱，我会喜欢他的。我心里怀疑，如果我还是原来的我，是否会喜欢这类男孩。

很难说。

“因为一开始她说‘不，不，不’，接着却说‘要’。”

“但是后来她又说了‘不’。”

卡尔和我并肩躺在橙绿条纹的浴巾上，身下是肮脏的海滩，对岸是林恩市郊的沼泽。乔蒂和她的意中人马克在游泳。卡尔不想下水，只想聊天，所以我们开始讨论一出戏。剧情是有个年轻人发现自己得了脑疾，因为他父亲和不清白的女人有染，他脑子不停软化，最后完全垮了，他的母亲在盘算要不要杀死他。

我怀疑是我母亲给乔蒂打电话，拜托她邀我外出，免得我成天窝在家里，连百叶窗都不开。一开始我不想答应，我怕乔蒂看出我的变化，任何人只要有眼睛都看得出来我的头颅里已经没有脑子了。

可是这一路下来，我们先是开车向北，然后再转向往东，乔蒂只顾说笑玩闹，似乎不在意我的回应只有“哦”“天哪”“不会吧”。

我们在海边的公共烤架上烤热狗，我仔细看着乔蒂、马克和卡尔怎么做，设法也把自己的热狗烤得恰到好处，没有像我担心的那样烤过了头，或是掉进火里。可是一转身，趁着没人注意，我就把热狗埋进了沙里。

吃完东西，乔蒂和马克手牵着手下水了，我躺下来凝望着天空，卡尔还在喋喋不休地谈论那出戏。

我记得这出戏的唯一原因是戏里有个疯子。我读过的东西中，只要与疯子有关的都会烙进我的脑海，其他部分则消逝无痕。

“可是，重要的是她说了‘要’。”卡尔说，“这是她最终会下的决定。”

我抬头眯眼望向大海，这海有如一只明亮湛蓝的大盘子——却带着一圈肮脏的边缘。离嶙峋的海角约莫一英里处，有一块灰色的大圆石像半个鸡蛋一样突起在水面上。

“她是用什么东西杀死他的？我忘了。”

其实我没忘，记得清清楚楚，但我想听听卡尔怎么说。

“吗啡粉。”

“美国有吗啡粉吗？”

卡尔想了一下，说：“我觉得没有，吗啡杀人的法子太落伍。”

我翻身趴着，眯眼看向林恩市的方向。烤肉架下的火气和路面的热气蒸腾起涟漪般的薄透雾气，有如一道清澈的水帘。我的视线穿过这雾气，看见油槽、工厂烟囱、起重机和桥梁轮廓构成的脏兮兮的天际线。

看起来乱七八糟。

我又翻身躺好，用漫不经心的口吻问：“如果你要自杀，会怎么做？”

卡尔对这个问题似乎很有兴趣。“我经常想这个问题。我会一枪轰掉自己的脑袋。”

我很失望。男人用枪理所当然，可我哪有机会碰枪？就算拿到枪，我也不晓得该朝身上哪个部位打。

我在报上读到过，有人想开枪自杀，却只打中了重要的神经，弄得全身瘫痪；或者炸毁了自己的脸后奇迹般地被外科医生救回一命，没有死掉。

举枪自戕风险着实太大。

“哪种枪？”

“我爸的霰弹枪，随时都有子弹上好膛。我只要哪天走进他的书房，然后——”卡尔用手指着太阳穴，做出一幅死透的滑稽表情，“砰！”他张大浅灰色的眼睛看着我。

“你爸住在波士顿附近吗？”我懒懒地问。

“不，他住在滨海克拉克顿。他是英国人。”

乔蒂和马克手牵手跑上岸，像两条相亲相爱的小狗一样，将身上滴滴答答的水甩落。我想这里很快就会人满为患，于是起身，假装打了个哈欠。

“我想去游个泳。”

与乔蒂、马克和卡尔共处，我的精神压力倍增，像一根沉重的木块压在琴弦上。我怕自己随时会失控，开始滔滔不绝地跟他们倾诉：我看不进书，写不出东西，全世界大概只有我整整一个月没睡却还没力竭而亡。

我的神经似乎开始冒烟，就像烤肉架和烈日炙烤过的路面冒出的热气。放眼望去——沙滩、海角、大洋和礁岩——一切都成了舞台的背景幕布，在我眼前发颤。

我想知道在空中的哪一点，天空中那愚蠢、虚假的蓝色会变成黑色。

“你也去游吧，卡尔。”

乔蒂开玩笑地轻推了卡尔一把。

“哦。”卡尔把脸埋入毛巾，“水太冷啦。”

我朝海水走去。

不知为什么，在万里无云的灿烂正午，海水看起来分外亲切宜人。

我想，溺水应该是最舒服的死法，最惨的莫过于烧死吧。巴迪·威拉德带我看的那些标本罐里的胎儿有些长了腮，他说在某个阶段，他们就跟鱼一样。

一排裹挟着垃圾的小浪涌向我的脚，浪里有糖果纸、橘子皮和海藻。

我听见背后传来脚踩沙地的声音，卡尔走了过来。

“我们游到那块礁岩吧。”我边指边说。

“你疯了吗？足有一英里远。”

“你这样算什么？”我说，“胆小鬼。”

卡尔抓住我的胳膊肘，推我走入水里，等到水深及腰，就把我往水里压。我浮上海面，拍着水，眼睛被咸水刺得生痛。水下是一片半透明的绿，有如一大块石英。

我以一种改良过的狗刨姿势开始游，一路向着礁岩而去。卡尔以自由式慢慢跟着。过了一会儿，他昂起头，开始踩水。

“游不动了。”他气喘吁吁地说。

“好。你回去吧。”

我想不停地往外游，游到没力气回到岸边。我游啊游，心跳在耳边咚咚作响，仿佛沉钝的马达声。

我在，我在，我在。

那天早上，我企图吊死自己。

母亲一出门上班，我就拿了她那件黄色浴袍上的丝质腰带。在卧室琥珀色的光影里，我把丝带打了个可以上下滑动的结。因为不擅长这个，我花了很长时间，不知道怎么打才好用。

接着，我到处找可以挂丝带的地方。

问题来了，我家的天花板不行。白色的天花板不仅低矮，而且墙皮抹得很光滑，放眼看不到任何灯座或木梁。真怀念外婆以前的房子，可惜她卖了老房子搬来和我们住，后来改和莉比姨妈住。

外婆的房子是十九世纪的精致风格，房间高挑，枝形吊灯支架粗壮，高大的衣柜里横着坚固的衣杆，没人上去过的阁楼里堆满了箱子、鹦鹉笼和裁缝用的试衣假人，屋顶上的横梁就像船骨一样厚重结实。

不过，终究是老房子，外婆已经卖掉了。从此我不知道谁家还有这样的房子。

我在屋里走来走去，怎么也找不到可以挂绳子的地方，套在脖子上的丝带像黄色的猫尾巴荡来荡去，最后我心灰意冷。我坐在母亲的床沿上，用力拉紧脖子上的丝带。

但是每次我一勒紧带子，就觉得耳朵发热，脸上充血，于是手一软，带子一松，我又缓过劲来。

我发现我的身体真是诡计多端。譬如这回，让我的手一次又一次地在关键时刻变得无力，救了它的命。要是我能完全做主，一眨眼就能了结自己。

很简单，要么我用仅存的理智对身体来个突袭，要么只好任由它将我关在这具蠢皮囊中，行尸走肉般地活上五十年。尽管母亲把自己的嘴管得很紧，但别人迟早会发现我的精神早已错乱，到时他们一定会力劝她把我送到精神病院接受治疗。

只是，我的病无药可救。

我曾在药房买了几本变态心理学的简装书，把我的症状与书中提到的症状做了比较，果不其然，我的症状完全与最没希望治愈的病例符合。

除了八卦小报，我现在唯一能读得进的东西就只剩变态心理学的书籍了。上天仿佛给我留了一条门缝，让我可以充分了解自己的病症，好找个合适的方式自我了断。

上吊的法子看来是行不通了，我怀疑是不是该打消轻生的念头，转身乖乖听医生的话。这么一想，我又记起了戈登大夫和他私人诊所里的电击设备，一旦被关进去，他们就可以随时用那个机器对付我了。

我继而又想，母亲、弟弟和朋友会坚持日复一日地来看我，盼我好转。但慢慢地，他们探访的次数会越来越少，最后对我彻底绝望。他们会变老。他们终会将我遗忘。

再说，他们也会变得拮据。

一开始，他们会给我最好的医疗条件，把所有的钱投入戈登大夫开设的私人诊所那种地方。等最后家财耗尽，我就会被转入公立医院，跟几百个同我一样的病人一起被关在地下室的大笼子里。

你越是没有康复的希望，就会被藏得越深。

卡尔掉头往岸上游。

我看着他在深及颈部的海水中费力地慢慢游走。在卡其色沙滩和沿岸绿波的衬托下，他白得像蠕虫一样的身体被一分为二。没多久，这只白色蠕虫完全游出了绿波，爬上了卡其色的沙滩，消失在其他数十只蠕动或游荡于海天之间的蠕虫中。

我继续在水里手脚并用地划着，可我和蛋形礁岩的距离并没有比我跟卡尔在岸上观察时更近。

然后我想明白了，何必游到礁岩那么远的地方去，因为到头来我的身体还是会找借口爬出水面，躺在礁岩的阳光下休息，等着恢复体力好游回去。

唯一的选择是淹死自己，就在此时此地。

于是，我不游了。

我把手收回胸前，头埋入水中，双手拨水，往深处潜。海水压迫着我的耳膜和心脏。我振臂往下，但我还没想明白自己在哪儿，就被海水拍上水面，重见天日。太阳下的世界闪闪发光，像是蓝、绿、黄色的宝石半成品围绕在我四周。

我抹去眼睛上的海水。

下潜真是耗费力气，搞得我气喘吁吁，可是浮在水上却毫不费劲。

我再次下潜，一次又一次下潜，每次都跟软木塞一样浮出水面。

灰色的礁岩嘲笑我在海里的这番折腾，上上下下简直像套了个救生圈一样。

我知道我被打败了。

我转身上岸。

我用手推车将花推过走廊，花儿一路颤巍巍地点头，宛如聪明可爱又知书达理的好孩子。

穿着这一身灰绿色的义工制服，我觉得自己既愚蠢又多余，比不上穿白色制服的医护人员，连穿褐色制服的女清洁工也不如，后者拿着拖把、提着污水桶走过我身边时话都懒得说一句。

如果有薪水，无论多微薄，起码算是一份正经工作，但我一整个早上推着车子分送杂志、糖果和鲜花，仅仅换得一顿免费午餐而已。

母亲说，对于那些成天胡思乱想的人来说，最好的药方就是去帮助比自己更惨的人，所以我们的家庭医生特雷莎安排我到当地医院当义工。要在这家医院当义工可没那么容易，因为青年联盟里的女人都抢着做这差事，不过我很幸运，这阵子她们很多人都度假去了。我本希望被分配到重症病房，因为我觉得那儿的病人会看出我麻木呆滞的表情底下隐藏的一片善意，并对此深表感激。可是义工领队——一位和我同一教区的社交名媛——瞟了我一眼后，说：“你去产科。”

于是我搭乘电梯去了三楼产科病房，向护士长报到。她给了我一推车的花，要我把正确的花瓶送到正确病房的正确床位上。

还没走到第一间病房，我就发现很多花垂头丧气，花瓣边缘已经枯萎发黄。我想，把一大束蔫了吧唧的花扔在刚刚生完孩子的女人面前，肯定会让她们很扫兴，所以我掉转推车，来到走廊内凹室的水槽边，把已经凋谢了的花一一挑拣出来。

行将凋谢的花也没有放过。

四处看不见垃圾桶，我把挑出来的花揉成一团，丢在白色深水槽里。这水槽感觉冷得像坟墓。我的脸上扬起微笑。医院太平间随手处置尸体的动作肯定和我一样，所以我这个弃花的小小举动正暗合了医护人员对待尸体的大动作。

我打开第一个房间的门，拉着推车走了进去，几个护士跳了起来。我模糊地看到几个架子和药品柜。

“你要做什么？”一个护士厉声问道。她们几个看起来都一个样，我分不清谁是谁。

“我来送花。”

刚刚说话的护士把手搭在我的肩膀上，引导我走出房间，另一只手熟练地拉着我的推车。她推开隔壁病房的门，欠身让我进去，然后她就不见了。

我听见外头传来咯咯的笑声，直到一扇门关上，笑声才听不见了。

房里有六张床，每张床上都坐着一个女人，有的打着毛线，有的浏览杂志，有的在上发卷，叽叽喳喳，就像鸟舍里的鹦鹉。

我以为她们会在睡觉，或者脸色苍白地静静躺着，这样我就能不惹任何麻烦地踮起脚尖，放轻步伐，把床号和花瓶胶带上用墨水写的编号匹配好。可我还没来得及辨清方向，就见一个聪明活泼、长着一张三角形尖脸的金发女人对我招手。

我走上前，把推车留在房间中央，但她比画了一个不耐烦的手势，我才明白她要我把车也推过去。

我把整车花推到她的床边，对她露出乐于效劳的微笑。

“喂，我的飞燕草呢？”病房另一边一个肌肉松弛的大个子女人用她老鹰般的锐利眼神扫视我。

长着三角形尖脸的金发女人俯身凑到推车上。“我的黄玫瑰在这里。”她说，“可是跟一些臭鸢尾混在一起了。”

其他女人也加入这两个女人的行列，怒气冲冲地大声抱怨着。

我开口解释：那束飞燕草已经枯死，所以被我扔进了水槽，另外一些奄奄一息的也被我剔除，花瓶里没剩几枝花，稀稀疏疏的，所以我就把几束凑成一把。正说着，房门被推开，一个护士阔步走入，查看这场骚动是怎么一回事。

“听我说，护士小姐，那一大束飞燕草是昨晚我家拉瑞带给我的。”

“她把我的黄玫瑰搞得乱七八糟。”

我边跑边解开绿制服的扣子，经过水槽时，一把将制服扔了进去，让它跟那些死花做伴吧。然后我从偏僻无人的侧梯下楼，一步两级台阶地奔向街道，一路上没遇到任何人。

“请问墓园怎么走？”

穿着黑色皮衣的意大利人停下脚步，指着白色卫理公会教堂后面的一条小路。我记得这间卫理公会教堂，九岁丧父之前我是卫理公会教徒，之后我们搬家，改信一神教。

母亲在成为卫理公会教徒之前信天主教，我的外祖父母和莉比姨妈依然是天主教徒。莉比姨妈曾与母亲同时离开天主教会，不过后来她爱上了一个意大利的天主教徒，于是重新皈依了天主教。

最近我在考虑加入天主教。我知道这个宗教认为自杀罪孽深重，果真如此的话，或许他们有办法断了我的这个念头。

当然，我不相信死后永生、处女生子、宗教裁判所这些事情，也不相信那个猴脸矮个子教皇永远不会犯错，但这些不必让神父知道，我只要专心认罪，他就会帮助我忏悔，打消我寻死的念头。

唯一的问题是，宗教并非生活的全部，就算是天主教也一样。不管你跪多久，祷告多长时间，你还是得一日三餐，工作和生活在现实世界里。

我想，也许可以看看当多久的天主教徒之后可以做修女，于是便询问母亲，想来她应该知道走这条路的最佳途径。

母亲嘲笑我说：“你以为他们会二话不说就收你这样的人当修女？你得熟知所有的教义、信条，而且要一股脑儿照单全收，毫不怀疑。就凭你这点儿脑子，想也别想了！”

不过，我还是幻想着自己跑到波士顿找神父——非得去波士顿不可，因为我不想让家乡的神父知道我有轻生的念头。神父最会散播流言。

我要穿着一身黑，惨白着一张脸，扑到神父的脚边，说：“哦，神父，救救我。”

我可不想让大家用医院里护士看我的怪异表情来看待我，既如此，这个计划必须尽早展开。

我很肯定天主教不会接纳发疯的修女。莉比姨妈的丈夫说过一件趣事：修女院送一名修女到特雷莎医生那里做检查，这修女老是觉得耳边有竖琴的声音，还有个声音不停地说：“哈利路亚！”医生详细询问时，她却不能确定听到的是哈利路亚还是亚利桑那，她就是在亚利桑那出生的。我想，她最终的下场是进疯人院吧。

我把黑色面纱拉到下巴，阔步穿越铸铁大门。真奇怪，父亲一直埋在这墓园，我们却从不曾来拜祭过。母亲没让我们参加父亲的葬礼，因为那时我们还小，加上他是在医院过世的，所以我总觉得墓园，乃至他的死，都很不真实。

最近我有种强烈的渴望，想弥补这么多年来对他的疏忽，好好照看他的坟墓。父亲向来最疼爱我，既然妈妈从未费心哀悼过，自当由我来表达哀悼之情。

我想，如果父亲没死，他一定会把有关昆虫的所有知识传授给我，他在大学里教的就是昆虫学。他也会教我他擅长的德文、希腊文和拉丁文。也许受他的影响，我会成为路德派信徒。父亲在威斯康星州时加入路德教派，但这个教派在新英格兰地区已经式微，所以他背离此教，后来变成了母亲嘴里的那个满腹愤恨的无神论者。

墓园让我大失所望。它位于镇郊的低地处，像个垃圾场。走在墓园的小径中，我甚至能闻到远处盐碱沼泽的腐臭味。

墓园的旧区还算好，扁平的墓石饱经风霜，纪念碑长着一层苔藓。不过我随即发现，父亲应该是葬在二十世纪四十年代修建的新墓区里。

新墓区的墓石看起来廉价而粗糙，有些墓穴的四周镶着大理石边，活像盛满泥土的长方形浴缸。生锈的金属花托立在大约是死者肚脐处的位置，里头插满塑料假花。

灰色的天空飘起毛毛雨，我的心情跌到谷底。

哪儿都找不到父亲的坟墓。

低沉的乌云翻卷，掠过沼泽和滨海小屋区域后方的海边地平线。雨点让我今早才买的雨衣更显黝黑，寒冷的湿气侵入我的肌肤。

当时我问女店员：“这雨衣防水吗？”她说：“没有雨衣能完全防水，它只是防雨。”

我问她防雨是什么意思，她告诉我最好还是买把伞。

可是我的钱不够买伞。往返波士顿的车票、花生、报纸、变态心理学的书以及回海边老家的旅程，几乎花光了我在纽约见习时攒下的钱。

我决定在花光银行存款时动手。而今天早上，最后一点钱就花在了这件黑色雨衣上。

就在这时，我看见了父亲的墓碑。

它挤在另一个墓碑上方，头对着头，犹如空间不足的救济院里人挤人的样子。斑驳的粉色大理石墓碑看起来像三文鱼罐头，上面只有父亲的名字，底下是两个日期，用一个小小的破折号隔开。

我把一束带雨的杜鹃花摆在墓碑底部，这是我从墓园入口的花丛里摘的。然后，我盘腿坐在湿答答的草地上，不明白自己怎么会哭得这么伤心。

接着，我想起自己从没为父亲的死掉过一滴泪。

母亲也没掉过。她只笑着说，他能这么去了也算是种解脱，因为假始他活着，肯定受不了终生残疾，宁愿一死了之。

我把脸贴在光滑的大理石上，在冰冷苦涩的雨中恸哭我失去的一切。

我知道该怎么做。

听着母亲的车轮嘎吱辗过车道，引擎声渐渐远去，我立刻跳下床，匆匆套上白衣绿裙，再披上黑雨衣。雨衣摸起来还带着昨天的湿气，不过这很快就无所谓了。

我来到楼下，从餐桌上拿起一个浅蓝色信封，费劲地在背面写上几个潦草的大字：我要去散个长长的步。

把留言信封支在母亲一进门就看得到的地方。

然后我笑了。

竟然忘了最重要的事。

我跑上楼，拖了把椅子到妈妈的壁橱前，爬上椅子，伸手去够顶层架子上绿色的小保险箱。箱子的锁很脆弱，我徒手就可以把那金属箱盖扯下来，但我想冷静有序地完成每个步骤。

我拉开母亲五斗柜右上层的抽屉，从喷了香水的爱尔兰亚麻手帕底下抽出一个蓝色的珠宝盒，从盒里的黑丝绒布上取下小钥匙，打开保险箱，拿出那瓶刚放入没多久的药。数量比我预想的要多。

至少有五十粒。

如果要等母亲每晚发一粒给我，得攒上五十个夜晚才能存够数。而五十个夜晚过后，学校就会开学，弟弟也会从德国回来，到时就来不及了。

我把钥匙放回珠宝盒里，跟一堆廉价的项链和戒指放在一起，再把珠宝盒藏回抽屉手帕底下，然后把保险箱放回壁橱架子上，椅子摆回地毯上原来的位置。

接着，我下楼走进厨房，打开水龙头，倒了一大杯水，带着水杯和那瓶药走向地下室。

昏暗如海底幽明的光，透过细窄的窗缝照进地下室。燃油暖气炉后方的墙上，约莫齐肩高的地方，有个黑黢黢的缺口，延伸至车库与主屋间的通道下方，看不见底。这个通道是在地下室挖好之后才增建的，所以就盖在这个隐秘泥土缺口的上方。

几根老旧的壁炉朽木挡住了入口，我用力将它们推开一点，然后把水杯和药瓶并排放在其中一根木头的扁平横面上，开始往缺口上爬。

费了不少时间，折腾了好几次，最终才把身体塞入缺口。在这黑暗之口，我佝偻着身体，像洞穴中的巨人。

光脚下的泥土亲切而冰冷。我暗想，这方泥土最后一次见到阳光，不知是多久以前的事了。

我用力拖动一根根布满尘土的沉重木头，挡住洞口。洞内的漆黑浓厚得像天鹅绒。我伸手拿过水杯和药瓶，小心翼翼地低头爬向最远的墙。

蛛网如柔软的飞蛾轻触我的脸。我裹紧身上的黑雨衣，将它当成我亲密的影子。打开药瓶，迅速吞下一粒粒药片，间或灌上一口水。

起初没什么感觉，但药瓶快见底时眼前开始闪现红光和蓝光。药瓶从指尖滑落，我倒了下去。

寂静退去，石子、贝壳，以及我生命中那些支离破碎的残骸一一浮现。接着，在视界的边缘，寂静重新聚集，以汹涌之势席卷而来，将我冲入梦乡。

14

彻头彻尾的黑。

除了黑，别无感觉。我抬起头，像条蠕虫的头，感受着这漆黑。有人在呜咽。接着，一个硬如石墙的重物砸中我的脸。呜咽声稍歇。

一切重归寂静，犹如被落石打破平静的水面，随着石子坠入黑暗的水底而再度归于平静。

一阵凉风袭过，我在一个隧道里极速坠往地底。之后，风停了，远处传来骚动，像是许多人在抗议、反对。接着，声音平息了。

眼皮被凿子撬开一道裂缝，一线光打开了，如张开的小嘴，又似一道伤口，旋即被黑暗夹住。我试图翻身，避开光的方向，但死死抓住我四肢的手像木乃伊的裹尸布，叫我动弹不得。

我想，我定是身处一间地下密室之中，屋内灯火眩目，里面满满都是人，只是不知他们为何要压着我不让我动。

凿子又开始敲击，光线射入我的脑袋，有个声音穿过又厚又暖的可怕的黑暗喊道：“妈妈！”

呼吸的气流在我脸上玩耍。

我分辨出这是个房间，窗户敞开的大房间。我头下堆着个枕头，身体飘浮在薄被与床单之间，没有任何压力。

接着，我感觉到一股暖意，仿佛是有人把手贴在我的脸上。我一定是躺在阳光下，睁开眼就会见到各式色彩和形状，像护士查看病人一样俯身靠近我。

我睁开眼。

一片漆黑。

身旁有呼吸声。

“我看不见。”我说。

黑暗中有个声音欢喜地说：“世界上有许多看不见的人。有一天你会嫁给一个瞎眼的好男人。”

拿凿子的男人又来了。

“何必费事呢？”我说，“没用的。”

“千万别说这种话。”他用手探了探我左眼上那个又大又痛的肿块，然后弄松了什么东西，一道参差破碎的光闪现，仿佛墙上开了个洞。一个男人的手隐约出现在洞的边缘。

“看得见我吗？”

“是的。”

“其他东西呢？”

这时我想起来了：“我什么都看不见。”光洞缩小，眼前恢复黑暗。“我瞎了。”

“胡扯！谁说的？”

“护士说的。”

他对此嗤之以鼻，把我眼睛上的绷带用胶布贴好，说：“姑娘，你运气很好，视力完好无损。”

“有人来看你了。”

护士笑笑，人就不见了。

母亲微笑着绕过床尾走来。她穿着有紫色车轮图案的衣服，看起来糟透了。

她身后跟着一个又高又大的男孩。起初我没认出他来，因为我的眼睛只能张开一点点，但很快我看清那是我弟弟。

“他们说你想见我。”

母亲坐在床沿上，一只手覆上我的腿，满脸爱之深责之切的模样，我真希望她走开。

“我想我没这么说过。”

“他们说你喊着要见我。”她泫然欲泣，脸紧皱起来，浑身颤抖得像一个苍白的果冻。

“你怎么样？”弟弟问。

我看着母亲的眼睛。

“老样子。”我说。

“你有访客。”

“我不想见什么访客。”

护士匆忙跑出去，向走廊里的某人窃窃耳语，然后又折回来。“他非常想见你。”

我低头看着身上那件陌生的白色丝质睡衣——这是医院里的人给我穿上的——下面伸出两条泛黄的腿。我一动，腿上的皮肤就松垮地晃动，好像里面没有肌肉支撑，只覆盖了一层短短的、浓密的黑色短汗毛。

“是谁？”

“你认识的人。”

“他叫什么名字？”

“乔治·贝克维尔。”

“我不认识叫乔治·贝克维尔的人。”

“他说他认识你。”

护士说完走了出去，一个很面熟的男孩走了进来，说：“我可以坐在床边吗？”

他穿着白袍，我瞧见他口袋里露出一截听诊器。我猜一定是我认识的哪个人冒充医生。

我原本打算有人进来就立马盖上自己的腿，但现在已然太迟，干脆让它们就这么摊着吧，恶心又丑陋。

“这就是我。”我想，“我就是恶心又丑陋。”

“你记得我吧，埃斯特？”我眯起剩下的那只好眼，斜斜看向他。另一眼还睁不开，但是医生说过几天就没事了。

男孩像看着动物园里新鲜好玩的动物一样盯着我，差一点就要扑哧笑出声来。

“你记得我吧，埃斯特？”他用那种跟笨小孩讲话的语气慢慢地说，“我是乔治·贝克维尔，咱俩是同一间教会的。你还跟我的室友在艾默斯特市约会过一次。”

我想我认出他的脸了，它模糊盘旋在记忆的边缘——那种我永远都懒得费心记下名字的脸。

“你在这里做什么？”

“我是这间医院的实习医生。”

这个乔治·贝克维尔怎么突然成了个医生？我不明白。他跟我也不是很熟，恐怕只是想看看疯到要自杀的女孩长得什么样吧。

我把脸转向墙壁。

“出去。”我说，“滚出去，别回来。”

“我要照镜子。”

护士哼着曲子忙里忙外，打开一个个抽屉，把母亲为我买的新内衣、衬衫、裙子和睡衣拿出来，塞进黑色漆皮小旅行箱里。

“为什么不让我照镜子？”

她们给我穿上像床垫布做的灰白条纹紧身女装，系上艳红的宽腰带，再把我搀上扶手椅。

“为什么不让？”

“因为你最好别看。”护士啪的一声合上小旅行箱的盖子。

“为什么？”

“因为你的模样不怎么好看。”

“哦，就让我看看吧。”

护士叹了口气，打开柜子最上面的抽屉，拿出一面木框大镜子递给我，镜框的材质和柜子是配套的。

一开始，我看不出有什么问题。因为这根本不是一面镜子，而是一幅画。

画里的人男女难辨。剃光的头上直竖着一簇簇鸡毛似的残发。半边脸肿胀变形，一片青紫，边缘转为绿色，再往外淡成土黄。浅褐色的嘴，嘴角两侧都是玫瑰色的溃疡。

一张脸上居然能聚集这么多鲜艳的色彩，真是让人啧啧称奇。

我笑了。

镜中的嘴也咧开，露出了一个笑容。

镜子坠地，过了一会儿另一个护士跑了进来。她看了一眼破碎的镜子，再看看站在刺眼反光的碎镜片中的我，把那个年轻护士拉出了房间。

“我不是告诉过你。”我听见她说话。

“但我只是……”

“我不是告诉过你！”

我没多大兴趣听下去。谁都可能失手打破镜子，不明白她们在紧张什么。

较年长的护士回到病房。她站在那儿，双臂交叉，狠狠地瞪着我。

“倒霉七年。”

“什么？”

“我说，”她提高嗓门，像在对聋子吼，“打破镜子会倒霉七年。”

年轻的护士拿着簸箕和扫帚回来了，开始打扫一地闪闪发光的碎片。

“那只是迷信。”我说。

“哼！”年长的护士对跪在地上的小护士说，仿佛我根本不存在一样，“到了‘那个地方’，看他们怎么收拾她！”

从救护车的后窗望出去，一条条熟悉的街道渐渐融入远方的夏日绿意中。母亲坐在我身侧，弟弟坐在另一边。

我假装不知道为什么要把我从本地医院转到市立医院，好看看他们会怎么说。

“他们想让你住特殊病房。”母亲开口道，“可我们这里没有那种病房。”

“我喜欢原来的病房。”

母亲抿紧了嘴唇。“那你应该表现得好一点。”

“什么意思？”

“你不该摔破镜子。那样，他们或许会让你继续待下去。”

我当然知道，这和镜子没有关系。

我坐在床上，被单盖到脖子。

“为什么我不能下床？我没病。”

“医生要巡房。”护士说，“巡完房你就可以下床了。”她用力拉开床边的帘子，我看见隔壁床是个很胖的意大利年轻女人。

这意大利女人有一头浓密的黑卷发，从额前一路高耸向上，到背后如瀑布般倾泻而下。她一动，庞然大物似的头发就跟着动，仿佛是黑色的硬纸做的。

她看着我咯咯笑。“你为什么来这儿？”没等我回答，她就说：“我来这儿，全是被我那法裔的加拿大婆婆害的。”她边笑边说，“我老公知道我受不了她，可他还让她来我们家。她来了之后，我就不由自主地吐舌头。他们先把我送到急诊室，接着又把我送到了这里。”她压低声音，“跟一群疯子关在一起。”此时她终于想起问我：“你呢？”

我把正脸转向她，让她看见我瘀青肿胀的眼睛。“我企图自杀。”

她盯着我看，然后仓皇地从床头柜上抓起一本电影杂志，装作在看书。

我床铺对面的房门被一把推开，一群穿着白大褂的年轻男女跟着一个年长的银发男子走了进来。他们脸上都挂着明快又做作的笑容，聚集在我的床尾。

“今早感觉如何，格林伍德小姐？”

我努力搞清楚是谁开的口。我讨厌和一群人讲话。非得如此，我会挑出其中一人当成说话的对象。可我还是觉得，其他人盯着我说话是占了我的大便宜。我也讨厌别人明知道你不好，却兴高采烈地问你感觉如何，还期望着你会回答“很好”。

“我感觉很不好。”

“唔，很不好。”有人搭腔，有个小伙子低下头微微一笑，还有个在夹板上潦草地记了几笔。接着有个人板起一张严肃的脸问：“为什么感觉不好？”

我猜，这群朝气蓬勃的年轻男女中，很有可能有人是巴迪·威拉德的朋友。他们知道我认识他，所以好奇地想看看我，之后我就会沦为他们的谈资。我想躲到没人认识我的地方去。

“我睡不着……”

他们打断我。“但护士说你昨晚睡着了。”我环视那排成弧形的一张张脸，新鲜而又陌生。

“我无法阅读。”我提高音量，“也吃不下东西。”说到这儿我突然想到，自打清醒后，我已经狼吞虎咽了不少东西。

那群人不再注意我，转过头窃窃私语。最后，银发男子站了出来。

“谢谢，格林伍德小姐。很快会有医生过来看你。”

接着，一群人走到意大利女人的床边。

“今天感觉怎么样……”有人问道。这女人的名字好长，听起来一堆L的音，像是托莫利洛太太。

托莫利洛太太咯咯笑了。“哦，我很好，医生。我真的很好。”她又压低嗓门，用我听不见的声音跟他们耳语了几句。有一两个医生朝我这边瞥了几眼，接着有人说：“好的，托莫利洛太太。”有人跨出一步，拉上我们之间的床帘，像筑起了一道白墙。

医院的四面砖墙围着一片方形的草地，我坐在草地上一个长木凳的一端，母亲穿着那件紫色车轮图案的衣服坐在另一端。她一只手托着腮，食指靠在脸颊上，拇指顶着下巴。

托莫利洛太太跟几个脸上堆着笑的黑发意大利人坐在旁边的长凳上。每次母亲改变姿势，托莫利洛太太就依样画葫芦。现在，托莫利洛太太也是食指靠在脸颊上，拇指顶着下巴，怅然地侧着头。

“别动。”我小声嘱咐母亲，“那个女人在学你的样子。”

母亲转头张望，眨眼工夫，托莫利洛太太就把她又白又肥的手放到了大腿上，跟朋友热络地聊起来。

“没有啊，她没有学我。”母亲说，“她甚至根本没注意我们呢。”

可是母亲转向我的那一刹那，托莫利洛太太马上效仿她的新姿势，把指尖对在一起，再对我投以凶狠嘲讽的目光。

草坪上走来许多医生，白晃晃的一片。

阳光照进高高的砖墙间，洒落成一道窄窄的锥形光柱。母亲和我在光柱中坐了一会儿，不断有医生走上前来自我介绍。“我是××医生。”“我是××大夫。”

有几个看起来太年轻，我觉得他们不是正经医生。其中一个的名字好奇怪，听起来像“梅毒医生”，于是我开始留心那些令人生疑的假名。果然，有个黑头发的走上前来跟我握手，说：“我是胰腺大夫。”他长得极像戈登大夫，只是他比较黑，不如戈登大夫白。

医生们自我介绍完，就站在听得见我说话的地方，我没法避开他们，告诉母亲他们会记下我们说的每一个字，所以只得靠近她，在她耳边悄声低语。

母亲的身体猛然向后一缩。

“唉，埃斯特，我希望你合作一点。他们说你不配合，不愿意跟任何医生说话，专业治疗时什么都不做……”

“我得离开这里。”我故意告诉她，“离开这地方，我就好了。是你把我送进来的，就得把我弄出去。”

我想，要是我能说服母亲让我离开医院，就能博取她对我的怜悯，像戏里那个得脑疾的男孩使的手段一样，让她接受我认为最妥当的办法。

出乎我的意料，母亲竟然说：“好吧，我会想办法让你出去——哪怕只是换个条件稍好的地方。”她把手放到我的膝盖上。“如果我这么做了，答应我，你会乖乖听话，好吗？”

我转身直瞪着“梅毒医生”，他就站在我的手肘旁边，在一本小到几乎看不见的便笺簿上做着笔记。“我答应你。”我大声回答，唯恐别人没听见。

一个黑人推着餐车进入病区餐厅。这家医院的精神科病区很小——只有两条L形走廊，两侧是病房，另外专业治疗室后面凹进去的小房间里也有病床，我就住在那里。L形走廊的转角处有个小区域，窗边摆了一张桌子和几把椅子，充当我们的休息室兼餐厅。

平常送饭的是个佝偻的白人老头，今天却换成一个黑人，身旁有一个穿着细高跟鞋的女人吩咐他做这做那。黑人从头到尾一直咧着嘴，吃吃傻笑。

他端着托盘来到我们这桌，把三个带盖的锡盆砰砰放在桌上。随他来的女人离开了，临走还锁上了餐厅的门。黑人乒里乓啷放下锡盆、磕出凹痕的银餐具和白色厚瓷盘，一双大眼睛骨碌碌地一直瞧着我们。

我看得出来，这是他头一回见到疯子。

全桌没一个人动手掀开锡盆，护士也往后一站，等着看谁先她一步打开盖子。通常这事都由托莫利洛太太效劳，她还会像小妈妈一样替大家分菜。可是她已经出院回家，似乎没人愿意接替她的位子。

我快饿死了，所以掀开了第一个盖子。

“你真好，埃斯特。”护士高兴地说，“你先盛些豆子，再把食物传给其他人，好吗？”

我给自己舀了一份绿色的豆角，然后把锡盆传给右边那个魁梧的红发女人，这是她第一次获准上桌吃饭。我见过她一次，她就站在L形走廊末尾一扇敞开的门前，门上安了一个带铁栅栏的正方形窗户。

她当时一直在粗野地吼叫和狂笑，对着经过的医生狂拍自己的大腿。有个负责照料这个病区的护理员，穿着白大褂，靠在走廊的暖气片上，笑得不能自已。

红发女人一把从我手中抢过锡盆，倒扣在自己的盘子上，堆得像小山一样的豆角洒得到处都是，滚落到她的腿上和地上，像绿色的硬稻草。

“哦，莫尔太太！”护士哀怨地说，“我看你今天最好还是在自己房间吃吧。”

说完，护士把大部分的豆角倒回锡盆，把它递给莫尔太太的邻座，然后领着莫尔太太离开了。沿着走廊回房的路上，莫尔太太频频回头，冲我们做着鬼脸，还发出猪叫般难听的声音。

黑人返回餐厅，开始收拾那些没盛豆角的空盘。

“我们还没吃完。”我告诉他，“你等一下吧。”

“哟嗬，哟嗬！”黑人睁大眼睛，故作惊讶。他四处张望了一下，护士要把莫尔太太锁回病房，还没回来。于是他对我无礼地鞠了个躬，没好气地说：“遵命——千金大小姐。”

我打开第二个锡盆的盖子，发现里面是一大团糊状通心粉，已经硬得像石头一样。第三个也是最后一个锡盆里装满了焗豆角。

于吃这一项上，现在我可是精通得很，一顿饭里不该有两种豆角。豆角配胡萝卜，或者豆角配豌豆，还说得过去，但是豆角配豆角绝对不行。那黑鬼分明是在试探我们忍耐的底线。

护士回来了，黑人侧身退到远处。我吃下尽可能多的焗豆角，然后起身，绕到护士看不见我腰部以下动作的另一边，站在清理脏盘子的黑人后面，脚往后一缩，对着他的小腿狠狠地一踢。

黑人号叫了一声跳开了，滚圆的眼珠子直瞪着我。“哎哟，小姐。哎哟，小姐。”他边呻吟边揉腿，“你不可以这样，不可以，真的不可以。”

“这是你的报应。”我瞪着他说。

“还不想起床呢？”

“不想。”我钻向被窝更深处，用被单遮住头，然后掀开被单的一角偷偷往外看。护士正在猛甩刚从我嘴里拿出来的温度计。

“瞧瞧，正常吧。”我总是在她收走体温计之前先看过读数，“你看，既然很正常，何必一直来量呢？”

我很想告诉她，如果真是身体的毛病，那倒好了。我宁可身体生病，也不愿脑子出问题。可是这么说恐怕她很难理解，解释起来又累得慌，干脆什么都别说了。我只有往被窝里钻得更深。

过了一会儿，隔着床单，我感觉到腿上微微有东西压着，不怎么舒服。我悄悄往外一看，是护士把放置体温计的托盘搁在我的床上，正背对着我帮邻床的病人测脉搏。那张床原是托莫利洛太太睡的。

恶作剧的强烈欲望在血管中膨胀，就像牙齿松动时的疼痛，让人又爱又恨。我打了个哈欠，转动身体，作势要翻身，把脚插入托盘下方。

“哦！”这护士发出求救般的声音，另一个护士跑了过来。“看你闯的祸！”

我把头钻出被窝，看向床边的地面。搪瓷托盘翻了个个儿，四周遍布着亮如星星的体温计碎片，一颗颗小水银球宛若仙境露珠般轻颤着。

“对不起。”我说，“我不是故意的。”

第二个护士恨恨地瞪着我不放。“你分明是故意的。我看见了。”

说完，她匆匆离开。几乎就在同时，两个护理员进入病房，把我连人带床整个推到莫尔太太之前住过的房间。不过，离去前我还是趁机捡了颗小水银球。

他们一锁上房门，我就看见那个黑人的脸，像焦糖色的月亮从门上的窗栅栏外升起，但我假装没看见。

我像个藏着秘密的孩子，把紧握的手松开一条缝，对着躺在掌心里的那颗小圆球笑了。如果它跌落在地，就会分裂成上百万颗一模一样的小颗粒，而如果把它们聚集在一起，它们又会重新融为一体，毫无瑕隙。

我对着这颗小水银球笑个不停。

真无法想象他们对莫尔太太做了什么。

15

费罗米娜·吉尼亚夫人的凯迪拉克像一辆迎宾车，缓缓驶过下午五点的拥挤车流，很快就要通过横跨查尔斯河的那些短桥中的一座。一上桥，我就会不假思索地打开车门，穿越车流，奔向桥栏。只需纵身一跃，河水就会没过我的头顶。

我心不在焉地将舒洁纸巾在指尖揉成药丸大小的纸团，准备伺机而动。我坐在凯迪拉克后排的中间，母亲坐在我一侧，弟弟在我另一侧，他们两人都微微前倾，像两条斜杆，挡住了两侧的车门。

前方是司机，他斯帕姆午餐肉颜色的宽阔后颈夹在蓝色帽子和蓝色夹克的肩膀之间，像块三明治。他旁边，是知名小说家费罗米娜·吉尼亚的银发和饰有绿宝石色羽毛的帽子，看起来像是一只柔弱的异国珍禽。

我不确定吉尼亚夫人怎么会出现，我只知道她很关注我的病情，而且据说当年事业如日中天时，她也曾进过精神病院。

母亲说，吉尼亚夫人从巴哈马群岛发来一封电报，说她在当地的一张波士顿报纸上看到了我的消息。她在电报里问：“此病是否跟男孩有关？”

如果这事牵涉到某个男孩，那吉尼亚夫人自然不会再介入。

可母亲回电报说：“无关，是写作上出了问题。埃斯特觉得她再也没办法提笔写作了。”

因此，吉尼亚夫人飞回波士顿，把我从那间拥挤压抑的市立疗养院带出来，现在正要送我到一家私人医院，那里有庭院、高尔夫球场和花园，像乡村俱乐部一样。她会支付一切费用，就当给我的奖学金，直至她认识的医生把我治好。

母亲说，我应该感恩戴德，家里的钱几乎被我的病耗尽了，要不是吉尼亚夫人，她不知道我会沦落到什么地方。其实我知道自己会沦落到哪里，一定是乡下的州立大医院，就在那家私人疗养院旁边。

我知道，但凡我有一丁点儿感觉，我都应该感激吉尼亚夫人。可就算她给我一张票，送我去欧洲，或者登上环游世界的邮轮，对我来说都毫无差别。因为不论我坐在哪里——轮船甲板上，巴黎街头的咖啡厅，或者是曼谷——我都好像坐在同一只玻璃钟形罩里，闷在自己散发出来的酸臭之气中。

蔚蓝的天穹罩在河面上方，河中帆影点点。我已做好随时跳车的准备，但母亲和弟弟立刻将手放在门把手上。车轮在烤肉架一样的桥梁上哧哧作响。河水、帆影、蓝天和凌空的海鸥一闪而过，画面像一张荒谬的明信片。就这样，我们到达了桥对岸。

我瘫倒在灰色的长毛绒椅里，闭上了眼睛。钟形罩里的空气团团包围了我，叫我动弹不得。

我又有了专属房间。

它让我想起戈登大夫诊所里的房间——一张床、一个五斗柜、一个衣橱、一张桌子和一把椅子。这里的窗户有纱网，没有铁栅栏。我的房间位于一楼，凭窗可以看到红砖墙环绕的绿树庭院，窗户离落满松针的地面很近，就算跳出去，膝盖也不会撞得瘀青。高墙内侧的砖面光滑如玻璃，恐怕爬不上去。

桥上那段行程的挣扎让我气馁。

我已错失良机。河水像一杯无人触碰的饮料，一去不回。我怀疑当时即使没有母亲和弟弟在场，我也不会跳下去。

在医院主楼登记时，有个身材纤细的女人上前自我介绍：“我是诺兰医生。今后埃斯特就由我来照顾。”

我很惊讶我的主治大夫是名女医生，我以为精神科医生都是男的。她的长相兼有演员玛娜·洛伊和我母亲的特色，白色衬衫和宽摆裙在腰间用宽皮带束住，戴着一副新月形的时髦眼镜。

护士领我穿过草坪，进入一栋名为卡普兰的阴暗的砖造建筑物中，我即将住在这个地方。诺兰医生并未前来，反而来了一群陌生男子。

我躺在床上，身上盖着厚厚的白毯子，他们一个接一个走进房间做自我介绍。我不明白为什么要来这么多人，他们又为什么要自我介绍。难道这是个测验，看我是否注意到他们人数众多？看来我得提高警惕。

最后，来了个帅气的白发医生，说他是疗养院的院长，然后开始谈起早期乘坐“五月花号”从欧洲来的清教徒移民和印第安人，以及在他们之后是哪些人占据了土地，又说起附近的河流，谁盖了第一家医院，那医院是如何烧毁，接着谁又盖了第二家医院，等等。我猜想，他一定在等着看我何时会打断他，告诉他之前他所说的什么河流、什么清教徒移民都是胡扯。

可是转念一想，也许其中有些是事实，所以我开始思索哪些是确有其事，哪些是胡说八道。没等我想明白，他就跟我道别了。

我等到所有医生的声音都渐渐消失，才掀开白毯子，起身穿上鞋子，走出房间。没人拦我，所以我沿着走廊，绕过我住的这一侧的转角，来到建筑物的另一侧，然后沿着一条更长的走廊继续走，途中经过一间大门敞开的餐厅。

一个穿着绿色制服的女工正在为晚餐摆放餐桌，桌上有白色的亚麻桌布，还有玻璃杯和餐巾纸。我把这里有真的玻璃杯的事偷偷藏进我记忆的角落，就像松鼠储存坚果一样。之前在市立医院，我们喝水用的是纸杯，也没有刀子可以切肉。为此，肉事先已经煮得很烂，用叉子就能切开。

终于，我走到一个大休息厅，里面的家具和地毯都已陈旧不堪。一个面色苍白、黑色短发的圆脸女孩坐在扶手椅上看杂志，她让我想起以前的一个女童子军队长。我朝她的脚望去，她果然穿的是褐色平底皮鞋，鞋面上的穗子改变了鞋头原本的运动风，鞋带的末端还缀着类似橡子的小饰物。

女孩抬起眼，笑着问我：“我是瓦莱丽，你叫什么名字？”

我假装没听见，离开休息厅，走向这一侧走廊的尽头。中间经过一扇及腰高的门，门后有几位护士。

“其他人上哪儿去了？”

“出去了。”回答我的护士在一片片小胶带上写字。我把身子探入门内，想看看她在写什么，发现她写的都是埃·格林伍德、埃·格林伍德、埃·格林伍德、埃·格林伍德。

“去哪儿了？”

“哦，去专业治疗啦，打高尔夫啦，打羽毛球啦。”

我注意到她身旁的椅子上有一堆衣服，正是我在之前那家医院打破镜子时，那里的护士正在为我打包装进漆皮手提箱的那些。护士开始把写有我名字的标签一一贴到衣服上。

我走回休息厅。我不明白这里的人到底在干些什么，居然可以打羽毛球和高尔夫。能做这些事情，他们一定不是真的有病。

我在瓦莱丽不远处坐下，仔细打量她。真的，我心想，她跟在女童子军营里没两样，正兴味盎然地看着手里那本破破烂烂的《时尚》杂志。

“她到底在这里做什么？”我纳闷，“她根本没毛病啊。”

“我可以抽烟吗？”诺兰医生往我床边的扶手椅里一靠。

我说抽吧，我喜欢烟味。我想，如果她抽上烟，或许会待得久一些。这是她第一次来找我谈话，等她一走，我就只能重新陷入一片茫然之中。

“跟我说说戈登大夫吧。”诺兰医生突然开口，“你喜欢他吗？”

我警惕地看了诺兰医生一眼。我想，医生都是一伙的，在这家医院的某个隐秘角落也会有一台机器，和戈登大夫诊所里的一模一样，随时可以把我电得魂飞魄散。

“不。”我说，“我一点儿也不喜欢他。”

“有意思。为什么呢？”

“我不喜欢他对我做的事。”

“他做了什么？”

我向诺兰医生描述了那台机器，那些蓝色的闪光、震动和巨响。我说这些的时候，她静静地听着。

“那样做不对。”她说，“不该是那样。”

我望着她。

“如果处理得好，就像睡着了一样。”她说。

“如果还有人对我这么做，我就自杀。”

诺兰医生坚定地说：“我们不会给你做电击治疗。”又补充解释道，“即使要做，我也会事先跟你说清楚，我保证绝对和你之前做的不一样。”最后她总结了一句：“你知道吗？有人甚至喜欢做呢。”

诺兰医生走后，我在窗台上发现一盒火柴。火柴盒不是一般的大小，非常迷你。我打开，拿出一排粉红头的白色火柴，试着点燃一根，却一划就断。

我想不出诺兰医生为什么要把这种愚蠢的玩意儿留给我。大概是想看看我会不会主动归还吧。我小心地把这盒玩具火柴藏在新羊毛浴袍的折边里。要是诺兰医生跟我要，我就说，我以为那是糖果做的，所以吃掉了。

隔壁房间刚住进一个女人。

我想，整个医院就数她来得比我还晚了，所以她不会像其他人那样了解我的斑斑劣迹。既如此，我应该去拜访一趟，同她交个朋友。

她躺在床上，身穿紫色裙子，领口别着一个浮雕宝石的胸针，裙子的长度介于膝盖和鞋子之间。红褐色的头发绾成女教师式的小圆髻，细边银框眼镜用黑色松紧带系在胸前的口袋上。

“你好，”我在床边坐下，像是跟她闲话家常，“我是埃斯特，你叫什么名字？”

她毫无反应，兀自望着天花板。我觉得很受伤，猜想是不是她前脚刚来，瓦莱丽或谁后脚就告诉她我这个人有多蠢。

有个护士探头进来。

“哦，你在这儿啊。”她对我说，“来拜访诺里斯小姐呀。你真好！”说完人就不见了。

我不知道自己坐了多久，就这么看着这个穿紫衣的女人，一直在想她噘起的粉唇会不会张开，如果张开了，又会说些什么。

终于，诺里斯小姐那穿着黑色扣式高筒靴的双脚一抬，从另一侧翻身下床，走出了房间，从头到尾没有跟我说一个字，连看也不看我一眼。我想，她可能试图不露痕迹地摆脱我。于是我隔着一小段距离，静静地跟着她穿过走廊。

诺里斯小姐到了餐厅门口，停住了。这一路上，她的每一步都精准无误地落在地毯表面编织的西洋蔷薇图案的正中央。她踌躇了一会儿，然后依次高抬两腿，迈过门槛，走进餐厅，那样子仿佛要越过的是一道高及小腿的隐形阶梯。

她坐在一张铺了亚麻桌布的圆桌旁，展开一块餐巾摊在腿上。

“一小时后才吃晚餐。”厨子在厨房里喊道。

诺里斯小姐没搭腔，只是斯文有礼地直视前方。

我拖出一张椅子在她对面坐下，也铺开一张餐巾。我们没有交谈，只这么坐着，沉浸在一种亲如姐妹的静默之中，直到走廊响起晚餐的铃声。

“躺好。”护士说，“还有一针要打。”

我翻身趴好，撩起裙子，拉下丝质睡裤。

“天哪。你的裙子下面还穿了什么呀？”

“睡裤。这样就不用成天穿穿脱脱了。”

护士轻笑了一声，然后说：“打哪边？”这对我是个老笑话了。

我抬头瞥了眼自己的光屁股，两边都因为一直打针而瘀青一片，不过左边的颜色看起来比右边的深一些。

“打右边。”

“听你的。”护士一针刺入，我缩了一下，感受到那轻微的刺痛。我一天打三次针，每次打完后一个小时，护士会给我端来一杯甜甜的果汁，站在旁边看我喝完。

“你运气好。”瓦莱丽说，“她们给你打胰岛素。”

“没什么感觉。”

“会有的。我就有过。等你有反应的时候告诉我。”

可是我一直都没反应，只是越来越胖，母亲买的新衣原本过大，现在已经完全被塞满。我低头看着自己的凸肚肥臀，就像快要生产的孕妇，心说，幸好吉尼亚夫人没看见我这副鬼样子。

“你见过我的疤吗？”

瓦莱丽拨开黑色刘海，指着前额两边的浅色疤痕，看起来像之前长了角，后来锯掉了。

我们两个由运动治疗师陪着，在疗养院的花园里散步。最近，我越来越经常获准到户外散步，但他们从来不让诺里斯小姐出来。

瓦莱丽说诺里斯小姐不该住在卡普兰楼，应该住到病症更严重的人住的威玛克楼。

“你知道这疤怎么来的吗？”瓦莱丽坚持聊她的疤。

“不知道。怎么来的？”

“我动了脑额叶切除术。”

我敬畏地看着瓦莱丽，第一次欣赏她始终如一的冷静沉着。“感觉如何？”

“很好。我再也不会生气了。以前我老是怒气冲冲，所以要住在威玛克楼里。现在我住卡普兰楼，而且可以由护士陪同，进城逛街看电影呢。”

“你出院之后要做什么？”

“哦，我不会走的。”瓦莱丽笑道，“我喜欢这儿。”

“搬家咯！”

“为什么我要搬家？”

护士开心地把抽屉和衣橱打开，清空，再关上，将我的东西都放进黑色的手提箱中。

我以为她们最终下了决定，要把我移到威玛克楼。“哦，你只是搬到这栋楼前面一点的房间。”护士欢快地说道，“你会喜欢的，那里阳光更充足。”

我们走出房间，在走廊上看见诺里斯小姐也在搬迁。一个看起来跟我的护士一样年轻开朗的护士站在她的房门口，正帮她穿上一件领口有细松鼠毛的紫色外套。

我曾须臾不离地守在诺里斯小姐的床前，放弃专业治疗、散步、羽毛球比赛，甚至是我喜爱而她却从来不去的每周一次的观影，只因挂念她那苍白无语的双唇。

我曾幻想，如果她开口说话将会是多么激动人心，我会冲上走廊向护士们宣告这大好消息，于是她们会表扬我鼓舞了诺里斯小姐，很有可能准许我以后进城逛街看电影，这样我就更有把握逃跑了。

可是我守候了这么久，诺里斯小姐却一字未吐。

“你要搬去哪里？”我问她。

护士碰碰诺里斯小姐的手肘，她猛地一动，就像脚下安了轮轴的洋娃娃。

“她要搬到威玛克楼去。”我的护士低声告诉我，“恐怕诺里斯小姐不像你那么有进展。”

我看着诺里斯小姐抬起一只脚，然后又抬起另一只脚，跨过门槛前那道看不见的阶梯。

“我有个惊喜给你。”护士把我带到这栋楼前侧的一间屋里，那里阳光充沛，还能俯视碧绿的高尔夫球场。安顿好我之后，她说：“有个你认识的人今天刚住进来。”

“我认识的人？”

护士笑了。“别这样看着我。放心，不是警察。”见我没说话，她继续说道，“她说是你的老朋友，就住在隔壁，你何不去看看她？”

我想护士一定是在开玩笑。如果我去敲隔壁的房间，肯定不会有人来开门。如果我直接进去，就会看见诺里斯小姐穿着松鼠毛领的紫色大衣躺在床上，嘴巴微张，像一朵玫瑰花苞在静如花瓶的身体里绽放。

不过，我还是走到隔壁敲了门。

“请进。”一个欢快的声音回应道。

我把门打开一条缝，往里面窥探。有个穿着马裤、人高马大的女孩坐在窗边，咧着嘴看向我。

“埃斯特！”她说话时带着气音，好像跑过了一段好长好长的路程才刚停下来。“好高兴看见你。他们说你也在这里。”

“琼？”我试探地唤她的名字，然后又一头雾水，难以置信地又唤了一声，“琼！”

琼笑容满面，露出闪闪发光的大牙。错不了，就是她。

“真的是我。我就知道你一定会大吃一惊。”

16

琼的房间跟我的一模一样，也有衣橱、五斗柜、桌子、椅子，以及印有代表卡普兰楼名称首字母的蓝色大C的白被单。我忽然想到，会不会是琼打听到我住在这里，就找了借口订了这间疗养院的病房，存心跟我开玩笑。这就解释了她为什么会跟护士说我是她的朋友，其实我跟她一点也不熟，只是泛泛之交。

“你怎么会来这里？”我窝在她的床上。

“我看到了你的消息。”琼说。

“什么消息？”

“反正我看到了你的消息，于是就离家出走了。”

“什么意思？”我心平气和地问。

“是这样的。”琼往疗养院的印花棉布扶手椅里一靠，“我暑假在某个兄弟会的分会长那里打工，你知道，就是像共济会那种性质，但又不是共济会，结果很惨。我得了拇指囊肿，几乎走不了路——最后几天连鞋子都没办法穿，只能穿橡胶靴上班，你可以想见这对我打击有多大……”

我想，要么琼真的疯了——居然穿着橡胶靴上班——要么就是她想看看我疯到什么程度，才会相信她的这番鬼话。况且，只有老人才会得拇指囊肿。我决定将计就计，假装相信她疯了，顺着她的意思说话。

“我总觉得不穿正式的鞋子很不像样。”我暧昧地笑道，“你的脚真的很疼吗？”

“疼死了。而且我的老板——他刚和老婆分居，不敢明说想离婚，因为离婚就违反了兄弟会的规定——我老板每隔一分钟就按铃找我，每次我一动，脚就疼得要命。刚坐回桌子前，催命铃声又来了，他非得做点什么一抒胸臆才行……”

“那你干吗不辞职走人？”

“哦，我是辞职啦，多少算吧。我请了病假不去上班，不出门，不见任何人，电话也丢进抽屉不接……”

“然后我的医生就把我送到一家大医院的精神科。我跟医生约了十二点，那时我的状态已经很糟糕了。结果到了十二点半，接待人员出来告诉我，医生去吃午饭了，问我要不要等，我说要。”

“那医生有没有回来？”如果这故事纯属虚构，听起来还真有点复杂。但我还是让琼继续讲下去，看看她还能编出什么东西来。

“他回来了。注意，当时我正准备自杀。我对自己说：‘如果这个医生也没有用，一切就都结束了。’然后，接待员带我走过一条长廊，正走到诊室门口时，她转过头对我说：‘你不介意有几个学生陪在医生旁边吧？’我能说什么？‘哦，没关系。’我说。结果我进去后，发现有九双眼睛盯着我。九双啊！整整十八只眼睛。

“如果接待员早告诉我里面有九个无关人员，我会掉头就走。可是到了这个地步，一切都太迟了。唉，那天我刚好穿了件毛皮大衣……”

“八月穿毛皮大衣？”

“呃，那几天刚好又湿又冷，而且我想，这是第一次见精神科医生——你知道的嘛。总之，我跟他说话时，这位精神科医生全程都盯着我的毛皮大衣。还有，当我要他给我学生优惠价，不要全额收费时，我完全清楚他在想什么。他的眼里全是钱。我跟他说我不知道所有的事——拇指囊肿，抽屉里的电话，自杀的念头，等等——他听了之后，要我到外头等着，他得和其他人讨论讨论我的病情。等他叫我回去的时候，你知道他怎么说吗？”

“怎么说？”

“他两手交握，看着我说：‘吉林小姐，我们认为团体治疗会对你有所帮助。’”

“团体治疗？”我想，我的声音一定假得像回音室里的声响，但是琼完全没注意到。

“他就是这么说的。你能想象吗？企图自杀的我竟然跟一堆陌生人谈论这件事，而且他们大部分人的心智比我好不了多少……”

“太扯了。”我情不自禁地越来越投入，“简直没人性。”

“我也是这么说的。我直接回家，给那医生写了一封行文优雅的信，告诉他，像他这样的人完全没资格悬壶济世……”

“他回信了吗？”

“我不知道。因为就在那天，我在报纸上看到了你的事。”

“什么事？”

“哦，”琼说，“就是警方认为你凶多吉少之类的。我还收集了一堆剪报。”她倏然起身，一股强烈的马骚味扑鼻而来，让我觉得鼻腔刺痛。琼曾在大学年度运动会上得过马术障碍赛的冠军，我怀疑她都睡在马厩里。

琼在打开的皮箱里一通好找，翻出一沓剪报来。

“给，你看。”

第一张剪报上有一张巨幅的放大照片，照片里的女孩涂着黑眼影，抹着黑唇膏，露齿而笑。我想不起我什么时候拍了这么放荡的照片，直到我注意到那副在布鲁明戴尔百货商店买的耳环，以及那条光彩夺目、熠熠生辉、亮如人造星星的项链，才反应过来。

资优女生失踪，母亲忧心忡忡

照片下方的报道说，该女生于八月十七日失踪，失踪时身穿绿裙白衣，仅在家中留下字条，说要出去散个长长的步。报道说，格林伍德小姐到了午夜仍未返家，其母随即向镇警署报案。

第二份剪报刊登了母亲、弟弟和我在后院的合照，我们仨都笑意盈盈。我依旧想不起是谁帮我们拍的照片，直到我看见我穿的粗布工作服和白色帆布鞋，才记起那是某个夏天炎热的午后，我去采收菠菜，朵朵·康威恰巧经过，替我们一家三口拍了几张照片。格林伍德夫人请报社刊登此照，希望能借此打动女儿回家。

安眠药恐被失踪女生带走

这张照片很暗，拍的是十几个脸圆如满月的人半夜在树林里活动。我觉得后排的人看起来怪怪的，特别矮，后来才发现那不是人，是狗。警方出动了警犬，搜寻失踪女孩。比尔·曼德利警长说情况不乐观。

失踪女孩生还

最后一张照片，是警察把一个用毯子卷起来的东西抬入救护车里，那东西长而软，五官不明，头颅宛如卷心菜。报道里提到，母亲去地下室洗一周的衣服，结果听到弃置不用的坑洞里传出微弱的呻吟……

我把剪报放在白色的床罩上。

“你留着吧。”琼说，“把它们贴到剪贴簿上。”

我把剪报折起来，放进口袋里。

“我看了所有关于你的消息。”琼继续说，“不仅是他们怎么找到的你，还包括之前的每一个细节。然后我把所有的钱凑了凑，搭第一班飞机赶往纽约。”

“为什么去纽约？”

“哦，我觉得在纽约自杀比较容易。”

“你做了什么？”

琼羞怯地一笑，伸出双手，掌心朝上。她白皙的手腕上隆起粗大的红色伤痕，犹如微型山脉。

“你怎么弄的？”我第一次觉得，琼和我之间或许有共通之处。

“我用拳头打破了室友的窗户。”

“哪个室友？”

“大学时的室友，她在纽约工作。我想不出还能去哪，而且身上也没剩多少钱了，所以只能去投靠她。结果我父母找到了我——是她写信告密，说我举止怪异——我爸飞到纽约，直接把我带回了家。”

“可是你现在已经好了。”我这话说得很肯定。

琼用她那双灰石色的明亮眼睛看着我。“大概吧。”她说，“你不也一样？”

晚餐后我睡着了。

一个很响亮的声音惊醒了我。那声音叫着：“班尼斯特太太，班尼斯特太太，班尼斯特太太，班尼斯特太太。”我从睡梦中睁开眼，发现自己猛拍床架，嘴里还大喊着班尼斯特太太。夜班护士班尼斯特太太敏捷、歪斜的身影映入眼帘。

“小心，别弄坏了。”

她解开我的表带。

“怎么了？发生了什么事？”

班尼斯特太太的脸迅速堆出一个笑容。“你有反应了。”

“反应？”

“是啊，你感觉如何？”

“怪怪的。有点虚，轻飘飘的。”

班尼斯特太太扶我坐起来。

“你会没事的，很快就会好起来。要不要喝点热牛奶？”

“好。”

班尼斯特太太将杯子端到我嘴边，我边喝边让热牛奶在舌头上漫开来，贪婪地品尝它的滋味，就像婴儿留恋母乳一般。

“班尼斯特太太说你有反应了。”诺兰医生坐在窗边的扶手椅里，拿出一小盒火柴，看起来和我藏在浴袍折边里的那盒一模一样。我一时怀疑，是不是哪个护士发现了我的火柴，不动声色地把它还给了诺兰医生。

诺兰医生在盒子一侧划燃火柴，一道黄热的火焰腾空而起，我看着她把火焰吸入香烟里。

“班太太说你觉得好些了。”

“只好了那么一会儿。现在又回到老样子了。”

“有件事要告诉你。”

我等着她说下去。每天的早上、下午、晚上，我裹着白色毯子，靠在走廊内凹室的躺椅上假装看书，已经不知有多少天了。我隐隐觉得诺兰医生会允许我过几天自由的日子，然后就会像戈登大夫一样对我说：“很抱歉，你似乎没什么进展，我想你最好接受电击治疗……”

“怎么，你不想知道是什么事吗？”

“什么事？”我无精打采地说，做好了心理准备。

“接下来一段时间我们不允许访客探视你。”

我惊讶地望着诺兰医生。“啊，这太好了。”

“我就知道你会很高兴。”她笑着说。

然后，我看着五斗柜旁的垃圾桶，诺兰医生也看着那里。垃圾桶外露出一打长茎玫瑰的血红花蕾。

那天下午，母亲来看我。

母亲只是络绎不绝的访客中的一个——我的前老板，那个信奉基督教科学派的女人来过，跟我在草坪上散步，谈起《圣经》中从地上升起的雾气。她说，这雾气不是真实的，而我的所有问题就在于把它当了真，只要我不再相信它，它就会消失无踪，我也会发现自己本就好端端的。我的高中英文老师也来过，他试图教我玩拼字游戏，认为这可以帮我重燃对文字的热情。来的人里还有费罗米娜·吉尼亚本人，她很不满意医生对我的治疗，对他们抱怨个不停。

我烦透了这些探视。

每次我坐在走廊内凹室或自己的房中，就会有护士笑着探进头来，说有这个或那个访客。有一次她们甚至带了个一神教的牧师进来，我从来都不喜欢这个人。他从头到尾都紧张兮兮，我看得出来，他认为我真的疯了，因为我告诉他我相信地狱。我还说，有些人，比如我，还没死就得活在地狱里，免得死后没地狱可下，谁让我们不相信死后会有来生。因为一个人相信死后有什么，死后便会有什么。

我讨厌这些访客，因为我总觉得他们老是盯着我油腻腻的打绺儿的头发，比较我从前的模样，或对照他们心目中的我。我知道，他们离去时对我的变化百思不解。

如果他们让我一个人待着，我或许能平静些。

母亲是所有访客中我最不想见的。她从不苛责我，却总是愁容满面地哀求我告诉她，她到底做错了什么。她说，她确定医生们都认为她有错，因为他们问了她许多关于训练我上厕所的往事。我年纪很小的时候这方面就被训练得很好，从没给她添过麻烦。

那天下午，母亲给我带来了玫瑰花。

“留到我的葬礼再送吧。”我说。

母亲蹙额皱眉，看起来快哭了。

“可是埃斯特，你不记得今天是什么日子吗？”

“不记得。”

我以为是情人节。“今天是你的生日。”

这时，我正好把玫瑰花扔进垃圾桶里。

“她这样做实在很蠢。”我对诺兰医生说。

诺兰医生点点头，似乎明白我的意思。“我恨她。”我说，等着她抨击我。

可是诺兰医生只是对我笑，好像有什么事逗得她非常非常开心，然后她说：“我想也是。”

17

“今天是你的幸运日哦。”

年轻护士收走我的早餐盘，我继续裹着白毯子，像个在轮船甲板上吹海风的旅客。

“为什么这么说？”

“嗯，不晓得该不该现在就告诉你，今天你就要搬到贝尔赛思楼了。”护士满眼期待地看着我。

“贝尔赛思楼。”我说，“我不能去那里。”

“为什么？”

“我还没准备好。我恢复得还不够好。”

“你当然够好了。别担心，要是你不够好，他们不会让你搬过去。”

护士走后，我开始苦苦思索诺兰医生这一新动作是怎么回事。她想证明什么？我根本没有变化。一切都没有变化。贝尔赛思是疗养院里最好的大楼，离开贝尔赛思的人就可以重回工作岗位，重回学校，重回家庭。

琼应该在贝尔赛思楼，她和她的物理书、高尔夫球杆、羽毛球拍、带着气音的声音一起住在那儿。琼，代表的就是我和即将康复的人之间的那道鸿沟。自打她离开卡普兰楼后，我就从各种小道消息随时了解她的进展。

琼有了散步权，琼有了购物权，琼有了进城权。我将搜集到的所有关于琼的消息聚拢成一个令我感到苦涩的小堆，尽管我表面上为她高兴。她就像以前最美时光的我，是故意来这里跟踪、折磨我的。

等我到贝尔赛思楼，她可能已经走了。

不过，至少在贝尔赛思楼可以忘了电击。卡普兰楼里很多女人都受过电击治疗，我能看出谁做过，因为她们不像我们其他人这样有人送早餐来。我们在房间吃早餐的时候，她们在接受电击。做完后，护士像领着一队小孩一样，带着安静不语、死气沉沉的她们去休息厅吃早餐。

每天清晨，听见护士敲门送早餐的声音，我心中都感到一阵汹涌澎湃的安慰，因为我知道那一天我安全了。我不明白诺兰医生自己没经历过电击治疗，凭什么说做电击的时候可以睡着。她又怎么会知道被电击的人并不像表面上看到的睡着的样子，其实从始至终病人的脑中都是蓝色的电流和巨响？

走廊尽头传来钢琴声。

晚餐时，我静静地坐着，听贝尔赛思楼的女人们叽叽喳喳。她们都打扮入时，妆容精致，有几个已经结了婚。有些人刚进城购物回来，有些则外出访过友，整个晚餐期间她们都不停地说着她们的私房笑话。

“我会给杰克打电话。”一个名叫蒂蒂的女人说，“只怕他不在家。当然喽，我知道可以打去哪里找他，他一定会在那儿。”

我同桌一个矮小活泼的女人笑着说：“我今天差点就搞定了罗林医生。”她睁着炯炯有神的蓝色眼睛，活像个洋娃娃，“我不介意用老波希换个新款式。”

在房间的另一头，琼狼吞虎咽地吃着斯帕姆午餐肉和焗番茄，胃口好得很。她似乎跟这些女人很合得来，对我却冷冰冰的，还带着点鄙夷，她似乎是把我当成一个迟钝的熟人，高攀不上她。

吃过晚餐我打算去睡觉，可正好听见了钢琴声，脑海中浮现琼、蒂蒂、金发女人罗贝尔和其他女人在客厅里背着我讲我闲话、肆意嘲笑我的画面。她们会说贝尔赛思楼有我这种人多可怕啊，我应该待在威玛克楼才对。

我决定让她们闭上鸟嘴。

把毯子往肩上一披，当成个松松垮垮的披肩，我沿着走廊慢慢踱向那片灯火和欢声笑语。

这个夜晚接下来的时间，我都在听蒂蒂用那台大钢琴自弹自唱，其他女人则围坐一圈打牌聊天，就像在大学宿舍里一样。只是她们多半超出大学年龄十岁。

其中有个叫萨维奇太太的，身材高大，头发灰白，声音低沉，毕业于名校瓦萨尔学院。我一眼就看出她是社交名媛，因为她谈的都是少女初入社交界的各种逸事。据说她有两三个女儿，就在她们即将进入社交圈的那年，她自愿进了精神病院，毁了女儿们的初次派对。

蒂蒂创作了首名为《送牛奶工》的歌。大家一直说她应该拿去发表，一定会成为畅销歌曲。她的双手先在琴键上敲出一小段旋律，像小马慢跑的嗒嗒声，接着另一段旋律加入，像送奶工在吹口哨，最后两段旋律合二为一。

“真好听。”我以闲聊的口吻说。

琼靠在钢琴的一角，翻阅着一本刚出版的时尚杂志，蒂蒂抬头冲她一笑，仿佛二人之间有什么心照不宣的秘密。

“哦，埃斯特，”琼举起那本杂志，说，“这不是你吗？”

蒂蒂停下演奏。“让我看看。”她拿走杂志，看着琼指出的那页，然后瞧了我一眼。

“哦，不会吧。”蒂蒂说，“肯定不是。”她又看看杂志，再看看我，“绝不可能！”

“但那就是埃斯特，对不对，埃斯特？”琼说。

罗贝尔和萨维奇太太袅娜而来，我强装信心十足，跟着她们一起走向钢琴。

杂志照片上的女孩穿着毛茸茸的白色无肩带晚礼服，笑得嘴巴简直要裂开，身边一群男生众星拱月似的围着她。那女孩手里端着一杯透明饮料，眼神似乎越过我的肩膀，注视着立在我身后稍偏左的什么东西。一阵微弱的气息吹过我的后颈，我旋即转过身。

夜班护士不知何时进来了，穿着软底胶鞋，没人注意到。

“别开玩笑了。”她说，“真是你吗？”

“不，不是我。琼完全搞错了。那是别人。”

“哦，说吧，是你！”蒂蒂嚷嚷道。我假装没听见，转过身去。罗贝尔求护士跟她们一起打牌，因为这会儿正好三缺一。尽管对桥牌一窍不通，我还是拉了张椅子在一旁观看。大学里我可没时间学这些富家女玩的东西。

我一边看着国王、杰克和王后拉长的扑克脸，一边听着护士大吐生活的苦水。“你们这些女士哪里知道打两份工的辛苦。”她说，“晚上我在这里照看你们……”

罗贝尔咯咯笑道：“哦，我们可乖了。我们是这么多人里最乖的，你知道。”

“对，你们很棒。”护士把一包绿薄荷口香糖分给大家，然后打开自己手上那片的锡纸，拿出一片粉红色的口香糖，“你们都很棒，是那些州立医院的笨蛋让我疲于奔命。”

“这么说，你在两个地方工作？”我忽然很有兴趣。

“可不。”护士直直看着我，我看得出来，她觉得我根本没资格待在贝尔赛思楼。“你绝对不会喜欢待在那种地方的，简女士。”

她明明知道我的名字，可是却叫我简女士，真是奇怪。

“为什么呢？”我追问。

“哦，那里可不比这里舒服。这里就像正规的乡村俱乐部，而那里什么都没有，没有专业治疗，不能散步……”

“为什么不能散步？”

“缺人——手——啊。”护士手里的牌占了先机，罗贝尔发出哀叹。护士接着说：“相信我，小姐们，只要存够了买车的银子，我就不干了。”

“连这里也不做了？”琼问。

“还用说么。以后只接私活，而且想接的时候才接……”

可我已经听不下去了。

我觉得这个护士是被派来暗示我的，给了我两条出路。要么我好转，要么我沉沦下去，一直沉沦，像一颗燃烧殆尽最终崩塌的星星，从贝尔赛思落到卡普兰，再落到威玛克。最终，当诺兰医生和吉尼亚夫人也放弃我时，就落到隔壁的州立疗养院去了。

我裹紧身上的毯子，将椅子向后推。

“冷啦？”护士粗声问道。

“对。”我说着朝走廊走去，“我快冻僵了。”

我在白色的茧中醒来，温暖而平静。镜子、柜子上的眼镜和金属门把上映出一道苍白却炫目的冬日阳光。厨房女工正在准备早餐，嘈杂的声音透过走廊传来。

我听见护士在敲着隔壁的房门，那是走廊尽头了。萨维奇太太睡意浓浓的声音隆隆作响，护士端着早餐盘，叮里当啷地走了进去。我带着淡淡的欢喜，期待热气腾腾的蓝瓷咖啡壶、蓝瓷早餐杯和那只绘有白色雏菊的蓝瓷奶油罐。

我开始放弃自己了。

即使我会沉沦，起码先把握当下这小小的慰藉，有多久算多久。

护士敲了敲门，没等我应门，就一阵风似的进来了。

今天是个新护士——这里的人总是换来换去——清瘦的脸和头发都是浅褐色的，骨感的鼻子上有斑斑点点的大雀斑。不知为什么，她的出现让我心里一慌。我看着她大步穿过房间，打开绿色百叶窗，才突然意识到，这种奇怪的感觉是因为她两手空空。

我想开口问她我的早餐呢，但随即闭上了嘴，她可能把我错认成别人了，新护士总是这样。贝尔赛思楼里一定有我不认识的人在进行电击治疗，这护士把我和其他病人搞混了，这倒情有可原。

我一直等着。护士在我房里巡了一圈，拍拍这里，扯扯那里，整理一下东西，然后拿着早餐托盘走向长廊的下一个门，那是罗贝尔的病房。

我把脚塞进拖鞋，拽着毯子——早上天气虽然晴朗，却非常冷——快速走到对门的厨房。穿着粉色制服的女帮工正把炉子上一只破旧大茶壶里的液体灌入一排蓝瓷咖啡壶中。

我深情款款地注视着列队等候的托盘——白色的餐巾纸，折成简洁的等边三角形，上面摆着银叉子，半熟的水煮蛋从蓝色蛋杯里露出白色的圆顶，扇贝形的玻璃碟子里盛着橙子果酱。我只要伸出手去，拿起属于我的托盘，世界就会恢复如常。

“一定是搞错了。”我靠着柜台，用亲密的口吻低声对女帮工说，“新来的护士今天忘了把早餐拿到我房间。”

我挤出一个开朗的笑容，表示我没有生气。

“你的名字？”

“格林伍德。埃斯特·格林伍德。”

“格林伍德，格林伍德，格林伍德。”女帮工伸出布满肿疣的食指，一路扫过墙上那张贝尔赛思楼病人名单，“格林伍德，今天没有早餐。”

我双手抓住柜台边缘。

“一定是弄错了。你确定是格林伍德没有早餐？”

“格林伍德。”女帮工坚定地说。正在此时，护士进来了。

她狐疑地看看我，又看看女帮工。“格林伍德小姐要拿她的早餐。”女帮工避开我的目光，告诉护士。

“哦。”护士笑着对我说，“你今天迟点吃早餐，格林伍德小姐。你……”

没等护士说完，我就没头没脑地冲入走廊。我没回房间，因为会被他们抓住，我去了走廊上的内凹室。虽然这里远远比不上卡普兰楼的内凹室，但好歹是走廊上的一个僻静角落，琼、罗贝尔、蒂蒂和萨维奇太太都不会来这里。

我用毯子蒙住头，蜷缩在内凹室的角落。真正打击我的不是电击治疗，而是诺兰医生公然的背叛。我喜欢诺兰医生，敬爱她，我对她推心置腹，倾诉一切，她也信誓旦旦跟我保证，如果非得做电击治疗，一定会事先通知我。

如果她昨晚告诉我，我一定会彻夜难眠，忐忑不安，心中充满不祥的预感，但一夜过后，我应该已经镇定下来，准备妥当。当两名护士挟着我穿过走廊，经过蒂蒂、罗贝尔、萨维奇太太和琼的门前时，我会保持尊严，冷静地奔赴“刑场”。

护士弯下腰，唤我的名字。

我挪动身体，又往角落里缩了缩。护士走了，我知道她马上就会带着两个身材魁梧的男看护过来，架着我走过休息厅里那群微笑的看客，任凭我一路嘶喊挣扎。

诺兰医生像母亲一样伸手抱住我。

“你说你会提前告诉我！”我躲在一团凌乱的毯子里对她吼道。

“我就是来告诉你的呀。”诺兰医生说，“我特地一大早来跟你说，而且我会亲自陪你过去。”

我睁开浮肿的眼皮盯着她。“昨晚为什么不告诉我？”

“我怕你会睡不着。要是早知道……”

“你说过，你会提前告诉我的。”

“听我说，埃斯特。”诺兰医生说，“我会陪你去，全程在场，一切都会像我保证过的那样进行。你醒来时就会看见我，我会把你带回来。”

我看着她，她一脸忧心。

等了一会儿，我说：“答应我，你会一直陪着我。”

“我保证。”

诺兰医生拿出一条白手帕擦擦我的脸，然后像老朋友一般挽起我的手臂，扶我起身，走向长廊。毯子纠缠在我脚边，我索性丢开它，不过诺兰医生似乎并未注意到。我们走过琼的房间，她正好出来，我对她露出一个意味深长的冷笑，她急忙躲回房去等着我们走远。

诺兰医生打开长廊尽头的一扇房门，领我走下台阶，进入神秘的地下通道。通道里有许多复杂的地道和洞穴，像张网一样连接着疗养院的各栋建筑。

通道墙壁贴着洗手间用的光面白瓷砖，黑色天花板上间隔有序地挂着光秃秃的灯泡。随处可见担架和轮椅靠在嘶嘶震动的管子上，管子沿着白亮的墙面延伸、分岔，形成一个复杂的神经系统图案。我吓得半死，紧紧攀着诺兰医生的手臂，她不时捏捏我，给我打气。

最后，我们停在一扇绿色的门前，门上印有黑色字体：电击治疗室。我裹足不前，诺兰医生耐心等着。然后我说：“做就做吧。”我们一起走了进去。

等候区里除了诺兰医生和我，还有一个面色惨白、穿着破旧紫褐色浴袍的男子和他的随行护士。

“要不要坐着等？”诺兰医生指着一张木质长椅，但我的双腿重得像灌了铅一样，坐下容易，等电疗人员进来带我时，站起来就难了。

“还是站着好了。”

终于，一个穿着白色工作服、一脸憔悴的高个子女人从里屋走出来。我以为她会带走那个穿紫褐色浴袍的男人，因为他排在我前面，所以她向我走来的时候我真的很吃惊。

“早上好，诺兰医生。”女人说着，伸手揽住我的肩膀，“这就是埃斯特吧？”

“没错，休伊小姐。埃斯特，这位是休伊小姐，她会好好照顾你的，我把你的情况都跟她说了。”

我想，这位休伊女士的身高足有七英尺。她亲切地弯下腰，我看见她的脸，暴突的门牙在中间突出，脸上都是青春痘疤，看起来就像是月球上的环形山分布图。

“我想我们可以先给你做，埃斯特。”休伊小姐说，“安德森先生不会介意稍等一下的，是不是，安德森先生？”

安德森先生没回答，于是休伊小姐搂着我的肩膀走进隔壁房间，诺兰医生紧随其后。

从眯起的眼缝中——我不敢把眼睛睁得太大，怕一下子看清房间会吓死自己——我看见一张高架床，白色床单紧绷如鼓面，床后就是机器，有个人站在机器后面——戴着口罩辨不出男女——床两侧也站了几个戴口罩的人。

休伊小姐扶我爬上床，帮我仰面躺好。

“跟我说话。”我说。

休伊小姐一边轻声细语安抚我，一边将软膏涂在我太阳穴上，然后在我头两侧贴上小小的电流片。“你绝对不会有事的，什么感觉也没有。来，咬住……”她往我舌头上塞了个东西，我惊恐地咬住。黑暗将我像黑板上的粉笔字一样擦去。

18

“埃斯特。”

我从沉睡中醒来，浑身湿透，首先映入眼帘的是诺兰医生晃来晃去的脸。她不停地唤我：“埃斯特，埃斯特。”

我用尚不灵便的双手揉了揉眼睛。

我看到诺兰医生身后有个穿着皱巴巴的黑白格纹长袍的女人，像从高处坠落一样正被抛到床上。没来得及细瞧，诺兰医生就把我带出了门。外面空气清爽，天空蔚蓝。

所有的燥热和恐惧都一扫而光，我感到一种出奇的平静。钟形罩悬在头顶上方几英尺处，我置身于开放流动的空气中。

“就像我跟你说的一样，对吧？”我们一路踩着窸窣作响的落叶回到贝尔赛思楼时，诺兰医生这么问我。

“对。”

“好，以后做起来也都是这种感觉。”她笃定地说，“你每周做三次——周二、周四和周六。”

我倒抽了一口长长的冷气。

“要做多久？”

“看情况。”诺兰医生说，“由你、我共同决定。”

我拿起银质餐刀，敲掉水煮蛋顶上的壳。放下刀，我怔怔地看着它。我努力回想为什么以前我那么喜欢刀子，但思绪却如出笼的鸟儿，在空虚中飞舞。

琼和蒂蒂肩并肩坐在琴凳上，蒂蒂在教琼弹奏《筷子曲》的低音部，她自己弹高音部。

我觉得琼真可悲，长得壮如牛，牙齿巨大，眼睛凸如灰色的鹅卵石。唉，她连巴迪·威拉德这样的男人都拴不住。蒂蒂的老公肯定跟某个情妇同居了，把她气得像只乖戾凶狠的老猫。

“我收到一封——信。”琼像吟诵歌曲一样，蓬乱的头探进我的房间。

“恭喜。”我的眼睛没有离开书本。连续做了五次电击治疗后，我有了进城的自由。打那时起，琼就像只大果蝇，成天气喘吁吁地绕着我转——仿佛只要靠近我，就能汲取康复的甜美滋味。他们拿走了她原本堆在房间里的物理书和落满灰尘的线圈笔记本，里面都是上课笔记。此外，她又被禁足在疗养院里了。

“你不想知道是谁寄来的吗？”

琼慢慢蹭进屋里，坐在我的床上。我想让她滚出去，她让我不舒服，但我说不出口。

“好吧。”我把手指夹入正在读的那一页，合上书，“谁寄来的？”

琼从裙子口袋里掏出一个浅蓝色的信封，调皮地挥了挥。

“哈，真是巧了。”我说。

“你说什么，巧？”

我起身走到五斗柜前，拿起一个浅蓝色的信封，像挥动告别时的手帕一样，对琼挥了挥。“我也收到一封信，不知道是不是一样的。”

“他好多了。”琼说，“已经出院了。”

一阵沉默。

“你会嫁给他吗？”

“不。”我说。“你呢？”

琼逃避地笑笑。“反正我也不是很喜欢他。”

“哦？”

“对，我喜欢的是他的家人。”

“你是说威拉德先生和太太？”

“是的。”琼的声音像一股气流，飕飕滑下我的脊背。“我喜欢他们。他们人很好，生活很开心，跟我的父母一点也不一样。我经常去看他们。”她停顿了一下，“直到你出现。”

“很抱歉。”我说，“既然你那么喜欢他们，为什么不保持来往呢？”

“唉，我做不到。”琼说，“因为你和巴迪在交往。如果我去了，好像……我也不知道怎么说，反正怪怪的。”

我想了想，道：“应该是。”

“那——”琼欲言又止，“你会让他来看你吗？”

“我不知道。”

一开始我觉得让巴迪来疗养院看我是一件很可怕的事——他很可能只会幸灾乐祸，或与其他医生相谈甚欢。不过随后又想，这或许可以是一记妙招，先评判他，再抛弃他，就算我身边没有其他男人——直接告诉他根本没有什么同声传译官，谁都没有，但他不是我想要的，我就是不想再跟他纠缠下去了。“你会让他来吗？”

“我会。”琼带着气音说，“他可能会带他妈来。我会叫他带妈妈一起来……”

“他妈妈？”

琼噘起嘴。“我喜欢威拉德太太啊。威拉德太太是个很棒很棒的女人。对我来说，她就像亲妈一样。”

我可以想见威拉德太太穿着杂色花呢大衣，穿着结实的鞋，说着充满母性光辉的智慧格言。威拉德先生是她的小宝贝，声音也如小男孩一样高亢可爱。琼和威拉德太太。琼……和威拉德太太……

那天早上我去敲蒂蒂的门，想借几张两个声部的乐谱。等了一会儿，见没有人来开门，我心想蒂蒂一定出门去了，我可以直接从她的柜子里拿。于是我推门而入。

在贝尔赛思楼，即便在病人情况最好的贝尔赛思楼，房间也有锁，只是病人没有钥匙。关门等同于上锁，代表病人的隐私权，这一点大家都会尊重。敲敲门，再敲敲，没人应门，就会主动离去。我从明亮的长廊猛地进入弥漫着麝香味的昏暗房间，眼睛一时无法适应，在原地呆站的时候才想起这规矩。

视力逐渐恢复，只见有个身影从床上坐起，接着发出咯咯轻笑。这身影拨弄了一下头发，两颗灰石色的眼睛在幽暗中盯着我。蒂蒂躺回床上，绿色的羊毛晨袍底下露出赤裸的双腿，她带着嘲讽的微笑望向我，右手指间闪着烟头的火光。

“我只是想……”我说。

“我知道。”蒂蒂说，“拿乐谱。”

“嗨，埃斯特。”琼开口了，她那粗嘎如剥玉米皮的声音让人作呕。“等一下，埃斯特，我来弹低音部，跟你合奏。”

现在，琼口吻坚决地说：“我从没真正喜欢过巴迪·威拉德。他自以为无所不知，以为自己完全了解女人……”

我看着琼。虽然她总让我寒毛倒竖，对她的反感由来已久且根深蒂固，但这会儿她真令我着迷，那感觉就像观察一个火星人或者一只特别丑陋多疣的癞蛤蟆。她的想法和我的想法不同，她的感觉和我的感觉不同，但我们又如此相近，她的想法和感受简直就是我的想法和感受的扭曲、黑暗版。

有时我怀疑，琼是不是我捏造出来的人物。有时则会想，是否在我生命的每一个关键时刻，她都会冒出来提醒我，过去的我是什么样的，又经历过什么，然后她就在我眼前度过她自己的危机，那些与我无关却又相似的危机。

“我不明白女人在其他女人身上可以得到什么。”那天中午跟诺兰医生会面时，我告诉她，“在女人身上，女人可以得到什么是男人所没有的？”

诺兰医生沉默了片刻，然后说：“温柔。”

我无言以对。

“我喜欢你。”琼说，“我喜欢你，胜于喜欢巴迪。”

她整个人呈大字躺在我的床上，一脸傻笑。我想起大学宿舍里的一件小丑闻：有个大四女生和一个大一女生，大四女生胖胖的，胸部丰满，平日里朴实得像老祖母一般，主修宗教，信仰虔诚；而大一女生高大笨拙，每次和对象约会，总是刚刚开始就被对方用尽各种方法甩掉。两人开始过从甚密，形影不离，据说后来有人撞见她们在大四女生的房间里拥抱。

“可她们做了什么？”我曾追问。每当我想到男人和男人，女人和女人在一起，我都无法想象出他们或她们到底会做些什么。

“哦。”探子说，“米莉坐在椅子上，西奥朵拉躺在床上，米莉轻抚着西奥朵拉的头发。”

我好生失望，还以为会听到什么天理不容的行径。莫非女人和女人在一起做的，只是躺着抱抱而已？

当然，我们学校就有这种事情，一个著名女诗人跟另一个女人同居——她的女伴是研究古典文学的老学者，身材矮胖，留着齐耳短发。当我告诉女诗人，我很可能有一天会找人嫁了，生一堆孩子时，她大惊失色地看着我，喊道：“那你的事业怎么办？”

我的头好痛。为什么我总是吸引这些怪里怪气的老女人？那个著名诗人、费罗米娜·吉尼亚、杰·茜和那个信奉基督教科学派的女老板，天知道还有谁。她们都想以某种方式领养我，要我跟她们看齐，以回报她们对我的关心和熏陶。

“我喜欢你。”

“这可难办了，琼。”我说着拿起书，“因为我不喜欢你。你让我作呕，如果你想知道的话。”

我离开房间，听任琼躺在我的床上，像匹粗笨的老马。

我一边等医生，一边想着是否要临阵脱逃。我知道我要做的事是违法的——至少在马萨诸塞州是如此，因为这个州全是天主教徒——但诺兰医生说这个医生是她的老友，是个很明理的人。

“你预约看的是什么病？”穿着白制服的接待员问话干脆利落，同时在笔记本的名单中勾出我的名字。

“什么意思？”除了医生之外，我没想过别人会问我这个问题。公共候诊室里满满都是其他医生的病人，她们多半身怀有孕或带着宝宝，我感到她们的目光都落在我尚是处女的平坦小腹上。

接待员抬头看着我，我的脸红了。

“是装避孕器的吧？”她和气地说，“我只是确认一下，才知道该收多少钱。你是学生吗？”

“是——是的。”

“那就是半价。原价十美元，只收你五美元。要寄账单给你吗？”

我正打算说出家庭住址，因为账单寄到时我也应该回家了，但就在这时，我想到万一母亲拆开账单，就会知道这钱花在什么事情上。除了家里，我只有一个邮政信箱号码是安全的，住在疗养院的人不想被人知道自己的状况时，都用这个信箱。可我又担心接待员认得这个信箱号码，所以我说：“我现在就付吧。”说着，从皮包里的一卷纸钞中抽出一张五美元的钞票来。

这五美元是费罗米娜·吉尼亚送我的康复贺礼中的一部分。我真好奇，要是她知道自己的钱派作了这个用途，不晓得会做何感想。

不管她知道与否，费罗米娜·吉尼亚替我买来了自由。

“一想到要受男人的摆布，我就心生恨意。”我告诉诺兰医生，“男人完全不必担心这种事，而会怀孕的阴影就像根大棒悬在我头顶，提醒我不可越界。”

“如果不必担心怀孕，你的做法会不一样吗？”

“会。”我说，“但是……”我向诺兰医生说起那位已婚的女律师和她那篇大作《捍卫贞操》。

诺兰医生耐心等我讲完，然后哈哈大笑。“纯属说教！”然后她在处方笺上草草写下我今天求诊的这位医生的名字和地址。

我魂不守舍地翻阅一本叫《宝宝经》的杂志。每一页都有胖嘟嘟的宝宝对我露出灿烂的笑脸——光头的宝宝，巧克力色的宝宝，艾森豪威尔长相的宝宝，第一次翻身的宝宝，伸手抓拨浪鼓的宝宝，吃下第一勺固体食物的宝宝，做各种小动作的宝宝。这些是他们成长的必经之路，然后一步一步，他们将走进一个令人躁郁不安的世界。

宝宝乐牌婴儿食品、发酸的牛奶和臭咸鱼一样的尿布混合在一起的气味触动了我，令我心生一种悲哀和温柔。怀孕对我身边的这些女人是多么轻松的一件事啊！我为什么如此缺乏母性，如此与世疏离？为什么我不能像朵朵·康威一样，梦想身边有一个又一个胖嘟嘟又爱哭的孩子？如果我必须整天围着孩子团团转，我会发疯的。我看着对面那个女人腿上坐着的宝宝。我猜不出宝宝的年龄，向来如此——我只知道他们会叽里咕噜地说话，噘起的粉嫩小嘴后面藏着二十颗牙。这个宝宝的脑袋摇摇晃晃地架在肩膀上——好像没脖子一样——带着柏拉图式的、充满智慧的表情望着我。

宝宝的妈妈笑个不停，抱着孩子的模样好似捧着天下至宝。我看着妈妈和宝宝，想弄明白是什么让他们彼此这么满足，可是没等我寻到蛛丝马迹，就被医生叫了进去。

“你要装避孕器。”轻快的声音让我松了口气，还好他不是那种问起话来让人尴尬的医生。我曾突发奇想，跟医生说我要嫁给一个水兵，只等他的船停靠在查尔斯镇的军港就举行婚礼，而我之所以没戴订婚戒指，是因为我们太穷。但是在最后一秒，我将这个动人的故事抛于脑后，只回答他：“对。”

我边爬上检查台，边想：“我正爬向自由，不再恐惧的自由，不会只因为上过床而要错嫁给像巴迪·威拉德那种人的自由，不必沦落到那些穷苦女孩去的未婚妈妈之家的自由。那些姑娘真该像我一样装避孕器，因为她们之前做过的事，反正以后还会再做，无论……”

完事后，我坐车回疗养院，腿上放着一个用素面褐色纸张包装的盒子。我就像是任何一个在城里待了一整天的某太太，回家时顺手买了施拉夫家的一块蛋糕或飞琳地下商场的一顶帽子，准备送给家里嫁不出去的老姨妈。慢慢地，我已不再怀疑天主教徒有一双锐利如X光的眼睛，而我也越来越自如。我想，今天外出购物的特权可真是物尽其用。

我是个自主的女性了。

下一步就是找个合适的男人。

19

“我要当精神科医生。”

琼像平常一样气息急促、充满热情地说。我们正在贝尔赛思楼的休息厅里喝苹果汁。

“哦。”我冷淡地回应，“不错。”

“我和昆因医生聊了很久，她认为这很有可能。”昆因是琼的主治医生，一个精明干练的单身女人。我常想，如果当初我被分配到昆因医生的手里，我很可能还在卡普兰楼待着，甚至有可能沦落到威玛克楼去。昆因医生有一种令琼深为之着迷的独特气质，却让我感到一种极地般的寒冷。

琼喋喋不休地谈着“自我”“本我”一类的东西，而我的思绪早已飘远，想着最下层抽屉里那个被打开了的褐色包裹。我不曾与诺兰医生谈过“自我”“本我”。其实，我都不知道我谈过些什么。

“……我要搬出去了。”

我把思绪收回到琼身上。“搬到哪里去？”我掩饰着嫉妒问道。

诺兰医生说，有她的保证和费罗米娜·吉尼亚的奖学金支持，学校愿意让我下学期复学。不过，医生反对我在返校前回家与母亲同住，所以我要在疗养院待到寒假后的新学期开始。

即便如此，我还是愤愤不平于琼先我一步出院。

“搬到哪儿去？”我继续追问。“他们不会让你自己一个人住吧？”直到这个星期，琼才重新获准进城。

“哦，当然不让。我会跟肯尼迪护士住在剑桥镇。她的室友刚结婚，搬走了，她得找个人合租。”

“恭喜。”我举起手里的苹果汁，和她碰杯。虽然我在心底对她仍有所保留，但我会永远珍惜这个朋友。好像我们俩被战争或瘟疫这类不可抗拒的大环境所迫，共享过一个只属于我们俩的世界。“什么时候走？”

“下个月一号。”

“很好。”

琼眼含期盼，问道：“你会来看我的吧，埃斯特？”

“当然。”

但我心想：“不大可能。”

“好痛。”我说，“本来就这么痛吗？”

欧文没回答，过了一会儿才说：“有时候会痛。”

我是在哈佛大学的怀德纳图书馆长阶上认识的欧文，当时我站在长阶的顶端，看着下方红墙之内的积雪中庭，准备乘电车回疗养院。一个个子颇高，长得相当丑陋，戴着眼镜但看起来挺聪明的年轻人走上前来，问我：“请问现在几点？”

我看了一眼手表。“四点零五。”

这男人胸前抱着一摞书，像端了个餐盘，他动了动手臂，露出细瘦的手腕。

“哎，你自己有表啊！”

他无奈地看着他的表，抬起手腕在耳边晃动。“坏了。”他露出迷人的微笑。“你去哪儿？”

我正打算说“回疗养院”，但这男人看起来会是个好对象，于是我改变主意说：“回家。”

“想先来杯咖啡吗？”

我犹豫了。我应该赶回疗养院吃晚饭的，他们就要批准我永远离开那里，我可不想这个马上就能永远离开疗养院的时候因为迟归而横生枝节。

“只喝小小的一杯咖啡？”

在我犹豫不决之时，他告诉我他叫欧文，是个薪水优渥的数学教授，而我决定在这个男人面前表现出我全新、正常的一面，于是我说：“好吧。”然后迈开大步，跟他并肩走下结冰的长阶。

不过，我是在参观过欧文的书房后，才决定要勾引他。

欧文住的地下室位于剑桥外围一条破落的街道上，里面幽暗舒适。他先带我到学生餐馆喝了三杯苦咖啡，然后开车载我到他家。“喝杯啤酒吧。”他说。我们坐在他书房的褐色皮椅上，四周堆满蒙尘的艰深晦涩的书籍，巨大的公式雅致地穿插在书页之中，像诗一样。

我小口啜着第一杯啤酒——我向来不喜欢在隆冬喝冰啤，不过为了让双手有坚实的东西可握，我还是接过了玻璃杯——这时，门铃响起。

欧文一脸尴尬。“我想可能是位女士。”

欧文有个老派的怪习惯，称呼女人为女士。

“没关系，没关系。”我夸张地挥挥手，“请她进来啊。”

欧文摇摇头。“她看到你会不高兴。”

我微笑地看着手中装着冰啤的琥珀色玻璃杯。

门铃又被用力地按响。欧文叹了口气，起身应门。他一走开，我立刻闪进浴室，躲在脏兮兮的银铝色软式百叶窗后面，从门缝中偷窥欧文那张如修士般的脸。

一个身材高大、胸部丰满的斯拉夫裔女子出现在门外。她穿着天然羊毛织的笨重毛衣，宽松的紫色长裤，脚上是波斯羊毛褶边的黑色高跟罩靴，头上戴着与鞋同款的小圆帽。我听不清她说了些什么，只看见吐露的字眼在冷冽的空气中凝成一团团白雾。欧文的声音沿着寒冷的走廊飘向我的耳朵。

“对不起，奥尔嘉……我在工作，奥尔嘉……不，我没这么想，奥尔嘉。”这位女士的红唇动个不停，一字一句都化作白雾，缭绕于门边那棵紫丁香光秃的枝丫间。最后，终于听见：“再说吧，奥尔嘉……再见，奥尔嘉。”

这位女士被羊毛覆盖的胸部宽广无垠，如草原一般，我自叹弗如。我眼看着她从我眼前渐渐后退，走下嘎吱作响的木头台阶，曾经鲜活的双唇似乎蒙上了西伯利亚的苦寒。

“我猜，你在剑桥有过很多很多的艳遇。”在剑桥附近一家坚守法式风格的餐厅里，我一边愉快地同欧文说着话，一边用一根针挑出蜗牛肉。

“我啊——”欧文谦虚地浅笑道，“似乎真的很有女士缘。”

我拿起空的蜗牛壳，嘬尽里面草绿色的肉汁。我不知道这样做是否显得失礼，但在疗养院吃了几个月索然无味的健康饮食，我太想念黄油的滋味了。

我在餐厅用公用电话打给诺兰医生，请她准许我在剑桥和琼住一晚。当然，我不确定晚餐后欧文会不会带我回他的公寓，不过我想他既然打发了那位斯拉夫女士——另一位教授的太太——看起来我很有希望。

我仰头饮尽一杯夜圣乔治葡萄酒。

“你确实很喜欢红酒。”欧文观察入微。

“只爱夜圣乔治。我想象着他……屠龙……”

欧文握住了我的手。

我曾想过，我的第一个男人一定得聪明，这样才能赢得我的敬重。欧文二十六岁就当上正教授，还有天才儿童般白皙无汗毛的皮肤，正合我意。况且，我也需要一个经验丰富的老手来弥补我的青涩懵懂，欧文的女士缘确保他在这方面是我的上上之选。另外，为安全起见，我要找的是以前不认识、以后也不会有瓜葛的对象——就像部落传说中那种了无私情的神职人员，帮助女孩完成初夜的仪式。

夜幕低垂之时，我已确定欧文是不二人选。

自从看清了巴迪·威拉德堕落的一面，贞操就成了我脖子上重如磐石的枷锁。这么久以来，我视守贞为头等大事，不计代价的捍卫甚至已经变成了一种习惯。五年了，我厌倦了。

回到公寓，欧文把我搂入怀中，将醉醺醺、软绵绵的我带入漆黑的卧室，这时我才对他喃喃低语：“欧文，我想我该告诉你，我还是处女。”

欧文笑着将我推倒在床上。

几分钟后，欧文一声惊呼。可见他之前并未拿我的话当真。我庆幸自己已经装了避孕器，否则晚上带着醉意，我一定无心采取那些细致的必要措施。我赤裸地躺在欧文的粗毛毯上，心驰神往地等候着奇妙新境界的降临。

可我感觉到的，只有慑人的剧痛。

“好痛。”我说，“本来就这么痛吗？”

欧文没回答，过了一会儿才说：“有时候会痛。”

没多久，欧文起身走进浴室，我听见哗哗的沐浴声。我不确定欧文是否按计划做了他想做的事，还是我的处女身份令他多少受了些妨碍。我很想问问他，我还是不是处女，但整个人晕乎乎的。突然两腿间涌出一股热流，我试探地伸手去摸。

收回手，借着浴室透出的光线，我的手指尖似乎是黑色的。

“欧文。”我紧张起来，“给我条毛巾。”

欧文腰间系着浴巾，闲适地走过来，扔给我一条小毛巾。我把毛巾塞在两腿之间，接着立刻就又抽了出来。毛巾被血染红了大半。

“我在流血！”我倏然起身，大声说道。

“哦，这是常有的事。”欧文向我保证，“一会儿就好。”

那一刻，各种故事浮现在我的脑海：新娘落红的床单，已非完璧的新娘私藏红墨水胶囊假造初夜。我一边想着到底会流多少血，一边躺回床上轻抚着毛巾，突然意识到这血就是我要的答案，我不可能再是处女了。黑暗中，我扬起嘴角，感到自己终于成为伟大传统的一分子。

我用白毛巾的干净部分偷偷擦拭我的创口，心想：等血止住了就搭夜班电车回疗养院，我要在全然平静之中思考人生的新境界。可是抽出毛巾一看，还是滴着黑色的血。

“我……我还是回家吧。”我虚弱地说。

“不用这么急。”

“不，我最好还是回家。”

我跟欧文借了那条毛巾，垫在两腿间当吸血的绷带，然后穿上汗湿的衣服。欧文要载我回家，但我怎么可能让他送我回疗养院呢，所以我从手提包里翻出琼的地址。欧文知道那条街，出去发动了车子。我心里很是慌张，没法告诉他我还在流血，只能默默祈祷血快点止住。

可是当欧文载着我穿过积雪的荒凉街巷，我感觉到两腿间的暖流透过层层叠叠的毛巾和裙子，渗到了车座上。

车速慢了下来，驶过一间间亮着灯的房子。我心想，还好不是在学校或家里时失去贞操，否则这狼狈的模样无论如何也无法掩饰。

琼打开门，一脸惊喜。欧文吻了我的手，交代琼要好好照顾我。

我靠在关好的门上，觉得自己脸部的血液也随着大出血流干了。

“怎么了，埃斯特？”琼问，“到底发生了什么事？”

不知琼何时才会注意到血正沿着我的大腿往下流，黏糊糊地渗进两只黑色漆皮鞋里。我想就算我中弹，奄奄一息，琼也只会茫然地看着我，等我开口要杯咖啡和三明治。

“护士在吗？”

“不在，她去卡普兰楼值夜班了……”

“好极了。”我苦笑一声，又一股血流冲过湿透的毛巾，开始直奔我鞋子而去的乏味旅程。“我是说……不妙。”

“你的样子好奇怪。”琼说。

“你最好去找医生来。”

“为什么？”

“快去。”

“但是……”

她还是什么都没发现。

我弯下腰，发出一声短促的呻吟，脱下一只购自布鲁明戴尔百货商店，已经因严冬而皲裂的黑皮鞋。我把这只鞋子举到琼那双睁大的灰石色眼睛前，将鞋子倾斜，看着她注视着一道血瀑从鞋里流到米色的地毯上。

“天哪！这是什么？”

“我大出血。”

琼把我半拖半拽到沙发上躺下，在我沾满血的双脚下垫了几个枕头，接着往后一退，质问道：“那个男人是谁？”

有那么一刻，我有个疯狂的念头，觉得要是我没全盘招认整晚和欧文干的好事，琼就不会帮我找医生，而且即便我坦白之后，她还是不会去请医生，这算是她对我的某种惩罚。但我随即意识到，她会真的认为我的解释就是表面的意思而已，所以她完全无法理解我和欧文上床这件事背后的意义。她很高兴我的到访，而欧文的出现不过让她有点扫兴罢了。

“只是某个人而已。”我边回答，边打出个无力再说的手势。又一股鲜血涌出，我惊恐地收缩腹部肌肉，“拿毛巾来。”

琼跑出去，转眼就拿了一叠毛巾和床单回来。她像个手脚麻利的护士，脱掉我被鲜血浸透的衣服，当她看见原来那条血红的毛巾时，飞快地吸了一口气，连忙为我换上干净的绷带。我躺在那里，努力让心跳慢下来，因为每一次的心跳都会推动又一波的血涌。

我想起在学校修过一门探讨维多利亚时期小说的恼人课程。那个时期的小说经常描写女人难产后，一个个苍白而高贵地死在血泊之中。或许欧文以某种可怕而隐晦的方式伤害了我，现在我躺在琼的沙发上，真的快要死了。

琼拉过一个印度风格的跪垫，就着一长串剑桥医生的名单开始拨电话。第一个号码没人接。第二个有人接，琼开始解释我的状况，但说到一半就打住，说声“明白了”后挂断电话。

“怎么了？”

“今天是星期天，他只看常客和急诊。”

我想抬手看看表，但放在身侧的手僵得像石头一样，根本动不了。星期天——医生的天堂！医生们会去乡村俱乐部，医生们会到海滩，医生们会约情人，医生们会陪老婆，医生们会上教堂，医生们会开游艇，每个医生都铁了心要当凡人，不当医生。

“看在上帝的分上。”我说，“就跟他们说我的状况很紧急。”

第三个号码没人接。第四个，一听琼说是月经问题就挂了电话。琼哭了起来。

“听着，琼。”我费力地说，“打给这里的医院，告诉他们是急诊，必须来接我。”

琼眼睛一亮，开始拨第五个电话。急诊室答应，如果我能设法自行前往医院，会有医生来处理我的状况。于是琼叫了辆出租车。

琼坚持要陪我去。我绝望般地按紧新换上的毛巾，琼告知的目的地让司机加足了马力，在破晓的街道上猛抄捷径，终于轮胎发出尖锐的刹车声，车子停在急诊处的门口。

我留下琼付车费，自己冲进空空荡荡却灯火通明的急诊室。护士从白色屏风后跑出来，我赶紧三言两语交代了来龙去脉。接着琼进来了，眨着大眼睛，活像只近视的猫头鹰。

急诊处的医生不紧不慢地走出来，护士扶着我爬上检查台，再对医生耳语了几句，医生点点头，解开我身上血淋淋的毛巾，我感觉到他的手指探入我体内。琼就像个军人一样直挺挺地站在我身旁，握着我的手，也不知道是为了给我打气，还是让她自己好受些。

“啊哦！”医生一个猛戳，我痛得身子一缩。

医生吹了声口哨。

“你是百万分之一。”

“什么意思？”

“我说，一百万人中只有一个人会发生你这种情况。”

医生低声和护士交代了几句，护士匆忙跑到边上的小桌旁，拿了几卷纱布和银亮的工具回来。“我看见了，”医生弯腰说道，“出血处就在那里。”

“能缝上吗？”

医生笑起来，“哦，能缝上，没问题。”

我被敲门声惊醒。已过午夜，疗养院一片死寂。我想不出这时还有谁没睡。

“进来。”我打开床头灯。门咔嗒一声开了，昆因医生长着利落黑发的头从门缝中探进来。我惊讶地看着她。虽然我知道她是谁，也常与她在长廊里擦身而过点头示意，但从不曾与她交谈过。

此时她说：“格林伍德小姐，我可以进来吗？”

我点点头。

昆因医生走进房间，静静地关上门。她穿着整洁的海军蓝套装——这种衣服她有好几件——V形领口下露出素净的白色衬衫。

“很抱歉打扰你，格林伍德小姐，尤其是现在这么晚了，但事关琼，我想或许你可以帮忙。”

一时之间，我以为昆因医生深夜来访是怪我害得琼重回疗养院。我不确定那晚去过急诊处后，琼到底知道了多少，不过几天之后她就住回贝尔赛思楼，但仍保有进城的自由。

“我会尽我所能。”我对昆因医生说。

昆因医生坐在我的床沿上，面色凝重。“我们想知道琼上哪儿去了。或许你知道。”

我突然想跟琼划清界限。“我不知道。”我冷冷地说，“她不在房间里吗？”

贝尔赛思楼的宵禁时间早就过了。

“不在。她今晚获准进城看电影，到现在还没回来。”

“她和谁一起去的？”

“她一个人。”昆因医生顿了顿，“你想得到她可能会在哪里过夜吗？”

“她肯定会回来的。一定是有事耽搁了。”但我实在想不出波士顿平常无奇的夜生活，能有什么事让她流连忘返。

昆因医生摇摇头。“末班电车一小时前就开走了。”

“也许她会坐出租车回来。”

昆因医生叹了口气。

“你们和那个肯尼迪护士联系过了吗？”我不死心，“之前琼和她住过。”

昆因医生点了点头。

“她的家人呢？”

“哦，她从不回家……但我们还是问过了。”

昆因医生在我房间逗留了一会儿，好像可以从这静谧的房间里嗅出点线索来。接着她说：“好吧，我们再尽力找找看。”然后就离开了。

我关上灯，倒回床上试图重新入睡，但眼前飘浮着琼的脸，没有身体，笑得像《爱丽丝梦游仙境》里的那只柴郡猫。我甚至感觉听见了她的声音，在黑暗中沙沙作响，但随即发现只是夜风吹过树梢……

雾蒙蒙的破晓时分，又一阵敲门声惊醒了我。

这一次我亲自开的门。

在我面前的是昆因医生。她立正的站姿像个疲弱的训练教官，而她的轮廓竟怪异地模糊不清。

“我想应该通知你一声。”昆因医生说，“琼被我们找到了。”

昆因医生的一个“被”字，让我的血液流速都减慢了。

“哪儿？”

“树林里，封冻的湖边。”

我张开嘴，却说不出话来。

“一名护理员发现的……”昆因医生继续道，“就在刚才，上班途中……”

“她没……”

“死了。”昆因医生说，“应该是上吊自杀。”

20

初雪在疗养院的地上覆了厚厚的一层——不是年底圣诞的那种絮絮薄雪，而是深可及人的一月大雪，足以让学校、办公室和教堂关闭，让备忘录、日程表和日历留下至少一日的空白。

如果我能顺利通过评估委员会的面谈，一周后，费罗米娜·吉尼亚的黑色大轿车就会载着我西行，送我回到学校的锻铁大门前。

隆冬时分！

马萨诸塞州会沉浸在一片大理石般的冷寂之中。我想起摩西奶奶笔下的村庄雪花纷扬，干枯的香蒲在绵延的沼泽地里沙沙作响，池塘里的青蛙和鲇鱼在冰层下做梦，树木簌簌轻摆。

然而，在表面白净平整的页岩之下，地形依旧。我要学着面对的不是旧金山、欧洲或火星，而是旧日的风景、小溪、山峦与草木。说起来也没什么大不了，不过是时隔半年，我从当初愤而出离的地方重新开始。

当然，我的事已经尽人皆知。

诺兰医生说得很直接，许多人会小心翼翼地对待我，甚至躲着我，当我是戴着警示铃铛的麻风病人。母亲的脸浮现在我的眼前，如同一轮充满自责的苍白满月，那是在我二十岁生日过后，母亲第一次也是最后一次来疗养院看我。女儿进了精神病院！是我令她承担这一切。可是，她显然已经决定原谅我。

“我们在哪里跌倒，就从哪里站起来吧，埃斯特。”她带着殉道者般慈爱的微笑说，“就当之前的一切是场噩梦吧。”

噩梦一场。

活在钟形罩里的人有如困在标本罐里茫然、停止生长的死婴，这世界本就是噩梦一场。

噩梦一场。

我记得梦里的每一件事。

我记得那些尸体，朵琳，无花果树的故事，马可的钻石，公园里的水兵，戈登大夫诊所里的斜眼护士，摔碎的体温计，黑人厨工和两种豆子配餐的那顿饭，注射胰岛素后我暴增的二十磅，还有海天交界处那块灰色头颅般的礁岩。

或许忘却就像一场雪，善意地麻痹和掩盖了一切。

但它们都是我的一部分，都是我人生的风景。

“有位先生来看你。”

帽子上沾了雪花的护士含笑探进头来。恍然之间我以为自己真的回到学校了，只是原本伤痕累累的桌椅和光秃秃的内院变成了白色松木家具和银装素裹的树林山丘。“一个男的找你！”值班女生打宿舍的内线电话告诉我。

贝尔赛思楼里的我们，究竟跟我即将返回的大学里那些打牌、聊八卦、读书的女孩有何不同？那些女孩不也是坐在某种钟形罩里么？

“进来。”我喊道。巴迪·威拉德走进房间，手里拿着顶卡其色的帽子。

“嗨，巴迪。”我说。

“嗨，埃斯特。”

我们就这么站着，彼此对望。我等待着我们俩之间情感的悸动，那最弱的一丝微光。没有，什么也没有，只有一团和气的强烈乏味感。穿着卡其色外套的巴迪看起来很小，而且似乎与我毫无关系，就像一年前的那天，他站在滑雪道的尽头，倚着那些褐色的柱子时一样。

“你怎么来的？”我终于开口问他。

“开我妈的车。”

“冒这么大的雪？”

“嗯。”巴迪笑道，“车陷在外面的雪堆里了。这条山路我真开不过来。有地方借铁锹吗？”

“可以跟管理员借一把。”

“好。”巴迪转身要走。

“等等，我也去帮忙。”

巴迪看着我，眼中闪过一抹怪异的神情，夹杂着好奇和谨慎。之前来探视我的那些人，例如信奉基督教科学派的前老板、英文老师和一神教的牧师，他们也都曾流露出这样的眼神。

“哎，巴迪。”我笑着说，“我没事的啦。”

“哦，我知道，我知道，埃斯特。”巴迪连忙说。

“倒是你别太费力铲雪挖车，巴迪。我没关系。”

结果巴迪让我干了大部分铲雪的活。

车子是在通往疗养院的光滑山路上打滑的，一个轮子冲出车道边缘，整辆车陷入了高高的雪堆中。

太阳从灰蒙蒙的云层后探出头，像夏日艳阳般照耀着无人踏足的山坡。我停下手里的活，眺望这片纯净原始的坡地，悸动油然而生，就像看到齐腰深的洪水淹没草木——仿佛这世界的寻常秩序有了轻微的改变，进入一个新的阶段。

幸好车子陷进了雪堆，这让巴迪没办法问出我知道他要问的问题。不过，在贝尔赛思楼喝下午茶的时候，他还是压低嗓子，紧张地问了。蒂蒂像只嫉妒的猫，从杯沿上偷瞄着我们。自从琼死后，蒂蒂被迁往威玛克楼住了一阵子，但现在又回来了。

“我一直在想……”巴迪笨拙地把杯子放回茶托上，发出脆响。

“你一直在想什么？”

“我一直在想……我的意思是，我想你或许可以告诉我一些事情。”巴迪迎着我的目光，我第一次发现他变了不少，原本像摄影师的闪光灯一样轻松且频繁浮现的笃定笑容已不复见，取而代之的是凝重，甚至踌躇的脸色——男人若是常常得不到想要的东西，就会有这种表情。

“如果可以，我会告诉你的，巴迪。”

“你觉得我身上是不是有什么东西，会把女人逼疯？”

我忍不住大笑起来——也许是因为巴迪的表情过于严肃，以及“逼疯”在这样的句子里所代表的含义。

“我的意思是，”巴迪继续解释，“我先跟琼交往，然后是你，后来你先……走了，接着琼也……”

我伸出一根手指，把桌上的面包屑推入一滴褐色的茶水里。

“当然不是你造成的。”我听见诺兰医生这么说。我去找她谈琼的事，结果她的话里带着怒气，这是我唯一一次见她这样。“没人让她这样。这是她的决定。”接着诺兰医生告诉我，即使是最厉害的精神科医生，病人里也有自杀的。如果真要追究责任，他们或许难辞其咎，但他们恰恰都认为自己无须负责……

“我们的事跟你无关，巴迪。”

“你确定？”

“确定。”

“好。”巴迪松了口气，“那我就放心了。”

他把茶一饮而尽，好像喝下的是补药。

“听说你要走了？”

在这个有护士陪同的小小散步行列中，我调整步伐与瓦莱丽并肩而行。“医生同意了才算数，他们明天和我面谈。”

被踩实的雪在脚下嘎吱作响，正午的太阳融化了冰柱和雪地，流水滴答的美妙声音随处可闻，而夜幕降临之前融雪又会变成一层光滑的冰面。

大片黑松林的树荫在灿烂的阳光下变成淡紫色，我和瓦莱丽走在熟悉的迷宫般的疗养院小径上。路面的雪已铲到两侧，堆在路边，毗邻小径上经过的医生护士都被遮住了下半身，看起来像脚上装了轮子似的移动。

“面谈！”瓦莱丽嗤之以鼻，“根本就是做做样子。如果他们真打算让你出去，你就能出去。”

“但愿如此。”

我和瓦莱丽在卡普兰楼前道别，她一脸淡定，就像雪姑娘，好事坏事仿佛都与她无关。我独自前行，尽管阳光明媚，呼出的气息仍化作缕缕白烟。瓦莱丽最后开心地冲我说了句“再见！会再相见的！”

“我觉得不会了吧。”我心想。

但是我不确定，根本不确定。我怎么知道，将来某天——在学校，在欧洲，在某个地方，在任何地方——那个让人窒息、扭曲一切的钟形罩会不会又凌空而下？

巴迪不也说了：“埃斯特，我都不知道你现在能和谁结婚。”他说这话，好像是为了报复我径自将他的车子从雪堆里挖出来，而把他晾在一旁干瞪眼。

“什么？”我边问，边把雪铲到一旁的小丘上，飞散的雪花很刺眼，我不得不眯缝起眼睛。

“我说，我不知道你现在能和谁结婚。你已经来到了——”巴迪双手一拢，环扫了山峦、松树和一栋栋尖顶覆盖着白雪、阻隔了绵延风景的朴实屋舍，“这地方。”

当然，我不知道走到了这一步，还能跟谁结婚。我真的不知道。

“欧文，我这里有张账单。”

我在疗养院行政大楼的大厅，对着付费电话的话筒，平静地说出这句话。一开始，我担心坐在总机台前的接线员会偷听，后来发现她忙着插拔那些小管线，连眼睛都没有眨一下。

“好。”欧文说。

“账单一共二十美元，包括十二月那天的急诊费和一周后的复检。”

“好。”欧文说。

“医院说他们把账单寄给我，是因为之前寄给你，你没有回应。”

“好的，好的，我现在就开支票。我给他们开一张空白的支票，金额随他们填。”接着，他的声音有了微妙的变化。“我什么时候可以再见到你？”

“你真想知道？”

“很想。”

“永远别想了。”我说完，决绝地挂断了电话。

有那么一刻，我担心欧文因此不寄支票给医院，但随后一想：“他一定会寄出支票的，他是数学教授——不会给人留下话柄。”

我没来由地觉得膝盖一软，同时也如释重负。

欧文的声音对我本就毫无意义。

自从跟他初次也是最后一次见面，这是我第一次和他说话。我十分确信，这将是我们的最后一次交谈。欧文绝无可能找到我，除非去肯尼迪护士的公寓。但自从琼死后，肯尼迪护士就搬走了，没有留下任何去向的线索。

我完全自由了。

琼的父母邀请我参加她的葬礼。

吉林夫人说，我是琼最好的朋友之一。

“你不一定要去，知道吧。”诺兰医生告诉我，“你可以随时写信给他们，说我建议你别去。”

“我要去。”我说，而且我真的去了。在简单的葬礼仪式过程中，我一直在想，我知道自己在埋葬什么吗？

祭坛上，灵柩掩映于白花之间——那是某个不在现场的东西的黑影。四周教堂长椅上的人，脸被烛光映得蜡黄。圣诞节残留的松枝在冷冽的空气中散发着阴郁的香气。

乔蒂在我身边，脸颊红润如苹果。在这一小群送葬的人中，我不时看到一些校友和同乡的脸。蒂蒂和肯尼迪护士包着头巾，坐在前排长椅上，低垂着头。

接着，在灵柩、鲜花、牧师的脸和吊唁者的脸的后方，我看见原本绵延起伏的墓园草坪如今雪深及膝，突出于雪面的墓碑宛如无烟的烟囱。

坚硬的土地上会掘出一个六英尺深的黑洞，那个黑影将跟这个黑洞结合，然后用当地特殊的黄土填补雪白大地的伤口，只要再来一场大雪，就将抹去琼坟茔上的新痕。

我深吸一口气，聆听内心昔日的豪言壮语。

我存在，我存在，我存在。

医生们正在开每周例会——旧事、新事、入院、出院、面谈。我在疗养院的图书馆里，心不在焉地翻着一本破烂的《国家地理》杂志，等着他们叫我进去。

一群病人由护士陪同，在摆满书籍的书架间来回走动，与图书管理员低声交谈，这位管理员本身也是疗养院的“女院友”。我看向她——近视眼，老处女，毫不起眼——我暗想，她怎么知道自己已经“毕业”，而且完全康复，跟她所服务的客人不一样？

“别怕。”诺兰医生告诉过我，“我会在场，其他医生你都认得，还有几位来宾。主任医生维宁大夫会问你一些问题，问完之后你就可以离开了。”

尽管诺兰医生一再保证，我还是怕得要死。

我曾经期盼，在我离开的时候，满怀信心，知晓未来要面对的一切——毕竟，我已经被“分析”过了。可是现在，我看见的只有一连串的问号。

我一次次将焦灼的目光投向会议室紧闭的大门。我的丝袜接缝笔直，黑皮鞋虽有裂痕，但擦得很亮，红色的羊毛套装就像我的计划一样光彩夺目。我这一身行头，有新有旧……

但我并非要结婚(1)。我只是想，应该有种仪式庆贺喜获重生——修补，翻新，获准重新上路。我正在想着什么样的仪式才恰当，诺兰医生忽然冒出来，拍拍我的肩。

“来吧，埃斯特。”

我起身跟她走向敞开的会议室大门。

跨过门槛时，我停下脚步，迅速调整了一下气息。我看见入院第一天跟我讲述河流和清教徒移民的银发医生，还有满脸痘疤、面色惨白的休伊小姐，还有几双我能认出的戴着口罩的人的眼睛。

那些眼睛和面孔全都转向我，我被他们引导着，仿佛是被一根神奇的绳子引导着，我走进那个房间。

(1) 西方婚礼中，按照习俗，新娘需要准备四样东西：新的，旧的，借来的，蓝色的。

One

It was a queer, sultry summer, the summer they electrocuted the Rosenbergs, and I didn't know what I was doing in New York. I'm stupid about executions. The idea of being electrocuted makes me sick, and that's all there was to read about in the papers—goggle-eyed headlines staring up at me on every street corner and at the fusty, peanut-smelling mouth of every subway. It had nothing to do with me, but I couldn't help wondering what it would be like, being burned alive all along your nerves.

I thought it must be the worst thing in the world.

New York was bad enough. By nine in the morning the fake, country-wet freshness that somehow seeped in overnight evaporated like the tail end of a sweet dream. Mirage-gray at the bottom of their granite canyons, the hot streets wavered in the sun, the car tops sizzled and glittered, and the dry, cindery dust blew into my eyes and down my throat.

I kept hearing about the Rosenbergs over the radio and at the office till I couldn't get them out of my mind. It was like the first time I saw a cadaver. For weeks afterward, the cadaver's head-or what there was left of it-floated up behind my eggs and bacon at breakfast and behind the face of Buddy Willard, who was responsible for my seeing it in the first place, and pretty soon I felt as though I were carrying that cadaver's head around with me on a string, like some black, noseless balloon stinking of vinegar.

I knew something was wrong with me that summer, because all I could think about was the Rosenbergs and how stupid I'd been to buy all those uncomfortable, expensive clothes, hanging limp as fish in my closet, and how all the little successes I'd totted up so happily at college fizzled to nothing outside the slick marble and plate-glass fronts along Madison Avenue.

I was supposed to be having the time of my life.

I was supposed to be the envy of thousands of other college girls just like me all over America who wanted nothing more than to be tripping about in those same size-seven patent leather shoes I'd bought in Bloomingdale's one lunch hour with a black patent leather belt and black patent leather pocketbook to match. And when my picture came out in the magazine the twelve of us were working on-drinking martinis in a skimpy, imitation silver-lamé bodice stuck on to a big, fat cloud of white tulle, on some Starlight Roof, in the company of several anonymous young men with all-American bone structures hired or loaned for the occasion-everybody would think I must be having a real whirl.

Look what can happen in this country, they'd say. A girl lives in some out-of-the-way town for nineteen years, so poor she can't afford a magazine, and then she gets a scholarship to college and wins a prize here and a prize there and ends up steering New York like her own private car.

Only I wasn't steering anything, not even myself. I just bumped from my hotel to work and to parties and from parties to my hotel and back to work like a numb trolleybus. I guess I should have been excited the way most of the other girls were, but I couldn't get myself to react. I felt very still and very empty, the way the eye of a tornado must feel, moving dully along in the middle of the surrounding hullabaloo.

There were twelve of us at the hotel.

We had all won a fashion magazine contest, by writing essays and stories and poems and fashion blurbs, and as prizes they gave us jobs in New York for a month, expenses paid, and piles and piles of free bonuses, like ballet tickets and passes to fashion shows and hair stylings at a famous expensive salon and chances to meet successful people in the field of our desire and advice about what to do with our particular complexions.

I still have the make-up kit they gave me, fitted out for a person with brown eyes and brown hair: an oblong of brown mascara with a tiny brush, and a round basin of blue eye shadow just big enough to dab the tip of your finger in, and three lipsticks ranging from red to pink, all cased in the same little gilt box with a mirror on one side. I also have a white plastic sunglasses case with colored shells and sequins and a green plastic starfish sewed onto it.

I realized we kept piling up these presents because it was as good as free advertising for the firms involved, but I couldn't be cynical. I got such a kick out of all those free gifts showering on to us. For a long time afterward I hid them away, but later, when I was all right again, I brought them out, and I still have them around the house. I use the lipsticks now and then, and last week I cut the plastic starfish off the sunglasses case for the baby to play with.

So there were twelve of us at the hotel, in the same wing on the same floor in single rooms, one after the other, and it reminded me of my dormitory at college. It wasn't a proper hotel-I mean a hotel where there are both men and women mixed about here and there on the same floor.

This hotel—the Amazon—was for women only, and they were mostly girls my age with wealthy parents who wanted to be sure their daughters would be living where men couldn't get at them and deceive them; and they were all going to posh secretarial schools like Katy Gibbs, where they had to wear hats and stockings and gloves to class, or they had just graduated from places like Katy Gibbs and were secretaries to executives and junior executives and simply hanging around in New York waiting to get married to some career man or other.

These girls looked awfully bored to me. I saw them on the sunroof, yawning and painting their nails and trying to keep up their Bermuda tans, and they seemed bored as hell. I talked with one of them, and she was bored with yachts and bored with flying around in airplanes and bored with skiing in Switzerland at Christmas and bored with the men in Brazil.

Girls like that make me sick. I'm so jealous I can't speak. Nineteen years, and I hadn't been out of New England except for this trip to New York. It was my first big chance, but here I was, sitting back and letting it run through my fingers like so much water.

I guess one of my troubles was Doreen.

I'd never known a girl like Doreen before. Doreen came from a society girls' college down South and had bright white hair standing out in a cotton candy fluff round her head and blue eyes like transparent agate marbles, hard and polished and just about indestructible, and a mouth set in a sort of perpetual sneer. I don't mean a nasty sneer, but an amused, mysterious sneer, as if all the people around her were pretty silly and she could tell some good jokes on them if she wanted to.

Doreen singled me out right away. She made me feel I was that much sharper than the others, and she really was wonderfully funny. She used to sit next to me at the conference table, and when the visiting celebrities were talking she'd whisper witty sarcastic remarks to me under her breath.

Her college was so fashion conscious, she said, that all the girls had pocketbook covers made out of the same material as their dresses, so each time they changed their clothes they had a matching pocketbook. This kind of detail impressed me. It suggested a whole life of marvelous, elaborate decadence that attracted me like a magnet.

The only thing Doreen ever bawled me out about was bothering to get my assignments in by a deadline.

“What are you sweating over that for?” Doreen lounged on my bed in a peach silk dressing gown, filing her long, nicotine-yellow nails with an emery board, while I typed up the draft of an interview with a best-selling novelist.

That was another thing—the rest of us had starched cotton summer nighties and quilted housecoats, or maybe terry-cloth robes that doubled as beach coats, but Doreen wore these full-length nylon and lace jobs you could half see through, and dressing gowns the color of skin, that stuck to her by some kind of electricity. She had an interesting, slightly sweaty smell that reminded me of those scallopy leaves of sweet fern you break off and crush between your fingers for the musk of them.

“You know old Jay Cee won't give a damn if that story's in tomorrow or Monday.” Doreen lit a cigarette and let the smoke flare slowly from her nostrils so her eyes were veiled. “Jay Cee's ugly as sin,” Doreen went on coolly. “I bet that old husband of hers turns out all the lights before he gets near her or he'd puke otherwise.”

Jay Cee was my boss, and I liked her a lot, in spite of what Doreen said. She wasn't one of the fashion magazine gushers with fake eyelashes and giddy jewelry. Jay Cee had brains, so her plug-ugly looks didn't seem to matter. She read a couple of languages and knew all the quality writers in the business.

I tried to imagine Jay Cee out of her strict office suit and luncheon-duty hat and in bed with her fat husband, but I just couldn't do it. I always had a terribly hard time trying to imagine people in bed together.

Jay Cee wanted to teach me something, all the old ladies I ever knew wanted to teach me something, but I suddenly didn't think they had anything to teach me. I fitted the lid on my typewriter and clicked it shut.

Doreen grinned. “Smart girl.”

Somebody tapped at the door.

“Who is it?” I didn't bother to get up.

“It's me, Betsy. Are you coming to the party?”

“I guess so.” I still didn't go to the door.

They imported Betsy straight from Kansas with her bouncing blonde ponytail and Sweetheart-of-Sigma-Chi smile. I remember once the two of us were called over to the office of some blue-chinned TV producer in a pinstripe suit to see if we had any angles he could build up for a program, and Betsy started to tell about the male and female corn in Kansas. She got so excited about that damn corn even the producer had tears in his eyes, only he couldn't use any of it, unfortunately, he said.

Later on, the Beauty Editor persuaded Betsy to cut her hair and made a cover girl out of her, and I still see her fare now and then, smiling out of those “P.Q.'s wife wears B.H. Wragge” ads.

Betsy was always asking me to do things with her and the other girls as if she were trying to save me in some way. She never asked Doreen. In private, Doreen called her Pollyanna Cowgirl.

“Do you want to come in our cab?” Betsy said through the door.

Doreen shook her head.

“That's all right, Betsy,” I said. “I'm going with Doreen.”

“Okay.” I could hear Betsy padding off down the hall.

“We'll just go till we get sick of it,” Doreen told me, stubbing out her cigarette in the base of my bedside reading lamp, “then we'll go out on the town. Those parties they stage here remind me of the old dances in the school gym. Why do they always round up Yalies? They're so stoo pit!”

Buddy Willard went to Yale, but now I thought of it, what was wrong with him was that he was stupid. Oh, he'd managed to get good marks all right, and to have an affair with some awful waitress on the Cape by the name of Gladys, but he didn't have one speck of intuition. Doreen had intuition. Everything she said was like a secret voice speaking straight out of my own bones.

We were stuck in the theater-hour rush. Our cab sat wedged in back of Betsy's cab and in front of a cab with four of the other girls, and nothing moved.

Doreen looked terrific. She was wearing a strapless white lace dress zipped up over a snug corset affair that curved her in at the middle and bulged her out again spectacularly above and below, and her skin had a bronzy polish under the pale dusting powder. She smelled strong as a whole perfume store.

I wore a black shantung sheath that cost me forty dollars. It was part of a buying spree I had with some of my scholarship money when I heard I was one of the lucky ones going to New York. This dress was cut so queerly I couldn't wear any sort of a bra under it, but that didn't matter much as I was skinny as a boy and barely rippled, and I liked feeling almost naked on the hot summer nights.

The city had faded my tan, though. I looked yellow as a Chinaman. Ordinarily, I would have been nervous about my dress and my odd color, but being with Doreen made me forget my worries. I felt wise and cynical as all hell.

When the man in the blue lumber shirt and black chinos and tooled leather cowboy boots started to stroll over to us from under the striped awning of the bar where he'd been eyeing our cab, I couldn't have any illusions. I knew perfectly well he'd come for Doreen. He threaded his way out between the stopped cars and leaned engagingly on the sill of our open window.

“And what, may I ask, are two nice girls like you doing all alone in a cab on a nice night like this?”

He had a big, wide, white toothpaste-ad smile.

“We're on our way to a party,” I blurted, since Doreen had gone suddenly dumb as a post and was fiddling in a blasé way with her white lace pocketbook cover.

“That sounds boring,” the man said. “Whyn't you both join me for a couple of drinks in that bar over there? I've some friends waiting as well.”

He nodded in the direction of several informally dressed men slouching around under the awning. They had been following him with their eyes, and when he glanced back at them, they burst out laughing.

The laughter should have warned me. It was a kind of low, know-it-all snicker, but the traffic showed signs of moving again, and I knew that if I sat tight, in two seconds I'd be wishing I'd taken this gift of a chance to see something of New York besides what the people on the magazine had planned out for us so carefully.

“How about it, Doreen?” I said.

“How about it, Doreen?” the man said, smiling his big smile. To this day I can't remember what he looked like when he wasn't smiling. I think he must have been smiling the whole time. It must have been natural for him, smiling like that.

“Well, all right,” Doreen said to me. I opened the door, and we stepped out of the cab just as it was edging ahead again and started to walk over to the bar.

There was a terrible shriek of brakes followed by a dull thump-thump.

“Hey you!” Our cabby was craning out of his window with a furious, purple expression. “Waddaya think you're doin'?”

He had stopped the cab so abruptly that the cab behind bumped smack into him, and we could see the four girls inside waving and struggling and scrambling up off the floor.

The man laughed and left us on the curb and went back and handed a bill to the driver in the middle of a great honking and some yelling, and then we saw the girls from the magazine moving off in a row, one cab after another, like a wedding party with nothing but bridesmaids.

“Come on, Frankie,” the man said to one of his friends in the group, and a short, scrunty fellow detached himself and came into the bar with us.

He was the type of fellow I can't stand. I'm five feet ten in my stocking feet, and when I am with little men I stoop over a bit and slouch my hips, one up and one down, so I'll look shorter, and I feel gawky and morbid as somebody in a sideshow.

For a minute I had a wild hope we might pair off according to size, which would line me up with the man who had spoken to us in the first place, and he cleared a good six feet, but he went ahead with Doreen and didn't give me a second look. I tried to pretend I didn't see Frankie dogging along at my elbow and sat close by Doreen at the table.

It was so dark in the bar I could hardly make out anything except Doreen. With her white hair and white dress she was so white she looked silver. I think she must have reflected the neons over the bar. I felt myself melting into the shadows like the negative of a person I'd never seen before in my life.

“Well, what'll we have?” the man asked with a large smile.

“I think I'll have an old-fashioned,” Doreen said to me.

Ordering drinks always floored me. I didn't know whisky from gin and never managed to get anything I really liked the taste of. Buddy Willard and the other college boys I knew were usually too poor to buy hard liquor or they scorned drinking altogether. It's amazing how many college boys don't drink or smoke. I seemed to know them all. The farthest Buddy Willard ever went was buying us a bottle of Dubonnet, which he only did because he was trying to prove he could be aesthetic in spite of being a medical student.

“I'll have a vodka,” I said.

The man looked at me more closely. “With anything?”

“Just plain,” I said. “I always have it plain.”

I thought I might make a fool of myself by saying I'd have it with ice or soda or gin or anything. I'd seen a vodka ad once, just a glass full of vodka standing in the middle of a snowdrift in a blue light, and the vodka looked clear and pure as water, so I thought having vodka plain must be all right. My dream was someday ordering a drink and finding out it tasted wonderful.

The waiter came up then, and the man ordered drinks for the four of us. He looked so at home in that citified bar in his ranch outfit I thought he might well be somebody famous.

Doreen wasn't saying a word, she only toyed with her cork placemat and eventually lit a cigarette, but the man didn't seem to mind. He kept staring at her the way people stare at the great white macaw in the zoo, waiting for it to say something human.

The drinks arrived, and mine looked clear and pure, just like the vodka ad.

“What do you do?” I asked the man, to break the silence shooting up around me on all sides, thick as jungle grass. “I mean what do you do here in New York?”

Slowly and with what seemed a great effort, the man dragged his eyes away from Doreen's shoulder. “I'm a disc jockey,” he said. “You prob'ly must have heard of me. The name's Lenny Shepherd.”

“I know you,” Doreen said suddenly.

“I'm glad about that, honey,” the man said, and burst out laughing. “That'll come in handy. I'm famous as hell.”

Then Lenny Shepherd gave Frankie a long look.

“Say, where do you come from?” Frankie asked, sitting up with a jerk. “What's your name?”

“This here's Doreen.” Lenny slid his hand around Doreen's bare arm and gave her a squeeze.

What surprised me was that Doreen didn't let on she noticed what he was doing. She just sat there, dusky as a bleached-blonde Negress in her white dress, and sipped daintily at her drink.

“My name's Elly Higginbottom,” I said. “I come from Chicago.” After that I felt safer. I didn't want anything I said or did that night to be associated with me and my real name and coming from Boston.

“Well, Elly, what do you say we dance some?”

The thought of dancing with that little runt in his orange suede elevator shoes and mingy T-shirt and droopy blue sports coat made me laugh. If there's anything I look down on, it's a man in a blue outfit. Black or gray, or brown, even. Blue just makes me laugh.

“I'm not in the mood,” I said coldly, turning my back on him and hitching my chair over nearer to Doreen and Lenny.

Those two looked as if they'd known each other for years by now. Doreen was spooning up the hunks of fruit at the bottom of her glass with a spindly silver spoon, and Lenny was grunting each time she lifted the spoon to her mouth, and snapping and pretending to be a dog or something, and trying to get the fruit off the spoon. Doreen giggled and kept spooning up the fruit.

I began to think vodka was my drink at last. It didn't taste like anything, but it went straight down into my stomach like a sword swallower's sword and made me feel powerful and godlike.

“I better go now,” Frankie said, standing up.

I couldn't see him very clearly, the place was so dim, but for the first time I heard what a high, silly voice he had. Nobody paid him any notice.

“Hey, Lenny, you owe me something. Remember, Lenny, you owe me something, don't you, Lenny?”

I thought it odd Frankie should be reminding Lenny he owed him something in front of us, and we being perfect strangers, but Frankie stood there saying the same thing over and over until Lenny dug into his pocket and pulled out a big roll of green bills and peeled one off and handed it to Frankie. I think it was ten dollars.

“Shut up and scram.”

For a minute I thought Lenny was talking to me as well, but then I heard Doreen say, “I won't come unless Elly comes.” I had to hand it to her the way she picked up my fake name.

“Oh, Elly'll come, won't you, Elly?” Lenny said, giving me a wink.

“Sure I'll come,” I said. Frankie had wilted away into the night, so I thought I'd string along with Doreen. I wanted to see as much as I could.

I liked looking on at other people in crucial situations. If there was a road accident or a street fight or a baby pickled in a laboratory jar for me to look at, I'd stop and look so hard I never forgot it.

I certainly learned a lot of things I never would have learned otherwise this way, and even when they surprised me or made me sick I never let on, but pretended that's the way I knew things were all the time.

Two

I wouldn't have missed Lenny's place for anything.

It was built exactly like the inside of a ranch, only in the middle of a New York apartment house. He'd had a few partitions knocked down to make the place broaden out, he said, and then had them pine-panel the walls and fit up a special pine-paneled bar in the shape of a horseshoe. I think the floor was pine-paneled, too.

Great white bearskins lay about underfoot, and the only furniture was a lot of low beds covered with Indian rugs. Instead of pictures hung up on the walls, he had antlers and buffalo horns and a stuffed rabbit head. Lenny jutted a thumb at the meek little gray muzzle and stiff jackrabbit ears.

“Ran over that in Las Vegas.”

He walked away across the room, his cowboy boots echoing like pistol shots.

“Acoustics,” he said, and grew smaller and smaller until he vanished through a door in the distance.

All at once music started to come out of the air on every side. Then it stopped, and we heard Lenny's voice say “This is your twelve o'clock disc jock, Lenny Shepherd, with a roundup of the tops in pops. Number Ten in the wagon train this week is none other than that little yaller-haired gal you been hearin' so much about lately…the one an' only Sunflower!”

I was born in Kansas, I was bred in Kansas,
And when I marry I'll be wed in Kansas…

“What a card!” Doreen said. “Isn't he a card?”

“You bet,” I said.

“Listen, Elly, do me a favor.” She seemed to think Elly was who I really was by now.

“Sure,” I said.

“Stick around, will you? I wouldn't have a chance if he tried anything funny. Did you see that muscle?” Doreen giggled.

Lenny popped out of the back room. “I got twenty grand's worth of recording equipment in there.” He ambled over to the bar and set out three glasses and a silver ice bucket and a big pitcher and began to mix drinks from several different bottles.

…to a true-blue gal who promised she would wait—
She's the sunflower of the Sunflower State.

“Terrific, huh?” Lenny came over, balancing three glasses. Big drops stood out on them like sweat, and the ice cubes jingled as he passed them around. Then the music twanged to a stop, and we heard Lenny's voice announcing the next number.

“Nothing like listening to yourself talk. Say,” Lenny's eye lingered on me, “Frankie vamoosed, you ought to have somebody, I'll call up one of the fellers.”

“That's okay,” I said. “You don't have to do that.” I didn't want to come straight out and ask for somebody several sizes larger than Frankie.

Lenny looked relieved. “Just so's you don't mind. I wouldn't want to do wrong by a friend of Doreen's.” He gave Doreen a big white smile. “Would I, honeybun?”

He held out a hand to Doreen, and without a word they both started to jitterbug, still hanging on to their glasses.

I sat cross-legged on one of the beds and tried to look devout and impassive like some businessmen I once saw watching an Algerian belly dancer, but as soon as I leaned back against the wall under the stuffed rabbit, the bed started to roll out into the room, so I sat down on a bearskin on the floor and leaned back against the bed instead.

My drink was wet and depressing. Each time I took another sip it tasted more and more like dead water. Around the middle of the glass there was painted a pink lasso with yellow polka dots. I drank to about an inch below the lasso and waited a bit, and when I went to take another sip, the drink was up to lasso-level again.

Out of the air Lenny's ghost voice boomed, “Wye oh wye did I ever leave Wyoming?”

The two of them didn't even stop jitterbugging during the intervals. I felt myself shrinking to a small black dot against all those red and white rugs and that pine paneling. I felt like a hole in the ground.

There is something demoralizing about watching two people get more and more crazy about each other, especially when you are the only extra person in the room.

It's like watching Paris from an express caboose heading in the opposite direction-every second the city gets smaller and smaller, only you feel it's really you getting smaller and smaller and lonelier and lonelier, rushing away from all those lights and that excitement at about a million miles an hour.

Every so often Lenny and Doreen would bang into each other and kiss and then swing to take a long drink and close in on each other again. I thought I might just lie down on the bearskin and go to sleep until Doreen felt ready to go back to the hotel.

Then Lenny gave a terrible roar. I sat up. Doreen was hanging on to Lenny's left earlobe with her teeth.

“Leggo, you bitch!”

Lenny stooped, and Doreen went flying up on to his shoulder, and her glass sailed out of her hand in a long, wide arc and fetched up against the pine paneling with a silly tinkle. Lenny was still roaring and whirling round so fast I couldn't see Doreen's face.

I noted, in the routine way you notice the color of somebody's eyes, that Doreen's breasts had popped out of her dress and were swinging out slightly like full brown melons as she circled belly-down on Lenny's shoulder, thrashing her legs in the air and screeching, and then they both started to laugh and slow up, and Lenny was trying to bite Doreen's hip through her skirt when I let myself out the door before anything more could happen and managed to get downstairs by leaning with both hands on the banister and half sliding the whole way.

I didn't realize Lenny's place had been air-conditioned until I wavered out onto the pavement. The tropical, stale heat the sidewalks had been sucking up all day hit me in the face like a last insult. I didn't know where in the world I was.

For a minute I entertained the idea of taking a cab to the party after all, but decided against it because the dance might be over by now, and I didn't feel like ending up in an empty barn of a ballroom strewn with confetti and cigarette butts and crumpled cocktail napkins.

I walked carefully to the nearest street corner, brushing the wall of the buildings on my left with the tip of one finger to steady myself. I looked at the street sign. Then I took my New York street map out of my pocketbook. I was exactly forty-three blocks by five blocks away from my hotel.

Walking has never fazed me. I just set out in the right direction, counting the blocks under my breath, and when I walked into the lobby of the hotel I was perfectly sober and my feet only slightly swollen, but that was my own fault because I hadn't bothered to wear any stockings.

The lobby was empty except for a night clerk dozing in his lit booth among the key rings and the silent telephones.

I slid into the self-service elevator and pushed the button for my floor. The doors folded shut like a noiseless accordion. Then my ears went funny, and I noticed a big, smudgy-eyed Chinese woman staring idiotically into my face. It was only me, of course. I was appalled to see how wrinkled and used up I looked.

There wasn't a soul in the hall. I let myself into my room. It was full of smoke. At first I thought the smoke had materialized out of thin air as a sort of judgment, but then I remembered it was Doreen's smoke and pushed the button that opened the window vent. They had the windows fixed so you couldn't really open them and lean out, and for some reason this made me furious.

By standing at the left side of the window and laying my cheek to the woodwork, I could see downtown to where the UN balanced itself in the dark, like a weird green Martian honeycomb. I could see the moving red and white lights along the drive and the lights of the bridges whose names I didn't know.

The silence depressed me. It wasn't the silence of silence. It was my own silence.

I knew perfectly well the cars were making noise, and the people in them and behind the lit windows of the buildings were making a noise, and the river was making a nowise, but I couldn't hear a thing. The city hung in my window, flat as a poster, glittering and blinking, but it might just as well not have been there at all, for the good it did me.

The china-white bedside telephone could have connected me up with things, but there it sat, dumb as a death's head. I tried to think of people I'd given my phone number to, so I could make a list of all the possible calls I might be about to receive, but all I could think of was that I'd given my phone number to Buddy Willard's mother so she could give it to a simultaneous interpreter she knew at the UN.

I let out a small, dry laugh.

I could imagine the sort of simultaneous interpreter Mrs. Willard would introduce me to when all the time she wanted me to marry Buddy, who was taking the cure for TB somewhere in upper New York State. Buddy's mother had even arranged for me to be given a job as a waitress at the TB sanatorium that summer so Buddy wouldn't be lonely. She and Buddy couldn't understand why I chose to go to New York City instead.

The mirror over my bureau seemed slightly warped and much too silver. The face in it looked like the reflection in a ball of dentist's mercury. I thought of crawling in between the bed sheets and trying to sleep, but that appealed to me about as much as stuffing a dirty, scrawled-over letter into a fresh, clean envelope. I decided to take a hot bath.

There must be quite a few things a hot bath won't cure, but I don't know many of them. Whenever I'm sad I'm going to die, or so nervous I can't sleep, or in love with somebody I won't be seeing for a week, I slump down just so far and then I say: “I'll go take a hot bath.”

I meditate in the bath. The water needs to be very hot, so hot you can barely stand putting your foot in it. Then you lower yourself, inch by inch, till the water's up to your neck.

I remember the ceiling over every bathtub I've stretched out in. I remember the texture of the ceilings and the cracks and the colors and the damp spots and the light fixtures. I remember the tubs, too: the antique griffin-legged tubs, and the modern coffin-shaped tubs, and the fancy pink marble tubs overlooking indoor lily ponds, and I remember the shapes and sizes of the water taps and the different sorts of soap holders.

I never feel so much myself as when I'm in a hot bath.

I lay in that tub on the seventeenth floor of this hotel for-women-only, high up over the jazz and push of New York, for near onto an hour, and I felt myself growing pure again. I don't believe in baptism or the waters of Jordan or anything like that, but I guess I feel about a hot bath the way those religious people feel about holy water.

I said to myself: “Doreen is dissolving, Lenny Shepherd is dissolving, Frankie is dissolving, New York is dissolving, they are all dissolving away and none of them matter any more. I don't know them, I have never known them and I am very pure. All that liquor and those sticky kisses I saw and the dirt that settled on my skin on the way back is turning into something pure.”

The longer I lay there in the clear hot water the purer I felt, and when I stepped out at last and wrapped myself in one of the big, soft white hotel bath towels I felt pure and sweet as a new baby.

I don't know how long I had been asleep when I heard the knocking. I didn't pay any attention at first, because the person knocking kept saying, “Elly, Elly, Elly, let me in,” and I didn't know any Elly. Then another kind of knock sounded over the first dull, bumping knock-a sharp tap-tap, and another, much crisper voice said, “Miss Greenwood, your friend wants you,” and I knew it was Doreen.

I swung to my feet and balanced dizzily for a minute in the middle of the dark room. I felt angry with Doreen for waking me up. All I stood a chance of getting out of that sad night was a good sleep, and she had to wake me up and spoil it. I thought if I pretended to be asleep the knocking might go away and leave me in peace, but I waited, and it didn't.

“Elly, Elly, Elly,” the first voice mumbled, while the other voice went on hissing, “Miss Greenwood, Miss Greenwood, Miss Greenwood,” as if I had a split personality or something.

I opened the door and blinked out into the bright hall. I had the impression it wasn't night and it wasn't day, but some lurid third interval that had suddenly slipped between them and would never end.

Doreen was slumped against the doorjamb. When I came out, she toppled into my arms. I couldn't see her face because her head was hanging down on her chest and her stiff blonde hair fell down from its dark roots like a hula fringe.

I recognized the short, squat, mustached woman in the black uniform as the night maid who ironed day dresses and party frocks in a crowded cubicle on our floor. I couldn't understand how she came to know Doreen or why she should want to help Doreen wake me up instead of leading her quietly back to her own room.

Seeing Doreen supported in my arms and silent except for a few wet hiccups, the woman strode away down the hall to her cubicle with its ancient Singer sewing machine and white ironing board. I wanted to run after her and tell her I had nothing to do with Doreen, because she looked stern and hardworking and moral as an old-style European immigrant and reminded me of my Austrian grandmother.

“Lemme lie down, lemme lie down,” Doreen was muttering. “Lemme lie down, lemme lie down.”

I felt if I carried Doreen across the threshold into my room and helped her onto my bed I would never get rid of her again.

Her body was warm and soft as a pile of pillows against my arm where she leaned her weight, and her feet, in their high, spiked heels, dragged foolishly. She was much too heavy for me to budge down the long hall.

I decided the only thing to do was to dump her on the carpet and shut and lock my door and go back to bed. When Doreen woke up she wouldn't remember what had happened and would think she must have passed out in front of my door while I slept, and she would get up of her own accord and go sensibly back to her room.

I started to lower Doreen gently onto the green hall carpet, but she gave a low moan and pitched forward out of my arms. A jet of brown vomit flew from her mouth and spread in a large puddle at my feet.

Suddenly Doreen grew even heavier. Her head drooped forward into the puddle, the wisps of her blonde hair dabbling in it like tree roots in a bog, and I realized she was asleep. I drew back. I felt half-asleep myself.

I made a decision about Doreen that night. I decided I would watch her and listen to what she said, but deep down I would have nothing at all to do with her. Deep down, I would be loyal to Betsy and her innocent friends. It was Betsy I resembled at heart.

Quietly, I stepped back into my room and shut the door. On second thought, I didn't lock it. I couldn't quite bring myself to do that.

When I woke up in the dull, sunless heat the next morning, I dressed and splashed my face with cold water and put on some lipstick and opened the door slowly. I think I still expected to see Doreen's body lying there in the pool of vomit like an ugly, concrete testimony to my own dirty nature.

There was nobody in the hall. The carpet stretched from one end of the hall to the other, clean and eternally verdant except for a faint, irregular dark stain before my door as if somebody had by accident spilled a glass of water there, but dabbed it dry again.

Three

Arrayed on the Ladies' Day banquet table were yellow-green avocado pear halves stuffed with crabmeat and mayonnaise, and platters of rare roast beef and cold chicken, and every so often a cut-glass bowl heaped with black caviar. I hadn't had time to eat any breakfast at the hotel cafeteria that morning, except for a cup of overstewed coffee so bitter it made my nose curl, and I was starving.

Before I came to New York I'd never eaten out in a proper restaurant. I don't count Howard Johnson's, where I only had french fries and cheeseburgers and vanilla frappes with people like Buddy Willard. I'm not sure why it is, but I love food more than just about anything else. No matter how much I eat, I never put on weight. With one exception I've been the same weight for ten years.

My favorite dishes are full of butter and cheese and sour cream. In New York we had so many free luncheons with people on the magazine and various visiting celebrities I developed the habit of running my eye down those huge handwritten menus, where a tiny side dish of peas cost fifty or sixty cents, until I'd picked the richest, most expensive dishes and ordered a string of them.

We were always taken out on expense accounts, so I never felt guilty. I made a point of eating so fast I never kept the other people waiting who generally ordered only chef's salad and grapefruit juice because they were trying to reduce. Almost everybody I met in New York was trying to reduce.

“I want to welcome the prettiest, smartest bunch of young ladies our staff has yet had the good luck to meet,” the plump, bald master-of-ceremonies wheezed into his lapel microphone. “This banquet is just a small sample of the hospitality our Food Testing Kitchens here on Ladies' Day would like to offer in appreciation for your visit.”

A delicate, ladylike spatter of applause, and we all sat down at the enormous linen-draped table.

There were eleven of us girls from the magazine, together with most of our supervising editors, and the whole staff of the Ladies' Day Food Testing Kitchens in hygienic white smocks, neat hairnets and flawless makeup of a uniform peach-pie color.

There were only eleven of us, because Doreen was missing. They had set her place next to mine for some reason, and the chair stayed empty. I saved her placecard for her—a pocket mirror with “Doreen” painted along the top of it in lacy script and a wreath of frosted daisies around the edge, framing the silver hole where her face would show.

Doreen was spending the day with Lenny Shepherd. She spent most of her free time with Lenny Shepherd now.

In the hour before our luncheon at Ladies' Day—the big women's magazine that features lush double-page spreads of Technicolor meals, with a different theme and locale each month—we had been shown around the endless glossy kitchens and seen how difficult it is to photograph apple pie à la mode under bright lights because the ice cream keeps melting and has to be propped up from behind with toothpicks and changed every time it starts looking too soppy.

The sight of all the food stacked in those kitchens made me dizzy. It's not that we hadn't enough to eat at home, it's just that my grandmother always cooked economy joints and economy meat loafs and had the habit of saying, the minute you lifted the first forkful to your mouth, “I hope you enjoy that, it cost forty-one cents a pound,” which always made me feel I was somehow eating pennies instead of Sunday roast.

While we were standing up behind our chairs listening to the welcome speech, I had bowed my head and secretly eyed the position of the bowls of caviar. One bowl was set strategically between me and Doreen's empty chair.

I figured the girl across from me couldn't reach it because of the mountainous centerpiece of marzipan fruit, and Betsy, on my right, would be too nice to ask me to share it with her if I just kept it out of the way at my elbow by my bread-and-butter plate. Besides, another bowl of caviar sat a little way to the right of the girl next to Betsy, and she could eat that.

My grandfather and I had a standing joke. He was the head waiter at a country club near my home town, and every Sunday my grandmother drove in to bring him home for his Monday off. My brother and I alternated going with her, and my grandfather always served Sunday supper to my grandmother and whichever of us was along as if we were regular club guests. He loved introducing me to special tidbits, and by the age of nine I had developed a passionate taste for cold vichyssoise and caviar and anchovy paste.

The joke was that at my wedding my grandfather would see I had all the caviar I could eat. It was a joke because I never intended to get married, and even if I did, my grandfather couldn't have afforded enough caviar unless he robbed the country club kitchen and carried it off in a suitcase.

Under cover of the clinking of water goblets and silverware and bone china, I paved my plate with chicken slices. Then I covered the chicken slices with caviar thickly as if I were spreading peanut butter on a piece of bread. Then I picked up the chicken slices in my fingers one by one, rolled them so the caviar wouldn't ooze off and ate them.

I'd discovered, after a lot of extreme apprehension about what spoons to use, that if you do something incorrect at table with a certain arrogance, as if you knew perfectly well you were doing it properly, you can get away with it and nobody will think you are bad-mannered or poorly brought up. They will think you are original and very witty.

I learned this trick the day Jay Cee took me to lunch with a famous poet. He wore a horrible, lumpy, speckled brown tweed jacket and gray pants and a red-and-blue checked open-throated jersey in a very formal restaurant full of fountains and chandeliers, where all the other men were dressed in dark suits and immaculate white shirts.

This poet ate his salad with his fingers, leaf by leaf, while talking to me about the antithesis of nature and art. I couldn't take my eyes off the pale, stubby white fingers traveling back and forth from the poet's salad bowl to the poet's mouth with one dripping lettuce leaf after another. Nobody giggled or whispered rude remarks. The poet made eating salad with your fingers seem to be the only natural and sensible thing to do.

None of our magazine editors or the Ladies' Day staff members sat anywhere near me, and Betsy seemed sweet and friendly, she didn't even seem to like caviar, so I grew more and more confident. When I finished my first plate of cold chicken and caviar, I laid out another. Then I tackled the avocado and crabmeat salad.

Avocados are my favorite fruit. Every Sunday my grandfather used to bring me an avocado pear hidden at the bottom of his briefcase under six soiled shirts and the Sunday comics. He taught me how to eat avocados by melting grape jelly and french dressing together in a saucepan and filling the cup of the pear with the garnet sauce. I felt homesick for that sauce. The crabmeat tasted bland in comparison.

“How was the fur show?” I asked Betsy, when I was no longer worried about competition over my caviar. I scraped the last few salty black eggs from the dish with my soup spoon and licked it clean.

“It was wonderful,” Betsy smiled. “They showed us how to make an all-purpose neckerchief out of mink tails and a gold chain, the sort of chain you can get an exact copy of at Woolworth's for a dollar ninety-eight, and Hilda nipped down to the wholesale fur warehouses right afterward and bought a bunch of mink tails at a big discount and dropped in at Woolworth's and then stitched the whole thing together coming up on the bus.”

I peered over at Hilda, who sat on the other side of Betsy. Sure enough, she was wearing an expensive-looking scarf of furry tails fastened on one side by a dangling gilt chain.

I never really understood Hilda. She was six feet tall, with huge, slanted green eyes and thick red lips and a vacant, Slavic expression. She made hats. She was apprenticed to the Fashion Editor, which set her apart from the more literary ones among us like Doreen and Betsy and I myself, who all wrote columns, even if some of them were only about health and beauty. I don't know if Hilda could read, but she made startling hats. She went to a special school for making hats in New York and every day she wore a new hat to work, constructed by her own hands out of bits of straw or fur or ribbon or veiling in subtle, bizarre shades.

“That's amazing,” I said. “Amazing.” I missed Doreen. She would have murmured some fine, scalding remark about Hilda's miraculous furpiece to cheer me up.

I felt very low. I had been unmasked only that morning by Jay Cee herself, and I felt now that all the uncomfortable suspicions I had about myself were coming true, and I couldn't hide the truth much longer. After nineteen years of running after good marks and prizes and grants of one sort and another, I was letting up, slowing down, dropping clean out of the race.

“Why didn't you come along to the fur show with us?” Betsy asked. I had the impression she was repeating herself, and that she'd asked me the same question a minute ago, only I couldn't have been listening. “Did you go off with Doreen?”

“No,” I said, “I wanted to go to the fur show, but Jay Cee called up and made me come into the office.” That wasn't quite true about wanting to go to the show, but I tried to convince myself now that it was true, so I could be really wounded about what Jay Cee had done.

I told Betsy how I had been lying in bed that morning planning to go to the fur show. What I didn't tell her was that Doreen had come into my room earlier and said, “What do you want to go to that assy show for, Lenny and I are going to Coney Island, so why don't you come along? Lenny can get you a nice fellow, the day's shot to hell anyhow with that luncheon and then the film première in the afternoon, so nobody'll miss us.”

For a minute I was tempted. The show certainly did seem stupid. I have never cared for furs. What I decided to do in the end was lie in bed as long as I wanted to and then go to Central Park and spend the day lying in the grass, the longest grass I could find in that bald, duck-ponded wilderness.

I told Doreen I would not go to the show or the luncheon or the film première, but that I would not go to Coney Island either, I would stay in bed. After Doreen left, I wondered why I couldn't go the whole way doing what I should any more. This made me sad and tired. Then I wondered why I couldn't go the whole way doing what I shouldn't, the way Doreen did, and this made me even sadder and more tired.

I didn't know what time it was, but I'd heard the girls bustling and calling in the hall and getting ready for the fur show, and then I'd heard the hall go still, and as I lay on my back in bed staring up at the blank, white ceiling the stillness seemed to grow bigger and bigger until I felt my eardrums would burst with it. Then the phone rang.

I stared at the phone for a minute. The receiver shook a bit in its bone-colored cradle, so I could tell it was really ringing. I thought I might have given my phone number to somebody at a dance or a party and then forgotten about it. I lifted the receiver and spoke in a husky, receptive voice.

“Hello?”

“Jay Cee here,” Jay Cee rapped out with brutal promptitude. “I wondered if you happened to be planning to come into the office today?”

I sank down into the sheets. I couldn't understand why Jay Cee thought I'd be coming into the office. We had these mimeographed schedule cards so we could keep track of all our activities, and we spent a lot of mornings and afternoons away from the office going to affairs in town. Of course, some of the affairs were optional.

There was quite a pause. Then I said meekly, “I thought I was going to the fur show.” Of course I hadn't thought any such thing, but I couldn't figure out what else to say.

“I told her I thought I was going to the fur show,” I said to Betsy. “But she told me to come into the office, she wanted to have a little talk with me, and there was some work to do.”

“Oh-oh!” Betsy said sympathetically. She must have seen the tears that plopped down into my dessert dish of meringue and brandy ice cream, because she pushed over her own untouched dessert and I started absently on that when I'd finished my own. I felt a bit awkward about the tears, but they were real enough. Jay Cee had said some terrible things to me.

When I made my wan entrance into the office at about ten o'clock, Jay Cee stood up and came round her desk to shut the door, and I sat in the swivel chair in front of my typewriter table facing her, and she sat in the swivel chair behind her desk facing me, with the window full of potted plants, shelf after shelf of them, springing up at her back like a tropical garden.

“Doesn't your work interest you, Esther?”

“Oh, it does, it does,” I said. “It interests me very much.” I felt like yelling the words, as if that might make them more convincing, but I controlled myself.

All my life I'd told myself studying and reading and writing and working like mad was what I wanted to do, and it actually seemed to be true, I did everything well enough and got all A's, and by the time I made it to college nobody could stop me.

I was college correspondent for the town Gazette and editor of the literary magazine and secretary of Honor Board, which deals with academic and social offenses and punishments—a popular office-and I had a well-known woman poet and professor on the faculty championing me for graduate school at the biggest universities in the east, and promises of full scholarships all the way, and now I was apprenticed to the best editor on an intellectual fashion magazine, and what did I do but balk and balk like a dull cart horse?

“I'm very interested in everything.” The words fell with a hollow flatness on to Jay Cee's desk, like so many wooden nickels.

“I'm glad of that,” Jay Cee said a bit waspishly. “You can learn a lot in this month on the magazine, you know, if you just roll up your shirtsleeves. The girl who was here before you didn't bother with any of the fashion-show stuff. She went straight from this office onto Time.”

“My!” I said, in the same sepulchral tone. “That was quick!”

“Of course, you have another year at college yet,” Jay Cee went on a little more mildly. “What do you have in mind after you graduate?”

What I always thought I had in mind was getting some big scholarship to graduate school or a grant to study all over Europe, and then I thought I'd be a professor and write books of poems or write books of poems and be an editor of some sort. Usually I had these plans on the tip of my tongue.

“I don't really know,” I heard myself say. I felt a deep shock, hearing myself say that, because the minute I said it, I knew it was true.

It sounded true, and I recognized it, the way you recognize some nondescript person that's been hanging around your door for ages and then suddenly comes up and introduces himself as your real father and looks exactly like you, so you know he really is your father, and the person you thought all your life was your father is a sham.

“I don't really know.”

“You'll never get anywhere like that.” Jay Cee paused. “What languages do you have?”

“Oh, I can read a bit of French, I guess, and I've always wanted to learn German.” I'd been telling people I'd always wanted to learn German for about five years.

My mother spoke German during her childhood in America and was stoned for it during the First World War by the children at school. My German-speaking father, dead since I was nine, came from some manic-depressive hamlet in the black heart of Prussia. My younger brother was at that moment on the Experiment in International Living in Berlin and speaking German like a native.

What I didn't say was that each time I picked up a German dictionary or a German book, the very sight of those dense, black, barbed-wire letters made my mind shut like a clam.

“I've always thought I'd like to go into publishing.” I tried to recover a thread that might lead me back to my old, bright salesmanship. “I guess what I'll do is apply at some publishing house.”

“You ought to read French and German,” Jay Cee said mercilessly, “and probably several other languages as well, Spanish and Italian—better still, Russian. Hundreds of girls flood into New York every June thinking they'll be editors. You need to offer something more than the run-of-the-mill person. You better learn some languages.”

I hadn't the heart to tell Jay Cee there wasn't one scrap of space on my senior year schedule to learn languages in. I was taking one of those honors programs that teach you to think independently, and except for a course in Tolstoy and Dostoevsky and a seminar in advanced poetry composition, I would spend my whole time writing on some obscure theme in the works of James Joyce. I hadn't picked out my theme yet, because I hadn't got round to reading Finnegans Wake, but my professor was very excited about my thesis and had promised to give me some leads on images about twins.

“I'll see what I can do,” I told Jay Cee. “I probably might just fit in one of those double-barreled accelerated courses in elementary German they've rigged up.” I thought at the time I might actually do this. I had a way of persuading my Class Dean to let me do irregular things. She regarded me as a sort of interesting experiment.

At college I had to take a required course in physics and chemistry. I had already taken a course in botany and done very well. I never answered one test question wrong the whole year, and for a while I toyed with the idea of being a botanist and studying the wild grasses in Africa or the South American rain forests, because you can win big grants to study offbeat things like that in queer areas much more easily than winning grants to study art in Italy or English in England; there's not so much competition.

Botany was fine, because I loved cutting up leaves and putting them under the microscope and drawing diagrams of bread mold and the odd, heart-shaped leaf in the sex cycle of the fern, it seemed so real to me.

The day I went into physics class it was death.

A short dark man with a high lisping voice, named Mr. Manzi, stood in front of the class in a tight blue suit holding a little wooden ball. He put the ball on a steep grooved slide and let it run down to the bottom. Then he started talking about let a equal acceleration and let t equal time and suddenly he was scribbling letters and numbers and equals signs all over the blackboard and my mind went dead.

I took the physics book back to my dormitory. It was a huge book on porous mimeographed paper—four hundred pages long with no drawings or photographs, only diagrams and formulas—between brick-red cardboard covers. This book was written by Mr. Manzi to explain physics to college girls, and if it worked on us he would try to have it published.

Well, I studied those formulas, I went to class and watched balls roll down slides and listened to bells ring and by the end of the semester most of the other girls had failed and I had a straight A. I heard Mr. Manzi saying to a bunch of the girls who were complaining that the course was too hard, “No, it can't be too hard, because one girl got a straight A.” “Who is it? Tell us,” they said, but he shook his head and didn't say anything and gave me a sweet little conspiring smile.

That's what gave me the idea of escaping the next semester of chemistry. I may have made a straight A in physics, but I was panic-struck. Physics made me sick the whole time I learned it. What I couldn't stand was this shrinking everything into letters and numbers. Instead of leaf shapes and enlarged diagrams of the holes the leaves breathe through and fascinating words like carotene and xanthophyll on the blackboard, there were these hideous, cramped, scorpion-lettered formulas in Mr. Manzi's special red chalk.

I knew chemistry would be worse, because I'd seen a big chart of the ninety-odd elements hung up in the chemistry lab, and all the perfectly good words like gold and silver and cobalt and aluminum were shortened to ugly abbreviations with different decimal numbers after them. If I had to strain my brain with any more of that stuff I would go mad. I would fail outright. It was only by a horrible effort of will that I had dragged myself through the first half of the year.

So I went to my Class Dean with a clever plan.

My plan was that I needed the time to take a course in Shakespeare, since I was, after all, an English major. She knew and I knew perfectly well I would get a straight A again in the chemistry course, so what was the point of my taking the exams; why couldn't I just go to the classes and look on and take it all in and forget about marks or credits? It was a case of honor among honorable people, and the content meant more than the form, and marks were really a bit silly anyway, weren't they, when you knew you'd always get an A? My plan was strengthened by the fact that the college had just dropped the second year of required science for the classes after me anyway, so my class was the last to suffer under the old ruling.

Mr. Manzi was in perfect agreement with my plan. I think it flattered him that I enjoyed his classes so much I would take them for no materialistic reason like credit and an A, but for the sheer beauty of chemistry itself. I thought it was quite ingenious of me to suggest sitting in on the chemistry course even after I'd changed over to Shakespeare. It was quite an unnecessary gesture and made it seem I simply couldn't bear to give chemistry up.

Of course, I would never have succeeded with this scheme if I hadn't made that A in the first place. And if my Class Dean had known how scared and depressed I was, and how I seriously contemplated desperate remedies such as getting a doctor's certificate that I was unfit to study chemistry, the formulas made me dizzy and so on, I'm sure she wouldn't have listened to me for a minute, but would have made me take the course regardless.

As it happened, the Faculty Board passed my petition, and my Class Dean told me later that several of the professors were touched by it. They took it as a real step in intellectual maturity.

I had to laugh when I thought about the rest of that year. I went to the chemistry class five times a week and didn't miss a single one. Mr. Manzi stood at the bottom of the big, rickety old amphitheater, making blue flames and red flares and clouds of yellow stuff by pouring the contents of one test tube into another, and I shut his voice out of my ears by pretending it was only a mosquito in the distance and sat back enjoying the bright lights and the colored fires and wrote page after page of villanelles and sonnets.

Mr. Manzi would glance at me now and then and see me writing, and send up a sweet little appreciative smile. I guess he thought I was writing down all those formulas not for exam time, like the other girls, but because his presentation fascinated me so much I couldn't help it.

Four

I don't know just why my successful evasion of chemistry should have floated into my mind there in Jay Cee's office.

All the time she talked to me, I saw Mr. Manzi standing on thin air in back of Jay Cee's head, like something conjured up out of a hat, holding his little wooden ball and the test tube that billowed a great cloud of yellow smoke the day before Easter vacation and smelt of rotten eggs and made all the girls and Mr. Manzi laugh.

I felt sorry for Mr. Manzi. I felt like going down to him on my hands and knees and apologizing for being such an awful liar.

Jay Cee handed me a pile of story manuscripts and spoke to me much more kindly. I spent the rest of the morning reading the stories and typing out what I thought of them on the pink Interoffice Memo sheets and sending them into the office of Betsy's editor to be read by Betsy the next day. Jay Cee interrupted me now and then to tell me something practical or a bit of gossip.

Jay Cee was going to lunch that noon with two famous writers, a man and a lady. The man had just sold six short stories to the New Yorker and six to Jay Cee. This surprised me, as I didn't know magazines bought stories in lots of six, and I was staggered by the thought of the amount of money six stories would probably bring in. Jay Cee said she had to be very careful at this lunch, because the lady writer wrote stories too, but she had never had any in the New Yorker and Jay Cee had only taken one from her in five years. Jay Cee had to flatter the more famous man at the same time as she was careful not to hurt the less famous lady.

When the cherubs in Jay Cee's French wall clock waved their wings up and down and put their little gilt trumpets to their lips and pinged out twelve notes one after the other, Jay Cee told me I'd done enough work for the day, and to go off to the Ladies' Day tour and banquet and to the film première, and she would see me bright and early tomorrow.

Then she slipped a suit jacket over her lilac blouse, pinned a hat of imitation lilacs on the top of her head, powdered her nose briefly and adjusted her thick spectacles. She looked terrible, but very wise. As she left the office, she patted my shoulder with one lilac-gloved hand.

“Don't let the wicked city get you down.”

I sat quietly in my swivel chair for a few minutes and thought about Jay Cee. I tried to imagine what it would be like if I were Ee Gee, the famous editor, in an office full of potted rubber plants and African violets my secretary had to water each morning. I wished I had a mother like Jay Cee. Then I'd know what to do.

My own mother wasn't much help. My mother had taught shorthand and typing to support us ever since my father died, and secretly she hated it and hated him for dying and leaving no money because he didn't trust life insurance salesmen. She was always on to me to learn shorthand after college, so I'd have a practical skill as well as a college degree. “Even the apostles were tentmakers,” she'd say. “They had to live, just the way we do.”

I dabbled my fingers in the bowl of warm water a Ladies' Day waitress set down in place of my two empty ice cream dishes. Then I wiped each finger carefully with my linen napkin which was still quite clean. Then I folded the linen napkin and laid it between my lips and brought my lips down on it precisely. When I put the napkin back on the table a fuzzy pink lip shape bloomed right in the middle of it like a tiny heart.

I thought what a long way I had come.

The first time I saw a fingerbowl was at the home of my benefactress. It was the custom at my college, the little freckled lady in the Scholarships Office told me, to write to the person whose scholarship you had, if they were still alive, and thank them for it.

I had the scholarship of Philomena Guinea, a wealthy novelist who went to my college in the early nineteen hundreds and had her first novel made into a silent film with Bette Davis as well as a radio serial that was still running, and it turned out she was alive and lived in a large mansion not far from my grandfather's country club.

So I wrote Philomena Guinea a long letter in coal-black ink on gray paper with the name of the college embossed on it in red. I wrote what the leaves looked like in autumn when I bicycled out into the hills, and how wonderful it was to live on a campus instead of commuting by bus to a city college and having to live at home, and how all knowledge was opening up before me and perhaps one day I would be able to write great books the way she did.

I had read one of Mrs. Guinea's books in the town library—the college library didn't stock them for some reason—and it was crammed from beginning to end with long, suspenseful questions: “Would Evelyn discern that Gladys knew Roger in her past? wondered Hector feverishly” and “How could Donald marry her when he learned of the child Elsie, hidden away with Mrs. Rollmop on the secluded country farm? Griselda demanded of her bleak, moonlit pillow.” These books earned Philomena Guinea, who later told me she had been very stupid at college, millions and millions of dollars.

Mrs. Guinea answered my letter and invited me to lunch at her home. That was where I saw my first fingerbowl.

The water had a few cherry blossoms floating in it, and I thought it must be some clear sort of Japanese after-dinner soup and ate every bit of it, including the crisp little blossoms. Mrs. Guinea never said anything, and it was only much later, when I told a debutante I knew at college about the dinner, that I learned what I had done.

When we came out of the sunnily lit interior of the Ladies' Day offices, the streets were gray and fuming with rain. It wasn't the nice kind of rain that rinses you clean, but the sort of rain I imagine they must have in Brazil. It flew straight down from the sky in drops the size of coffee saucers and hit the hot sidewalks with a hiss that sent clouds of steam writhing up from the gleaming, dark concrete.

My secret hope of spending the afternoon alone in Central Park died in the glass eggbeater of Ladies' Day revolving doors. I found myself spewed out through the warm rain and into the dim, throbbing cave of a cab, together with Betsy and Hilda and Emily Ann Offenbach, a prim little girl with a bun of red hair and a husband and three children in Teaneck, New Jersey.

The movie was very poor. It starred a nice blond girl who looked like June Allyson but was really somebody else, and a sexy black-haired girl who looked like Elizabeth Taylor but was also somebody else, and two big, broad-shouldered bone-heads with names like Rick and Gil.

It was a football romance and it was in Technicolor.

I hate Technicolor. Everybody in a Technicolor movie seems to feel obliged to wear a lurid costume in each new scene and to stand around like a clotheshorse with a lot of very green trees or very yellow wheat or very blue ocean rolling away for miles and miles in every direction.

Most of the action in this picture took place in the football stands, with the two girls waving and cheering in smart suits with orange chrysanthemums the size of cabbages on their lapels, or in a ballroom, where the girls swooped across the floor with their dates, in dresses like something out of Gone With the Wind, and then sneaked off into the powder room to say nasty intense things to each other.

Finally I could see the nice girl was going to end up with the nice football hero and the sexy girl was going to end up with nobody, because the man named Gil had only wanted a mistress and not a wife all along and was now packing off to Europe on a single ticket.

At about this point I began to feel peculiar. I looked round me at all the rows of rapt little heads with the same silver glow on them at the front and the same black shadow on them at the back, and they looked like nothing more or less than a lot of stupid moonbrains.

I felt in terrible danger of puking. I didn't know whether it was the awful movie giving me a stomachache or all that caviar I had eaten.

“I'm going back to the hotel,” I whispered to Betsy through the half-dark.

Betsy was staring at the screen with deadly concentration. “Don't you feel good?” she whispered, barely moving her lips.

“No,” I said. “I feel like hell.”

“So do I, I'll come back with you.”

We slipped out of our seats and said Excuse me Excuse me Excuse me down the length of our row, while the people grumbled and hissed and shifted their rain boots and umbrellas to let us pass, and I stepped on as many feet as I could because it took my mind off this enormous desire to puke that was ballooning up in front of me so fast I couldn't see round it.

The remains of a tepid rain were still sifting down when we stepped out into the street.

Betsy looked a fright. The bloom was gone from her cheeks and her drained face floated in front of me, green and sweating. We fell into one of those yellow checkered cabs that are always waiting at the curb when you are trying to decide whether or not you want a taxi, and by the time we reached the hotel I had puked once and Betsy had puked twice.

The cab driver took the corners with such momentum that we were thrown together first on one side of the back seat and then on the other. Each time one of us felt sick, she would lean over quietly as if she had dropped something and was picking it up off the floor, and the other one would hum a little and pretend to be looking out the window.

The cab driver seemed to know what we were doing, even so.

“Hey,” he protested, driving through a light that had just turned red, “you can't do that in my cab, you better get out and do it in the street.”

But we didn't say anything, and I guess he figured we were almost at the hotel so he didn't make us get out until we pulled up in front of the main entrance.

We didn't dare wait to add up the fare. We stuffed a pile of silver into the cabby's hand and dropped a couple of Kleenexes to cover the mess on the floor, and ran in through the lobby and on to the empty elevator. Luckily for us, it was a quiet time of day. Betsy was sick again in the elevator and I held her head, and then I was sick and she held mine.

Usually after a good puke you feel better right away. We hugged each other and then said good-bye and went off to opposite ends of the hall to lie down in our own rooms. There is nothing like puking with somebody to make you into old friends.

But the minute I'd shut the door behind me and undressed and dragged myself on to the bed, I felt worse than ever. I felt I just had to go to the toilet. I struggled into my white bathrobe with the blue cornflowers on it and staggered down to the bathroom.

Betsy was already there. I could hear her groaning behind the door, so I hurried on around the corner to the bathroom in the next wing. I thought I would die, it was so far.

I sat on the toilet and leaned my head over the edge of the washbowl and I thought I was losing my guts and my dinner both. The sickness rolled through me in great waves. After each wave it would fade away and leave me limp as a wet leaf and shivering all over and then I would feel it rising up in me again, and the glittering white torture chamber tiles under my feet and over my head and on all four sides closed in and squeezed me to pieces.

I don't know how long I kept at it. I let the cold water in the bowl go on running loudly with the stopper out, so anybody who came by would think I was washing my clothes, and then when I felt reasonably safe I stretched out on the floor and lay quite still.

It didn't seem to be summer any more. I could feel the winter shaking my bones and banging my teeth together, and the big white hotel towel I had dragged down with me lay under my head numb as a snowdrift.

I thought it very bad manners for anyone to pound on a bathroom door the way some person was pounding. They could just go around the corner and find another bathroom the way I had done and leave me in peace. But the person kept banging and pleading with me to let them in and I thought I dimly recognized the voice. It sounded a bit like Emily Ann Offenbach.

“Just a minute,” I said then. My words bungled out thick as molasses.

I pulled myself together and slowly rose and flushed the toilet for the tenth time and sopped the bowl clean and rolled up the towel so the vomit stains didn't show very clearly and unlocked the door and stepped out into the hall.

I knew it would be fatal if I looked at Emily Ann or anybody else so I fixed my eyes glassily on a window that swam at the end of the hall and put one foot in front of the other.

The next thing I had a view of was somebody's shoe.

It was a stout shoe of cracked black leather and quite old, with tiny air holes in a scalloped pattern over the toe and a dull polish, and it was pointed at me. It seemed to be placed on a hard green surface that was hurting my right cheekbone.

I kept very still, waiting for a clue that would give me some notion of what to do. A little to the left of the shoe I saw a vague heap of blue cornflowers on a white ground and this made me want to cry. It was the sleeve of my own bathrobe I was looking at, and my left hand lay pale as a cod at the end of it.

“She's all right now.”

The voice came from a cool, rational region far above my head. For a minute I didn't think there was anything strange about it, and then I thought it was strange. It was a man's voice, and no men were allowed to be in our hotel at any time of the night or day.

“How many others are there?” the voice went on.

I listened with interest. The floor seemed wonderfully solid. It was comforting to know I had fallen and could fall no farther.

“Eleven, I think,” a woman's voice answered. I figured she must belong to the black shoe. “I think there's eleven more of 'um, but one's missin' so there's oney ten.”

“Well, you get this one to bed and I'll take care of the rest.”

I heard a hollow boomp boomp in my right ear that grew fainter and fainter. Then a door opened in the distance and there were voices and groans, and the door shut again.

Two hands slid under my armpits and the woman's voice said, “Come, come, lovey, we'll make it yet,” and I felt myself being half lifted, and slowly the doors began to move by, one by one, until we came to an open door and went in.

The sheet on my bed was folded back, and the woman helped me lie down and covered me up to the chin and rested for a minute in the bedside armchair, fanning herself with one plump, pink hand. She wore gilt-rimmed spectacles and a white nurse's cap.

“Who are you?” I asked in a fault voice.

“I'm the hotel nurse.”

“What's the matter with me?”

“Poisoned,” she said briefly. “Poisoned, the whole lot of you. I never seen anythin' like it. Sick here, sick there, whatever have you young ladies been stuffin' yourselves with?”

“Is everybody else sick too?” I asked with some hope.

“The whole of your lot,” she affirmed with relish. “Sick as dogs and cryin' for ma.”

The room hovered around me with great gentleness, as if the chairs and the tables and the walls were withholding their weight out of sympathy for my sudden frailty.

“The doctor's given you an injection,” the nurse said from the doorway. “You'll sleep now.”

And the door took her place like a sheet of blank paper, and then a larger sheet of paper took the place of the door, and I drifted toward it and smiled myself to sleep.

Somebody was standing by my pillow with a white cup.

“Drink this,” they said.

I shook my head. The pillow crackled like a wad of straw.

“Drink this and you'll feel better.”

A thick white china cup was lowered under my nose. In the wan light that might have been evening and might have been dawn I contemplated the clean amber liquid. Pads of butter floated on the surface and a faint chickeny aroma fumed up to my nostrils.

My eyes moved tentatively to the skirt behind the cup. “Betsy,” I said.

“Betsy nothing, it's me.”

I raised my eyes then, and saw Doreen's head silhouetted against the paling window, her blonde hair lit at the tips from behind like a halo of gold. Her face was in shadow, so I couldn't make out her expression, but I felt a sort of expert tenderness flowing from the ends of her fingers. She might have been Betsy or my mother or a fern-scented nurse.

I bent my head and took a sip of the broth. I thought my mouth must be made of sand. I took another sip and then another and another until the cup was empty.

I felt purged and holy and ready for a new life.

Doreen set the cup on the windowsill and lowered herself into the armchair. I noticed that she made no move to take out a cigarette, and as she was a chain smoker this surprised me.

“Well, you almost died,” she said finally.

“I guess it was all that caviar.”

“Caviar nothing! It was the crabmeat. They did tests on it and it was chock-full of ptomaine.”

I had a vision of the celestially white kitchens of Ladies' Day stretching into infinity. I saw avocado pear after avocado pear being stuffed with crabmeat and mayonnaise and photographed under brilliant lights. I saw the delicate, pink-mottled claw meat poking seductively through its blanket of mayonnaise and the bland yellow pear cup with its rim of alligator-green cradling the whole mess.

Poison.

“Who did tests?” I thought the doctor might have pumped somebody's stomach and then analyzed what he found in his hotel laboratory.

“Those dodos on Ladies' Day. As soon as you all started keeling over like ninepins somebody called into the office and the office called across to Ladies' Day and they did tests on everything left over from the big lunch. Ha!”

“Ha!” I echoed hollowly. It was good to have Doreen back.

“They sent presents,” she added. “They're in a big carton out in the hall.”

“How did they get here so fast?”

“Special express delivery, what do you think? They can't afford to have the lot of you running around saying you got poisoned at Ladies' Day. You could sue them for every penny they own if you just knew some smart law man.”

“What are the presents?” I began to feel if it was a good enough present I wouldn't mind about what happened, because I felt so pure as a result.

“Nobody's opened the box yet, they're all out flat. I'm supposed to be carting soup in to everybody, seeing as I'm the only one on my feet, but I brought you yours first.”

“See what the present is,” I begged. Then I remembered and said, “I've a present for you as well.”

Doreen went out into the hall. I could hear her rustling around for a minute and then the sound of paper tearing. Finally she came back carrying a thick book with a glossy cover and people's names printed all over it.

“The Thirty Best Short Stories of the Year.” She dropped the book in my lap. “There's eleven more of them out there in that box. I suppose they thought it'd give you something to read while you were sick.” She paused. “Where's mine?”

I fished in my pocketbook and handed Doreen the mirror with her name and the daisies on it. Doreen looked at me and I looked at her and we both burst out laughing.

“You can have my soup if you want,” she said. “They put twelve soups on the tray by mistake and Lenny and I stuffed down so many hotdogs while we were waiting for the rain to stop I couldn't eat another mouthful.”

“Bring it in,” I said. “I'm starving.”

Five

At seven the next morning the telephone rang.

Slowly I swam up from the bottom of a black sleep. I already had a telegram from Jay Cee stuck in my mirror, telling me not to bother to come in to work but to rest for a day and get completely well, and how sorry she was about the bad crabmeat, so I couldn't imagine who would be calling.

I reached out and hitched the receiver onto my pillow so the mouthpiece rested on my collarbone and the earpiece lay on my shoulder.

“Hello?”

A man's voice said, “Is that Miss Esther Greenwood?” I thought I detected a slight foreign accent.

“It certainly is,” I said.

“This is Constantin Something-or-Other.”

I couldn't make out the last name, but it was full of S's and K's. I didn't know any Constantin, but I hadn't the heart to say so.

Then I remembered Mrs. Willard and her simultaneous interpreter.

“Of course, of course!” I cried, sitting up and clutching the phone to me with both hands.

I'd never have given Mrs.Willard credit for introducing me to a man named Constantin.

I collected men with interesting names. I already knew a Socrates. He was tall and ugly and intellectual and the son of some big Greek movie producer in Hollywood, but also a Catholic, which ruined it for both of us. In addition to Socrates, I knew a White Russian named Attila at the Boston School of Business Administration.

Gradually I realized that Constantin was trying to arrange a meeting for us later in the day.

“Would you like to see the UN this afternoon?”

“I can already see the UN,” I told him, with a little hysterical giggle.

He seemed nonplussed.

“I can see it from my window.” I thought perhaps my English was a touch too fast for him.

There was a silence.

Then he said, “Maybe you would like a bite to eat afterward.”

I detected the vocabulary of Mrs. Willard and my heart sank. Mrs. Willard always invited you for a bite to eat. I remembered that this man had been a guest at Mrs.Willard's house when he first came to America—Mrs. Willard had one of these arrangements where you open your house to foreigners and then when you go abroad they open their houses to you.

I now saw quite clearly that Mrs.Willard had simply traded her open house in Russia for my bite to eat in New York.

“Yes, I would like a bite to eat,” I said stiffly. “What time will you come?”

“I'll call for you in my car about two. It's the Amazon, isn't it?”

“Yes.”

“Ah, I know where that is.”

For a moment I thought his tone was laden with special meaning, and then I figured that probably some of the girls at the Amazon were secretaries at the UN and maybe he had taken one of them out at one time. I let him hang up first, and then I hung up and lay back in the pillows, feeling grim.

There I went again, building up a glamorous picture of a man who would love me passionately the minute he met me, and all out of a few prosy nothings. A duty tour of the UN and a post-UN sandwich!

I tried to jack up my morale.

Probably Mrs.Willard's simultaneous interpreter would be short and ugly and I would come to look down on him in the end the way I looked down on Buddy Willard. This thought gave me a certain satisfaction. Because I did look down on Buddy Willard, and although everybody still thought I would marry him when he came out of the TB place, I knew I would never marry him if he were the last man on earth.

Buddy Willard was a hypocrite.

Of course, I didn't know he was a hypocrite at first. I thought he was the most wonderful boy I'd ever seen. I'd adored him from a distance for five years before he even looked at me, and then there was a beautiful time when I still adored him and he started looking at me, and then just as he was looking at me more and more I discovered quite by accident what an awful hypocrite he was, and now he wanted me to marry him and I hated his guts.

The worst part of it was I couldn't come straight out and tell him what I thought of him, because he caught TB before I could do that, and now I had to humor him along till he got well again and could take the unvarnished truth.

I decided not to go down to the cafeteria for breakfast. It would only mean getting dressed, and what was the point of getting dressed if you were staying in bed for the morning? I could have called down and asked for a breakfast tray in my room, I guess, but then I would have to tip the person who brought it up and I never knew how much to tip. I'd had some very unsetting experiences trying to tip people in New York.

When I first arrived at the Amazon a dwarfish, bald man in a bellhop's uniform carried my suitcase up in the elevator and unlocked my room for me. Of course I rushed immediately to the window and looked out to see what the view was. After a while I was aware of this bellhop turning on the hot and cold taps in the washbowl and saying “This is the hot and this is the cold” and switching on the radio and telling me all the names of all the New York stations and I began to get uneasy, so I kept my back to him and said firmly, “Thank you for bringing up my suitcase.”

“Thank you thank you thank you. Ha!” he said in a very nasty insinuating tone, and before I could wheel round to see what had come over him he was gone, shutting the door behind him with a rude slam.

Later, when I told Doreen about his curious behavior, she said, “You ninny, he wanted his tip.”

I asked how much I should have given and she said a quarter at least and thirty-five cents if the suitcase was too heavy. Now I could have carried that suitcase to my room perfectly well by myself, only the bellhop seemed so eager to do it that I let him. I thought that sort of service came along with what you paid for your hotel room.

I hate handing over money to people for doing what I could just as easily do myself, it makes me nervous.

Doreen said ten percent was what you should tip a person, but I somehow never had the right change and I'd have felt awfully silly giving somebody half a dollar and saying, “Fifteen cents of this is a tip for you, please give me thirty-five cents back.”

The first time I took a taxi in New York I tipped the driver ten cents. The fare was a dollar, so I thought ten cents was exactly right and gave the driver my dime with a little flourish and a smile. But he only held it in the palm of his hand and stared and stared at it, and when I stepped out of the cab, hoping I had not handed him a Canadian dime by mistake, he started yelling, “Lady, I gotta live like you and everybody else,” in a loud voice which scared me so much I broke into a run. Luckily he was stopped at a traffic light or I think he would have driven along beside me yelling in that embarrassing way.

When I asked Doreen about this she said the tipping percentage might well have risen from ten to fifteen percent since she was last in New York. Either that, or that particular cabdriver was an out-and-out louse.

I reached for the book the people from Ladies' Day had sent.

When I opened it a card fell out. The front of the card showed a poodle in a flowered bedjacket sitting in a poodle basket with a sad face, and the inside of the card showed the poodle lying down in the basket with a smile, sound asleep under an embroidered sampler that said, “You'll get well best with lots and lots of rest.” At the bottom of the card somebody had written, “Get well quick! from all of your good friends at Ladies' Day,” in lavender ink.

I flipped through one story after another until finally I came to a story about a fig tree.

This fig grew on a green lawn between the house of a Jewish man and a convent, and the Jewish man and a beautiful dark nun kept meeting at the tree to pick the ripe figs, until one day they saw an egg hatching in a bird's nest on a branch of the tree, and as they watched the little bird peck its way out of the egg, they touched the backs of their hands together, and then the nun didn't come out to pick figs with the Jewish man any more but a mean-faced Catholic kitchen maid came to pick them instead and counted up the figs the man picked after they were both through to be sure he hadn't picked any more than she had, and the man was furious.

I thought it was a lovely story, especially the part about the fig tree in winter under the snow and then the fig tree in spring with all the green fruit. I felt sorry when I came to the last page. I wanted to crawl in between those black lines of print the way you crawl through a fence, and go to sleep under that beautiful big green fig tree.

It seemed to me Buddy Willard and I were like that Jewish man and that nun, although of course we weren't Jewish or Catholic but Unitarian. We had met together under our own imaginary fig tree, and what we had seen wasn't a bird coming out of an egg but a baby coming out of a woman, and then something awful happened and we went our separate ways.

As I lay there in my white hotel bed feeling lonely and weak, I thought I was up in that sanatorium in the Adirondacks, and I felt like a heel of the worst sort. In his letters Buddy kept telling me how he was reading poems by a poet who was also a doctor and how he'd found out about some famous dead Russian short-story writer who had been a doctor too, so maybe doctors and writers could get along fine after all.

Now this was a very different tune from what Buddy Willard had been singing all the two years we were getting to know each other. I remember the day he smiled at me and said, “Do you know what a poem is, Esther?”

“No, what?” I said.

“A piece of dust.” And he looked so proud of having thought of this that I just stared at his blond hair and his blue eyes and his white teeth—he had very long, strong white teeth —and said, “I guess so.”

It was only in the middle of New York a whole year later that I finally thought of an answer to that remark.

I spent a lot of time having imaginary conversations with Buddy Willard. He was a couple of years older than I was and very scientific, so he could always prove things. When I was with him I had to work to keep my head above water.

These conversations I had in my mind usually repeated the beginnings of conversations I'd really had with Buddy, only they finished with me answering him back quite sharply, instead of just sitting around and saying, “I guess so.”

Now, lying on my back in bed, I imagined Buddy saying, “Do you know what a poem is, Esther?”

“No, what?” I would say.

“A piece of dust.”

Then just as he was smiling and starting to look proud, I would say, “So are the cadavers you cut up. So are the people you think you're curing. They're dust as dust as dust. I reckon a good poem lasts a whole lot longer than a hundred of those people put together.”

And of course Buddy wouldn't have any answer to that, because what I said was true. People were made of nothing so much as dust, and I couldn't see that doctoring all that dust was a bit better than writing poems people would remember and repeat to themselves when they were unhappy or sick and couldn't sleep.

My trouble was I took everything Buddy Willard told me as the honest-to-God truth. I remember the first night he kissed me. It was after the Yale Junior Prom.

It was strange, the way Buddy had invited me to that prom.

He popped into my house out of the blue one Christmas vacation, wearing a thick white turtleneck sweater and looking so handsome I could hardly stop staring, and said, “I might drop over to see you at college some day, all right?”

I was flabbergasted. I only saw Buddy at church on Sundays when we were both home from college, and then at a distance, and I couldn't figure what had put it into his head to run over and see me—he had run the two miles between our houses for cross-country practice, he said.

Of course, our mothers were good friends. They had gone to school together and then both married their professors and settled down in the same town, but Buddy was always off on a scholarship at prep school in the fall or earning money by fighting blister rust in Montana in the summer, so our mothers being old school chums really didn't matter a bit.

After this sudden visit I didn't hear a word from Buddy until one fine Saturday morning in early March. I was up in my room at college, studying about Peter the Hermit and Walter the Penniless for my history exam on the crusades the coming Monday, when the hall phone rang.

Usually people are supposed to take turns answering the hall phone, but as I was the only freshman on a floor with all seniors they made me answer it most of the time. I waited a minute to see if anybody would beat me to it. Then I figured everybody was probably out playing squash or away on weekends, so I answered it myself.

“Is that you, Esther?” the girl on watch downstairs said, and when I said yes, she said, “There's a man to see you.”

I was surprised to hear this, because of all the blind dates I'd had that year not one called me up again for a second date. I just didn't have any luck. I hated coming downstairs sweaty-handed and curious every Saturday night and having some senior introduce me to her aunt's best friend's son and finding some pale, mushroomy fellow with protruding ears or buck teeth or a bad leg. I didn't think I deserved it. After all, I wasn't crippled in any way, I just studied too hard, I didn't know when to stop.

Well, I combed my hair and put on some more lipstick and took my history book—so I could say I was on my way to the library if it turned out to be somebody awful—and went down, and there was Buddy Willard leaning against the mail table in a khaki zipper jacket and blue dungarees and frayed gray sneakers and grinning up at me.

“I just came over to say hello,” he said.

I thought it odd he should come all the way up from Yale even hitchhiking, as he did, to save money, just to say hello.

“Hello,” I said. “Let's go out and sit on the porch.”

I wanted to go out on the porch because the girl on watch was a nosy senior and eyeing me curiously. She obviously thought Buddy had made a big mistake.

We sat side by side in two wicker rocking chairs. The sunlight was clean and windless and almost hot.

“I can't stay for more than a few minutes,” Buddy said.

“Oh, come on, stay for lunch,” I said.

“Oh, I can't do that. I'm up here for the Sophomore Prom with Joan.”

I felt like a prize idiot.

“How is Joan?” I asked coldly.

Joan Gilling came from our home town and went to our church and was a year ahead of me at college. She was a big wheel—president of her class and a physics major and the college hockey champion. She always made me feel squirmy with her starey pebble-colored eyes and her gleaming tombstone teeth and her breathy voice. She was big as a horse, too. I began to think Buddy had pretty poor taste.

“Oh, Joan,” he said. “She asked me up to this dance two months ahead of time and her mother asked my mother if I would take her, so what could I do?”

“Well, why did you say you'd take her if you didn't want to?” I asked meanly.

“Oh, I like Joan. She never cares whether you spend any money on her or not and she enjoys doing things out-of-doors. The last time she came down to Yale for house weekend we went on a bicycle trip to East Rock and she's the only girl I haven't had to push up hills. Joan's all right.”

I went cold with envy. I had never been to Yale, and Yale was the place all the seniors in my house liked to go best on weekends. I decided to expect nothing from Buddy Willard. If you expect nothing from somebody you are never disappointed.

“You better go and find Joan then,” I said in a matter-of-fact voice. “I've a date coming any minute and he won't like seeing me sitting around with you.”

“A date?” Buddy looked surprised. “Who is it?”

“It's two,” I said, “Peter the Hermit and Walter the Penniless.”

Buddy didn't say anything, so I said, “Those are their nicknames.”

Then I added, “They're from Dartmouth.”

I guess Buddy never read much history, because his mouth stiffened. He swung up from the wicker rocking chair and gave it a sharp little unnecessary push. Then he dropped a pale blue envelope with a Yale crest into my lap.

“Here's a letter I meant to leave for you if you weren't in. There's a question in it you can answer by mail. I don't feel like asking you about it right now.”

After Buddy had gone I opened the letter. It was a letter inviting me to the Yale Junior Prom.

I was so surprised I let out a couple of yips and ran into the house shouting, “I'm going I'm going I'm going.” After the bright white sun on the porch it looked pitch dark in there, and I couldn't make out a thing. I found myself hugging the senior on watch. When she heard I was going to the Yale Junior Prom she treated me with amazement and respect.

Oddly enough, things changed in the house after that. The seniors on my floor started speaking to me and every now and then one of them would answer the phone quite spontaneously and nobody made any more nasty loud remarks outside my door about people wasting their golden college days with their noses stuck in a book.

Well, all during the Junior Prom Buddy treated me like a friend or a cousin.

We danced about a mile apart the whole time, until during “Auld Lang Syne” he suddenly rested his chin on the top of my head as if he were very tired. Then in the cold, black, three-o'clock wind we walked very slowly the five miles back to the house where I was sleeping in the living room on a couch that was too short because it only cost fifty cents a night instead of two dollars like most of the other places with proper beds.

I felt dull and flat and full of shattered visions.

I had imagined Buddy would fall in love with me that weekend and that I wouldn't have to worry about what I was doing on any more Saturday nights the rest of the year. Just as we approached the house where I was staying Buddy said, “Let's go up to the chemistry lab.”

I was aghast. “The chemistry lab?”

“Yes.” Buddy reached for my hand. “There's a beautiful view up there behind the chemistry lab.”

And sure enough, there was a sort of hilly place behind the chemistry lab from which you could see the lights of a couple of houses in New Haven.

I stood pretending to admire them while Buddy got a good footing on the rough soil. While he kissed me I kept my eyes open and tried to memorize the spacing of the house lights so I would never forget them.

Finally Buddy stepped back. “Wow!” he said.

“Wow what?” I said, surprised. It had been a dry, uninspiring little kiss, and I remember thinking it was too bad both our mouths were so chapped from walking five miles in that cold wind.

“Wow, it makes me feel terrific to kiss you.”

I modestly didn't say anything.

“I guess you go out with a lot of boys,” Buddy said then.

“Well, I guess I do.” I thought I must have gone out with a different boy for every week in the year.

“Well, I have to study a lot.”

“So do I,” I put in hastily. “I have to keep my scholarship after all.”

“Still, I think I could manage to see you every third weekend.”

“That's nice.” I was almost fainting and dying to get back to college and tell everybody.

Buddy kissed me again in front of the house steps, and the next fall, when his scholarship to medical school came through, I went there to see him instead of to Yale and it was there I found out how he had fooled me all those years and what a hypocrite he was.

I found out on the day we saw the baby born.

Six

I had kept begging Buddy to show me some really interesting hospital sights, so one Friday I cut all my classes and came down for a long weekend and he gave me the works.

I started out by dressing in a white coat and sitting on a tall stool in a room with four cadavers, while Buddy and his friends cut them up. These cadavers were so unhuman-looking they didn't bother me a bit. They had stiff, leathery, purple-black skin and they smelt like old pickle jars.

After that, Buddy took me out into the hall where they had some big glass bottles full of babies that had died before they were born. The baby in the first bottle had a large white head bent over a tiny curled-up body the size of a frog. The baby in the next bottle was bigger and the baby next to that one was bigger still and the baby in the last bottle was the size of a normal baby and he seemed to be looking at me and smiling a little piggy smile.

I was quite proud of the calm way I stared at all these gruesome things. The only time I jumped was when I leaned my elbow on Buddy's cadaver's somach to watch him dissect a lung. After a minute or two I felt this burning sensation in my elbow and it occurred to me the cadaver might just be half alive since it was still warm, so I leapt off my stool with a small exclamation. Then Buddy explained the burning was only from the pickling fluid, and I sat back in my old position.

In the hour before lunch Buddy took me to a lecture on sickle-cell anemia and some other depressing diseases, where they wheeled sick people out onto the platform and asked them questions and then wheeled them off and showed colored slides.

One slide I remember showed a beautiful laughing girl with a black mole on her cheek. “Twenty days after that mole appeared the girl was dead,” the doctor said, and everybody went very quiet for a minute and then the bell rang, so I never really found out what the mole was or why the girl died.

In the afternoon we went to see a baby born.

First we found a linen closet in the hospital corridor where Buddy took out a white mask for me to wear and some gauze.

A tall fat medical student, big as Sydney Greenstreet, lounged nearby, watching Buddy wind the gauze round and round my head until my hair was completely covered and only my eyes peered out over the white mask.

The medical student gave an unpleasant little snicker. “At least your mother loves you,” he said.

I was so busy thinking how very fat he was and how unfortunate it must be for a man and especially a young man to be fat, because what woman could stand leaning over that big stomach to kiss him, that I didn't immediately realize what this student had said to me was an insult. By the time I figured he must consider himself quite a fine fellow and had thought up a cutting remark about how only a mother loves a fat man, he was gone.

Buddy was examining a queer wooden plaque on the wall with a row of holes in it, starting from a hole about the size of a silver dollar and ending with one the size of a dinner plate.

“Fine, fine,” he said to me. “There's somebody about to have a baby this minute.”

At the door of the delivery room stood a thin, stoop-shouldered medical student Buddy knew.

“Hello, Will,” Buddy said. “Who's on the job?”

“I am,” Will said gloomily, and I noticed little drops of sweat beading his high pale forehead. “I am, and it's my first.”

Buddy told me Will was a third-year man and had to deliver eight babies before he could graduate.

Then he noticed a bustle at the far end of the hall and some men in lime-green coats and skull caps and a few nurses came moving toward us in a ragged procession wheeling a trolley with a big white lump on it.

“You oughtn't to see this,” Will muttered in my ear. “You'll never want to have a baby if you do. They oughtn't to let women watch. It'll be the end of the human race.”

Buddy and I laughed, and then Buddy shook Will's hand and we all went into the room.

I was so struck by the sight of the table where they were lifting the woman I didn't say a word. It looked like some awful torture table, with these metal stirrups sticking up in mid-air at one end and all sorts of instruments and wires and tubes I couldn't make out properly at the other.

Buddy and I stood together by the window, a few feet away from the woman, where we had a perfect view.

The woman's stomach stuck up so high I couldn't see her face or the upper part of her body at all. She seemed to have nothing but an enormous spider-fat stomach and two little ugly spindly legs propped in the high stirrups, and all the time the baby was being born she never stopped making this unhuman whooing noise.

Later Buddy told me the woman was on a drug that would make her forget she'd had any pain and that when she swore and groaned she really didn't know what she was doing because she was in a kind of twilight sleep.

I thought it sounded just like the sort of drug a man would invent. Here was a woman interrible pain, obviously feeling every bit of it or she wouldn't groan like that, and she would go straight home and start another baby, because the drug would make her forget how bad the pain had been, when all the time, in some secret part of her, that long, blind, doorless and windowless corridor of pain was waiting to open up and shut her in again.

The head doctor, who was supervising Will, kept saying to the woman, “Push down, Mrs. Tomolillo, push down, that's a good girl, push down,” and finally through the split, shaven place between her legs, lurid with disinfectant, I saw a dark fuzzy thing appear.

“The baby's head,” Buddy whispered under cover of the woman's groans.

But the baby's head stuck for some reason, and the doctor told Will he'd have to make a cut. I heard the scissors close on the woman's skin like cloth and the blood began to run down—a fierce, bright red. Then all at once the baby seemed to pop out into Will's hands, the color of a blue pluto and floured with white stuff and streaked with blood, and Will kept saying, “I'm going to drop it, I'm going to drop it, I'm going to drop it,” in a terrified voice.

“No, you're not,” the doctor said, and took the baby out of Will's hands and started massaging it, and the blue color went away and the baby started to cry in a lorn, croaky voice and I could see it was a boy.

The first thing that baby did was pee in the doctor's face. I told Buddy later I didn't see how that was possible, but he said it was quite possible, though unusual, to see something like that happen.

As soon as the baby was born the people in the room divided up into two groups, the nurses tying a metal dog tag on the baby's wrist and swabbing its eyes with cotton on the end of a stick and wrapping it up and putting it in a canvas-sided cot, while the doctor and Will started sewing up the woman's cut with a needle and a long thread.

I think somebody said, “It's a boy, Mrs. Tomolillo,” but the woman didn't answer or raise her head.

“Well, how was it?” Buddy asked with a satisfied expression as we walked across the green quadrangle to his room.

“Wonderful,” I said. “I could see something like that every day.”

I didn't feel up to asking him if there were any other ways to have babies. For some reason the most important thing to me was actually seeing the baby come out of you yourself and making sure it was yours. I thought if you had to have all that pain anyway you might just as well stay awake.

I had always imagined myself hitching up on to my elbows on the delivery table after it was all over—dead white, of course, with no makeup and from the awful ordeal, but smiling and radiant, with my hair down to my waist, and reaching out for my first little squirmy child and saying its name, whatever it was.

“Why was it all covered with flour?” I asked then, to keep the conversation going, and Buddy told me about the waxy stuff that guarded the baby's skin.

When we were back in Buddy's room, which reminded me of nothing so much as a monk's cell, with its bare walls and bare bed and bare floor and the desk loaded with Gray's Anatomy and other thick gruesome books, Buddy lit a candle and uncorked a bottle of Dubonnet. Then we lay down side by side on the bed and Buddy sipped his wine while I read aloud “somewhere I have never travelled” and other poems from a book I'd brought.

Buddy said he figured there must be something in poetry if a girl like me spent all her days over it, so each time we met I read him some poetry and explained to him what I found in it. It was Buddy's idea. He always arranged our weekends so we'd never regret wasting our time in any way. Buddy's father was a teacher, and I think Buddy could have been a teacher as well, he was always trying to explain things to me and introduce me to new knowledge.

Suddenly, after I finished a poem, he said, “Esther, have you ever seen a man?”

The way he said it I knew he didn't mean a regular man or a man in general, I knew he meant a man naked.

“No,” I said. “Only statues.”

“Well, don't you think you would like to see me?”

I didn't know what to say. My mother and my grandmother had started hinting around to me a lot lately about what a fine, clean boy Buddy Willard was, coming from such a fine, clean family, and how everybody at church thought he was a model person, so kind to his parents and to older people, as well as so athletic and so handsome and so intelligent.

All I'd heard about, really, was how fine and clean Buddy was and how he was the kind of a person a girl should stay fine and clean for. So I didn't really see the harm in anything Buddy would think up to do.

“Well, all right, I guess so,” I said.

I stared at Buddy while he unzipped his chino pants and took them off and laid them on a chair and then took off his underpants that were made of something like nylon fishnet.

“They're cool,” he explained, “and my mother says they wash easily.”

Then he just stood there in front of me and I kept on staring at him. The only thing I could think of was turkey neck and turkey gizzards and I felt very depressed.

Buddy seemed hurt I didn't say anything. “I think you ought to get used to me like this,” he said. “Now let me see you.”

But undressing in front of Buddy suddenly appealed to me about as much as having my Posture Picture taken at college, where you have to stand naked in front of a camera, knowing all the time that a picture of you stark naked, both full view and side view, is going into the college gym files to be marked A B C or D depending on how straight you are.

“Oh, some other time,” I said.

“All right.” Buddy got dressed again.

Then we kissed and hugged a while and I felt a little better. I drank the rest of the Dubonnet and sat cross-legged at the end of Buddy's bed and asked for a comb. I began to comb my hair down over my face so Buddy couldn't see it. Suddenly I said, “Have you ever had an affair with anyone, Buddy?”

I don't know what made me say it, the words just popped out of my mouth. I never thought for one minute that Buddy Willard would have an affair with anyone. I expected him to say, “No, I have been saving myself for when I get married to somebody pure and a virgin like you.”

But Buddy didn't say anything, he just turned pink.

“Well, have you?”

“What do you mean, an affair?” Buddy asked then in a hollow voice.

“You know, have you ever gone to bed with anyone?” I kept rhythmically combing the hair down over the side of my face nearest to Buddy, and I could feel the little electric filaments clinging to my hot cheeks and I wanted to shout, “Stop, stop, don't tell me, don't say anything.” But I didn't, I just kept still.

“Well, yes, I have,” Buddy said finally.

I almost fell over. From the first night Buddy Willard kissed me and said I must go out with a lot of boys, he made me feel I was much more sexy and experienced than he was and that everything he did like hugging and kissing and petting was simply what I made him feel like doing out of the blue, he couldn't help it and didn't know how it came about.

Now I saw he had only been pretending all this time to be so innocent.

“Tell me about it.” I combed my hair slowly over and over, feeling the teeth of the comb dig into my cheek at every stroke. “Who was it?”

Buddy seemed relieved I wasn't angry. He even seemed relieved to have somebody to tell about how he was seduced.

Of course, somebody had seduced Buddy, Buddy hadn't started it and it wasn't really his fault. It was this waitress at the hotel he worked at as a busboy the last summer at Cape Cod. Buddy had noticed her staring at him queerly and shoving her breasts up against him in the confusion of the kitchen, so finally one day he asked her what the trouble was and she looked him straight in the eye and said, “I want you.”

“Served up with parsley?” Buddy had laughed innocently.

“No,” she had said. “Some night.”

And that's how Buddy had lost his pureness and his virginity.

At first I thought he must have slept with the waitress only the once, but when I asked how many times, just to make sure, he said he couldn't remember but a couple of times a week for the rest of the summer. I multiplied three by ten and got thirty, which seemed beyond all reason.

After that something in me just froze up.

Back at college I started asking a senior here and a senior there what they would do if a boy they knew suddenly told them he'd slept thirty times with some slutty waitress one summer, smack in the middle of knowing them. But these seniors said most boys were like that and you couldn't honestly accuse them of anything until you were at least pinned or engaged to be married.

Actually, it wasn't the idea of Buddy sleeping with somebody that bothered me. I mean I'd read about all sorts of people sleeping with each other, and if it had been any other boy I would merely have asked him the most interesting details, and maybe gone out and slept with somebody myself just to even things up, and then thought no more about it.

What I couldn't stand was Buddy's pretending I was so sexy and he was so pure, when all the time he'd been having an affair with that tarty waitress and must have felt like laughing in my face.

“What does your mother think about this waitress?” I asked Buddy that weekend.

Buddy was amazingly close to his mother. He was always quoting what she said about the relationship between a man and a woman, and I knew Mrs.Willard was a real fanatic about virginity for men and women both. When I first went to her house for supper she gave me a queer, shrewd, searching look, and I knew she was trying to tell whether I was a virgin or not.

Just as I thought, Buddy was embarrassed. “Mother asked me about Gladys,” he admitted.

“Well, what did you say?”

“I said Gladys was free, white and twenty-one.”

Now I knew Buddy would never talk to his mother as rudely as that for my sake. He was always saying how his mother said, “What a man wants is a mate and what a woman wants is infinite security,” and, “What a man is is an arrow into the future and what a woman is is the place the arrow shoots off from,” until it made me tired.

Every time I tried to argue, Buddy would say his mother still got pleasure out of his father and wasn't that wonderful for people their age, it must mean she really knew what was what.

Well, I had just decided to ditch Buddy Willard for once and for all, not because he'd slept with that waitress but because he didn't have the honest guts to admit it straight off to everybody and face up to it as part of his character, when the phone in the hall rang and somebody said in a little knowing singsong, “It's for you, Esther, it's from Boston.”

I could tell right away something must be wrong, because Buddy was the only person I knew in Boston, and he never called me long distance because it was so much more expensive than letters. Once, when he had a message he wanted me to get almost immediately, he went all round his entry at medical school asking if anybody was driving up to my college that weekend, and sure enough, somebody was, so he gave them a note for me and I got it the same day. He didn't even have to pay for a stamp.

It was Buddy all right. He told me that the annual fall chest X-ray showed he had caught TB and he was going off on a scholarship for medical students who caught TB to a TB place in the Adirondacks. Then he said I hadn't written since that last weekend and he hoped nothing was the matter between us, and would I please try to write him at least once a week and come to visit him at this TB place in my Christmas vacation?

I had never heard Buddy so upset. He was very proud of his perfect health and was always telling me it was psychosomatic when my sinuses blocked up and I couldn't breathe. I thought this an odd attitude for a doctor to have and perhaps he should study to be a psychiatrist instead, but of course I never came right out and said so.

I told Buddy how sorry I was about the TB and promised to write, but when I hung up I didn't feel one bit sorry. I only felt a wonderful relief.

I thought the TB might just be a punishment for living the kind of double life Buddy lived and feeling so superior to people. And I thought how convenient it would be now I didn't have to announce to everybody at college I had broken off with Buddy and start the boring business of blind dates all over again.

I simply told everyone that Buddy had TB and we were practically engaged, and when I stayed in to study on Saturday nights they were extremely kind to me because they thought I was so brave, working the way I did just to hide a broken heart.

Seven

Of course, Constantin was much too short, but in his own way he was handsome, with light brown hair and dark blue eyes and a lively, challenging expression. He could almost have been an American, he was so tan and had such good teeth, but I could tell straight away that he wasn't. He had what no American man I've ever met has had, and that's intuition.

From the start Constantin guessed I wasn't any protégée of Mrs. Willard's. I raised an eyebrow here and dropped a dry little laugh there, and pretty soon we were both openly raking Mrs. Willard over the coals and I thought, “This Constantin won't mind if I'm too tall and don't know enough languages and haven't been to Europe, he'll see through all that stuff to what I really am.”

Constantin drove me to the UN in his old green convertible with cracked, comfortable brown leather seats and the top down. He told me his tan came from playing tennis, and when we were sitting there side by side flying down the streets in the open sun he took my hand and squeezed it, and I felt happier than I had been since I was about nine and running along the hot white beaches with my father the summer before he died.

And while Constantin and I sat in one of those hushed plush auditoriums in the UN, next to a stern muscular Russian girl with no makeup who was a simultaneous interpreter like Constantin, I thought how strange it had never occurred to me before that I was only purely happy until I was nine years old.

After that—in spite of the Girl Scouts and the piano lessons and the water-color lesson sand the dancing lessons and the sailing camp, all of which my mother scrimped to give me, and college, with crewing in the mist before breakfast and blackbottom pies and the little new firecrackers of ideas going off every day—I had never been really happy again.

I stared through the Russian girl in her double-breasted gray suit, rattling off idiom after idiom in her own unknowable tongue—which Constantin said was the most difficult part because the Russians didn't have the same idioms as our idioms—and I wished with all my heart I could crawl into her and spend the rest of my life barking out one idiom after another. It mightn't make me any happier, but it would be one more little pebble of efficiency among all the other pebbles.

Then Constantin and the Russian girl interpreter and the whole bunch of black and white and yellow men arguing down there behind their labeled microphones seemed to move off at a distance. I saw their mouths going up and down without a sound, as if they were sitting on the deck of a departing ship, stranding me in the middle of a huge silence.

I started adding up all the things I couldn't do.

I began with cooking.

My grandmother and my mother were such good cooks that I left everything to them. They were always trying to teach me one dish or another, but I would just look on and say, “Yes, yes, I see,” while the instructions slid through my head like water, and then I'd always spoil what I did so nobody would ask me to do it again.

I remember Jody, my best and only girlfriend at college in my freshman year, making me scrambled eggs at her house one morning. They tasted unusual, and when I asked her if she had put in anything extra, she said cheese and garlic salt. I asked who told her to do that, and she said nobody, she just thought it up. But then, she was practical and a sociology major.

I didn't know shorthand either.

This meant I couldn't get a good job after college. My mother kept telling me nobody wanted a plain English major. But an English major who knew shorthand was something else again. Everybody would want her. She would be in demand among all the up-and-coming young men and she would transcribe letter after thrilling letter.

The trouble was, I hated the idea of serving men in any way. I wanted to dictate my own thrilling letters. Besides, those little shorthand symbols in the book my mother showed me seemed just as bad as let t equal time and let s equal the total distance.

My list grew longer.

I was a terrible dancer. I couldn't carry a tune. I had no sense of balance, and when we had to walk down a narrow board with our hands out and a book on our heads in gym class I always fell over. I couldn't ride a horse or ski, the two things I wanted to do most, because they cost too much money. I couldn't speak German or read Hebrew or write Chinese. I didn't even know where most of the old out-of-the-way countries the UN men in front of me represented fitted in on the map.

For the first time in my life, sitting there in the soundproof heart of the UN building between Constantin who could play tennis as well as simultaneouly interpret and the Russian girl who knew so many idioms, I felt dreadfully inadequate. The trouble was, I had been inadequate all along, I simply hadn't thought about it.

The one thing I was good at was winning scholarships and prizes, and that era was coming to an end.

I felt like a racehorse in a world without racetracks or a champion college footballer suddenly confronted by Wall Street and a business suit, his days of glory shrunk to a little gold cup on his mantel with a date engraved on it like the date on a tombstone.

I saw my life branching out before me like the green fig tree in the story.

From the tip of every branch, like a fat purple fig, a wonderful future beckoned and winked. One fig was a husband and a happy home and children, and another fig was a famous poet and another fig was a brilliant professor, and another fig was Ee Gee, the amazing editor, and another fig was Europe and Africa and South America, and another fig was Constantin and Socrates and Attila and a pack of other lovers with queer names and offbeat professions, and another fig was an Olympic lady crew champion, and beyond and above these figs were many more figs I couldn't quite make out.

I saw myself sitting in the crotch of this fig tree, starving to death, just because I couldn't make up my mind which of the figs I would choose. I wanted each and every one of them, but choosing one meant losing all the rest, and, as I sat there, unable to decide, the figs began to wrinkle and go black, and, one by one, they plopped to the ground at my feet.

Constantin's restaurant smelt of herbs and spices and sour cream. All the time I had been in New York I had never found such a restaurant. I only found those Heavenly Hamburger places, where they serve giant hamburgers and soup-of-the-day and four kinds of fancy cake at a very clean counter facing a long glarey mirror.

To reach this restaurant we had to climb down seven dimly lit steps into a sort of cellar.

Travel posters plastered the smoke-dark walls, like so many picture windows overlooking Swiss lakes and Japanese mountains and African velds, and thick, dusty bottle-candles, that seemed for centuries to have wept their colored waxes red over blue over green in a fine, three-dimensional lace, cast a circle of light round each table where the faces floated, flushed and flamelike themselves.

I don't know what I ate, but I felt immensely better after the first mouthful. It occurred to me that my vision of the fig tree and all the fat figs that withered and fell to earth might well have arisen from the profound void of an empty stomach.

Constantin kept refilling our glasses with a sweet Greek wine that tasted of pine bark, and I found myself telling him how I was going to learn German and go to Europe and be a war correspondent like Maggie Higgins.

I felt so fine by the time we came to the yogurt and strawberry jam that I decided I would let Constantin seduce me.

Ever since Buddy Willard had told me about that waitress I had been thinking I ought to go out and sleep with somebody myself. Sleeping with Buddy wouldn't count, though, because he would still be one person ahead of me, it would have to be with somebody else.

The only boy I ever actually discussed going to bed with was a bitter, hawk-nosed Southerner from Yale, who came up to college one weekend only to find his date had eloped with a taxi driver the day before. As the girl had lived in my house and I was the only one home that particular night, it was my job to cheer him up.

At the local coffee shop, hunched in one of the secretive, high-backed booths with hundreds of people's names gouged into the wood, we drank cup after cup of black coffee and talked frankly about sex.

This boy—his name was Eric—said he thought it disgusting the way all the girls at my college stood around on the porches under the porch lights and in the bushes in plain view, necking madly before the one o'clock curfew, so everybody passing by could see them. A million years of evolution, Eric said bitterly, and what are we? Animals.

Then Eric told me how he had slept with his first woman.

He went to a Southern prep school that specialized in building all-round gentlemen, and by the time you graduated it was an unwritten rule that you had to have known a woman. Known in the Biblical sense, Eric said.

So one Saturday Eric and a few of his classmates took a bus into the nearest city and visited a notorious whorehouse. Eric's whore hadn't even taken off her dress. She was a fat, middle-aged woman with dyed red hair and suspiciously thick lips and rat-colored skin and she wouldn't turn off the light, so he had had her under a fly-spotted twenty-five-watt bulb, and it was nothing like it was cracked up to be. It was boring as going to the toilet.

I said maybe if you loved a woman it wouldn't seem so boring, but Eric said it would be spoiled by thinking this woman too was just an animal like the rest, so if he loved anybody he would never go to bed with her. He'd go to a whore if he had to and keep the woman he loved free of all that dirty business.

It had crossed my mind at the time that Eric might be a good person to go to bed with, since he had already done it and, unlike the usual run of boys, didn't seem dirty-minded or silly when he talked about it. But then Eric wrote me a letter saying he thought he might really be able to love me, I was so intelligent and cynical and yet had such a kind face, surprisingly like his older sister's; so I knew it was no use, I was the type he would never go to bed with, and wrote him I was unfortunately about to marry a childhood sweetheart.

The more I thought about it the better I liked the idea of being seduced by a simultaneous interpreter in New York City. Constantin seemed mature and considerate in every way. There were no people I knew he would want to brag to about it, the way college boys bragged about sleeping with girls in the backs of cars to their roommates or their friends on the basketball team. And there would be a pleasant irony in sleeping with a man Mrs. Willard had introduced me to, as if she were, in a roundabout way, to blame for it.

When Constantin asked if I would like to come up to his apartment to hear some balalaika records I smiled to myself. My mother had always told me never under any circumstances to go with a man to a man's rooms after an evening out, it could mean only the one thing.

“I am very fond of balalaika music,” I said.

Constantin's room had a balcony, and the balcony overlooked the river, and we could hear the hooing of the tugs down in the darkness. I felt moved and tender and perfectly certain about what I was going to do.

I knew I might have a baby, but that thought hung far and dim in the distance and didn't trouble me at all. There was no one hundred percent sure way not to have a baby, it said in an article my mother cut out of the Reader's Digest and mailed to me at college. This article was written by a married woman lawyer with children and called “In Defense of Chastity.”

It gave all the reasons a girl shouldn't sleep with anybody but her husband and then only after they were married.

The main point of the article was that a man's world is different from a woman's world and a man's emotions are different from a woman's emotions and only marriage can bring the two worlds and the two different sets of emotions together properly. My mother said this was something a girl didn't know about till it was too late, so she had to take the advice of people who were already experts, like a married woman.

This woman lawyer said the best men wanted to be pure for their wives, and even if they weren't pure, they wanted to be the ones to teach their wives about sex. Of course they would try to persuade a girl to have sex and say they would marry her later, but as soon as she gave in, they would lose all respect for her and start saying that if she did that with them she would do that with other men and they would end up by making her life miserable.

The woman finished her article by saying better be safe than sorry and besides, there was no sure way of not getting stuck with a baby and then you'd really be in a pickle.

Now the one thing this article didn't seem to me to consider was how a girl felt.

It might be nice to be pure and then to marry a pure man, but what if he suddenly confessed he wasn't pure after we were married, the way Buddy Willard had? I couldn't stand the idea of a woman having to have a single pure life and a man being able to have a double life, one pure and one not.

Finally I decided that if it was so difficult to find a red-blooded intelligent man who was still pure by the time he was twenty-one I might as well forget about staying pure myself and marry somebody who wasn't pure either. Then when he started to make my life miserable I could make his miserable as well.

When I was nineteen, pureness was the great issue.

Instead of the world being divided up into Catholics and Protestants or Republicans and Democrats or white men and black men or even men and women, I saw the world divided into people who had slept with somebody and people who hadn't, and this seemed the only really significant difference between one person and another.

I thought a spectacular change would come over me the day I crossed the boundary line.

I thought it would be the way I'd feel if I ever visited Europe. I'd come home, and if I looked closely into the mirror I'd be able to make out a little white Alp at the back of my eye. Now I thought that if I looked into the mirror tomorrow I'd see a doll-size Constantin sitting in my eye and smiling out at me.

Well, for about an hour we lounged on Constantin's balcony in two separate slingback chairs with the victrola playing and the balalaika records stacked between us. A faint milky light diffused from the street lights or the half moon or the cars or the stars, I couldn't tell what, but apart from holding my hand Constantin showed no desire to seduce me whatsoever.

I asked if he was engaged or had any special girlfriend, thinking maybe that's what was the matter, but he said no, he made a point of keeping clear of such attachments.

At last I felt a powerful drowsiness drifting through my veins from all the pine-bark wine I had drunk.

“I think I'll go in and lie down,” I said.

I strolled casually into the bedroom and stooped over to nudge off my shoes. The clean bed bobbed before me like a safe boat. I stretched full length and shut my eyes. Then I heard Constantin sigh and come in from the balcony. One by one his shoes clonked on to the floor, and he lay down by my side.

I looked at him secretly from under a fall of hair.

He was lying on his back, his hands under his head, staring at the ceiling. The starched white sleeves of his shirt, rolled up to the elbows, glimmered eerily in the half dark and his tan skin seemed almost black. I thought he must be the most beautiful man I'd ever seen.

I thought if only I had a keen, shapely bone structure to my face or could discuss politics shrewdly or was a famous writer Constantin might find me interesting enough to sleep with.

And then I wondered if as soon as he came to like me he would sink into ordinariness,and if as soon as he came to love me I would find fault after fault, the way I did with Buddy Willard and the boys before him.

The same thing happened over and over:

I would catch sight of some flawless man off in the distance, but as soon as he moved closer I immediately saw he wouldn't do at all.

That's one of the reasons I never wanted to get married. The last thing I wanted was infinite security and to be the place an arrow shoots off from. I wanted change and excitement and to shoot off in all directions myself, like the colored arrows from a Fourth of July rocket.

I woke to the sound of rain.

It was pitch dark. After a while I deciphered the faint outlines of an unfamiliar window. Every so often a beam of light appeared out of thin air, traversed the wall like a ghostly, exploratory finger, and slid off into nothing again.

Then I heard the sound of somebody breathing.

At first I thought it was only myself, and that I was lying in the dark in my hotel room after being poisoned. I held my breath, but the breathing kept on.

A green eye glowed on the bed beside me. It was divided into quarters like a compass. I reached out slowly and dosed my hand on it. I lifted it up. With it came an arm, heavy as a dead man's, but warm with sleep.

Constantin's watch said three o'clock.

He was lying in his shirt and trousers and stocking feet just as I had left him when I dropped asleep, and as my eyes grew used to the darkness I made out his pale eyelids and his straight nose and his tolerant, shapely mouth, but they seemed insubstantial, as if drawn on fog. For a few minutes I leaned over, studying him. I had never fallen asleep beside a man before.

I tried to imagine what it would be like if Constantin were my husband.

It would mean getting up at seven and cooking him eggs and bacon and toast and coffee and dawdling about in my nightgown and curlers after he'd left for work to wash up the dirty plates and make the bed, and then when he came home after a lively, fascinating day he'd expect a big dinner, and I'd spend the evening washing up even more dirty plates till I fell into bed, utterly exhausted.

This seemed a dreary and wasted life for a girl with fifteen years of straight A's, but I knew that's what marriage was like, because cook and clean and wash was just what Buddy Willard's mother did from morning till night, and she was the wife of a university professor and had been a private school teacher herself.

Once when I visited Buddy I found Mrs.Willard braiding a rug out of strips of wool from Mr. Willard's old suits. She'd spent weeks on that rug, and I had admired the tweedy browns and greens and blues patterning the braid, but after Mrs. Willard was through, instead of hanging the rug on the wall the way I would have done, she put it down in place of her kitchen mat, and in a few days it was soiled and dull and indistinguishable from any mat you could buy for under a dollar in the five and ten.

And I knew that in spite of all the roses and kisses and restaurant dinners a man showered on a woman before he married her, what he secretly wanted when the wedding service ended was for her to flatten out underneath his feet like Mrs. Willard's kitchenmat.

Hadn't my own mother told me that as soon as she and my father left Reno on their honeymoon—my father had been married before, so he needed a divorce—my father said to her, “Whew, that's a relief, now we can stop pretending and be ourselves?” —and from that day on my mother never had a minute's peace.

I also remembered Buddy Willard saying in a sinister, knowing way that after I had children I would feel differently, I wouldn't want to write poems any more. So I began to think maybe it was true that when you were married and had children it was like being brainwashed, and afterward you went about numb as a slave in some private, totalitarian state.

As I stared down at Constantin the way you stare down at a bright, unattainable pebble at the bottom of a deep well, his eyelids lifted and he looked through me, and his eyes were full of love. I watched dumbly as a shutter of recognition clicked across the blur of tenderness and the wide pupils went glossy and depthless as patent leather.

Constantin sat up, yawning. “What time is it?”

“Three,” I said in a flat voice. “I better go home. I have to be at work first thing in the morning.”

“I'll drive you.”

As we sat back to back on our separate sides of the bed fumbling with our shoes in the horrid cheerful white light of the bed lamp, I sensed Constantin turn round. “Is your hair always like that?”

“Like what?”

He didn't answer but reached over and put his hand at the root of my hair and ran his fingers out slowly to the tip ends like a comb. A little electric shock flared through me and I sat quite still. Ever since I was small I loved feeling somebody comb my hair. It made me go all sleepy and peaceful.

“Ah, I know what it is,” Constantin said. “You've just washed it.”

And he bent to lace up his tennis shoes.

An hour later I lay in my hotel bed, listening to the rain. It didn't even sound like rain, it sounded like a tap running. The ache in the middle of my left shin bone came to life, and I abandoned any hope of sleep before seven, when my radio-alarm clock would rouse me with its hearty renderings of Sousa.

Every time it rained the old leg-break seemed to remember itself, and what it remembered was a dull hurt.

Then I thought, “Buddy Willard made me break that leg.”

Then I thought, “No, I broke it myself. I broke it on purpose to pay myself back for being such a heel.”

Eight

Mr. Willard drove me up to the Adirondacks.

It was the day after Christmas and a gray sky bellied over us, fat with snow. I felt overstuffed and dull and disappointed, the way I always do the day after Christmas, as if whatever it was the pine boughs and the candles and the silver and gilt-ribboned presents and the birch-log fires and the Christmas turkey and the carols at the piano promised never came to pass.

At Christmas I almost wished I was a Catholic.

First Mr. Willard drove and then I drove. I don't know what we talked about, but as the countryside, already deep under old falls of snow, turned us a bleaker shoulder, and as the fir trees crowded down from the gray hills to the road edge, so darkly green they looked black, I grew gloomier and gloomier.

I was tempted to tell Mr. Willard to go ahead alone, I would hitchhike home.

But one glance at Mr.Willard's face—the silver hair in its boyish crewcut, the clear blue eyes, the pink cheeks, all frosted like a sweet wedding cake with the innocent, trusting expression—and I knew I couldn't do it. I'd have to see the visit through to the end.

At midday the grayness paled a bit, and we parked in an icy turnoff and shared out the tunafish sandwiches and the oatmeal cookies and the apples and the thermos of black coffee Mrs. Willard had packed for our lunch.

Mr. Willard eyed me kindly. Then he cleared his throat and brushed a few last crumbs from his lap. I could tell he was going to say something serious, because he was very shy, and I'd heard him clear his throat in that same way before giving an important economics lecture.

“Nelly and I have always wanted a daughter.”

For one crazy minute I thought, Mr. Willard was going to announce that Mrs. Willard was pregnant and expecting a baby girl. Then he said, “But I don't see how any daughter could be nicer than you.”

Mr. Willard must have thought I was crying because I was so glad he wanted to be a father to me. “There, there,” he patted my shoulder and cleared his throat once or twice. “I think we understand each other.”

Then he opened the car door on his side and strolled round to my side, his breath shaping tortuous smoke signals in the gray air. I moved over to the seat he had left and he started the car and we drove on.

I'm not sure what I expected of Buddy's sanatorium.

I think I expected a kind of wooden chalet perched up on top of a small mountain, with rosy-cheeked young men and women, all very attractive but with hectic glittering eyes, lying covered with thick blankets on outdoor balconies.

“TB is like living with a bomb in your lung,” Buddy had written to me at college. “You just lie around very quietly hoping it won't go off.”

I found it hard to imagine Buddy lying quietly. His whole philosophy of life was to be up and doing every second. Even when we went to the beach in the summer he never lay down to drowse in the sun the way I did. He ran back and forth or played ball or did a little series of rapid pushups to use the time.

Mr. Willard and I waited in the reception room for the end of the afternoon rest cure.

The color scheme of the whole sanatorium seemed to be based on liver. Dark, glowering woodwork, burnt-brown leather chairs, walls that might once have been white but had succumbed under a spreading malady of mold or damp. A mottled brown linoleum sealed off the floor.

On a low coffee table, with circular and semicircular stains bitten into the dark veneer, lay a few wilted numbers of Time and Life. I flipped to the middle of the nearest magazine.The face of Eisenhower beamed up at me, bald and blank as the face of a fetus in a bottle.

After a while I became aware of a sly, leaking noise. For a minute I thought the walls had begun to discharge the moisture that must saturate them, but then I saw the noise came from a small fountain in one corner of the room.

The fountain spurted a few inches into the air from a rough length of pipe, threw up its hands, collapsed and drowned its ragged dribble in a stone basin of yellowing water. The basin was paved with the white hexagonal tiles one finds in public lavatories.

A buzzer sounded. Doors opened and shut in the distance. Then Buddy came in.

“Hello, Dad.”

Buddy hugged his father, and promptly, with a dreadful brightness, came over to me and held out his hand. I shook it. It felt moist and fat.

Mr. Willard and I sat together on a leather couch. Buddy perched opposite us on the edge of a slippery armchair. He kept smiling, as if the corners of his mouth were strung up on invisible wire.

The last thing I expected was for Buddy to be fat. All the time I thought of him at the sanatorium I saw shadows carving themselves under his cheekbones and his eyes burning out of almost fleshless sockets.

But everything concave about Buddy had suddenly turned convex. A pot belly swelled under the tight white nylon shirt and his cheeks were round and ruddy as marzipan fruit. Even his laugh sounded plump.

Buddy's eyes met mine. “It's the eating,” he said. “They stuff us day after day and then just make us lie around. But I'm allowed out on walk hours now, so don't worry, I'll thin down in a couple of weeks.” He jumped up, smiling like a glad host. “Would you like to see my room?”

I followed Buddy, and Mr. Willard followed me, through a pair of swinging doors set with panes of frosted glass down a dim, liver-colored corridor smelling of floor wax and Lysol and another vaguer odor, like bruised gardenias.

Buddy threw open a brown door, and we filed into the narrow room.

A lumpy bed, shrouded by a thin white spread, pencil-striped with blue, took up most of the space. Next to it stood a bed table with a pitcher and a water glass and the silver twig of a thermometer poking up from a jar of pink disinfectant. A second table, covered with books and papers and off-kilter clay pots—baked and painted, but not glazed—squeezed itself between the bed foot and the closet door.

“Well,” Mr. Willard breathed, “it looks comfortable enough.”

Buddy laughed.

“What are these?” I picked up a clay ashtray in the shape of a lilypad, with the veinings carefully drawn in yellow on a murky green ground. Buddy didn't smoke.

“That's an ashtray,” Buddy said. “It's for you.”

I put the tray down. “I don't smoke.”

“I know,” Buddy said. “I thought you might like it, though.”

“Well,” Mr. Willard rubbed one papery lip against another. “I guess I'll be getting on. I guess I'll be leaving you two young people…”

“Fine, Dad. You be getting on.”

I was surprised. I had thought Mr. Willard was going to stay the night before driving me back the next day. “Shall I come too?”

“No, no.” Mr. Willard peeled a few bills from his wallet and handed them to Buddy. “See that Esther gets a comfortable seat on the train. She'll stay a day or so, maybe.” Buddy escorted his father to the door.

I felt Mr. Willard had deserted me. I thought he must have planned it all along, but Buddy said no, his father simply couldn't stand the sight of sickness and especially his own son's sickness, because he thought all sickness was sickness of the will. Mr. Willard had never been sick a day in his life.

I sat down on Buddy's bed. There simply wasn't anywhere else to sit.

Buddy rummaged among his papers in a businesslike way. Then he handed me a thin, gray magazine. “Turn to page eleven.”

The magazine was printed somewhere in Maine and full of stenciled poems and descriptive paragraphs separated from each other by asterisks. On page eleven I found a poem titled “Florida Dawn.” I skipped down through image after image about watermelon lights and turtle-green palms and shells fluted like bits of Greek architecture.

“Not bad.” I thought it was dreadful.

“Who wrote it?” Buddy asked with an odd, pigeony smile.

My eye dropped to the name on the lower right-hand corner of the page. B. S. Willard.

“I don't know.” Then I said, “Of course I know, Buddy. You wrote it.”

Buddy edged over to me.

I edged back. I have very little knowledge about TB, but it seemed to me an extremely sinister disease, the way it went on so invisibly. I thought Buddy might well be sitting in his own little murderous aura of TB germs.

“Don't worry,” Buddy lughed. “I'm not positive.”

“Positive?”

“You can't catch anything.”

Buddy stopped for a breath, the way you do in the middle of climbing something very steep.

“I want to ask you a question.” He had a disquieting new habit of boring into my eyes with his look as if actually bent on piercing my head, the better to analyze what went on inside it.

“I'd thought of asking it by letter.”

I had a fleeting vision of a pale blue envelope with a Yale crest on the back flap.

“But then I decided it would be better if I waited until you came up, so I could ask you in person.” He paused. “Well, don't you want to know what it is?”

“What?” I said in a small, unpromising voice.

Buddy sat down beside me. He put his arm around my waist and brushed the hair from my ear. I didn't move. Then I heard him whisper, “How would you like to be Mrs. Buddy Willard?”

I had an awful impulse to laugh.

I thought how that question would have bowled me over at any time in my five-or six-year period of adoring Buddy Willard from a distance.

Buddy saw me hesitate.

“Oh, I'm in no shape now, I know,” he said quickly. “I'm still on P.A.S. and I may yet lose a rib or two, but I'll be back at med school by next fall. A year from this spring at the latest…”

“I think I should tell you something, Buddy.”

“I know,” Buddy said stiffly. “You've met someone.”

“No, it's not that.”

“What is it, then?”

“I'm never going to get married.”

“You're crazy.” Buddy brightened. “You'll change your mind.”

“No. My mind's made up.”

But Buddy just went on looking cheerful.

“Remember,” I said, “that time you hitchhiked back to college with me after Skit Night?”

“I remember.”

“Remember how you asked me where would I like to live best, the country or the city?”

“And you said…”

“And I said I wanted to live in the country and in the city both?”

Buddy nodded.

“And you,” I continued with sudden force, “laughed and said I had the perfect setup of a true neurotic and that that question came from some questionnaire you'd had in psychology class that week?”

Buddy's smile dimmed.

“Well, you were right. I am neurotic. I could never settle down in either the country or the city.”

“You could live between them,” Buddy suggested helpfully. “Then you could go to the city sometimes and to the country sometimes.”

“Well, what's so neurotic about that?”

Buddy didn't answer.

“Well?” I rapped out, thinking, You can't coddle these sick people, it's the worst thing for them, it'll spoil them to bits.

“Nothing,” Buddy said in a pale, still voice.

“Neurotic, ha!” I let out a scornful laugh. “If neurotic is wanting two mutually exclusive things at one and the same time, then I'm neurotic as hell. I'll be flying back and forth between one mutually exclusive thing and another for the rest of my days.”

Buddy put his hand on mine.

“Let me fly with you.”

I stood at the top of the ski slope on Mount Pisgah, looking down. I had no business to be up there. I had never skied before in my life. Still, I thought I would enjoy the view while I had the chance.

At my left, the rope tow deposited skier after skier on the snowy summit which, packed by much crossing and recrossing and slightly melted in the noon sun, had hardened to the consistency and polish of glass. The cold air punished my lungs and sinuses to a visionary clearness.

On every side of me the red and blue and white jacketed skiers tore away down the blinding slope like fugitive bits of an American flag. From the foot of the ski run, the imitation log cabin lodge piped its popular songs into the overhang of silence.

Gazing down on the Jungfrau
From our chalet for two…

The lilt and boom threaded by me like an invisible rivulet in a desert of snow. One careless, superb gesture, and I would be hurled into motion down the slope toward the small khaki spot in the sidelines, among the spectators, which was Buddy Willard.

All morning Buddy had been teaching me how to ski.

First, Buddy borrowed skis and ski poles from a friend of his in the village, and ski boots from a doctor's wife whose feet were only one size larger than my own, and a red ski jacket from a student nurse. His persistence in the face of mulishness was astounding.

Then I remembered that at medical school Buddy had won a prize for persuading the most relatives of dead people to have their dead ones cut up whether they needed it or not, in the interests of science. I forget what the prize was, but I could just see Buddy in his white coat with his stethoscope sticking out of a side pocket like part of his anatomy, smiling and bowing and talking those numb, dumb relatives into signing the postmortem papers.

Next, Buddy borrowed a car from his own doctor, who'd had TB himself and was very understanding, and we drove off as the buzzer for walk hour rasped along the sunless sanatorium corridors.

Buddy had never skied before either, but he said that the elementary principles were quite simple, and as he'd often watched the ski instructors and their pupils he could teach me all I'd need to know.

For the first half hour I obediently herringboned up a small slope, pushed off with my poles and coasted straight down. Buddy seemed pleased with my progress.

“That's fine, Esther,” he observed, as I negotiated my slope for the twentieth time. “Now let's try you on the rope tow.”

I stopped in my tracks, flushed and panting.

“But Buddy, I don't know how to zigzag yet. All those people coming down from the top know how to zigzag.”

“Oh, you need only go halfway. Then you won't gain very much momentum.”

And Buddy accompanied me to the rope tow and showed me how to let the rope run through my hands, and then told me to close my fingers round it and go up.

It never occurred to me to say no.

I wrapped my fingers around the rough, bruising snake of a rope that slithered through them, and went up.

But the rope dragged me, wobbling and balancing, so rapidly I couldn't hope to dissociate myself from it halfway. There was a skier in front of me and a skier behind me, and I'd have been knocked over and stuck full of skis and poles the minute I let go, and I didn't want to make trouble, so I hung quietly on.

At the top, though, I had second thoughts.

Buddy singled me out, hesitating there in the red jacket. His arms chopped the air like khaki windmills. Then I saw he was signaling me to come down a path that had opened in the middle of the weaving skiers. But as I poised, uneasy, with a dry throat, the smooth white path from my feet to his feet grew blurred.

A skier crossed it from the left, another crossed it from the right, and Buddy's arms went on waving feebly as antennae from the other side of a field swarming with tiny moving animalcules like germs, or bent, bright exclamation marks.

I looked up from that churning amphitheater to the view beyond it.

The great, gray eye of the sky looked back at me, its mist-shrouded sun focusing all the white and silent distances that poured from every point of the compass, hill after pale hill, to stall at my feet.

The interior voice nagging me not to be a fool—to save my skin and take off my skis and walk down, camouflaged by the scrub pines bordering the slope—fled like a disconsolate mosquito. The thought that I might kill myself formed in my mind coolly as a tree or a flower.

I measured the distance to Buddy with my eye.

His arms were folded, now, and he seemed of a piece with the split-rail fence behind him—numb, brown and inconsequential.

Edging to the rim of the hilltop, I dug the spikes of my poles into the snow and pushed myself into a flight I knew I couldn't stop by skill or any belated access of will.

I aimed straight down.

A keen wind that had been hiding itself struck me full in the mouth and raked the hair back horizontal on my head. I was descending, but the white sun rose no higher. It hung over the suspended waves of the hills, an insentient pivot without which the world would not exist.

A small, answering point in my own body flew toward it. I felt my lungs inflate with the inrush of scenery—air, mountains, trees, people. I thought, “This is what it is to be happy.”

I plummeted down past the zigzaggers, the students, the experts, through year after year of doubleness and smiles and compromise, into my own past.

People and trees receded on either hand like the dark sides of a tunnel as I hurtled on to the still, bright point at the end of it, the pebble at the bottom of the well, the white sweet baby cradled in its mother's belly.

My teeth crunched a gravelly mouthful. Ice water seeped down my throat.

Buddy's face hung over me, near and huge, like a distracted planet. Other faces showed themselves up in back of his. Behind him, black dots swarmed on a plane of whiteness. Piece by piece, as at the strokes of a dull godmother's wand, the old world sprang back into position.

“You were doing fine,” a familiar voice informed my ear, “until that man stepped into your path.”

People were unfastening my bindings and collecting my ski poles from where they poked skyward, askew, in their separate snowbanks. The lodge fence propped itself at my back.

Buddy bent to pull off my boots and the several pairs of white wool socks that padded them. His plump hand shut on my left foot, then inched up my ankle, closing and probing, as if feeling for a concealed weapon.

A dispassionate white sun shone at the summit of the sky. I wanted to hone myself on it till I grew saintly and thin and essential as the blade of a knife.

“I'm going up,” I said. “I'm going to do it again.”

“No, you're not.”

A queer, satisfied expression came over Buddy's face.

“No, you're not,” he repeated with a final smile. “Your leg's broken in two places. You'll be stuck in a cast for months.”

Nine

“I'm so glad they're going to die.”

Hilda arched her cat-limbs in a yawn, buried her head in her arms on the conference table and went back to sleep. A wisp of bilious green straw perched on her brow like a tropical bird.

Bile green. They were promoting it for fall, only Hilda, as usual, was half a year ahead of time. Bile green with black, bile green with white, bile green with nile green, its kissing cousin.

Fashion blurbs, silver and full of nothing, sent up their fishy bubbles in my brain. They surfaced with a hollow pop.

I'm so glad they're going to die.

I cursed the luck that had timed my arrival in the hotel cafeteria to coincide with Hilda's. After a late night I felt too dull to think up the excuse that would take me back to my room for the glove, the handkerchief, the umbrella, the notebook I forgot. My penalty was the long, dead walk from the frosted glass doors of the Amazon to the strawberry-marble slab of our entry on Madison Avenue.

Hilda moved like a mannequin the whole way.

“That's a lovely hat, did you make it?”

I half expected Hilda to turn on me and say, “You sound sick,” but she only extended and then retracted her swanny neck.

“Yes.”

The night before I'd seen a play where the heroine was possessed by a dybbuk, and when the dybbuk spoke from her mouth its voice sounded so cavernous and deep you couldn't tell whether it was a man or a woman. Well, Hilda's voice sounded just like the voice of that dybbuk.

She stared at her reflection in the glossed shop windows as if to make sure, moment by moment, that she contained to exist. The silence between us was so profound I thought part of it must be my fault.

So I said, “Isn't it awful about the Rosenbergs?” The Rosenbergs were to be electrocuted late that night.

“Yes!” Hilda said, and at last I felt I had touched a human string in the cat's cradle of her heart. It was only as the two of us waited for the others in the tomblike morning gloom of the conference room that Hilda amplified that Yes of hers.

“It's awful such people should be alive.”

She yawned then, and her pale orange mouth opened on a large darkness. Fascinated, I stared at the blind cave behind her face until the two lips met and moved and the dybbuk spoke out of its hiding place, “I'm so glad they're going to die.”

“Come on, give us a smile.”

I sat on the pink velvet loveseat in Jay Cee's office, holding a paper rose and facing the magazine photographer. I was the last of the twelve to have my picture taken. I had tried concealing myself in the powder room, but it didn't work. Betsy had spied my feet under the doors.

I didn't want my picture taken because I was going to cry. I didn't know why I was going to cry, but I knew that if anybody spoke to me or looked at me too closely the tears would fly out of my eyes and the sobs would fly out of my throat and I'd cry for a week. I could feel the tears brimming and sloshing in me like water in a glass that is unsteady and too full.

This was the last round of photographs before the magazine went to press and were turned to Tulsa or Biloxi or Teaneck or Coos Bay or wherever we'd come from, and we were supposed to be photographed with props to show what we wanted to be.

Betsy held an ear of corn to show she wanted to be a farmer's wife, and Hilda held the bald, faceless head of a hatmaker's dummy to show she wanted to design hats, and Doreen held a gold-embroidered sari to show she wanted to be a social worker in India (she didn't really, she told me, she only wanted to get her hands on a sari) .

When they asked me what I wanted to be I said I didn't know.

“Oh, sure you know,” the photographer said.

“She wants,” said Jay Cee wittily, “to be everything.”

I said I wanted to be a poet.

Then they scouted about for something for me to hold.

Jay Cee suggested a book of poems, but the photographer said no, that was too obvious. It should be something that showed what inspired the poems. Finally Jay Cee undipped the single, long-stemmed paper rose from her latest hat.

The photographer fiddled with his hot white lights. “Show us how happy it makes you to write a poem.”

I stared through the frieze of rubber-plant leaves in Jay Cee's window to the blue sky beyond. A few stagey cloud puffs were traveling from right to left. I fixed my eyes on the largest cloud, as if, when it passed out of sight, I might have the good luck to pass with it.I felt it was very important to keep the line of my mouth level.

“Give us a smile.”

At last, obediently, like the mouth of a ventriloquist's dummy, my own mouth started to quirk up.

“Hey,” the photographer protested, with sudden foreboding, “you look like you're going to cry.”

I couldn't stop.

I buried my face in the pink velvet facade of Jay Cee's loveseat and with immense relief the salt tears and miserable noises that had been prowling around in me all morning burst out into the room.

When I lifted my head, the photographer had vanished. Jay Cee had vanished as well. I felt limp and betrayed, like the skin shed by a terrible animal. It was a relief to be free of the animal, but it seemed to have taken my spirit with it, and everything else it could lay its paws on.

I fumbled in my pocketbook for the gilt compact with the mascara and the mascara brush and the eyeshadow and the three lipsticks and the side mirror. The face that peered back at me seemed to be peering from the grating of a prison cell after a prolonged beating. It looked bruised and puffy and all the wrong colors. It was a face that needed soap and water and Christian tolerance.

I started to paint it with small heart.

Jay Cee breezed back after a decent interval with an armful of manuscripts.

“These'll amuse you,” she said. “Have a good read.”

Every morning a snowy avalanche of manuscripts swelled the dust-gray piles in the office of the Fiction Editor. Secretly, in studies and attics and schoolrooms all over America, people must be writing. Say someone or other finished a manuscript every minute; in five minutes that would be five manuscripts stacked on the Fiction Editor's desk. Within the hour there would be sixty, crowding each other onto the floor. And in a year…

I smiled, seeing a pristine, imaginary manuscript floating in mid-air, with Esther Greenwood typed in the upper-right-hand corner. After my month on the magazine I'd applied for a summer school course with a famous writer where you sent in the manuscript of a story and he read it and said whether you were good enough to be admitted into his class.

Of course, it was a very small class, and I had sent in my story a long time ago and hadn't heard from the writer yet, but I was sure I'd find the letter of acceptance waiting on the mail table at home.

I decided I'd surprise Jay Cee and send in a couple of the stories I wrote in this class under a pseudonym. Then one day the Fiction Editor would come in to Jay Cee personally and plop the stories down on her desk and say, “Here's something a cut above the usual,” and Jay Cee would agree and accept them and ask the author to lunch and it would be me.

“Honestly,” Doreen said, “this one'll be different.”

“Tell me about him,” I said stonily.

“He's from Peru.”

“They're squat,” I said. “They're ugly as Aztecs.”

“No, no, no, sweetie, I've already met him.”

We were sitting on my bed in a mess of dirty cotton dresses and laddered nylons and gray underwear, and for ten minutes Doreen had been trying to persuade me to go to a country club dance with a friend of somebody Lenny knew which, she insisted, was a very different thing from a friend of Lenny's, but as I was catching the eight o'clock train home the next morning I felt I should make some attempt to pack.

I also had a dim idea that if I walked the streets of New York by myself all night something of the city's mystery and magnificence might rub off on to me at last.

But I gave it up.

It was becoming more and more difficult for me to decide to do anything in those last days. And when I eventually did decide to do something, such as packing a suitcase, I only dragged all my grubby, expensive clothes out of the bureau and the closet and spread them on the chairs and the bed and the floor and then sat and stared at them, utterly perplexed. They seemed to have a separate, mulish identity of their own that refused to be washed and folded and stowed.

“It's these clothes,” I told Doreen. “I just can't face these clothes when I come back.”

“That's easy.”

And in her beautiful, one-track way, Doreen started to snatch up slips and stockings and the elaborate strapless bra, full of steel springs—a free gift from the Primrose Corset Company, which I'd never had the courage to wear—and finally, one by one, the sad array of queerly cut forty-dollar dresses…

“Hey, leave that one out. I'm wearing it.”

Doreen extricated a black scrap from her bundle and dropped it in my lap. Then, snowballing the rest of the clothes into one soft, conglomerate mass, she stuffed them out of sight under the bed.

Doreen knocked on the green door with the gold knob.

Scuffing and a man's laugh, cut short, sounded from inside. Then a tall boy in shirtsleeves and a blond crewcut inched the door open and peered out.

“Baby!” he roared.

Doreen disappeared in his arms. I thought it must be the person Lenny knew.

I stood quietly in the doorway in my black sheath and my black stole with the fringe, yellower than ever, but expecting less. “I am an observer,” I told myself, as I watched Doreen being handed into the room by the blond boy to another man, who was also tall, but dark, with slightly longer hair. This man was wearing an immaculate white suit, a pale blue shirt and a yellow satin tie with a bright stickpin.

I couldn't take my eyes off that stickpin.

A great white light seemed to shoot out of it, illuminating the room. Then the light withdrew into itself, leaving a dewdrop on a field of gold.

I put one foot in front of the other.

“That's a diamond,” somebody said, and a lot of people burst out laughing.

My nail tapped a glassy facet

“Her first diamond.”

“Give it to her,Marco.”

Marco bowed and deposited the stickpin in my palm.

It dazzled and danced with light like a heavenly ice cube. I slipped it quickly into my imitation jet bead evening bag and looked around. The faces were empty as plates, and nobody seemed to be breathing.

“Fortunately,” a dry, hard hand encircled my upper arm, “I am escorting the lady for the rest of the evening. Perhaps,” the spark in Marco's eyes extinguished, and they went black, “I shall perform some small service…”

Somebody laughed.

“…worthy of a diamond.”

The hand round my arm tightened.

“Ouch!”

Marco removed his hand. I looked down at my arm. A thumbprint purpled into view. Marco watched me. Then he pointed to the underside of my arm. “Look there.”

I looked, and saw four, faint matching prints.

“You see, I am quite serious.”

Marco's small, flickering smile reminded me of a snake I'd teased in the Bronx Zoo. When I tapped my finger on the stout cage glass the snake had opened its clockwork jaws and seemed to smile. Then it struck and struck and struck at the invisible pane till I moved off.

I had never met a woman-hater before.

I could tell Marco was a woman-hater, because in spite of all the models and TV starlets in the room that night he paid attention to nobody but me. Not out of kindness or even curiosity, but because I'd happened to be dealt to him, like a playing card in a pack of identical cards.

A man in the country club band stepped up to the mike and started shaking those seedpod rattles that mean South American music.

Marco reached for my hand, but I hung on to my fourth daiquiri and stayed put. I'd never had a daiquiri before. The reason I had a daiquiri was because Marco ordered it for me, and I felt so grateful he hadn't asked what sort of drink I wanted that I didn't say a word, I just drank one daiquiri after another.

Marco looked at me.

“No,” I said.

“What do you mean, no?”

“I can't dance to that kind of music.”

“Don't be stupid.”

“I want to sit here and finish my drink.”

Marco bent toward me with a tight smile, and in one scoop my drink took wing and landed in a potted palm. Then Marco gripped my hand in such a way I had to choose between following him on to the floor or having my arm torn off.

“It's a tango.” Marco maneuvered me out among the dancers. “I love tangos.”

“I can't dance.”

“You don't have to dance. I'll do the dancing.”

Marco hooked an arm around my waist and jerked me up against his dazzling white suit. Then he said, “Pretend you are drowning.”

I shut my eyes, and the music broke over me like a rainstorm. Marco's leg slid forwardag ainst mine and my leg slid back and I seemed to be riveted to him, limb for limb, moving as he moved, without any will or knowledge of my own, and after a while I thought, “It doesn't take two to dance, it only takes one,” and I let myself blow and bend like a tree in the wind.

“What did I tell you?” Marco's breath scorched my ear. “You're a perfectly respectable dancer.”

I began to see why woman-haters could make such fools of women. Woman-haters were like gods: invulnerable and chock-full of power. They descended, and then they disappeared. You could never catch one.

After the South American music there was an interval.

Marco led me through the French doors into the garden. Lights and voices spilled from the ballroom window, but a few yards beyond the darkness drew up its barricade and sealed them off. In the infinitesimal glow of the stars, the trees and flowers were strewing their cool odors. There was no moon.

The box hedges shut behind us. A deserted golf course stretched away toward a few hilly clumps of trees, and I felt the whole desolate familiarity of the scene—the country club and the dance and the lawn with its single cricket.

I didn't know where I was, but it was somewhere in the wealthy suburbs of New York.

Marco produced a slim cigar and a silver lighter in the shape of a bullet. He set the cigar between his lips and bent over the small flare. His face, with its exaggerated shadows and planes of light, looked alien and pained, like a refugee's.

I watched him.

“Who are you in love with?” I said then.

For a minute Marco didn't say anything, he simply opened his mouth and breathed out ablue, vaporous ring.

“Perfect!” he laughed.

The ring widened and blurred, ghost-pale on the dark air.

Then he said, “I am in love with my cousin.”

I felt no surprise.

“Why don't you marry her?”

“Impossible.”

“Why?”

Marco shrugged. “She's my first cousin. She's going to be a nun.”

“Is she beautiful?”

“There's no one to touch her.”

“Does she know you love her?”

“Of course.”

I paused. The obstacle seemed unreal to me.

“If you love her,” I said, “you'll love somebody else someday.”

Marco dashed his cigar underfoot.

The ground soared and struck me with a soft shock. Mud squirmed through my fingers. Marco waited until I half rose. Then he put both hands on my shoulders and flung me back.

“My dress…”

“Your dress!” The mud oozed and adjusted itself to my shoulder blades. “Your dress!” Marco's face lowered cloudily over mine. A few drops of spit struck my lips. “Your dress is black and the dirt is black as well.”

Then he threw himself face down as if he would grind his body through me and into the mud.

“It's happening,” I thought. “It's happening. If I just lie here and do nothing it will happen.”

Marco set his teeth to the strap at my shoulder and tore my sheath to the waist. I saw the glimmer of bare skin, like a pale veil separating two bloody-minded adversaries.

“Slut!”

The words hissed by my ear.

“Slut!”

The dust cleared, and I had a full view of the battle.

I began to writhe and bite.

Marco weighed me to the earth.

“Slut!”

I gouged at his leg with the sharp heel of my shoe. He turned, fumbling for the hurt.

Then I fisted my fingers together and smashed them at his nose. It was like hitting the steel plate of a battleship. Marco sat up. I began to cry.

Marco pulled out a white handkerchief and dabbed his nose. Blackness, like ink, spread over the pale cloth.

I sucked at my salty knuckles.

“I want Doreen.”

Marco stared off across the golf links.

“I want Doreen. I want to go home.”

“Sluts, all sluts.” Marco seemed to be talking to himself. “Yes or no, it is all the same.”

I poked Marco's shoulder. “Where's Doreen?”

Marco snorted. “Go to the parking lot. Look in the backs of all the cars.”

Then he spun around.

“My diamond.”

I got up and retrieved my stole from the darkness. I started to walk off. Marco sprang to his feet and blocked my path. Then, deliberately, he wiped his finger under his bloody nose and with two strokes stained my cheeks. “I have earned my diamond with this blood. Give it to me.”

“I don't know where it is.”

Now I knew perfectly well that the diamond was in my evening bag and that when Marco knocked me down my evening bag had soared, like a night bird, into the enveloping darkness. I began to think I would lead him away and then return on my own and hunt for it.I had no idea what a diamond that size would buy, but whatever it was, I knew it would be a lot.

Marco took my shoulders in both hands.

“Tell me,” he said, giving each word equal emphasis. “Tell me, or I'll break your neck.”

Suddenly I didn't care.

“It's in my imitation jet bead evening bag,” I said. “Somewhere in the muck.”

I left Marco on his hands and knees, scrabbling in the darkness for another, smaller darkness that hid the light of his diamond from his furious eyes.

Doreen was not in the ballroom nor in the parking lot. I kept to the fringe of the shadows so nobody would notice the grass plastered to my dress and shoes, and with my black stole I covered my shoulders and bare breasts.

Luckily for me, the dance was nearly over, and groups of people were leaving and coming out to the parked cars. I asked at one car after another until finally I found a car that had room and would drop me in the middle of Manhattan.

At that vague hour between dark and dawn, the sunroof of the Amazon was deserted.

Quiet as a burglar in my cornflower-sprigged bathrobe, I crept to the edge of the parapet. The parapet reached almost to my shoulders, so I dragged a folding chair from the stack against the wall, opened it, and climbed onto the precarious seat.

A stiff breeze lifted the hair from my head. At my feet, the city doused its lights in sleep, its buildings blackened, as if for a funeral.

It was my last night.

I grasped the bundle I carried and pulled at a pale tail. A strapless elasticized slip which, in the course of wear, had lost its elasticity, slumped into my hand. I waved it, like a flag of truce, once, twice…The breeze caught it, and I let go.

A white flake floated out into the night, and began its slow descent. I wondered on what street or rooftop it would come to rest.

I tugged at the bundle again.

The wind made an effort, but failed, and a batlike shadow sank toward the roof garden of the penthouse opposite.

Piece by piece, I fed my wardrobe to the night wind, and flutteringly, like a loved one's ashes, the gray scraps were ferried off, to settle here, there, exactly where I would never know, in the dark heart of New York.

Ten

The face in the mirror looked like a sick Indian.

I dropped the compact into my pocketbook and stared out of the train window. Like a colossal junkyard, the swamps and back lots of Connecticut flashed past, one broken-down fragment bearing no relation to another.

What a hotchpotch the world was!

I glanced down at my unfamiliar skirt and blouse.

The skirt was a green dirndl with tiny black, white and electric-blue shapes swarming across it, and it stuck out like a lampshade. Instead of sleeves, the white eyelet blouse had frills at the shoulder, floppy as the wings of a new angel.

I'd forgotten to save any day clothes from the ones I let fly over New York, so Betsy had traded me a blouse and skirt for my bathrobe with the cornflowers on it.

A wan reflection of myself, white wings, brown ponytail and all, ghosted over the landscape.

“Pollyanna Cowgirl,” I said out loud.

A woman in the seat opposite looked up from her magazine.

I hadn't, at the last moment, felt like washing off the two diagonal lines of dried blood that marked my cheeks. They seemed touching, and rather spectacular, and I thought I would carry them around with me, like the relic of a dead lover, till they wore off of their own accord.

Of course, if I smiled or moved my face much, the blood would flake away in no time, so I kept my face immobile, and when I had to speak I spoke through my teeth, without disturbing my lips.

I didn't really see why people should look at me.

Plenty of people looked queerer than I did.

My gray suitcase rode on the rack over my head, empty except for The Thirty Best Short Stories of the Year, a white plastic sunglasses case and two dozen avocado pears, a parting present from Doreen.

The pears were unripe, so they would keep well, and whenever I lifted my suitcase up or down or simply carried it along, they cannoned from one end to the other with a special little thunder of their own.

“Root Wan Twenny Ate!” the conductor bawled.

The domesticated wilderness of pine, maple and oak rolled to a halt and stuck in the frame of the train window like a bad picture. My suitcase grumbled and bumped as I negotiated the long aisle.

I stepped from the air-conditioned compartment onto the station platform, and the motherly breath of the suburbs enfolded me. It smelt of lawn sprinklers and station wagons and tennis rackets and dogs and babies.

A summer calm laid its soothing hand over everything, like death.

My mother was waiting by the glove-gray Chevrolet.

“Why lovey, what's happened to your face?”

“Cut myself,” I said briefly, and crawled into the back seat after my suitcase. I didn't want her staring at me the whole way home.

The upholstery felt slippery and clean.

My mother climbed behind the wheel and tossed a few letters into my lap, then turned her back.

The car purred into life.

“I think I should tell you right away,” she said, and I could see bad news in the set of her neck, “you didn't make that writing course.”

The air punched out of my stomach.

All through June the writing course stretched before me like a bright, safe bridge over the dull gulf of the summer. Now I saw it totter and dissolve, and a body in a white blouse and green skirt plummet into the gap.

Then my mouth shaped itself sourly.

I had expected it.

I slunk down on the middle of my spine, my nose level with the rim of the window, and watched the houses of outer Boston glide by. As the houses grew more familiar I slunk still lower.

I felt it was very important not to be recognized.

The gray, padded car roof closed over my head like the roof of a prison van, and the white, shining, identical clapboard houses with their interstices of well-groomed green proceeded past, one bar after another in a large but escape-proof cage.

I had never spent a summer in the suburbs before.

The soprano screak of carriage wheels punished my ear. Sun, seeping through the blinds, filled the bedroom with a sulphurous light. I didn't know how long I had slept, but I felt one big twitch of exhaustion.

The twin bed next to mine was empty and unmade.

At seven I had heard my mother get up, slip into her clothes and tiptoe out of the room. Then the buzz of the orange squeezer sounded from downstairs, and the smell of coffee and bacon filtered under my door. Then the sink water ran from the tap and dishes clinked as my mother dried them and put them back in the cupboard.

Then the front door opened and shut. Then the car door opened and shut, and the motor went broom-broom and, edging off with a crunch of gravel, faded into the distance.

My mother was teaching shorthand and typing to a lot of city college girls and wouldn't be home till the middle of the afternoon.

The carriage wheels screaked past again. Somebody seemed to be wheeling a baby back and forth under my window.

I slipped out of bed and onto the rug, and quietly, on my hands and knees, crawled over to see who it was.

Ours was a small, white clapboard house set in the middle of a small green lawn on the corner of two peaceful suburban streets, but in spite of the little maple trees planted at intervals around our property, anybody passing along the sidewalk could glance up at the second story windows and see just what was going on.

This was brought home to me by our next-door neighbor, a spiteful woman named Mrs. Ockenden.

Mrs. Ockenden was a retired nurse who had just married her third husband—the other two died in curious circumstances—and she spent an inordinate amount of time peering from behind the starched white curtains of her windows.

She had called my mother up twice about me—once to report that I had been sitting in front of the house for an hour under the streetlight and kissing somebody in a blue Plymouth, and once to say that I had better pull the blinds down in my room, because she had seen me half-naked getting ready for bed one night when she happened to be out walking her Scotch terrier.

With great care, I raised my eyes to the level of the windowsill.

A woman not five feet tall, with a grotesque, protruding stomach, was wheeling an old black baby carriage down the street. Two or three small children of various sizes, all pale, with smudgy faces and bare smudgy knees, wobbled along in the shadow of her skirts.

A serene, almost religious smile lit up the woman's face. Her head tilted happily back, like a sparrow egg perched on a duck egg, she smiled into the sun.

I knew the woman well.

It was Dodo Conway.

Dodo Conway was a Catholic who had gone to Barnard and then married an architect who had gone to Columbia and was also a Catholic. They had a big, rambling house up the street from us, set behind a morbid facade of pine trees, and surrounded by scooters, tricycles, doll carriages, toy fire trucks, baseball bats, badminton nets, croquet wickets, hamster cages and cocker spaniel puppies—the whole sprawling paraphernalia of suburban childhood.

Dodo interested me in spite of myself.

Her house was unlike all the others in our neighborhood in its size (it was much bigger)and its color (the second story was constructed of dark brown clapboard and the first of gray stucco, studded with gray and purple golfball-shaped stones), and the pine trees completely screened it from view, which was considered unsociable in our community of adjoining lawns and friendly, waist-high hedges.

Dodo raised her six children—and would no doubt raise her seventh—on Rice Krispies, peanut-butter-and-marshmallow sandwiches, vanilla ice cream and gallon upon gallon of Hoods milk. She got a special discount from the local milkman.

Everybody loved Dodo, although the swelling size of her family was the talk of the neighborhood. The older people around, like my mother, had two children, and the younger, more prosperous ones had four, but nobody but Dodo was on the verge of a seventh. Even six was considered excessive, but then, everybody said, of course Dodo was a Catholic.

I watched Dodo wheel the youngest Conway up and down. She seemed to be doing it for my benefit. Children made me sick.

A floorboard creaked, and I ducked down again, just as Dodo Conway's face, by instinct, or some gift of supernatural hearing, turned on the little pivot of its neck.

I felt her gaze pierce through the white clapboard and the pink wallpaper roses and uncover me, crouching there behind the silver pickets of the radiator.

I crawled back into bed and pulled the sheet over my head. But even that didn't shut out the light, so I buried my head under the darkness of the pillow and pretended it was night. I couldn't see the point of getting up. I had nothing to look forward to.

After a while I heard the telephone ringing in the downstairs hall. I stuffed the pillow into my ears and gave myself five minutes. Then I lifted my head from its bolt hole. The ringing had stopped.

Almost at once it started up again.

Cursing whatever friend, relative or stranger had sniffed out my homecoming, I padded barefoot downstairs. The black instrument on the hall table trilled its hysterical note over and over, like a nervous bird. I picked up the receiver. “Hullo,” I said, in a low, disguised voice.

“Hullo, Esther, what's the matter, have you got laryngitis?” It was my old friend Jody, calling from Cambridge.

Jody was working at the Coop that summer and taking a lunchtime course in sociology. She and two other girls from my college had rented a big apartment from four Harvard law students, and I'd been planning to move in with them when my writing course began.

Jody wanted to know when they could expect me.

“I'm not coming,” I said. “I didn't make the course.”

There was a small pause.

“He's an ass,” Jody said then. “He doesn't know a good thing when he sees it.”

“My sentiments exactly.” My voice sounded strange and hollow in my ears.

“Come anyway. Take some other course.”

The notion of studying German or abnormal psychology flitted through my head. After all, I'd saved nearly the whole of my New York salary, so I could just about afford it.

But the hollow voice said, “You better count me out.”

“Well,” Jody began, “there's this other girl who wanted to come in with us if anybody dropped out…”

“Fine. Ask her.”

The minute I hung up I knew I should have said I would come. One morning listening to Dodo Conway's baby carriage would drive me crazy. And I made a point of never living in the same house with my mother for more than a week.

I reached for the receiver.

My hand advanced a few inches, then retreated and fell limp. I forced it toward the receiver again, but again it stopped short, as if it had collided with a pane of glass.

I wandered into the dining room.

Propped on the table I found a long, businesslike letter from the summer school and a thin blue letter on leftover Yale stationery, addressed to me in Buddy Willard's lucid hand.

I slit open the summer school letter with a knife.

Since I wasn't accepted for the writing course, it said, I could choose some other course instead, but I should call in to the Admissions Office that same morning, or it would be too late to register, the courses were almost full.

I dialed the Admissions Office and listened to the zombie voice leave a message that Miss Esther Greenwood was canceling all arrangements to come to summer school.

Then I opened Buddy Willard's letter.

Buddy wrote that he was probably falling in love with a nurse who also had TB, but his mother had rented a cottage in the Adirondacks for the month of July, and if I came along with her, he might well find his feeling for the nurse was a mere infatuation.

I snatched up a pencil and crossed out Buddy's message. Then I turned the letter paper over and on the opposite side wrote that I was engaged to a simultaneous interpreter and never wanted to see Buddy again as I did not want to give my children a hypocrite for a father.

I stuck the letter back in the envelope, Scotch-taped it together, and readdressed it to Buddy, without putting on a new stamp. I thought the message was worth a good three cents.

Then I decided I would spend the summer writing a novel.

That would fix a lot of people.

I strolled into the kitchen, dropped a raw egg into a teacup of raw hamburger, mixed it up and ate it. Then I set up the card table on the screened breezeway between the house and the garage.

A great wallowing bush of mock orange shut off the view of the street in front, the house wall and the garage wall took care of either side, and a clump of birches and a box hedge protected me from Mrs. Ockenden at the back.

I counted out three hundred and fifty sheets of corrasable bond from my mother's stock in the hall closet, secreted away under a pile of old felt hats and clothes brushes and woolen scarves.

Back on the breezeway, I fed the first, virgin sheet into my old portable and rolled it up.

From another, distanced mind, I saw myself sitting on the breezeway, surrounded by two white clapboard walls, a mock orange bush and a clump of birches and a box hedge, small as a doll in a doll's house.

A feeling of tenderness filled my heart. My heroine would be myself, only in disguise. She would be called Elaine. Elaine. I counted the letters on my fingers. There were six letters in Esther, too. It seemed a lucky thing.

Elaine sat on the breezeway in an old yellow nightgown of her mother's waiting for something to happen. It was a sweltering morning in July, and drops of sweat crawled down her back one by one, like slow insects.

I leaned back and read what I had written.

It seemed lively enough, and I was quite proud of the bit about the drops of sweat like insects, only I had the dim impression I'd probably read it somewhere else a long time ago.

I sat like that for about an hour, trying to think what would come next, and in my mind, the barefoot doll in her mother's old yellow nightgown sat and stared into space as well.

“Why, honey, don't you want to get dressed?”

My mother took care never to tell me to do anything. She would only reason with me sweetly, like one intelligent mature person with another.

“It's almost three in the afternoon.”

“I'm writing a novel,” I said. “I haven't got time to change out of this and change into that.”

I lay on the couch on the breezeway and shut my eyes. I could hear my mother clearing the typewriter and the papers from the card table and laying out the silver for supper, but I didn't move.

Inertia oozed like molasses through Elaine's limbs. That's what it must feel like to have malaria, she thought.

At any rate, I'd be lucky if I wrote a page a day.

Then I knew what the trouble was.

I needed experience.

How could I write about life when I'd never had a love affair or a baby or even seen anybody die? A girl I knew had just won a prize for a short story about her adventures among the pygmies in Africa. How could I compete with that sort of thing?

By the end of supper my mother had convinced me I should study shorthand in the evenings. Then I would be killing two birds with one stone, writing a novel and learning something practical as well. I would also be saving a whole lot of money.

That same evening, my mother unearthed an old blackboard from the cellar and set it up on the breezeway. Then she stood at the blackboard and scribbled little curlicues in white chalk while I sat in a chair and watched.

At first I felt hopeful.

I thought I might learn shorthand in no time, and when the freckled lady in the Scholarships Office asked me why I hadn't worked to earn money in July and August, the way you were supposed to if you were a scholarship girl, I could tell her I had taken a free shorthand course instead, so I could support myself right after college.

The only thing was, when I tried to picture myself in some job, briskly jotting down line after line of shorthand, my mind went blank. There wasn't one job I felt like doing where you used shorthand. And, as I sat there and watched, the white chalk curlicues blurred into senselessness.

I told my mother I had a terrible headache, and went to bed.

An hour later the door inched open, and she crept into the room. I heard the whisper of her clothes as she undressed. She climbed into bed. Then her breathing grew slow and regular.

In the dim light of the streetlamp that filtered through the drawn blinds, I could see the pin curls on her head glittering like a row of little bayonets.

I decided I would put off the novel until I had gone to Europe and had a lover, and that I would never learn a word of shorthand. If I never learned shorthand I would never have to use it.

I thought I would spend the summer reading Finnegans Wake and writing my thesis.

Then I would be way ahead when college started at the end of September, and able to enjoy my last year instead of swotting away with no makeup and stringy hair, on a diet of coffee and Benzedrine, the way most of the seniors taking honors did, until they finished their thesis.

Then I thought I might put off college for a year and apprentice myself to a pottery maker.

Or work my way to Germany and be a waitress, until I was bilingual.

Then plan after plan started leaping through my head, like a family of scatty rabbits.

I saw the years of my life spaced along a road in the form of telephone poles, threaded together by wires. I counted one, two, three…nineteen telephone poles, and then the wires dangled into space, and try as I would, I couldn't see a single pole beyond the nineteenth.

The room blued into view, and I wondered where the night had gone. My mother turned from a foggy log into a slumbering, middle-aged woman, her mouth slightly open and a snore raveling from her throat. The piggish noise irritated me, and for a while it seemed to me that the only way to stop it would be to take the column of skin and sinew from which it rose and twist it to silence between my hands.

I feigned sleep until my mother left for school, but even my eyelids didn't shut out the light. They hung the raw, red screen of their tiny vessels in front of me like a wound. I crawled between the mattress and the padded bedstead and let the mattress fall across me like a tombstone. It felt dark and safe under there, but the mattress was not heavy enough.

It needed about a ton more weight to make me sleep.

riverrun, past Eve and Adam's, from swerve of shore to bend of bay, brings us by a commodius vicus of recirculation back to Howth Castle and Environs…

The thick book made an unpleasant dent in my stomach.

riverrun, past Eve and Adam's…

I thought the small letter at the start might mean that nothing ever really began all new, with a capital, but that it just flowed on from what came before. Eve and Adam's was Adam and Eve, of course, but it probably signified something else as well.

Maybe it was a pub in Dublin.

My eyes sank through an alphabet soup of letters to the long word in the middle of the page.

bababadalgharaghtakamminarronnkonnbronntonner-ronntuonnthunntrovarrhounawnskawntoohoohoordenenth-urnuk!

I counted the letters. There were exactly a hundred of them. I thought this must be important.

Why should there be a hundred letters?

Haltingly, I tried the word aloud.

It sounded like a heavy wooden object falling downstairs, boomp boomp boomp, step after step. Lifting the pages of the book, I let them fan slowly by my eyes. Words, dimly familiar but twisted all awry, like faces in a funhouse mirror, fled past, leaving no impression on the glassy surface of my brain.

I squinted at the page.

The letters grew barbs and rams' horns. I watched them separate, each from the other, and jiggle up and down in a silly way. Then they associated themselves in fantastic, untranslatable shapes, like Arabic or Chinese.

I decided to junk my thesis.

I decided to junk the whole honors program and become an ordinary English major. I went to look up the requirements of an ordinary English major at my college.

There were lots of requirements, and I didn't have half of them. One of the requirements was a course in the eighteenth century. I hated the very idea of the eighteenth century, with all those smug men writing tight little couplets and being so dead keen on reason. So I'd skipped it. They let you do that in honors, you were much freer. I had been so free I'd spent most of my time on Dylan Thomas.

A friend of mine, also in honors, had managed never to read a word of Shakespeare; butshe was a real expert on the Four Quartets.

I saw how impossible and embarrassing it would be for me to try to switch from my free program into the stricter one. So I looked up the requirements for English majors at the city college where my mother taught.

They were even worse.

You had to know Old English and the History of the English Language and a representative selection of all that had been written from Beowulf to the present day.

This surprised me. I had always looked down on my mother's college, as it was coed, and filled with people who couldn't get scholarships to the big eastern colleges.

Now I saw that the stupidest person at my mother's college knew more than I did. I saw they wouldn't even let me in through the door, let alone give me a large scholarship like the one I had at my own college.

I thought I'd better go to work for a year and think things over. Maybe I could study the eighteenth century in secret.

But I didn't know shorthand, so what could I do?

I could be a waitress or a typist.

But I couldn't stand the idea of being either one.

“You say you want more sleeping pills?”

“Yes.”

“But the ones I gave you last week are very strong.”

“They don't work any more.”

Teresa's large, dark eyes regarded me thoughtfully. I could hear the voices of her three children in the garden under the consulting-room window. My Aunt Libby had married an Italian, and Teresa was my aunt's sister-in-law and our family doctor.

I liked Teresa. She had a gentle, intuitive touch.

I thought it must be because she was Italian.

There was a little pause.

“What seems to be the matter?” Teresa said then.

“I can't sleep. I can't read.” I tried to speak in a cool, calm way, but the zombie rose up in my throat and choked me off. I turned my hands palm up.

“I think,” Teresa tore off a white slip from her prescription pad and wrote down a name and address, “you'd better see another doctor I know. He'll be able to help you more than I can.”

I peered at the writing, but I couldn't read it.

“Doctor Gordon,” Teresa said. “He's a psychiatrist.”

Eleven

Doctor Gordon's waiting room was hushed and beige.

The walls were beige, and the carpets were beige, and the upholstered chairs and sofas were beige. There were no mirrors or pictures, only certificates from different medical schools, with Doctor Gordon's name in Latin, hung about the walls. Pale green loopy ferns and spiked leaves of a much darker green filled the ceramic pots on the end table and the coffee table and the magazine table.

At first I wondered why the room felt so safe. Then I realized it was because there were no windows.

The air-conditioning made me shiver.

I was still wearing Betsy's white blouse and dirndl skirt. They drooped a bit now, as I hadn't washed them in my three weeks at home. The sweaty cotton gave off a sour but friendly smell.

I hadn't washed my hair for three weeks, either.

I hadn't slept for seven nights.

My mother told me I must have slept, it was impossible not to sleep in all that time, but if I slept, it was with my eyes wide open, for I had followed the green, luminous course of the second hand and the minute hand and the hour hand of the bedside clock through their circles and semi-circles, every night for seven nights, without missing a second, or a minute, or an hour.

The reason I hadn't washed my clothes or my hair was because it seemed so silly.

I saw the days of the year stretching ahead like a series of bright, white boxes, and separating one box from another was sleep, like a black shade. Only for me, the long perspective of shades that set off one box from the next had suddenly snapped up, and I could see day after day after day glaring ahead of me like a white, broad, infinitely desolate avenue.

It seemed silly to wash one day when I would only have to wash again the next.

It made me tired just to think of it.

I wanted to do everything once and for all and be through with it.

Doctor Gordon twiddled a silver pencil

“Your mother tells me you are upset.”

I curled in the cavernous leather chair and faced Doctor Gordon across an acre of highly polished desk.

Doctor Gordon waited. He tapped his pencil—tap, tap, tap—across the neat green field of his blotter.

His eyelashes were so long and thick they looked artificial. Black plastic reeds fringing two green, glacial pools.

Doctor Gordon's features were so perfect he was almost pretty.

I hated him the minute I walked in through the door.

I had imagined a kind, ugly, intuitive man looking up and saying “Ah!” in an encoraging way, as if he could see something I couldn't, and then I would find words to tell him how I was so scared, as if I were being stuffed farther and farther into a black, airless sack with no way out.

Then he would lean back in his chair and match the tips of his fingers together in a little steeple and tell me why I couldn't sleep and why I couldn't read and why I couldn't eat and why everything people did seemed so silly, because they only died in the end.

And then, I thought, he would help me, step by step, to be myself again.

But Doctor Gordon wasn't like that at all. He was young and good-looking, and I could see right away he was conceited.

Doctor Gordon had a photograph on his desk, in a silver frame, that half faced him and half faced my leather chair. It was a family photograph, and it showed a beautiful dark-haired woman, who could have been Doctor Gordon's sister, smiling out over the heads of two blond children.

I think one child was a boy and one was a girl, but it may have been that both children were boys or that both were girls, it is hard to tell when children are so small. I think there was also a dog in the picture, toward the bottom—a kind of airedale or a golden retriever—but it may have only been the pattern in the woman's skirt.

For some reason the photograph made me furious.

I didn't see why it should be turned half toward me unless Doctor Gordon was trying to show me right away that he was married to some glamorous woman and I'd better not get any funny ideas.

Then I thought, how could this Doctor Gordon help me anyway, with a beautiful wife and beautiful children and a beautiful dog haloing him like the angels on a Christmas card?

“Suppose you try and tell me what you think is wrong.”

I turned the words over suspiciously, like round, sea-polished pebbles that might suddenly put out a claw and change into something else.

What did I think was wrong?

That made it sound as if nothing was really wrong, I only thought it was wrong.

In a dull, flat voice—to show I was not beguiled by his good looks or his family photograph—I told Doctor Gordon about not sleeping and not eating and not reading. I didn't tell him about the handwriting, which bothered me most of all.

That morning I had tried to write a letter to Doreen, down in West Virginia, asking whether I could come and live with her and maybe get a job at her college waiting on table or something.

But when I took up my pen, my hand made big, jerky letters like those of a child, and the lines sloped down the page from left to right almost diagonally, as if they were loops of string lying on the paper, and someone had come along and blown them askew.

I knew I couldn't send a letter like that, so I tore it up in little pieces and put them in my pocketbook, next to my all-purpose compact, in case the psychiatrist asked to see them.

But of course Doctor Gordon didn't ask to see them, as I hadn't mentioned them, and I began to feel pleased at my cleverness. I thought I only need tell him what I wanted to, and that I could control the picture he had of me by hiding this and revealing that, all the while he thought he was so smart.

The whole time I was talking, Doctor Gordon bent his head as if he were praying, and the only noise apart from the dull, flat voice was the tap, tap, tap of Doctor Gordon's pencil at the same point on the green blotter, like a stalled walking stick.

When I had finished, Doctor Gordon lifted his head. “Where did you say you went to college?” Baffled, I told him. I didn't see where college fitted in. “Ah!” Doctor Gordon leaned back in his chair, staring into the air over my shoulder with a reminiscent smile.

I thought he was going to tell me his diagnosis, and that perhaps I had judged him too hastily and too unkindly. But he only said, “I remember your college well. I was up there, during the war. They had a WAC station, didn't they? Or was it WAVES?”

I said I didn't know.

“Yes, a WAC station, I remember now. I was doctor for the lot, before I was sent overseas. My, they were a pretty bunch of girls.”

Doctor Gordon laughed.

Then, in one smooth move, he rose to his feet and strolled toward me round the corner of his desk. I wasn't sure what he meant to do, so I stood up as well.

Doctor Gordon reached for the hand that hung at my right side and shook it.

“See you next week, then.”

The full, bosomy elms made a tunnel of shade over the yellow and red brick fronts along Commonwealth Avenue, and a trolley car was threading itself toward Boston down its slim, silver track. I waited for the trolley to pass, then crossed to the gray Chevrolet at the opposite curb.

I could see my mother's face, anxious and sallow as a slice of lemon, peering up at me through the windshield.

“Well, what did he say?”

I pulled the car door shut. It didn't catch. I pushed it out and drew it in again with a dull slam.

“He said he'll see me next week.”

My mother sighed.

Doctor Gordon cost twenty-five dollars an hour.

“Hi there, what's your name?”

“Elly Higginbottom.”

The sailor fell into step beside me, and I smiled.

I thought there must be as many sailors on the Common as there were pigeons. They seemed to come out of a dun-colored recruiting house on the far side, with blue and white “Join the Navy” posters stuck up on billboards round it and all over the inner walls.

“Where do you come from, Elly?”

“Chicago.”

I had never been to Chicago, but I knew one or two boys who went to Chicago University, and it seemed the sort of place where unconventional, mixed-up people would come from.

“You sure are a long way from home.”

The sailor put his arm around my waist, and for a long time we walked around the Common like that, the sailor stroking my hip through the green dirndl skirt, and me smiling mysteriously and trying not to say anything that would show I was from Boston and might at any moment meet Mrs.Willard, or one of my mother's other friends, crossing the Common after tea on Beacon Hill or shopping in Filene's Basement.

I thought if I ever did get to Chicago, I might change my name to Elly Higginbottom for good. Then nobody would know I had thrown up a scholarship at a big eastern women's college and mucked up a month in New York and refused a perfectly solid medical student for a husband who would one day be a member of the AMA and earn pots of money.

In Chicago, people would take me for what I was.

I would be simple Elly Higgenbottom, the orphan. People would love me for my sweet, quiet nature. They wouldn't be after me to read books and write long papers on the twins in James Joyce. And one day I might just marry a virile, but tender, garage mechanic and have a big cowy family, like Dodo Conway.

If I happened to feel like it.

“What do you want to do when you get out of the Navy?” I asked the sailor suddenly.

It was the longest sentence I had said, and he seemed taken aback. He pushed his white cupcake cap to one side and scratched his head.

“Well, I dunno, Elly,” he said. “I might just go to college on the G.I. Bill.”

I paused. Then I said suggestively, “You ever thought of opening a garage?”

“Nope,” said the sailor. “Never have.”

I peered at him from the corner of my eye. He didn't look a day over sixteen.

“Do you know how old I am?” I said accusingly.

The sailor grinned at me. “Nope, and I don't care either.”

It occurred to me that this sailor was really remarkably handsome. He looked Nordic and virginal. Now I was simple-minded it seemed I attracted clean, handsome people.

“Well, I'm thirty,” I said, and waited.

“Gee, Elly, you don't look it.” The sailor squeezed my hip.

Then he glanced quickly from left to right. “Listen, Elly, if we go round to those steps over there, under the monument, I can kiss you.”

At that moment I noticed a brown figure in sensible flat brown shoes striding across the Common in my direction. From the distance, I couldn't make out any features on the dime-sized face, but I knew it was Mrs. Willard.

“Could you please tell me the way to the subway?” I said to the sailor in a loud voice.

“Huh?”

“The subway that goes out to the Deer Island Prison?”

When Mrs. Willard came up I would have to pretend I was only asking the sailor directions, and didn't really know him at all.

“Take your hands off me,” I said between my teeth.

“Say, Elly, what's up?”

The woman approached and passed by without a look or a nod, and of course it wasn't Mrs. Willard. Mrs. Willard was at her cottage in the Adirondacks.

I fixed the woman's receding back with a vengeful stare.

“Say, Elly…”

“I thought it was somebody I knew,” I said. “Some blasted lady from this orphan home in Chicago.”

The sailor put his arm around me again.

“You mean you got no mom and dad, Elly?”

“No.” I let out a tear that seemed ready. It made a little hot track down my cheek.

“Say, Elly, don't cry. This lady, was she mean to you?”

“She was…she was awful.”

The tears came in a rush, then, and while the sailor was holding me and patting them dry with a big, clean, white linen handkerchief in the shelter of an American elm, I thought what an awful woman that lady in the brown suit had been, and how she, whether she knew it or not, was responsible for my taking the wrong turn here and the wrong path there and for everything bad that happened after that.

“Well, Esther, how do you feel this week?”

Doctor Gordon cradled his pencil like a slim, silver bullet.

“The same.”

“The same?” He quirked an eyebrow, as if he didn't believe it.

So I told him again, in the same dull, flat voice, only it was angrier this time, because he seemed so slow to understand, how I hadn't slept for fourteen nights and how I couldn't read or write or swallow very well.

Doctor Gordon seemed unimpressed.

I dug into my pocketbook and found the scraps of my letter to Doreen. I took them out and let them flutter on to Doctor Gordon's immaculate green blotter. They lay there, dumb as daisy petals in a summer meadow.

“What,” I said, “do you think of that?”

I thought Doctor Gordon must immediately see how bad the handwriting was, but he only said, “I think I would like to speak to your mother. Do you mind?”

“No.” But I didn't like the idea of Doctor Gordon talking to my mother one bit. I though the might tell her I should be locked up. I picked up every scrap of my letter to Doreen, so Doctor Gordon couldn't piece them together and see I was planning to run away, and walked out of his office without another word.

I watched my mother grow smaller and smaller until she disappeared into the door of Doctor Gordon's office building. Then I watched her grow larger and larger as she came back to the car.

“Well?” I could tell she had been crying.

My mother didn't look at me. She started the car.

Then she said, as we glided under the cool, deep-sea shade of the elms, “Doctor Gordon doesn't think you've improved at all. He thinks you should have some shock treatments at his private hospital in Walton.”

I felt a sharp stab of curiosity, as if I had just read a terrible newspaper headline about somebody else.

“Does he mean live there?”

“No,” my mother said, and her chin quivered.

I thought she must be lying.

“You tell me the truth,” I said, “or I'll never speak to you again.”

“Don't I always tell you the truth?” my mother said, and burst into tears.

SUICIDE SAVED FROM 7-STORY LEDGE!

After two hours on a narrow ledge seven stories above a concrete parking lot and gathered crowds, Mr. George Pollucci let himself be helped to safety through a nearby window by Sgt. Will Kilmartin of the Charles Street police force.

I cracked open a peanut from the ten-cent bag I had bought to feed the pigeons, and ate it. It tasted dead, like a bit of old tree bark.

I brought the newspaper close up to my eyes to get a better view of George Pollucci's face, spotlighted lie a three-quarter moon against a vague background of brick and black sky. I felt he had something important to tell me, and whatever it was might just be written on his face.

But the smudgy crags of George Pollucci's features melted away as I peered at them, and resolved themselves into a regular pattern of dark and light and medium-gray dots.

The inky-black newspaper paragraph didn't tell why Mr. Pollucci was on the ledge, or what Sgt. Kilmartin did to him when he finally got him in through the window.

The trouble about jumping was that if you didn't pick the right number of stories, you might still be alive when you hit bottom. I thought seven stories must be a safe distance.

I folded the paper and wedged it between the slats of the park bench. It was what my mother called a scandal sheet, full of the local murders and suicides and beatings and robbings, and just about every page had a half-naked lady on it with her breasts surging over the edge of her dress and her legs arranged so you could see to her stocking tops.

I didn't know why I had never bought any of these papers before. They were the only things I could read. The little paragraphs between the pictures ended before the letters had a chance to get cocky and wiggle about. At home, all I ever saw was the Christian Science Monitor, which appeared on the doorstep at five o'clock every day but Sunday and treated suicides and sex crimes and airplane crashes as if they didn't happen.

A big white swan full of little children approached my bench, then turned around a bosky islet covered with ducks and paddled back under the dark arch of the bridge. Everything I looked at seemed bright and extremely tiny.

I saw, as if through the keyhole of a door I couldn't open, myself and my younger brother, knee-high and holding rabbit-eared balloons, climb aboard a swanboat and fight for a seat at the edge, over the peanut-shell-paved water. My mouth tasted of cleanness and peppermint. If we were good at the dentist's, my mother always bought us a swanboat ride.

I circled the Public Garden—over the bridge and under the blue-green monuments, past the American flag flowerbed and the entrance where you could have your picture taken in an orange-and-white striped canvas booth for twenty-five cents—reading the names of the trees.

My favorite tree was the Weeping Scholar Tree. I thought it must come from Japan. They understood things of the spirit in Japan.

They disemboweled themselves when anything went wrong.

I tried to imagine how they would go about it. They must have an extremely sharp knife. No, probably two extremely sharp knives. Then they would sit down, cross-legged, a knife in either hand. Then they would cross their hands and point a knife at each side of their stomach. They would have to be naked, or the knife would get stuck in their clothes.

Then in one quick flash, before they had time to think twice, they would jab the knives in and zip them round, one on the upper crescent and one on the lower crescent, making a full circle. Then their stomach skin would come loose, like a plate, and their insides would fall out, and they would die.

It must take a lot of courage to die like that.

My trouble was I hated the sight of blood.

I thought I might stay in the park all night.

The next morning Dodo Conway was driving my mother and me to Walton, and if I was to run away before it was too late, now was the time. I looked in my pocketbook and counted out a dollar bill and seventy-nine cents in dimes and nickels and pennies.

I had no idea how much it would cost to get to Chicago, and I didn't dare go to the bank and draw out all my money, because I thought Doctor Gordon might well have warned the bank clerk to intercept me if I made an obvious move.

Hitchhiking occurred to me, but I had no idea which of all the routes out of Boston led to Chicago. It's easy enough to find directions on a map, but I had very little knowledge of directions when I was smack in the middle of somewhere. Every time I wanted to figure what was east or what was west it seemed to be noon, or cloudy, which was no help at all, or nighttime, and except for the Big Dipper and Cassiopeia's Chair, I was hopeless at stars, a failing which always disheartened Buddy Willard.

I decided to walk to the bus terminal and inquire about the fares to Chicago. Then I might go to the bank and withdraw precisely that amount, which would not cause so much suspicion.

I had just strolled in through the glass doors of the terminal and was browsing over the rack of colored tour leaflets and schedules, when I realized that the bank in my home town would be closed, as it was already mid-afternoon, and I couldn't get any money out till the next day.

My appointment at Walton was for ten o'clock.

At that moment, the loudspeaker crackled into life and started announcing the stops of a bus getting ready to leave in the parking lot outside. The voice on the loudspeaker went bockle bockle bockle, the way they do, so you can't understand a word, and then, in the middle of all the static, I heard a familiar name clear as A on the piano in the middle of all the tuning instruments of an orchestra.

It was a stop two blocks from my house.

I hurried out into the hot, dusty, end-of-July afternoon, sweating and sandy-mouthed, as if late for a difficult interview, and boarded the red bus, whose motor was already running.

I handed my fare to the driver, and silently, on gloved hinges, the door folded shut at my back.

Twelve

Doctor Gordon's private hospital crowned a grassy rise at the end of a long, secluded drive that had been whitened with broken quahog shells. The yellow clapboard walls of the large house, with its encircling veranda, gleamed in the sun, but no people strolled on the green dome of the lawn.

As my mother and I approached the summer heat bore down on us, and a cicada started up, like an aerial lawnmower, in the heart of a copper beech tree at the back. The sound of the cicada only served to underline the enormous silence.

A nurse met us at the door.

“Will you wait in the living room, please. Doctor Gordon will be with you presently.”

What bothered me was that everything about the house seemed normal, although I knew it must be chock-full of crazy people. There were no bars on the windows that I could see, and no wild or disquieting noises. Sunlight measured itself out in regular oblongs on the shabby, but soft red carpets, and a whiff of fresh-cut grass sweetened the air.

I paused in the doorway of the living room.

For a minute I thought it was the replica of a lounge in a guest house I visited once on an island off the coast of Maine. The French doors let in a dazzle of white light, a grand piano filled the far corner of the room, and people in summer clothes were sitting about at card tables and in the lopsided wicker armchairs one so often finds at down-at-heel seaside resorts.

Then I realized that none of the people were moving.

I focused more closely, trying to pry some clue from their stiff postures. I made out men and women, and boys and girls who must be as young as I, but there was a uniformity to their faces, as if they had lain for a long time on the shelf, out of the sunlight, under siftings of pale, fine dust.

Then I saw that some of the people were indeed moving, but with such small, birdlike gestures I had not at first discerned them.

A gray-faced man was counting out a deck of cards, one, two, three, four…I though he must be seeing if it was a full pack, but when he had finished counting, he started over again. Next to him, a fat lady played with a string of wooden beads. She drew all the beads up to one end of the string. Then click, click, click, she let them fall back on each other.

At the piano, a young girl leafed through a few sheets of music, but when she saw me looking at her, she ducked her head crossly and tore the sheets in half.

My mother touched my arm, and I followed her into the room.

We sat, without speaking, on a lumpy sofa that creaked each time one stirred.

Then my gaze slid over the people to the blaze of green beyond the diaphanous curtains, and I felt as if I were sitting in the window of an enormous department store. The figures around me weren't people, but shop dummies, painted to resemble people and propped up in attitudes counterfeiting life.

I climbed after Doctor Gordon's dark-jacketed back.

Downstairs, in the hall, I had tried to ask him what the shock treatment would be like, but when I opened my mouth no words came out, my eyes only widened and stared at the smiling, familiar face that floated before me like a plate full of assurances.

At the top of the stairs, the garnet-colored carpet stopped. A plain, brown linoleum, tacked to the floor, took its place, and extended down a corridor lined with shut white doors. As I followed Doctor Gordon, a door opened somewhere in the distance, and I heard a woman shouting.

All at once a nurse popped around the corner of the corridor ahead of us leading a woman in a blue bathrobe with shaggy, waist-length hair. Doctor Gordon stepped back, and I flattened against the wall。

As the woman was dragged by, waving her arms and struggling in the grip of the nurse, she was saying, “I'm going to jump out of the window, I'm going to jump out of the window, I'm going to jump out of the window.”

Dumpy and muscular in her smudge-fronted uniform, the wall-eyed nurse wore such thick spectacles that four eyes peered out at me from behind the round, twin panes of glass. I was trying to tell which eyes were the real eyes and which the false eyes, and which of the real eyes was the wall-eye and which the straight eye, when she brought her face up to mine with a large, conspiratorial grin and hissed, as if to reassure me, “She thinks she's going to jump out the window but she can't jump out the window because they're all barred!”

And as Doctor Gordon led me into a bare room at the back of the house, I saw that the windows in that part were indeed barred, and that the room door and the closet door and the drawers of the bureau and everything that opened and shut was fitted with a keyhole so it could be locked up.

I lay down on the bed.

The wall-eyed nurse came back. She unclasped my watch and dropped it in her pocket. Then she started tweaking the hairpins from my hair.

Doctor Gordon was unlocking the closet. He dragged out a table on wheels with a machine on it and rolled it behind the head of the bed. The nurse started swabbing my temples with a smelly grease.

As she leaned over to reach the side of my head nearest the wall, her fat breast muffled my face like a cloud or a pillow. A vague, medicinal stench emanated from her flesh.

“Don't worry,” the nurse grinned down at me. “Their first time everybody's scared to death.”

I tried to smile, but my skin had gone stiff, like parchment.

Doctor Gordon was fitting two metal plates on either side of my head. He buckled them into place with a strap that dented my forehead, and gave me a wire to bite.

I shut my eyes.

There was a brief silence, like an indrawn breath.

Then something bent down and took hold of me and shook me like the end of the world.Whee-ee-ee-ee-ee, it shrilled, through an air crackling with blue light, and with each flash a great jolt drubbed me till I thought my bones would break and the sap fly out of me like a split plant.

I wondered what terrible thing it was that I had done.

I was sitting in a wicker chair, holding a small cocktail glass of tomato juice. The watch had been replaced on my wrist, but it looked odd. Then I realised it had been fastened upside down. I sensed the unfamiliar positioning of the hairpins in my hair.

“How do you feel?”

An old metal floor lamp surfaced in my mind. One of the few relics of my father's study, it was surrounded by a copper bell which held the light bulb, and from which a frayed, tiger-colored cord ran down the length of the metal stand to a socket in the wall.

One day I decided to move this lamp from the side of my mother's bed to my desk at the other end of the room. The cord would be long enough, so I didn't unplug it. I closed both hands around the lamp and the fuzzy cord and gripped them tight.

Then something leapt out of the lamp in a blue flash and shook me till my teeth rattled, and I tried to pull my hands off, but they were stuck, and I screamed, or a scream was torn from my throat, for I didn't recognize it, but heard it soar and quaver in the air like a violently disembodied spirit.

Then my hands jerked free, and I fell back onto my mother's bed. A small hole, blackened as if with pencil lead, pitted the center of my right palm.

“How do you feel?”

“All right.”

But I didn't. I felt terrible.

“Which college did you say you went to?”

I said what college it was.

“Ah!” Doctor Gordon's face lighted with a slow, almost tropical smile. “They had a WAC station up there, didn't they, during the war?”

My mother's knuckles were bone-white, as if the skin had worn off them in the hour of waiting. She looked past me to Doctor Gordon, and he must have nodded, or smiled, because her face relaxed.

“A few more shock treatments, Mrs. Greenwood,” I heard Doctor Gordon say, “and I think you'll notice a wonderful improvement.”

The girl was still sitting on the piano stool, the torn sheet of music splayed at her feet like a dead bird. She stared at me, and I stared back. Her eyes narrowed. She stuck out her tongue.

My mother was following Doctor Gordon to the door. I lingered behind, and when their backs were turned, I rounded on the girl and thumbed both ears at her. She pulled her tongue in, and her face went stony.

I walked out into the sun.

Pantherlike in a dapple of tree shadow, Dodo Conway's black station wagon lay in wait.

The station wagon had been ordered originally by a wealthy society lady, black, without a speck of chrome, and with black leather upholstery, but when it came, it depressed her. It was the dead spit of a hearse, she said, and everybody else thought so too, and nobody would buy it, so the Conways drove it home, cut-price, and saved themselves a couple of hundred dollars.

Sitting in the front seat, between Dodo and my mother, I felt dumb and subdued. Every time I tried to concentrate, my mind glided off, like a skater, into a large empty space, and pirouetted there, absently.

“I'm through with that Doctor Gordon,” I said, after we had left Dodo and her black station wagon behind the pines. “You can call him up and tell him I'm not coming next week.”

My mother smiled. “I knew my baby wasn't like that.”

I looked at her. “Like what.”

“Like those awful people. Those awful dead people at that hospital.” She paused. “I knew you'd decide to be all right again.”

STARLET SUCCUMBS AFTER 68-HOUR COMA.

I felt in my pocketbook among the paper scraps and the compact and the peanut shells and the dimes and nickels and the blue jiffy box containing nineteen Gillette blades, till I unearthed the snapshot I'd had taken that afternoon in the orange-and-white striped booth.

I brought it up next to the smudgy photograph of the dead girl. It matched, mouth for mouth, nose for nose. The only difference was the eyes. The eyes in the snapshot were open, and those in the newspaper photograph were closed. But I knew if the dead girl's eyes were to be thumbed wide, they would look at me with the same dead, black, vacant expression as the eyes in the snapshot.

I stuffed the snapshot back in my pocketbook.

“I will just sit here in the sun on this park bench five minutes more by the clock on that building over there,” I told myself, “and then I will go somewhere and do it.”

I summoned my little chorus of voices.

Doesn't your work interest you, Esther?

You know, Esther, you've got the perfect setup of a true neurotic.

You'll never get anywhere like that, you'll never get anywhere like that, you'll never get anywhere like that.

Once on a hot summer night, I had spent an hour kissing a hairy, ape-shaped law student from Yale because I felt sorry for him, he was so ugly. When I had finished, he said, “I have you typed, baby. You'll be a prude at forty.”

“Factitious!” my creative writing professor at college scrawled on a story of mine called “The Big Weekend.”

I hadn't known what factitious meant, so I looked it up in the dictionary.

Factitious, artificial, sham.

You'll never get anywhere like that.

I hadn't slept for twenty-one nights.

I thought the most beautiful thing in the world must be shadow, the million moving shapes and cul-de-sacs of shadow. There was shadow in bureau drawers and closets and suitcases, and shadow under houses and trees and stones, and shadow at the back of people's eyes and smiles, and shadow, miles and miles and miles of it, on the night side of the earth.

I looked down at the two flesh-colored Band-Aids forming a cross on the calf of my right leg.

That morning I had made a start.

I had locked myself in the bathroom, and run a tub full of warm water, and taken out a Gillette blade.

When they asked some old Roman philosopher or other how he wanted to die, he said he would open his veins in a warm bath. I thought it would be easy, lying in the tub and seeing the redness flower from my wrists, flush after flush through the clear water, till I sank to sleep under a surface gaudy as poppies.

But when it came right down to it, the skin of my wrist looked so white and defenseless that I couldn't do it. It was as if what I wanted to kill wasn't in that skin or the thin blue pulse that jumped under my thumb, but somewhere else, deeper, more secret, a whole lot harder to get at.

It would take two motions. One wrist, then the other wrist. Three motions, if you counted changing the razor from hand to hand. Then I would step into the tub and lie down.

I moved in front of the medicine cabinet. If I looked in the mirror while I did it, it would be like watching somebody else, in a book or a play.

But the person in the mirror was paralyzed and too stupid to do a thing.

Then I thought maybe I ought to spill a little blood for practice, so I sat on the edge of the tub and crossed my right ankle over my left knee. Then I lifted my right hand with the razor and let it drop of its own weight, like a guillotine, onto the calf of my leg.

I felt nothing. Then I felt a small, deep thrill, and a bright seam of red welled up at the lip of the slash. The blood gathered darkly, like fruit, and rolled down my ankle into the cup of my black patent leather shoe.

I thought of getting into the tub then, but I realized my dallying had used up the better part of the morning, and that my mother would probably come home and find me before I was done.

So I bandaged the cut, packed up my Gillette blades and caught the eleven-thirty bus to Boston.

“Sorry, baby, there's no subway to the Deer Island Prison, it's on an island.”

“No, it's not on an island, it used to be on an island, but they filled up the water with dirt and now it joins on to the mainland.”

“There's no subway.”

“I've got to get there.”

“Hey,” the fat man in the ticket booth peered at me through the grating, “don't cry. Who you got there, honey, some relative?”

People shoved and bumped by me in the artificially lit dark, hurrying after the trains that rumbled in and out of the intestinal tunnels under Scollay Square. I could feel the tears start to spurt from the screwed-up nozzles of my eyes.

“It's my father.”

The fat man consulted a diagram on the wall of his booth. “Here's how you do,” he said, “you take a car from that track over there and get off at Orient Heights and then hop a bus with The Point on it.” He beamed at me. “It'll run you straight to the prison gate.”

“Hey you!” A young fellow in a blue uniform waved from the hut.

I waved back and kept on going.

“Hey you!”

I stopped and walked slowly over to the hut that perched like a circular living room on the waste of sands.

“Hey, you can't go any further. That's prison property, no trespassers allowed.”

“I thought you could go anyplace along the beach,” I said. “So long as you stayed under the tideline.”

The fellow thought a minute. Then he said, “Not this beach.”

He had a pleasant, fresh face.

“You've a nice place here,” I said. “It's like a little house.”

He glanced back into the room, with its braided rug and chintz curtains. He smiled.

“We even got a coffee pot.”

“I used to live near here.”

“No kidding. I was born and brought up in this town myself.”

I looked across the sands to the parking lot and the barred gate, and past the barred gate to the narrow road, lapped by the ocean on both sides, that led out to the one-time island.

The red brick buildings of the prison looked friendly, like the buildings of a seaside college. On a green hump of lawn to the left, I could see small white spots and slightly larger pink spots moving about. I asked the guard what they were, and he said, “Them's pigs 'n' chickens.”

I was thinking that if I'd had the sense to go on living in that old town I might just have met this prison guard in school and married him and had a parcel of little kids by now. It would be nice, living by the sea with piles of little kids and pigs and chickens, wearing what my grandmother called wash dresses, and sitting about in some kitchen with bright linoleum and fat arms, drinking pots of coffee.

“How do you get into that prison?”

“You get a pass.”

“No, how do you get locked in?”

“Oh,” the guard laughed, “you steal a car, you rob a store.”

“You got any murderers in there?”

“No. Murderers go to a big state place.”

“Who else is in there?”

“Well, the first day of winter we get these old bums out of Boston. They heave a brick through a window, and then they get picked up and spend the winter out of the cold, with TV and plenty to eat, and basketball games on the weekend.”

“That's nice.”

“Nice if you like it,” said the guard.

I said good-bye and started to move off, glancing back over my shoulder only once. The guard still stood in the doorway of his observation booth, and when I turned he lifted his arm in a salute.

The log I sat on was lead-heavy and smelled of tar. Under the stout, gray cylinder of the water tower on its commanding hill, the sandbar curved out into the sea. At high tide the bar completely submerged itself.

I remembered that sandbar well. It harbored, in the crook of its inner curve, a particular shell that could be found nowhere else on the beach.

The shell was thick, smooth, big as a thumb joint, and usually white, although sometimes pink or peach-colored. It resembled a sort of modest conch.

“Mummy, that girl's still sitting there.”

I looked up, idly, and saw a small, sandy child being dragged up from the sea's edge by a skinny, bird-eyed woman in red shorts and a red-and-white polka-dot halter.

I hadn't counted on the beach being overrun with summer people. In the ten years of my absence, fancy blue and pink and pale green shanties had sprung up on the flat sands of the Point like a crop of tasteless mushrooms, and the silver airplanes and cigar-shaped blimps had given way to jets that scoured the rooftops in their loud offrush from the airport across the bay.

I was the only girl on the beach in a skirt and high heels, and it occurred to me I must stand out. I had removed my patent leather shoes after a while, for they foundered badly in the sand. It pleased me to think they would be perched there on the silver log, pointing out to sea, like a sort of soul-compass, after I was dead.

I fingered the box of razors in my pocketbook.

Then I thought how stupid I was. I had the razors, but no warm bath.

I considered renting a room. There must be a boarding-house among all those summer places. But I had no luggage. That would create suspicion. Besides, in a boardinghouse other people are always wanting to use the bathroom. I'd hardly have time to do it and step into the tub when somebody would be pounding at the door.

The gulls on their wooden stilts at the tip of the bar miaowed like cats. Then they flapped up, one by one, in their ash-colored jackets, circling my head and crying.

“Say, lady, you better not sit out here, the tide's coming in.”

The small boy squatted a few feet away. He picked up a round purple stone and lobbed it into the water. The water swallowed it with a resonant plop. Then he scrabbled around, and I heard the dry stones clank together like money.

He skimmed a flat stone over the dull green surface, and it skipped seven times before it sliced out of sight.

“Why don't you go home?” I said.

The boy skipped another, heavier stone. It sank after the second bounce.

“Don't want to.”

“Your mother's looking for you.”

“She is not.” He sounded worried.

“If you go home, I'll give you some candy.”

The boy hitched closer. “What kind?”

But I knew without looking into my pocketbook that all I had was peanut shells.

“I'll give you some money to buy some candy.”

“Ar-thur!”

A woman was indeed coming out on the sandbar, slipping and no doubt cursing to herself, for her lips went up and down between her clear, peremptory calls.

“Ar-thur!”

She shaded her eyes with one hand, as if this helped her discern us through the thickening sea dusk.

I could sense the boy's interest dwindle as the pull of his mother increased. He began to pretend he didn't know me. He kicked over a few stones, as if searching for something, and edged off.

I shivered.

The stones lay lumpish and cold under my bare feet. I thought longingly of the black shoes on the beach. A wave drew back, like a hand, then advanced and touched my foot.

The drench seemed to come off the sea floor itself, where blind white fish ferried themselves by their own light through the great polar cold. I saw sharks' teeth and whales' earbones littered about down there like gravestones.

I waited, as if the sea could make my decision for me.

A second wave collapsed over my feet, lipped with white froth, and the chill gripped my ankles with a mortal ache.

My flesh winced, in cowardice, from such a death.

I picked up my pocketbook and started back over the cold stones to where my shoes kept their vigil in the violet light.

Thirteen

“Of course his mother killed him.”

I looked at the mouth of the boy Jody had wanted me to meet. His lips were thick and pink and a baby face nestled under the silk of white-blond hair. His name was Cal, which I thought must be short for something, but I couldn't think what it would be short for, unless it was California.

“How can you be sure she killed him?” I said.

Cal was supposed to be very intelligent, and Jody had said over the phone that he was cute and I would like him. I wondered, if I'd been my old self, if I would have liked him.

It was impossible to tell.

“Well, first she says No no no, and then she says Yes.”

“But then she says No no again.”

Cal and I lay side by side on an orange-and-green striped towel on a mucky beach across the swamps from Lynn. Jody and Mark, the boy she was pinned to, were swimming. Cal hadn't wanted to swim, he had wanted to talk, and we were arguing about this play where a young man finds out he has a brain disease, on account of his father fooling around with unclean women, and in the end his brain, which has been softening all along, snaps completely, and his mother is debating whether to kill him or not.

I had a suspicion that my mother had called Jody and begged her to ask me out, so I wouldn't sit around in my room all day with the shades drawn. I didn't want to go at first, because I thought Jody would notice the change in me, and that anybody with half an eye would see I didn't have a brain in my head.

But all during the drive north, and then east, Jody had joked and laughed and chattered and not seemed to mind that I only said, “My” or “Gosh” or “You don't say.”

We browned hot dogs on the public grills at the beach, and by watching Jody and Mark and Cal very carefully I managed to cook my hot dog just the right amount of time and didn't burn it or drop it into the fire, the way I was afraid of doing. Then, when nobody was looking, I buried it in the sand.

After we ate, Jody and Mark ran down to the water hand-in-hand, and I lay back, staring into the sky, while Cal went on and on about this play.

The only reason I remembered this play was because it had a mad person in it, and everything I had ever read about mad people stuck in my mind, while everything else flew out.

“But it's the Yes that matters,” Cal said. “It's the Yes she'll come back to in the end.”

I lifted my head and squinted out at the bright blue plate of the sea—a bright blue plate with a dirty rim. A big round gray rock, like the upper half of an egg, poked out of the water about a mile from the stony headland.

“What was she going to kill him with? I forget.”

I hadn't forgotten. I remembered perfectly well, but I wanted to hear what Cal would say.

“Morphia powders.”

“Do you suppose they have morphia powders in America?”

Cal considered a minute. Then he said, “I wouldn't think so. They sound awfully old-fashioned.”

I rolled over onto my stomach and squinted at the view in the other direction, toward Lynn. A glassy haze rippled up from the fires in the grills and the heat on the road, and through the haze, as through a curtain of clear water, I could make out a smudgy skyline of gas tanks and factory stacks and derricks and bridges.

It looked one hell of a mess.

I rolled onto my back again and made my voice casual. “If you were going to kill yourself, how would you do it?”

Cal seemed pleased. “I've often thought of that. I'd blow my brains out with a gun.”

I was disappointed. It was just like a man to do it with a gun. A fat chance I had of laying my hands on a gun. And even if I did, I wouldn't have a clue as to what part of me to shoot at.

I'd already read in the papers about people who'd tried to shoot themselves, only they ended up shooting an important nerve and getting paralyzed or blasting their face off, but being saved, by surgeons and a sort of miracle, from dying outright.

The risks of a gun seemed great.

“What kind of a gun?”

“My father's shotgun. He keeps it loaded. I'd just have to walk into his study one day and,” Cal pointed a finger to his temple and made a comical, screwed-up face, “click!” He widened his pale gray eyes and looked at me.

“Does your father happen to live near Boston?” I asked idly.

“Nope, in Clacton-on-Sea. He's English.”

Jody and Mark ran up hand-in-hand, dripping and shaking off water drops like two loving puppies. I thought there would be too many people, so I stood up and pretended to yawn.

“I guess I'll go for a swim.”

Being with Jody and Mark and Cal was beginning to weigh on my nerves, like a dull wooden block on the strings of a piano. I was afraid that at any moment my control would snap, and I would start babbling about how I couldn't read and couldn't write and how I must be just about the only person who had stayed awake for a solid month without dropping dead of exhaustion.

A smoke seemed to be going up from my nerves like the smoke from the grills and the sun-saturated road. The whole landscape—beach and headland and sea and rock—quavered in front of my eyes like a stage backcloth.

I wondered at what point in space the silly, sham blue of the sky turned black.

“You swim too, Cal.”

Jody gave Cal a playful little push.

“Ohhh.” Cal hid his face in the towel. “It's too cold.”

I started to walk toward the water.

Somehow, in the broad, shadowless light of noon, the water looked amiable and welcoming.

I thought drowning must be the kindest way to die, and burning the worst. Some of those babies in the jars that Buddy Willard showed me had gills, he said. They went through a stage where they were just like fish.

A little, rubbishy wavelet, full of candy wrappers and orange peel and seaweed, folded over my foot.

I heard the sand thud behind me, and Cal came up.

“Let's swim to that rock out there.” I pointed at it.

“Are you crazy? That's a mile out.”

“What are you?” I said. “Chicken?”

Cal took me by the elbow and jostled me into the water. When we were waist high, he pushed me under. I surfaced, splashing, my eyes seared with salt. Underneath, the water was green and semi-opaque as a hunk of quartz.

I started to swim, a modified dogpaddle, keeping my face toward the rock. Cal did a slow crawl. After a while he put his head up and treaded water.

“Can't make it.” He was panting heavily.

“Okay. You go back.”

I thought I would swim out until I was too tired to swim back. As I paddled on, my heartbeat boomed like a dull motor in my ears.

I am I am I am.

That morning I had tried to hang myself.

I had taken the silk cord of my mother's yellow bathrobe as soon as she left for work, and, in the amber shade of the bedroom, fashioned it into a knot that slipped up and down on itself. It took me a long time to do this, because I was poor at knots and had no idea how to make a proper one.

Then I hunted around for a place to attach the rope.

The trouble was, our house had the wrong kind of ceilings. The ceilings were low, white and smoothly plastered, without a light fixture or a wood beam in sight. I thought with longing of the house my grandmother had before she sold it to come and live with us, and then with my Aunt Libby.

My grandmother's house was built in the fine, nineteenth-century style, with lofty rooms and sturdy chandelier brackets and high closets with stout rails across them, and an attic where nobody ever went, full of trunks and parrot cages and dressmakers' dummies and overhead beams thick as a ship's timbers.

But it was an old house, and she'd sold it, and I didn't know anybody else with a house like that.

After a discouraging time of walking about with the silk cord dangling from my neck like a yellow cat's tail and finding no place to fasten it, I sat on the edge of my mother's bed and tried pulling the cord tight.

But each time I would get the cord so tight I could feel a rushing in my ears and a flush of blood in my face, my hands would weaken and let go, and I would be all right again.

Then I saw that my body had all sorts of little tricks, such as making my hands go limp at the crucial second, which would save it, time and again, whereas if I had the whole say, I would be dead in a flash.

I would simply have to ambush it with whatever sense I had left, or it would trap me in its stupid cage for fifty years without any sense at all. And when people found out my mind had gone, as they would have to, sooner or later, in spite of my mother's guarded tongue, they would persuade her to put me into an asylum where I could be cured.

Only my case was incurable.

I had bought a few paperbacks on abnormal psychology at the drugstore and compared my symptoms with the symptoms in the books, and sure enough, my symptoms tallied with the most hopeless cases.

The only thing I could read, besides the scandal sheets, were those abnormal-psychology books. It was as if some slim opening had been left, so I could learn all I needed to know about my case to end it in the proper way.

I wondered, after the hanging fiasco, if I shouldn't just give it up and turn myself over to the doctors, and then I remembered Doctor Gordon and his private shock machine. Once I was locked up they could use that on me all the time.

And I thought of how my mother and brother and friends would visit me, day after day, hoping I would be better. Then their visits would slacken off, and they would give up hope. They would grow old. They would forget me.

They would be poor, too.

They would want me to have the best of care at first, so they would sink all their money in a private hospital like Doctor Gordon's. Finally, when the money was used up, I would be moved to a state hospital, with hundreds of people like me, in a big cage in the basement.

The more hopeless you were, the further away they hid you.

Cal had turned around and was swimming in.

As I watched, he dragged himself slowly out of the neck-deep sea. Against the khaki-colored sand and the green shore wavelets, his body was bisected for a moment, like a white worm. Then it crawled completely out of the green and onto the khaki and lost itself among dozens and dozens of other worms that were wriggling or just lolling about between the sea and the sky.

I paddled my hands in the water and kicked my feet. The egg-shaped rock didn't seem to be any nearer than it had been when Cal and I had looked at it from the shore.

Then I saw it would be pointless to swim as far as the rock, because my body would take that excuse to climb out and lie in the sun, gathering strength to swim back.

The only thing to do was to drown myself then and there.

So I stopped.

I brought my hands to my breast, ducked my head, and dived, using my hands to push the water aside. The water pressed in on my eardrums and on my heart. I fanned myself down, but before I knew where I was, the water had spat me up into the sun, the world was sparkling all about me like blue and green and yellow semi-precious stones.

I dashed the water from my eyes.

I was panting, as after a strenuous exertion, but floating, without effort.

I dived, and dived again, and each time popped up like a cork.

The gray rock mocked me, bobbing on the water easy as a lifebuoy.

I knew when I was beaten.

I turned back.

The flowers nodded like bright, knowledgeable children as I trundled them down the hall.

I felt silly in my sage-green volunteer's uniform, and superfluous, unlike the white-uniformed doctors and nurses, or even the brown-uniformed scrubwomen with their mops and their buckets of grimy water, who passed me without a word.

If I had been getting paid, no matter how little, I could at least count this a proper job, but all I got for a morning of pushing round magazines and candy and flowers was a free lunch.

My mother said the cure for thinking too much about yourself was helping somebody who was worse off than you, so Teresa had arranged for me to sign on as a volunteer at our local hospital. It was difficult to be a volunteer at this hospital, because that's what all the Junior League women wanted to do, but luckily for me, a lot of them were away on vacation. I had hoped they would send me to a ward with some really gruesome cases, who would see through my numb, dumb face to how I meant well, and be grateful. But the head of the volunteers, a society lady at our church, took one look at me and said, “You're on maternity.”

So I rode the elevator up three flights to the maternity ward and reported to the head nurse. She gave me the trolley of flowers. I was supposed to put the right vases at the right beds in the right rooms.

But before I came to the door of the first room I noticed that a lot of the flowers were droopy and brown at the edges. I thought it would be discouraging for a woman who'd just had a baby to see somebody plonk down a big bouquet of dead flowers in front of her, so I steered the trolley to a washbasin in an alcove in the hall and began to pick out all the flowers that were dead.

Then I picked out all those that were dying.

There was no wastebasket in sight, so I crumpled the flowers up and laid them in the deep white basin. The basin felt cold as a tomb. I smiled. This must be how they laid the bodies away in the hospital morgue. My gesture, in its small way, echoed the larger gesture of the doctors and nurses.

I swung the door of the first room open and walked in, dragging my trolley. A couple of nurses jumped up, and I had a confused impression of shelves and medicine cabinets.

“What do you want?” one of the nurses demanded sternly. I couldn't tell one from the other, they all looked just alike.

“I'm taking the flowers round.”

The nurse who had spoken put a hand on my shoulder and led me out of the room, maneuvering the trolley with her free, expert hand. She flung open the swinging doors of the room next to that one and bowed me in. Then she disappeared.

I could hear giggles in the distance till a door shut and cut them off.

There were six beds in the room, and each bed had a woman in it. The women were all sitting up and knitting or riffling through magazines or putting their hair in pin curls and chattering like parrots in a parrot house.

I had thought they would be sleeping, or lying quiet and pale, so I could tiptoe round without any trouble and match the bed numbers to the numbers inked on adhesive tape on the vases, but before I had a chance to get my bearings, a bright, jazzy blonde with a sharp, triangular face beckoned to me.

I approached her, leaving the trolley in the middle of the floor, but then she made an impatient gesture, and I saw she wanted me to bring the trolley too.

I wheeled the trolley over to her bedside with a helpful smile.

“Hey, where's my larkspur?” A large, flabby lady from across the ward raked me with an eagle eye.

The sharp-faced blonde bent over the trolley. “Here are my yellow roses,” she said, “but they're all mixed up with some lousy iris.”

Other voices joined the voices of the first two women. They sounded cross and loud and full of complaint.

I was opening my mouth to explain that I had thrown a bunch of dead larkspur in the sink, and that some of the vases I had weeded out looked skimpy, there were so few flowers left, so I had joined a few of the bouquets together to fill them out, when the swinging door flew open and a nurse stalked in to see what the commotion was.

“Listen, nurse, I had this big bunch of larkspur Larry brought last night.”

“She's loused up my yellow roses.”

Unbuttoning the green uniform as I ran, I stuffed it, in passing, into the washbasin with the rubbish of dead flowers. Then I took the deserted side steps down to the street two at a time, without meeting another soul.

“Which way is the graveyard?”

The Italian in the black leather jacket stopped and pointed down an alley behind the white Methodist church. I remembered the Methodist church. I had been a Methodist for the first nine years of my life, before my father died and we moved and turned Unitarian.

My mother had been a Catholic before she was a Methodist. My grandmother and my grandfather and my Aunt Libby were all still Catholics. My Aunt Libby had broken away from the Catholic Church at the same time my mother did, but then she'd fallen in love with an Italian Catholic, so she'd gone back again.

Lately I had considered going into the Catholic Church myself. I knew the Catholics thought killing yourself was an awful sin. But perhaps, if this was so, they might have a good way to persuade me out of it.

Of course, I didn't believe in life after death or the virgin birth or the Inquisition or the infallibility of that little monkey-faced Pope or anything, but I didn't have to let the priest see this, I could just concentrate on my sin, and he would help me repent.

The only trouble was, Church, even the Catholic Church, didn't take up the whole of your life. No matter how much you knelt and prayed, you still had to eat three meals a day and have a job and live in the world.

I thought I might see how long you had to be a Catholic before you became a nun, so I asked my mother, thinking she'd know the best way to go about it.

My mother had laughed at me. “Do you think they'll take somebody like you, right off the bat? Why you've got to know all these catechisms and credos and believe in them, lock, stock and barrel. A girl with your sense!”

Still, I imagined myself going to some Boston priest—it would have to be Boston, because I didn't want any priest in my home town to know I'd thought of killing myself. Priests were terrible gossips.

I would be in black, with my dead white face, and I would throw myself at this priest's feet and say, “O Father, help me.”

But that was before people had begun to look at me in a funny way, like those nurses in the hospital.

I was pretty sure the Catholics wouldn't take in any crazy nuns. My Aunt Libby's husband had made a joke once, about a nun that a nunnery sent to Teresa for a checkup. This nun kept hearing harp notes in her ears and a voice saying over and over, “Alleluia!” Only she wasn't sure, on being closely questioned, whether the voice was saying Alleluia or Arizona. The nun had been born in Arizona. I think she ended up in some asylum.

I tugged my black veil down to my chin and strode in through the wrought-iron gates. I thought it odd that in all the time my father had been buried in this graveyard, none of us had ever visited him. My mother hadn't let us come to his funeral because we were only children then, and he had died in the hospital, so the graveyard and even his death had always seemed unreal to me.

I had a great yearning, lately, to pay my father back for all the years of neglect, and start tending his grave. I had always been my father's favorite, and it seemed fitting I should take on a mourning my mother had never bothered with.

I thought that if my father hadn't died, he would have taught me all about insects, which was his specialty at the university. He would also have taught me German and Greek and Latin, which he knew, and perhaps I would be a Lutheran. My father had been a Lutheran in Wisconsin, but they were out of style in New England, so he had become a lapsed Lutheran and then, my mother said, a bitter atheist.

The graveyard disappointed me. It lay at the outskirts of the town, on low ground, like a rubbish dump, and as I walked up and down the gravel paths, I could smell the stagnant salt marshes in the distance.

The old part of the graveyard was all right, with its worn, flat stones and lichen-bitten monuments, but I soon saw my father must be buried in the modern part with dates in the nineteen forties.

The stones in the modern part were crude and cheap, and here and there a grave was rimmed with marble, like an oblong bathtub full of dirt, and rusty metal containers stuck up about where the person's navel would be, full of plastic flowers.

A fine drizzle started drifting down from the gray sky, and I grew very depressed.

I couldn't find my father anywhere.

Low, shaggy clouds scudded over that part of the horizon where the sea lay, behind the marshes and the beach shanty settlements, and raindrops darkened the black mackintosh I had bought that morning. A clammy dampness sank through to my skin.

I had asked the sales girl, “Is it water-repellent?” And she had said, “No raincoat is ever water-repellent. It's showerproofed.”

And when I asked her what showerproofed was, she told me I had better buy an umbrella.

But I hadn't enough money for an umbrella. What with bus fare in and out of Boston and peanuts and newspapers and abnormal-psychology books and trips to my old home town by the sea, my New York fund was almost exhausted.

I had decided that when there was no more money in my bank account I would do it, and that morning I'd spent the last of it on the black raincoat.

Then I saw my father's gravestone.

It was crowded right up by another gravestone, head to head, the way people are crowded in a charity ward when there isn't enough space. The stone was of a mottled pink marble, like canned salmon, and all there was on it was my father's name and, under it, two dates, separated by a little dash.

At the foot of the stone I arranged the rainy armful of azaleas I had picked from a bush at the gateway of the graveyard. Then my legs folded under me, and I sat down in the sopping grass. I couldn't understand why I was crying so hard.

Then I remembered that I had never cried for my father's death.

My mother hadn't cried either. She had just smiled and said what a merciful thing it was for him he had died, because if he had lived he would have been crippled and an invalid for life, and he couldn't have stood that, he would rather have died than had that happen.

I laid my face to the smooth face of the marble and howled my loss into the cold salt rain.

I knew just how to go about it.

The minute the car tires crunched off down the drive and the sound of the motor faded, I jumped out of bed and hurried into my white blouse and green figured skirt and black raincoat. The raincoat felt damp still, from the day before, but that would soon cease to matter.

I went downstairs and picked up a pale blue envelope from the dining room table and scrawled on the back, in large, painstaking letters: I am going for a long walk.

I propped the message where my mother would see it the minute she came in.

Then I laughed.

I had forgotten the most important thing.

I ran upstairs and dragged a chair into my mother's closet. Then I climbed up and reached for the small green strongbox on the top shelf. I could have torn the metal cover off with my bare hands, the lock was so feeble, but I wanted to do things in a calm, orderly way.

I pulled out my mother's upper right-hand bureau drawer and slipped the blue jewelry box from its hiding place under the scented Irish linen handkerchiefs. I unpinned the little key from the dark velvet. Then I unlocked the strongbox and took out the bottle of new pills. There were more than I had hoped.

There were at least fifty.

If I had waited until my mother doled them out to me, night by night, it would have taken me fifty nights to save up enough. And in fifty nights, college would have opened, and my brother would have come back from Germany, and it would be too late.

I pinned the key back in the jewelry box among the clutter of inexpensive chains and rings, put the jewelry box back in the drawer under the handkerchiefs, returned the strongbox to the closet shelf and set the chair on the rug in the exact spot I had dragged it from.

Then I went downstairs and into the kitchen. I turned on the tap and poured myself a tall glass of water. Then I took the glass of water and the bottle of pills and went down into the cellar.

A dim, undersea light filtered through the slits of the cellar windows. Behind the oil burner, a dark gap showed in the wall at about shoulder height and ran back under the breezeway, out of sight. The breezeway had been added to the house after the cellar was dug, and built out over this secret, earth-bottomed crevice.

A few old, rotting fireplace logs blocked the hole mouth. I shoved them back a bit. Then I set the glass of water and the bottle of pills side by side on the flat surface of one of the logs and started to heave myself up.

It took me a good while to heft my body into the gap, but at last, after many tries, I managed it, and crouched at the mouth of the darkness, like a troll.

The earth seemed friendly under my bare feet, but cold. I wondered how long it had been since this particular square of soil had seen the sun.

Then, one after the other, I lugged the heavy, dust-covered logs across the hole mouth. The dark felt thick as velvet. I reached for the glass and bottle, and carefully, on my knees, with bent head, crawled to the farthest wall.

Cobwebs touched my face with the softness of moths. Wrapping my black coat round me like my own sweet shadow, I unscrewed the bottle of pills and started taking them swiftly, between gulps of water, one by one by one.

At first nothing happened, but as I approached the bottom of the bottle, red and blue lights began to flash before my eyes. The bottle slid from my fingers and I lay down.

The silence drew off, baring the pebbles and shells and all the tatty wreckage of my life. Then, at the rim of vision, it gathered itself, and in one sweeping tide, rushed me to sleep.

Fourteen

It was completely dark.

I felt the darkness, but nothing else, and my head rose, feeling it, like the head of a worm. Someone was moaning. Then a great, hard weight smashed against my cheek like a stone wall and the moaning stopped.

The silence surged back, smoothing itself as black water smooths to its old surface calm over a dropped stone.

A cool wind rushed by. I was being transported at enormous speed down a tunnel into the earth. Then the wind stopped. There was a rumbling, as of many voices, protesting and disagreeing in the distance. Then the voices stopped.

A chisel cracked down on my eye, and a slit of light opened, like a mouth or a wound, till the darkness clamped shut on it again. I tried to roll away from the direction of the light, but hands wrapped round my limbs like mummy bands, and I couldn't move.

I began to think I must be in an underground chamber, lit by blinding lights, and that the chamber was full of people who for some reason were holding me down.

Then the chisel struck again, and the light leapt into my head, and through the thick, warm, furry dark, a voice cried, “Mother!”

Air breathed and played over my face.

I felt the shape of a room around me, a big room with open windows. A pillow molded itself under my head, and my body floated, without pressure, between thin sheets.

Then I felt warmth, like a hand on my face. I must be lying in the sun. If I opened my eyes, I would see colors and shapes bending in upon me like nurses.

I opened my eyes.

It was completely dark.

Somebody was breathing beside me.

“I can't see,” I said.

A cheery voice spoke out of the dark. “There are lots of blind people in the world. You'll marry a nice blind man someday.”

The man with the chisel had come back.

“Why do you bother?” I said. “It's no use.”

“You musn't talk like that.” His fingers probed at the great, aching boss over my left eye. Then he loosened something, and a ragged gap of light appeared, like the hole in a wall. A man's hand peered round the edge of it.

“Can you see me?”

“Yes.”

“Can you see anything else?”

Then I remembered. “I can't see anything.” The gap narrowed and went dark. “I'm blind.”

“Nonsense! Who told you that?”

“The nurse.”

The man snorted. He finished taping the bandage back over my eye. “You are a very lucky girl. Your sight is perfectly intact.”

“Somebody to see you.”

The nurse beamed and disappeared.

My mother came smiling round the foot of the bed. She was wearing a dress with purple cartwheels on it and she looked awful.

A big tall boy followed her. At first I couldn't make out who it was, because my eye only opened a short way, but then I saw it was my brother.

“They said you wanted to see me.”

My mother perched on the edge of the bed and laid a hand on my leg. She looked loving and reproachful, and I wanted her to go away.

“I didn't think I said anything.”

“They said you called for me.” She seemed ready to cry. Her face puckered up and quivered like a pale jelly.

“How are you?” my brother said.

I looked my mother in the eye.

“The same,” I said.

“You have a visitor.”

“I don't want a visitor.”

The nurse bustled out and whispered to somebody in the hall. Then she came back. “He'd very much like to see you.”

I looked down at the yellow legs sticking out of the unfamiliar white silk pajamas they had dressed me in. The skin shook flabbily when I moved, as if there wasn't a muscle in it, and it was covered with a short, thick stubble of black hair.

“Who is it?”

“Somebody you know.”

“What's his name?”

“George Bakewell.”

“I don't know any George Bakewell.”

“He says he knows you.”

Then the nurse went out, and a very familiar boy came in and said, “Mind if I sit on the edge of your bed?”

He was wearing a white coat, and I could see a stethoscope poking out of his pocket. I thought it must be somebody I knew dressed up as a doctor.

I had meant to cover my legs if anybody came in, but now I saw it was too late, so I let them stick out, just as they were, disgusting and ugly.

“That's me,” I thought. “That's what I am.”

“You remember me, don't you, Esther?” I squinted at the boy's face through the crack of my good eye. The other eye hadn't opened yet, but the eye doctor said it would be all right in a few days.

The boy looked at me as if I were some exciting new zoo animal and he was about to burst out laughing.

“You remember me, don't you, Esther?” He spoke slowly, the way one speaks to a dull child. “I'm George Bakewell. I go to your church. You dated my roommate once at Amherst.”

I thought I placed the boy's face then. It hovered dimly at the rim of memory—the sort of face to which I would never bother to attach a name.

“What are you doing here?”

“I'm houseman at this hospital.”

How could this George Bakewell have become a doctor so suddenly? I wondered. He didn't really know me, either. He just wanted to see what a girl who was crazy enough to kill herself looked like.

I turned my face to the wall.

“Get out,” I said. “Get the hell out and don't come back.”

“I want to see a mirror.”

The nurse hummed busily as she opened one drawer after another, stuffing the new underclothes and blouses and skirts and pajamas my mother had bought me into the black patent leather overnight case.

“Why can't I see a mirror?”

I had been dressed in a sheath, striped gray and white, like mattress ticking, with a wide, shiny red belt, and they had propped me up in an armchair.

“Why can't I?”

“Because you better not.” The nurse shut the lid of the overnight case with a little snap.

“Why?”

“Because you don't look very pretty.”

“Oh, just let me see.”

The nurse sighed and opened the top bureau drawer. She took out a large mirror in a wooden frame that matched the wood of the bureau and handed it to me.

At first I didn't see what the trouble was. It wasn't a mirror at all, but a picture.

You couldn't tell whether the person in the picture was a man or a woman, because their hair was shaved off and sprouted in bristly chicken-feather tufts all over their head. One side of the person's face was purple, and bulged out in a shapeless way, shading to green along the edges, and then to a sallow yellow. The person's mouth was pale brown, with a rose-colored sore at either corner.

The most startling thing about the face was its supernatural conglomeration of bright colors.

I smiled.

The mouth in the mirror cracked into a grin.

A minute after the crash another nurse ran in. She took one look at the broken mirror, and at me, standing over the blind, white pieces, and hustled the young nurse out of the room.

“Didn't I tell you,” I could hear her say.

“But I only…”

“Didn't I tell you!”

I listened with mild interest. Anybody could drop a mirror. I didn't see why they should get so stirred up.

The other, older nurse came back into the room. She stood there, arms folded, staring hard at me.

“Seven years' bad luck.”

“What?”

“I said,” the nurse raised her voice, as if speaking to a deaf person, “seven years' bad luck.”

The young nurse returned with a dustpan and brush and began to sweep up the glittery splinters.

“That's only a superstition,” I said then.

“Huh!” The second nurse addressed herself to the nurse on her hands and knees as if I wasn't there. “At you-know-where they'll take care of her!”

From the back window of the ambulance I could see street after familiar street funneling off into a summery green distance. My mother sat on one side of me, and my brother on the other.

I had pretended I didn't know why they were moving me from the hospital in my hometown to a city hospital, to see what they would say.

“They want you to be in a special ward,” my mother said. “They don't have that sort of ward at our hospital.”

“I liked it where I was.”

My mother's mouth tightened. “You should have behaved better, then.”

“What?”

“You shouldn't have broken that mirror. Then maybe they'd have let you stay.”

But of course I knew the mirror had nothing to do with it.

I sat in bed with the covers up to my neck.

“Why can't I get up? I'm not sick.”

“Ward rounds,” the nurse said. “You can get up after ward rounds.” She shoved the bed curtains back and revealed a fat young Italian woman in the next bed.

The Italian woman had a mass of tight black curls, starting at her forehead, that rose in a mountainous pompadour and cascaded down her back. Whenever she moved, the huge arrangement of hair moved with her, as if made of stiff black paper.

The woman looked at me and giggled. “Why are you here?” She didn't wait for an answer. “I'm here on account of my French-Canadian mother-in-law.” She giggled again. “My husband knows I can't stand her, and still he said she could come and visit us, and when she came, my tongue stuck out of my head, I couldn't stop it. They ran me into Emergency and then they put me up here,” she lowered her voice, “along with the nuts.” Then she said, “What's the matter with you?”

I turned her my full face, with the bulging purple and green eye. “I tried to kill myself.”

The woman stared at me. Then, hastily, she snatched up a movie magazine from her bed table and pretended to be reading.

The swinging door opposite my bed flew open, and a whole troop of young boys and girls in white coats came in, with an older, gray-haired man. They were all smiling with bright, artificial smiles. They grouped themselves at the foot of my bed.

“And how are you feeling this morning, Miss Greenwood?”

I tried to decide which one of them had spoken. I hate saying anything to a group of people. When I talk to a group of people I always have to single out one and talk to him, and all the while I am talking I feel the others are peering at me and taking unfair advantage. I also hate people to ask cheerfully how you are when they know you're feeling like hell and expect you to say “Fine.”

“I feel lousy.”

“Lousy. Hmm,” somebody said, and a boy ducked his head with a little smile. Somebody else scribbled something on a clipboard. Then somebody pulled a straight, solemn face and said, “And why do you feel lousy?”

I thought some of the boys and girls in that bright group might well be friends of Buddy Willard. They would know I knew him, and they would be curious to see me, and afterward they would gossip about me among themselves. I wanted to be where nobody I knew could ever come.

“I can't sleep…”

They interrupted me. “But the nurse says you slept last night.” I looked around the crescent of fresh, strange faces.

“I can't read.” I raised my voice. “I can't eat.” It occurred to me I'd been eating ravenously ever since I came to.

The people in the group had turned from me and were murmuring in low voices to each other. Finally, the gray-haired man stepped out.

“Thank you, Miss Greenwood. You will be seen by one of the staff doctors presently.”

Then the group moved on to the bed of the Italian woman.

“And how are you feeling today, Mrs…” somebody said, and the name sounded long and full of l's, like Mrs. Tomolillo.

Mrs. Tomolillo giggled. “Oh, I'm fine, doctor. I'm just fine.” Then she lowered her voice and whispered something I couldn't hear. One or two people in the group glanced in my direction. Then somebody said, “All right, Mrs. Tomolillo,” and somebody stepped out and pulled the bed curtain between us like a white wall.

I sat on one end of a wooden bench in the grassy square between the four brick walls of the hospital. My mother, in her purple cartwheel dress, sat at the other end. She had her head propped in her hand, index finger on her cheek and thumb under her chin.

Mrs. Tomolillo was sitting with some dark-haired, laughing Italians on the next bench down. Every time my mother moved, Mrs. Tomolillo imitated her. Now Mrs. Tomolillo was sitting with her index finger on her cheek and her thumb under her chin, and her head tilted wistfully to one side.

“Don't move,” I told my mother in a low voice. “That woman's imitating you.”

My mother turned to glance round, but quick as a wink, Mrs. Tomolillo dropped her fat white hands in her lap and started talking vigorously to her friends.

“Why no, she's not,” my mother said. “She's not even paying any attention to us.”

But the minute my mother turned round to me again, Mrs. Tomolillo matched the tips of her fingers together the way my mother had just done and cast a black, mocking look at me.

The lawn was white with doctors.

All the time my mother and I had been sitting there, in the narrow cone of sun that shone down between the tall brick walls, doctors had been coming up to me and introducing themselves. “I'm Doctor Soandso, I'm Doctor Soandso.”

Some of them looked so young I knew they couldn't be proper doctors, and one of them had a queer name that sounded just like Doctor Syphilis, so I began to look out for suspicious, fake names, and sure enough, a dark-haired fellow who looked very like Doctor Gordon, except that he had black skin where Doctor Gordon's skin was white, came up and said, “I'm Doctor Pancreas,” and shook my hand.

After introducing themselves, the doctors all stood within listening distance, only I couldn't tell my mother that they were taking down every word we said without their hearing me, so I leaned over and whispered into her ear.

My mother drew back sharply.

“Oh, Esther, I wish you would cooperate. They say you don't cooperate. They say you won't talk to any of the doctors or make anything in Occupational Therapy…”

“I've got to get out of here,” I told her meaningly. “Then I'd be all right. You got me in here,” I said. “You get me out.”

I thought if only I could persuade my mother to get me out of the hospital I could work on her sympathies, like that boy with brain disease in the play, and convince her what was the best thing to do.

To my surprise, my mother said, “All right, I'll try to get you out—even if only to a better place. If I try to get you out,” she laid a hand on my knee, “promise you'll be good?”

I spun round and glared straight at Doctor Syphilis, who stood at my elbow taking notes on a tiny, almost invisible pad. “I promise,” I said in a loud, conspicuous voice.

The Negro wheeled the food cart into the patients' dining room. The Psychiatric Ward at the hospital was very small—just two corridors in an L-shape, lined with rooms, and an alcove of beds behind the OT shop, where I was, and a little area with a table and a few seats by a window in the corner of the L, which was our lounge and dining room.

Usually it was a shrunken old white man that brought our food, but today it was a Negro. The Negro was with a woman in blue stiletto heels, and she was telling him what to do. The Negro kept grinning and chuckling in a silly way.

Then he carried a tray over to our table with three lidded tin tureens on it, and started banging the tureens down. The woman left the room, locking the door behind her. All the time the Negro was banging down the tureens and then the dinted silver and the thick, white china plates, he gawped at us with big, rolling eyes.

I could tell we were his first crazy people.

Nobody at the table made a move to take the lids off the tin tureens, and the nurse stood back to see if any of us would take the lids off before she came to do it. Usually Mrs. Tomolillo had taken the lids off and dished out everybody's food like a little mother, but then they sent her home, and nobody seemed to want to take her place.

I was starving, so I lifted the lid off the first bowl.

“That's very nice of you, Esther,” the nurse said pleasantly. “Would you like to take some beans and pass them round to the others?”

I dished myself out a helping of green string beans and turned to pass the tureen to the enormous red-headed woman at my right. This was the first time the red-headed woman had been allowed up to the table. I had seen her once, at the very end of the L-shaped corridor, standing in front of an open door with bars on the square, inset windows.

She had been yelling and laughing in a rude way and slapping her thighs at the passing doctors, and the white-jacketed attendant who took care of the people in that end of the ward was leaning against the radiator, laughing himself sick.

The red-headed woman snatched the tureen from me and upended it on her plate. Beans mountained up in front of her and scattered over onto her lap and onto the floor like stiff, green straws.

“Oh, Mrs. Mole!” the nurse said in a sad voice. “I think you better eat in your room today.”

And she returned most of the beans to the tureen and gave it to the person next to Mrs. Mole and led Mrs. Mole off. All the way down the hall to her room, Mrs. Mole kept turning round and making leering faces at us, and ugly, oinking noises.

The Negro had come back and was starting to collect the empty plates of people who hadn't dished out any beans yet.

“We're not done,” I told him. “You can just wait.”

“Mah, mah!” The Negro widened his eyes in mock wonder. He glanced round. The nurse had not yet returned from locking up Mrs. Mole. The Negro made me an insolent bow. “Miss Mucky-Muck,” he said under his breath.

I lifted the lid off the second tureen and uncovered a wedge of macaroni, stone-cold and stuck together in a gluey paste. The third and last tureen was chock-full of baked beans.

Now I knew perfectly well you didn't serve two kinds of beans together at a meal. Beans and carrots, or beans and peas, maybe, but never beans and beans. The Negro was just trying to see how much we would take.

The nurse came back, and the Negro edged off at a distance. I ate as much as I could of the baked beans. Then I rose from the table, passing round to the side where the nurse couldn't see me below the waist, and behind the Negro, who was clearing the dirty plates. I drew my foot back and gave him a sharp, hard kick on the calf of the leg.

The Negro leapt away with a yelp and rolled his eyes at me. “Oh Miz, oh Miz,” he moaned, rubbing his leg. “You shouldn't of done that, you shouldn't, you reely shouldn't.”

“That's what you get,” I said, and stared him in the eye.

“Don't you want to get up today?”

“No.” I huddled down more deeply in the bed and pulled the sheet up over my head. Then I lifted a corner of the sheet and peered out. The nurse was shaking down the thermometer she had just removed from my mouth.

“You see, it's normal.” I had looked at the thermometer before she came to collect it, the way I always did. “You see, it's normal, what do you keep taking it for?”

I wanted to tell her that if only something were wrong with my body it would be fine, I would rather have anything wrong with my body than something wrong with my head, but the idea seemed so involved and wearisome that I didn't say anything. I only burrowed down further in the bed.

Then, through the sheet, I felt a slight, annoying pressure on my leg. I peeped out. The nurse had set her tray of thermometers on my bed while she turned her back and took the pulse of the person who lay next to me, in Mrs. Tomolillo's place.

A heavy naughtiness pricked through my veins, irritating and attractive as the hurt of a loose tooth. I yawned and stirred, as if about to turn over, and edged my foot under the box.

“Oh!” The nurse's cry sounded like a cry for help, and another nurse came running. “Look what you've done!”

I poked my head out of the covers and stared over the edge of the bed. Around the overturned enamel tray, a star of thermometer shards glittered, and balls of mercury trembled like celestial dew.

“I'm sorry,” I said. “It was an accident.”

The second nurse fixed me with a baleful eye. “You did it on purpose. I saw you.”

Then she hurried off, and almost immediately two attendants came and wheeled me, bed and all, down to Mrs. Mole's old room, but not before I had scooped up a ball of mercury.

Soon after they had locked the door, I could see the Negro's face, a molasses-colored moon, risen at the window grating, but I pretended not to notice.

I opened my fingers a crack, like a child with a secret, and smiled at the silver globe cupped in my palm. If I dropped it, it would break into a million little replicas of itself, and if I pushed them near each other, they would fuse, without a crack, into one whole again.

I smiled and smiled at the small silver ball.

I couldn't imagine what they had done with Mrs. Mole.

Fifteen

Philomena Guinea's black Cadillac eased through the tight, five o'clock traffic like a ceremonial car. Soon it would cross one of the brief bridges that arched the Charles, and I would, without thinking, open the door and plunge out through the stream of traffic to the rail of the bridge. One jump and the water would be over my head.

Idly I twisted a Kleenex to small, pill-sized pellets between my fingers and watched my chance. I sat in the middle of the back seat of the Cadillac, my mother on one side of me, and my brother on the other, both leaning slightly forward, like diagonal bars, one across each car door.

In front of me I could see the Spam-colored expanse of the chauffeur's neck, sandwiched between a blue cap and the shoulders of a blue jacket and, next to him, like a frail, exotic bird, the silver hair and emerald-feathered hat of Philomena Guinea, the famous novelist.

I wasn't quite sure why Mrs. Guinea had turned up. All I knew was that she had interested herself in my case and that at one time, at the peak of her career, she had been in an asylum as well.

My mother said that Mrs. Guinea had sent her a telegram from the Bahamas, where she read about me in a Boston paper. Mrs. Guinea had telegrammed, “Is there a boy in the case?”

If there was a boy in the case, Mrs. Guinea couldn't, of course, have anything to do with it.

But my mother had telegrammed back, “No, it is Esther's writing. She thinks she will never write again.”

So Mrs. Guinea had flown back to Boston and taken me out of the cramped city hospital ward, and now she was driving me to a private hospital that had grounds and golf courses and gardens, like a country club, where she would pay for me, as if I had a scholarship, until the doctors she knew of there had made me well.

My mother told me I should be grateful. She said I had used up almost all her money, and if it weren't for Mrs. Guinea she didn't know where I'd be. I knew where I'd be though. I'd be in the big state hospital in the country, cheek by jowl to this private place.

I knew I should be grateful to Mrs. Guinea, only I couldn't feel a thing. If Mrs. Guinea had given me a ticket to Europe, or a round-the-world cruise, it wouldn't have made one scrap of difference to me, because wherever I sat—on the deck of a ship or at a street cafe in Paris or Bangkok—I would be sitting under the same glass bell jar, stewing in my own sour air.

Blue sky opened its dome above the river, and the river was dotted with sails. I readied myself, but immediately my mother and my brother each laid one hand on a door handle. The tires hummed briefly over the grill of the bridge. Water, sails, blue sky and suspended gulls flashed by like an improbable postcard, and we were across.

I sank back in the gray, plush seat and closed my eyes. The air of the bell jar wadded round me and I couldn't stir.

I had my own room again.

It reminded me of the room in Doctor Gordon's hospital—a bed, a bureau, a closet, a table and chair. A window with a screen, but no bars. My room was on the first floor, and the window, a short distance above the pine-needle-padded ground, overlooked a wooded yard ringed by a red brick wall. If I jumped I wouldn't even bruise my knees. The inner surface of the tall wall seemed smooth as glass.

The journey over the bridge had unnerved me.

I had missed a perfectly good chance. The river water passed me by like an untouched drink. I suspected that even if my mother and brother had not been there I would have made no move to jump.

When I enrolled in the main building of the hospital, a slim young woman had come and introduced herself. “My name is Doctor Nolan. I am to be Esther's doctor.”

I was surprised to have a woman. I didn't think they had woman psychiatrists. This woman was a cross between Myrna Loy and my mother. She wore a white blouse and a full skirt gathered at the waist by a wide leather belt, and stylish, crescent-shaped spectacles.

But after a nurse had led me across the lawn to the gloomy brick building called Caplan,where I would live, Doctor Nolan didn't come to see me, a whole lot of strange men came instead.

I lay on my bed under the thick white blanket, and they entered my room, one by one, and introduced themselves. I couldn't understand why there should be so many of them, or why they would want to introduce themselves, and I began to think they were testing me, to see if I noticed there were too many of them, and I grew wary.

Finally, a handsome, white-haired doctor came in and said he was the director of the hospital. Then he started talking about the Pilgrims and Indians and who had the land after them, and what rivers ran nearby, and who had built the first hospital, and how it had burned down, and who had built the next hospital, until I thought he must be waiting to see when I would interrupt him and tell him I knew all that about rivers and Pilgrims was a lot of nonsense.

But then I thought some of it might be true, so I tried to sort out what was likely to be true and what wasn't, only before I could do that, he had said good-bye.

I waited till I heard the voices of all the doctors die away. Then I threw back the white blanket and put on my shoes and walked out into the hall. Nobody stopped me, so I walked round the corner of my wing of the hall and down another, longer hall, past an open dining room.

A maid in a green uniform was setting the tables for supper. There were white linen tablecloths and glasses and paper napkins. I stored the fact that they were real glasses in the corner of my mind the way a squirrel stores a nut. At the city hospital we had drunk out of paper cups and had no knives to cut our meat. The meat had always been so overcooked we could cut it with a fork.

Finally I arrived at a big lounge with shabby furniture and a threadbare rug. A girl with a round pasty face and short black hair was sitting in an armchair, reading a magazine. She reminded me of a Girl Scout leader I'd had once. I glanced at her feet, and sure enough, she wore those flat brown leather shoes with fringed tongues lapping down over the front that are supposed to be so sporty, and the ends of the laces were knobbed with little imitation acorns.

The girl raised her eyes and smiled. “I'm Valerie. Who are you?”

I pretended I hadn't heard and walked out of the lounge to the end of the next wing. On the way, I passed a waist-high door behind which I saw some nurses.

“Where is everybody?”

“Out.” The nurse was writing something over and over on little pieces of adhesive tape. I leaned across the gate of the door to see what she was writing, and it was E. Greenwood, E. Greenwood, E. Greenwood, E. Greenwood.

“Out where?”

“Oh, OT, the golf course, playing badminton.”

I noticed a pile of clothes on a chair beside the nurse. They were the same clothes the nurse in the first hospital had been packing into the patent leather case when I broke the mirror. The nurses began sticking the labels onto the clothes.

I walked back to the lounge. I couldn't understand what these people were doing, playing badminton and golf. They mustn't be really sick at all, to do that.

I sat down near Valerie and observed her carefully. Yes, I thought, she might just as well be in a Girl Scout camp. She was reading her tatty copy of Vogue with intense interest.

“What the hell is she doing here?” I wondered. “There's nothing the matter with her.”

“Do you mind if I smoke?” Doctor Nolan leaned back in the armchair next to my bed.

I said no, I liked the smell of smoke. I thought if Doctor Nolan smoked, she might stay longer. This was the first time she had come to talk with me.When she left I would simply lapse into the old blankness.

“Tell me about Doctor Gordon,” Doctor Nolan said suddenly. “Did you like him?”

I gave Doctor Nolan a wary look. I thought the doctors must all be in it together, and that somewhere in this hospital, in a hidden corner, there reposed a machine exactly like Doctor Gordon's, ready to jolt me out of my skin.

“No,” I said. “I didn't like him at all.”

“That's interesting. Why?”

“I didn't like what he did to me.”

“Did to you?”

I told Doctor Nolan about the machine, and the blue flashes, and the jolting and the noise. While I was telling her she went very still.

“That was a mistake,” she said then. “It's not supposed to be like that.”

I stared at her.

“If it's done properly,” Doctor Nolan said, “it's like going to sleep.”

“If anyone does that to me again I'll kill myself.”

Doctor Nolan said firmly, “You won't have any shock treatments here. Or if you do,” she amended, “I'll tell you about it beforehand, and I promise you it won't be anything like what you had before. Why,” she finished, “some people even like them.”

After Doctor Nolan had gone I found a box of matches on the windowsill. It wasn't an ordinary-size box, but an extremely tiny box. I opened it and exposed a row of little white sticks with pink tips. I tried to light one, and it crumpled in my hand.

I couldn't think why Doctor Nolan would have left me such a stupid thing. Perhaps she wanted to see if I would give it back. Carefully I stored the toy matches in the hem of my new wool bathrobe. If Doctor Nolan asked me for the matches, I would say I'd thought they were made of candy and had eaten them.

A new woman had moved into the room next to mine.

I thought she must be the only person in the building who was newer than I was, so she wouldn't know how really bad I was, the way the rest did. I thought I might go in and make friends.

The woman was lying on her bed in a purple dress that fastened at the neck with a cameo brooch and reached midway between her knees and her shoes. She had rusty hair knotted in a schoolmarmish bun, and thin, silver-rimmed spectacles attached to her breast pocket with a black elastic.

“Hello,” I said conversationally, sitting down on the edge of the bed. “My name's Esther, what's your name?”

The woman didn't stir, just stared up at the ceiling. I felt hurt. I thought maybe Valerie or somebody had told her when she first came in how stupid I was.

A nurse popped her head in at the door.

“Oh, there you are,” she said to me. “Visiting Miss Norris. How nice!” And she disappeared again.

I don't know how long I sat there, watching the woman in purple and wondering if her pursed pink lips would open, and if they did open, what they would say.

Finally, without speaking or looking at me, Miss Norris swung her feet in their high, black, buttoned boots over the other side of the bed and walked out of the room. I thought she might be trying to get rid of me in a subtle way. Quietly, at a little distance, I followed her down the hall.

Miss Norris reached the door of the dining room and paused. All the way to the dining room she had walked precisely, placing her feet in the very center of the cabbage roses that twined through the pattern of the carpet. She waited a moment and then, one by one, lifted her feet over the doorsill and into the dining room as though stepping over an invisible shin-high stile.

She sat down at one of the round, linen-covered tables and unfolded a napkin in her lap.

“It's not supper for an hour yet,” the cook called out of the kitchen.

But Miss Norris didn't answer. She just stared straight ahead of her in a polite way.

I pulled up a chair opposite her at the table and unfolded a napkin. We didn't speak, but sat there, in a close, sisterly silence, until the gong for supper sounded down the hall.

“Lie down,” the nurse said. “I'm going to give you another injection.”

I rolled over on my stomach on the bed and hitched up my skirt. Then I pulled down the trousers of my silk pajamas.

“My word, what all have you got under there?”

“Pajamas. So I won't have to bother getting in and out of them all the time.”

The nurse made a little clucking noise. Then she said, “Which side?” It was an old joke.

I raised my head and glanced back at my bare buttocks. They were bruised purple and green and blue from past injections. The left side looked darker than the right.

“The right.”

“You name it.” The nurse jabbed the needle in, and I winced, savoring the tiny hurt. Three times each day the nurses injected me, and about an hour after each injection they gave me a cup of sugary fruit juice and stood by, watching me drink it.

“Lucky you,” Valerie said. “You're on insulin.”

“Nothing happens.”

“Oh, it will. I've had it. Tell me when you get a reaction.”

But I never seemed to get any reaction. I just grew fatter and fatter. Already I filled the new, too-big clothes my mother had bought, and when I peered down at my plump stomach and my broad hips I thought it was a good thing Mrs. Guinea hadn't seen me like this, because I looked just as if I were going to have a baby.

“Have you seen my scars?”

Valerie pushed aside her black bangs and indicated two pale marks, one on either side of her forehead, as if at some time she had started to sprout horns, but cut them off.

We were walking, just the two of us, with the Sports Therapist in the asylum gardens. Nowadays I was let out on walk privileges more and more often. They never let Miss Norris out at all.

Valerie said Miss Norris shouldn't be in Caplan, but in a building for worse people called Wymark.

“Do you know what these scars are?” Valerie persisted.

“No. What are they?”

“I've had a lobotomy.”

I looked at Valerie in awe, appreciating for the first time her perpetual marble calm. “How do you feel?”

“Fine. I'm not angry any more. Before, I was always angry. I was in Wymark before, and now I'm in Caplan. I can go to town, now, or shopping or to a movie, along with a nurse.”

“What will you do when you get out?”

“Oh, I'm not leaving,” Valerie laughed. “I like it here.”

“Moving day!”

“Why should I be moving?”

The nurse went on blithely opening and shutting my drawers, emptying the closet and folding my belongings into the black overnight case.

I thought they must at last be moving me to Wymark. “Oh, you're only moving to the front of the house,” the nurse said cheerfully. “You'll like it. There's lots more sun.”

When we came out into the hall, I saw that Miss Norris was moving too. A nurse, young and cheerful as my own, stood in the doorway of Miss Norris's room, helping Miss Norris into a purple coat with a scrawny squirrel-fur collar.

Hour after hour I had been keeping watch by Miss Norris's bedside, refusing the diversion of OT and walks and badminton matches and even the weekly movies, which I enjoyed, and which Miss Norris never went to, simply to brood over the pale, speechless circlet of her lips.

I thought how exciting it would be if she opened her mouth and spoke, and I rushed out into the hall and announced this to the nurses. They would praise me for encouraging Miss Norris, and I would probably be allowed shopping privileges and movie privileges downtown, and my escape would be assured.

But in all my hours of vigil Miss Norris hadn't said a word.

“Where are you moving to?” I asked her now.

The nurse touched Miss Norris's elbow, and Miss Norris jerked into motion like a doll on wheels.

“She's going to Wymark,” my nurse told me in a low voice. “I'm afraid Miss Norris isn't moving up like you.”

I watched Miss Norris lift one foot, and then the other, over the invisible stile that barred the front doorsill.

“I've a surprise for you,” the nurse said as she installed me in a sunny room in the front wing overlooking the green golf links. “Somebody you know's just come today.”

“Somebody I know?”

The nurse laughed. “Don't look at me like that. It's not a policeman.” Then, as I didn't say anything, she added, “She says she's an old friend of yours. She lives next door. Why don't you pay her a visit?”

I thought the nurse must be joking, and that if I knocked on the door next to mine I would hear no answer, but go in and find Miss Norris, buttoned into her purple, squirrel-collared coat and lying on the bed, her mouth blooming out of the quiet vase of her body like the bud of a rose.

Still, I went out and knocked on the neighboring door.

“Come in!” called a gay voice.

I opened the door a crack and peered into the room. The big, horsey girl in jodhpurs sitting by the window glanced up with a broad smile.

“Esther!” She sounded out of breath, as if she had been running a long, long distance and only just come to a halt. “How nice to see you. They told me you were here.”

“Joan?” I said tentatively, then “Joan!” in confusion and disbelief.

Joan beamed, revealing her large, gleaming, unmistakable teeth.

“It's really me. I thought you'd be surprised.”

Sixteen

Joan's room, with its closet and bureau and table and chair and white blanket with the big blue C on it, was a mirror image of my own. It occurred to me that Joan, hearing where I was, had engaged a room at the asylum on pretense, simply as a joke. That would explain why she had told the nurse I was her friend. I had never known Joan, except at a cool distance.

“How did you get here?” I curled up on Joan's bed.

“I read about you,” Joan said.

“What?”

“I read about you, and I ran away,”

“How do you mean?” I said evenly.

“Well,” Joan leaned back in the chintz-flowered asylum armchair, “I had a summer job working for the chapter head of some fraternity, like the Masons, you know, but not the Masons, and I felt terrible. I had these bunions, I could hardly walk—in the last days I had to wear rubber boots to work, instead of shoes, and you can imagine what that did to my morale…”

I thought either Joan must be crazy—wearing rubber boots to work—or she must be trying to see how crazy I was, believing all that. Besides, only old people ever got bunions. I decided to pretend I thought she was crazy, and that I was only humoring her along.

“I always feel lousy without shoes,” I said with an ambiguous smile. “Did your feet hurt much?”

“Terribly. And my boss—he'd just separated from his wife, he couldn't come right out and get a divorce, because that wouldn't go with this fraternal order—my boss kept buzzing me in every other minute, and each time I moved my feet hurt like the devil, but the second I'd sit down at my desk again, buzz went the buzzer, and he'd have something else he wanted to get off his chest…”

“Why didn't you quit?”

“Oh, I did quit, more or less. I stayed off work on sick leave. I didn't go out. I didn't see anyone. I stowed the telephone in a drawer and never answered it…”

“Then my doctor sent me to a psychiatrist at this big hospital. I had an appointment for twelve o'clock, and I was in an awful state. Finally, at half past twelve, the receptionist came out and told me the doctor had gone to lunch. She asked me if I wanted to wait, and I said yes.”

“Did he come back?” The story sounded rather involved for Joan to have made up out of whole cloth, but I led her on, to see what would come of it.

“Oh yes. I was going to kill myself, mind you. I said ‘If this doctor doesn't do the trick, that's the end.’ Well, the receptionist led me down a long hall, and just as we got to the door she turned to me and said, ‘You won't mind if there are a few students with the doctor, will you?’ What could I say? ‘Oh no,’ I said. I walked in and found nine pairs of eyes fixed on me. Nine! Eighteen separate eyes.

“Now, if that receptionist had told me there were going to be nine people in that room, I'd have walked out on the spot. But there I was, and it was too late to do a thing about it. Well, on this particular day I happened to be wearing a fur coat…”

“In August?”

“Oh, it was one of those cold, wet days, and I thought, my first psychiatrist—you know. Anyway, this psychiatrist kept eyeing that fur coat the whole time I talked to him, and I could just see what he thought of my asking to pay the student's cut rate instead of the full fee. I could see the dollar signs in his eyes. Well, I told him I don't know whatall—about the bunions and the telephone in the drawer and how I wanted to kill myself—and then he asked me to wait outside while he discussed my case with the others, and when he called me back in, you know what he said?”

“What?”

“He folded his hands together and looked at me and said, ‘Miss Gilling, we have decided that you would benefit by group therapy.’”

“Group therapy?” I thought I must sound phony as an echo chamber, but Joan didn't pay any notice.

“That's what he said. Can you imagine me wanting to kill myself, and coming round to chat about it with a whole pack of strangers, and most of them no better than myself…”

“That's crazy.” I was growing involved in spite of myself. “That's not even human.”

“That's just what I said. I went straight home and wrote that doctor a letter. I wrote him one beautiful letter about how a man like that had no business setting himself up to help sick people…”

“Did you get any answer?”

“I don't know. That was the day I read about you.”

“How do you mean?”

“Oh,” Joan said, “about how the police thought you were dead and all. I've got a pile of clippings somewhere.” She heaved herself up, and I had a strong horsey whiff that made my nostrils prickle. Joan had been a champion horse-jumper at the annual college gymkhana, and I wondered if she had been sleeping in a stable.

Joan rummaged in her open suitcase and came up with a fistful of clippings.

“Here, have a look.”

The first clipping showed a big, blown-up picture of a girl with black-shadowed eyes and black lips spread in a grin. I couldn't imagine where such a tarty picture had been taken until I noticed the Bloomingdale earrings and the Bloomingdale necklace glinting out of it with bright, white highlights, like imitation stars.

SCHOLARSHIP GIRL MISSING. MOTHER WORRIED.

The article under the picture told how this girl had disappeared from her home on August 17th, wearing a green skirt and a white blouse, and had left a note saying she was taking a long walk. When Miss Greenwood had not returned by midnight, it said, her mother called the town police.

The next clipping showed a picture of my mother and brother and me grouped together in our backyard and smiling. I couldn't think who had taken that picture either, until I saw I was wearing dungarees and white sneakers and remembered that was what I wore in my spinach-picking summer, and how Dodo Conway had dropped by and taken some family snaps of the three of us one hot afternoon. Mrs. Greenwood asked that this picture be printed in hopes that it will encourage her daughter to return home.

SLEEPING PILLS FEARED MISSING WITH GIRL

A dark, midnight picture of about a dozen moon-faced people in a wood. I thought the people at the end of the row looked queer and unusually short until I realized they were not people, but dogs. Bloodhounds used in search for missing girl. Police Sgt. Bill Hindly says: It doesn't look good.

GIRL FOUND ALIVE!

The last picture showed policemen lifting a long, limp blanket roll with a featureless cabbage head into the back of an ambulance. Then it told how my mother had been down in the cellar, doing the week's laundry, when she heard faint groans coming from a disused hole…

I laid the clippings on the white spread of the bed.

“You keep them,” Joan said. “You ought to stick them in a scrapbook.”

I folded the clippings and slipped them in my pocket.

“I read about you,” Joan went on. “Not how they found you, but everything up to that, and I put all my money together and took the first plane to New York.”

“Why New York?”

“Oh, I thought it would be easier to kill myself in New York.”

“What did you do?”

Joan grinned sheepishly and stretched out her hands, palm up. Like a miniature mountain range, large reddish weals upheaved across the white flesh of her wrists.

“How did you do that?” For the first time it occurred to me Joan and I might have something in common.

“I shoved my fists through my roommate's window.”

“What roommate?”

“My old college roommate. She was working in New York, and I couldn't think of anyplace else to stay, and besides, I'd hardly any money left, so I went to stay with her. My parents found me there—she'd written them I was acting funny—and my father flew straight down and brought me back.”

“But you're all right now.” I made it a statement.

Joan considered me with her bright, pebble-gray eyes. “I guess so,” she said. “Aren't you?”

I had fallen asleep after the evening meal.

I was awakened by a loud voice. Mrs. Bannister, Mrs. Bannister, Mrs. Bannister, Mrs. Bannister. As I pulled out of sleep, I found I was beating on the bedpost with my hands and calling. The sharp, wry figure of Mrs. Bannister, the night nurse, scurried into view.

“Here, we don't want you to break this.”

She unfastened the band of my watch.

“What's the matter? What happened?”

Mrs. Bannister's face twisted into a quick smile. “You've had a reaction.”

“A reaction?”

“Yes, how do you feel?”

“Funny. Sort of light and airy.”

Mrs. Bannister helped me sit up.

“You'll be better now. You'll be better in no time. Would you like some hot milk?”

“Yes.”

And when Mrs. Bannister held the cup to my lips, I fanned the hot milk out on my tongue as it went down, tasting it luxuriously, the way a baby tastes its mother.

“Mrs. Bannister tells me you had a reaction.” Doctor Nolan seated herself in the armchair by the window and took out a tiny box of matches. The box looked exactly like the one I had hidden in the hem of my bathrobe, and for a moment I wondered if a nurse had discovered it there and given it back to Doctor Nolan on the quiet.

Doctor Nolan scraped a match on the side of the box. A hot yellow flame jumped into life, and I watched her suck it up into the cigarette.

“Mrs. B. says you felt better.”

“I did for a while. Now I'm the same again.”

“I've news for you.”

I waited. Every day now, for I didn't know how many days, I had spent the mornings and afternoons and evenings wrapped up in my white blanket on the deck chair in the alcove, pretending to read. I had a dim notion that Doctor Nolan was allowing me a certain number of days and then she would say just what Doctor Gordon had said: “I'm sorry, you don't seem to have improved, I think you'd better have some shock treatments…”

“Well, don't you want to hear what it is?”

“What?” I said dully, and braced myself.

“You're not to have any more visitors for a while.”

I stared at Doctor Nolan in surprise. “Why that's wonderful.”

“I thought you'd be pleased.” She smiled.

Then I looked, and Doctor Nolan looked, at the wastebasket beside my bureau. Out of the wastebasket poked the blood-red buds of a dozen long-stemmed roses.

That afternoon my mother had come to visit me.

My mother was only one in a long stream of visitors—my former employer, the lady Christian Scientist, who walked on the lawn with me and talked about the mist going up from the earth in the Bible, and the mist being error, and my whole trouble being that I believed in the mist, and the minute I stopped believing in it, it would disappear and I would see I had always been well, and the English teacher I had in high school who came and tried to teach me how to play Scrabble, because he thought it might revive my old interest in words, and Philomena Guinea herself, who wasn't at all satisfied with what the doctors were doing and kept telling them so.

I hated these visits.

I would be sitting in my alcove or in my room, and a smiling nurse would pop in and announce one or another of the visitors. Once they'd even brought the minister of the Unitarian church, whom I'd never really liked at all. He was terribly nervous the whole time, and I could tell he thought I was crazy as a loon, because I told him I believed in hell, and that certain people, like me, had to live in hell before they died, to make up for missing out on it after death, since they didn't believe in life after death, and what each person believed happened to him when he died.

I hated these visits, because I kept feeling the visitors measuring my fat and stringy hair a gainst what I had been and what they wanted me to be, and I knew they went away utterly confounded.

I thought if they left me alone I might have some peace.

My mother was the worst. She never scolded me, but kept begging me, with a sorrowful face, to tell her what she had done wrong. She said she was sure the doctors thought she had done something wrong because they asked her a lot of questions about my toilet training, and I had been perfectly trained at a very early age and given her no trouble whatsoever.

That afternoon my mother had brought me the roses.

“Save them for my funeral,” I'd said.

My mother's face puckered, and she looked ready to cry.

“But Esther, don't you remember what day it is today?”

“No.”

I thought it might be Saint Valentine's day. “It's your birthday.”

And that was when I had dumped the roses in the waste-basket.

“That was a silly thing for her to do,” I said to Doctor Nolan.

Doctor Nolan nodded. She seemed to know what I meant. “I hate her,” I said, and waited for the blow to fall.

But Doctor Nolan only smiled at me as if something had pleased her very, very much, and said, “I suppose you do.”

Seventeen

“You're a lucky girl today.”

The young nurse cleared my breakfast tray away and left me wrapped in my white blanket like a passenger taking the sea air on the deck of a ship.

“Why am I lucky?”

“Well, I'm not sure if you're supposed to know yet, but today, you're moving to Belsize.” The nurse looked at me expectantly.

“Belsize,” I said. “I can't go there.”

“Why not?”

“I'm not ready. I'm not well enough.”

“Of course, you're well enough. Don't worry, they wouldn't be moving you if you weren't well enough.”

After the nurse left, I tried to puzzle out this new move on Doctor Nolan's part. What was she trying to prove? I hadn't changed. Nothing had changed. And Belsize was the best house of all. From Belsize people went back to work and back to school and back to their homes.

Joan would be at Belsize. Joan with her physics books and her golf clubs and her badminton rackets and her breathy voice. Joan, marking the gulf between me and the nearly well ones. Ever since Joan left Caplan I'd followed her progress through the asylum grapevine.

Joan had walk privileges, Joan had shopping privileges, Joan had town privileges. I gathered all my news of Joan into a little, bitter heap, though I received it with surface gladness. Joan was the beaming double of my old best self, specially designed to follow and torment me.

Perhaps Joan would be gone when I got to Belsize.

At least at Belsize I could forget about shock treatments. At Caplan a lot of the women had shock treatments. I could tell which ones they were, because they didn't get their breakfast trays with the rest of us. They had their shock treatments while we breakfasted in our rooms, and then they came into the lounge, quiet and extinguished, led like children by the nurses, and ate their breakfasts there.

Each morning, when I heard the nurse knock with my tray, an immense relief flooded through me, because I knew I was out of danger for that day. I didn't see how Doctor Nolan could tell you went to sleep during a shock treatment if she'd never had a shock treatment herself. How did she know the person didn't just look as if he was asleep, while all the time, inside, he was feeling the blue volts and the noise?

Piano music sounded from the end of the hall.

At supper I sat quietly, listening to the chatter of the Belsize women. They were all fashionably dressed and carefully made up, and several of them were married. Some of them had been shopping downtown, and others had been out visiting friends, and all during supper they kept tossing back and forth these private jokes.

“I'd call Jack,” a woman named DeeDee said, “only I'm afraid he wouldn't be home. I know just where I could call him, though, and he'd be in, all right.”

The short, spry blonde woman at my table laughed. “I almost had Doctor Loring where I wanted him today.” She widened her starey blue eyes like a little doll. “I wouldn't mind trading old Percy in for a new model.”

At the opposite end of the room, Joan was wolfing her Spam and broiled tomato with great appetite. She seemed perfectly at home among these women and treated me coolly,with a slight sneer, like a dim and inferior acquaintance.

I had gone to bed right after supper, but then I heard the piano music and pictured Joan and DeeDee and Loubelle, the blonde woman, and the rest of them, laughing and gossiping about me in the living room behind my back. They would be saying how awful it was to have people like me in Belsize and that I should be in Wymark instead.

I decided to put a lid on their nasty talk.

Draping my blanket loosely around my shoulders, like a stole, I wandered down the hall toward the light and the gay noise.

For the rest of the evening I listened to DeeDee thump out some of her own songs on the grand piano, while the other women sat round playing bridge and chatting, just the way they would in a college dormitory, only most of them were ten years over college age.

One of them, a great, tall, gray-haired woman with a booming bass voice, named Mrs. Savage, had gone to Vassar. I could tell right away she was a society woman, because she talked about nothing but débutantes. It seemed she had two or three daughters, and that year they were all going to be débutantes, only she had loused up their débutante party by signing herself into the asylum.

DeeDee had one song she called “The Milkman” and everybody kept saying she ought to get it published, it would be a hit. First her hands would clop out a little melody on the keys, like the hoofbeats of a slow pony, and next another melody came in, like the milkman whistling, and then the two melodies went on together.

“That's very nice,” I said in a conversational voice.

Joan was leaning on one corner of the piano and leafing through a new issue of some fashion magazine, and DeeDee smiled up at her as if the two of them shared a secret.

“Oh, Esther,” Joan said then, holding up the magazine, “isn't this you?”

DeeDee stopped playing. “Let me see.” She took the magazine, peered at the page Joan pointed to, and then glanced back at me.

“Oh no,” DeeDee said. “Surely not.” She looked at the magazine again, then at me. “Never!”

“Oh, but it is Esther, isn't it, Esther?” Joan said.

Loubelle and Mrs. Savage drifted over, and pretending I knew what it was all about, I moved to the piano with them.

The magazine photograph showed a girl in a strapless evening dress of fuzzy white stuff, grinning fit to split, with a whole lot of boys bending around her. The girl was holding a glass full of a transparent drink and seemed to have her eyes fixed over my shoulder on something that stood behind me, a little to my left. A faint breath fanned the back of my neck. I wheeled round.

The night nurse had come in, unnoticed, on her soft rubber soles.

“No kidding,” she said, “is that really you?”

“No, it's not me. Joan's quite mistaken. It's somebody else.”

“Oh, say it's you!” DeeDee cried. But I pretended I didn't hear her and turned away.Then Loubelle begged the nurse to make a fourth at bridge, and I drew up a chair to watch, although I didn't know the first thing about bridge, because I hadn't had time to pick it up at college, the way all the wealthy girls did.

I stared at the flat poker faces of the kings and jacks and queens and listened to the nurse talking about her hard life. “You ladies don't know what it is, holding down two jobs,” she said. “Nights I'm over here, watching you…”

Loubelle giggled. “Oh, we're good. We're the best of the lot, and you know it.”

“Oh, you're all right.” The nurse passed round a packet of spearmint gum, then unfolded a pink strap from its tinfoil wrapper herself. “You're all right, it's those boobies at the state place that worry me off my feet.”

“Do you work in both places then?” I asked with sudden interest.

“You bet.” The nurse gave me a straight look, and I could see she thought I had no business in Belsize at all. “You wouldn't like it over there one bit, Lady Jane.”

I found it strange that the nurse should call me Lady Jane when she knew what my name was perfectly well.

“Why?” I persisted.

“Oh, it's not a nice place, like this. This is a regular country club. Over there they've got nothing. No OT to talk of, no walks…”

“Why haven't they got walks?”

“Not enough em-ploy-ees.” The nurse scooped in a trick and Loubelle groaned. “Believe me, ladies, when I collect enough do-re-mi to buy me a car, I'm clearing out.”

“Will you clear out of here, too?” Joan wanted to know.

“You bet. Only private cases from then on. When I feel like it…”

But I'd stopped listening.

I felt the nurse had been instructed to show me my alternatives. Either I got better, or I fell, down, down, like a burning, then burnt-out star, from Belsize, to Caplan, to Wymark and finally, after Doctor Nolan and Mrs. Guinea had given me up, to the state place next door.

I gathered my blanket round me and pushed back my chair.

“You cold?” the nurse demanded rudely.

“Yes,” I said, moving off down the hall. “I'm frozen stiff.”

I woke warm and placid in my white cocoon. A shaft of pale, wintry sunlight dazzled the mirror and the glasses on the bureau and the metal doorknobs. From across the hall came the early-morning clatter of the maids in the kitchen, preparing the breakfast trays.

I heard the nurse knock on the door next to mine, at the far end of the hall. Mrs. Savage's sleepy voice boomed out, and the nurse went in to her with the jingling tray. I thought, with a mild stir of pleasure, of the steaming blue china coffee pitcher and the blue china breakfast cup and the fat blue china cream jug with the white daisies on it.

I was beginning to resign myself.

If I was going to fall, I would hang on to my small comforts, at least, as long as I possibly could.

The nurse rapped on my door and, without waiting for an answer, breezed in.

It was a new nurse—they were always changing—with a lean, sand-colored face and sandy hair, and large freckles polka-dotting her bony nose. For some reason the sight of this nurse made me sick at heart, and it was only as she strode across the room to snap up the green blind that I realized part of her strangeness came from being empty-handed.

I opened my mouth to ask for my breakfast tray, but silenced myself immediately. The nurse would be mistaking me for somebody else. New nurses often did that. Somebody in Belsize must be having shock treatments, unknown to me, and the nurse had, quite understandably, confused me with her.

I waited until the nurse had made her little circuit of my room, patting, straightening, arranging, and taken the next tray in to Loubelle one door farther down the hall.

Then I shoved my feet into my slippers, dragging my blanket with me, for the morning was bright, but very cold, and crossed quickly to the kitchen. The pink-uniformed maid was filling a row of blue china coffee pitchers from a great, battered kettle on the stove.

I looked with love at the lineup of waiting trays—the white paper napkins, folded in their crisp, isosceles triangles, each under the anchor of its silver fork, the pale domes of soft-boiled eggs in the blue egg cups, the scalloped glass shells of orange marmalade. All I had to do was reach out and claim my tray, and the world would be perfectly normal.

“There's been a mistake,” I told the maid, leaning over the counter and speaking in a low, confidential tone. “The new nurse forgot to bring me in my breakfast tray today.”

I managed a bright smile, to show there were no hard feelings.

“What's the name?”

“Greenwood. Esther Greenwood.”

“Greenwood, Greenwood, Greenwood.” The maid's warty index finger slid down the list of names of the patients in Belsize tacked upon the kitchen wall. “Greenwood, no breakfast today.”

I caught the rim of the counter with both hands.

“There must be a mistake. Are you sure it's Greenwood?”

“Greenwood,” the maid said decisively as the nurse came in.

The nurse looked questioningly from me to the maid. “Miss Greenwood wanted her tray,” the maid said, avoiding my eyes.

“Oh,” the nurse smiled at me, “you'll be getting your tray later on this morning, Miss Greenwood. You…”

But I didn't wait to hear what the nurse said. I strode blindly out into the hall, not to my room, because that was where they would come to get me, but to the alcove, greatly inferior to the alcove at Caplan, but an alcove, nevertheless, in a quiet corner of the hall,where Joan and Loubelle and DeeDee and Mrs. Savage would not come.

I curled up in the far corner of the alcove with the blanket over my head. It wasn't the shock treatment that struck me, so much as the bare-faced treachery of Doctor Nolan. I liked Doctor Nolan, I loved her, I had given her my trust on a platter and told her everything, and she had promised, faithfully, to warn me ahead of time if ever I had to have another shock treatment.

If she had told me the night before I would have lain awake all night, of course, full of dread and foreboding, but by morning I would have been composed and ready. I would have gone down the hall between two nurses, past DeeDee and Loubelle and Mrs. Savage and Joan, with dignity, like a person coolly resigned to execution.

The nurse bent over me and called my name.

I pulled away and crouched farther into the corner. The nurse disappeared. I knew she would return, in a minute, with two burly men attendants, and they would bear me, howling and hitting, past the smiling audience now gathered in the lounge.

Doctor Nolan put her arm around me and hugged me like a mother.

“You said you'd tell me!” I shouted at her through the dishevelled blanket.

“But I am telling you,” Doctor Nolan said. “I've come specially early to tell you, and I'm taking you over myself.”

I peered at her through swollen lids. “Why didn't you tell me last night?”

“I only thought it would keep you awake. If I'd known…”

“You said you'd tell me.”

“Listen, Esther,” Doctor Nolan said. “I'm going over with you. I'll be there the whole time, so everything will happen right, the way I promised. I'll be there when you wake up, and I'll bring you back again.”

I looked at her. She seemed very upset.

I waited a minute. Then I said, “Promise you'll be there.”

“I promise.”

Doctor Nolan took out a white handkerchief and wiped my face. Then she hooked her arm in my arm, like an old friend, and helped me up, and we started down the hall. My blanket tangled about my feet, so I let it drop, but Doctor Nolan didn't seem to notice. We passed Joan, coming out of her room, and I gave her a meaning, disdainful smile and she ducked back and waited until we had gone by.

Then Doctor Nolan unlocked a door at the end of the hall and led me down a flight of stairs into the mysterious basement corridors that linked, in an elaborate network of tunnels and burrows, all the various buildings of the hospital.

The walls were bright, white lavatory tile with bald bulbs set at intervals in the black ceiling. Stretchers and wheelchairs were beached here and there against the hissing, knocking pipes that ran and branched in an intricate nervous system along the glittering walls. I hung on to Doctor Nolan's arm like death, and every so often she gave me an encouraging squeeze.

Finally, we stopped at a green door with Electrotherapy printed on it in black letters. I held back, and Doctor Nolan waited. Then I said, “Let's get it over with,” and we went in.

The only people in the waiting room besides Doctor Nolan and me were a pallid man in a shabby maroon bathrobe and his accompanying nurse.

“Do you want to sit down?” Doctor Nolan pointed at a wooden bench, but my legs felt full of heaviness, and I thought how hard it would be to hoist myself from a sitting position when the shock treatment people came in.

“I'd rather stand.”

At last a tall, cadaverous woman in a white smock entered the room from an inner door. I thought that she would go up and take the man in the maroon bathrobe, as he was first, so I was surprised when she came toward me.

“Good morning, Doctor Nolan,” the woman said, putting her arm around my shoulders. “Is this Esther?”

“Yes, Miss Huey. Esther, this is Miss Huey, she'll take good care of you. I've told her about you.”

I thought the woman must be seven feet tall. She bent over me in a kind way, and I could see that her face, with the buck teeth protruding in the center, had at one time been badly pitted with acne. It looked like maps of the craters on the moon.

“I think we can take you right away, Esther,” Miss Huey said. “Mr. Anderson won't mind waiting, will you, Mr. Anderson?”

Mr. Anderson didn't say a word, so with Miss Huey's arm around my shoulder, and Doctor Nolan following, I moved into the next room.

Through the slits of my eyes, which I didn't dare open too far, lest the full view strike me dead, I saw the high bed with its white, drumtight sheet, and the machine behind the bed, and the masked person—I couldn't tell whether it was a man or a woman—behind the machine, and other masked people flanking the bed on both sides.

Miss Huey helped me climb up and lie down on my back.

“Talk to me,” I said.

Miss Huey began to talk in a low, soothing voice, smoothing the salve on my temples and fitting the small electric buttons on either side of my head. “You'll be perfectly all right, you won't feel a thing, just bite down…” And she set something on my tongue and in panic I bit down, and darkness wiped me out like chalk on a blackboard.

Eighteen

“Esther.”

I woke out of a deep, drenched sleep, and the first thing I saw was Doctor Nolan's face swimming in front of me and saying, “Esther, Esther.”

I rubbed my eyes with an awkward hand.

Behind Doctor Nolan I could see the body of a woman wearing a rumpled black-and-white checked robe and flung out on a cot as if dropped from a great height. But before I could take in any more, Doctor Nolan led me through a door into fresh, blue-skied air.

All the heat and fear purged itself. I felt surprisingly at peace. The bell jar hung, suspended, a few feet above my head. I was open to the circulating air.

“It was like I told you it would be, wasn't it?” said Doctor Nolan, as we walked back to Belsize together through the crunch of brown leaves.

“Yes.”

“Well, it will always be like that,” she said firmly. “You will be having shock treatments three times a week—Tuesday, Thursday and Saturday.”

I gulped in a long draught of air.

“For how long?”

“That depends,” Doctor Nolan said, “on you and me.”

I took up the silver knife and cracked off the cap of my egg. Then I put down the knife and looked at it. I tried to think what I had loved knives for, but my mind slipped from the noose of the thought and swung, like a bird, in the center of empty air.

Joan and DeeDee were sitting side by side on the piano bench, and DeeDee was teaching Joan to play the bottom half of “Chopsticks” while she played the top.

I thought how sad it was Joan looked so horsey, with such big teeth and eyes like two gray, goggly pebbles. Why, she couldn't even keep a boy like Buddy Willard. And DeeDee's husband was obviously living with some mistress or other and turning her sour as an old fusty cat.

“I've got a let-ter,” Joan chanted, poking her tousled head inside my door.

“Good for you.” I kept my eyes on my book. Ever since the shock treatments had ended, after a brief series of five, and I had town privileges, Joan hung about me like a large and breathless fruitfly—as if the sweetness of recovery were something she could suck up by mere nearness. They had taken away her physics books and the piles of dusty spiral pads full of lecture notes that had ringed her room, and she was confined to grounds again.

“Don't you want to know who it's from ?”

Joan edged into the room and sat down on my bed. I wanted to tell her to get the hell out, she gave me the creeps, only I couldn't do it.

“All right.” I stuck my finger in my place and shut the book. “Who from?”

Joan slipped out a pale blue envelope from her skirt pocket and waved it teasingly.

“Well, isn't that a coincidence!” I said.

“What do you mean, a coincidence?”

I went over to my bureau, picked up a pale blue envelope and waved it at Joan like aparting handkerchief. “I got a letter too. I wonder if they're the same.”

“He's better,” Joan said. “He's out of the hospital.”

There was a little pause.

“Are you going to marry him?”

“No,” I said. “Are you?”

Joan grinned evasively. “I didn't like him much, anyway.”

“Oh?”

“No, it was his family I liked.”

“You mean Mr. and Mrs. Willard?”

“Yes.” Joan's voice slid down my spine like a draft. “I loved them. They were so nice, so happy, nothing like my parents. I went over to see them all the time,” she paused, “until you came.”

“I'm sorry.” Then I added, “Why didn't you go on seeing them, if you liked them so much?”

“Oh, I couldn't,” Joan said. “Not with you dating Buddy. It would have looked…I don't know, funny.”

I considered. “I suppose so.”

“Are you,” Joan hesitated, “going to let him come?”

“I don't know.”

At first I had thought it would be awful having Buddy come and visit me at the asylum— he would probably only come to gloat and hobnob with the other doctors. But then it seemed to me it would be a step, placing him, renouncing him, in spite of the fact that I had nobody—telling him there was no simultaneous interpreter, nobody, but that he was the wrong one, that I had stopped hanging on. “Are you?”

“Yes,” Joan breathed. “Maybe he'll bring his mother. I'm going to ask him to bring his mother…”

“His mother?”

Joan pouted. “I like Mrs. Willard. Mrs. Willard's a wonderful, wonderful woman. She's been a real mother to me.”

I had a picture of Mrs. Willard, with her heather-mixture tweeds and her sensible shoes and her wise, maternal maxims. Mr. Willard was her little boy, and his voice was high and dear, like a little boy's. Joan and Mrs. Willard. Joan…and Mrs.Willard…

I had knocked on DeeDee's door that morning, wanting to borrow some two-part sheet music. I waited a few minutes and then, hearing no answer and thinking DeeDee must be out, and I could pick up the music from her bureau, I pushed the door open and stepped into the room.

At Belsize, even at Belsize, the doors had locks, but the patients had no keys. A shut door meant privacy, and was respected, like a locked door. One knocked, and knocked again, then went away. I remembered this as I stood, my eyes half-useless after the brilliance of the hall, in the room's deep, musky dark.

As my vision cleared, I saw a shape rise from the bed. Then somebody gave a low giggle. The shape adjusted its hair, and two pale, pebble eyes regarded me through the gloom. DeeDee lay back on the pillows, bare-legged under her green wool dressing gown, and watched me with a little mocking smile. A cigarette glowed between the fingers of her right hand.

“I just wanted…” I said.

“I know,” said DeeDee. “The music.”

“Hello, Esther,” Joan said then, and her cornhusk voice made me want to puke. “Wait for me, Esther, I'll come play the bottom part with you.”

Now Joan said stoutly, “I never really liked Buddy Willard. He thought he knew everything. He thought he knew everything about women…”

I looked at Joan. In spite of the creepy feeling, and in spite of my old, ingrained dislike, Joan fascinated me. It was like observing a Martian, or a particularly warty toad. Her thoughts were not my thoughts, nor her feelings my feelings, but we were close enough so that her thoughts and feelings seemed a wry, black image of my own.

Sometimes I wondered if I had made Joan up. Other times I wondered if she would continue to pop in at every crisis of my life to remind me of what I had been, and what I had been through, and carry on her own separate but similar crisis under my nose.

“I don't see what women see in other women,” I'd told Doctor Nolan in my interview that noon. “What does a woman see in a woman that she can't see in a man?”

Doctor Nokn paused. Then she said, “Tenderness.”

That shut me up.

“I like you,” Joan was saying. “I like you better than Buddy.”

And as she stretched out on my bed with a silly smile, I remembered a minor scandal at our college dormitory when a fat, matronly-breasted senior, homely as a grandmother and a pious Religion major, and a tall, gawky freshman with a history of being deserted at an early hour in all sorts of ingenious ways by her blind dates, started seeing too much of each other. They were always together, and once somebody had come upon them embracing, the story went, in the fat girl's room.

“But what were they doing?” I had asked. Whenever I thought about men and men, and women and women, I could never really imagine what they would be actually doing.

“Oh,” the spy had said, “Milly was sitting on the chair and Theodora was lying on the bed, and Milly was stroking Theodora's hair.”

I was disappointed. I had thought I would have some revelation of specific evil. I wondered if all women did with other women was lie and hug.

Of course, the famous woman poet at my college lived with another woman—a stumpy old Classical scholar with a cropped Dutch cut. And when I had told the poet I might well get married and have a pack of children someday, she stared at me in horror. “But what about your career?” she had cried.

My head ached. Why did I attract these weird old women? There was the famous poet, and Philomena Guinea, and Jay Cee, and the Christian Scientist lady and lord knows who, and they all wanted to adopt me in some way, and, for the price of their care and influence, have me resemble them.

“I like you.”

“That's tough, Joan,” I said, picking up my book. “Because I don't like you. You make me puke, if you want to know.”

And I walked out of the room, leaving Joan lying, lumpy as an old horse, across my bed.

I waited for the doctor, wondering if I should bolt. I knew what I was doing was illegal—in Massachusetts, anyway, because the state was cram-jam full of Catholics—but Doctor Nolan said this doctor was an old friend of hers, and a wise man.

“What's your appointment for?” the brisk, white-uniformed receptionist wanted to know, ticking my name off on a notebook list.

“What do you mean, for?” I hadn't thought anybody but the doctor himself would ask me that, and the communal waiting room was full of other patients waiting for other doctors,most of them pregnant or with babies, and I felt their eyes on my flat, virgin stomach.

The receptionist glanced up at me, and I blushed.

“A fitting, isn't it?” she said kindly. “I only wanted to make sure so I'd know what to charge you. Are you a student?”

“Ye-es.”

“That will only be half-price then. Five dollars, instead of ten. Shall I bill you?”

I was about to give my home address, where I would probably be by the time the bill arrived, but then I thought of my mother opening the bill and seeing what it was for. The only other address I had was the innocuous box number which people used who didn't want to advertise the fact they lived in an asylum. But I thought the receptionist might recognize the box number, so I said, “I better pay now,” and peeled five dollar notes off the roll in my pocketbook.

The five dollars was part of what Philomena Guinea had sent me as a sort of get-well present. I wondered what she would think if she knew to what use her money was being put.

Whether she knew it or not, Philomena Guinea was buying my freedom.

“What I hate is the thought of being under a man's thumb,” I had told Doctor Nolan. “A man doesn't have a worry in the world, while I've got a baby hanging over my head like a big stick, to keep me in line.”

“Would you act differently if you didn't have to worry about a baby?”

“Yes,” I said, “but…” and I told Doctor Nolan about the married woman lawyer and her Defense of Chastity.

Doctor Nolan waited until I was finished. Then she burst out laughing. “Propaganda!” she said, and scribbled the name and address of this doctor on a prescription pad.

I leafed nervously through an issue of Baby Talk. The fat, bright faces of babies beamed up at me, page after page—bald babies, chocolate-colored babies, Eisenhower-faced babies, babies rolling over for the first time, babies reaching for rattles, babies eating their first spoonful of solid food, babies doing all the little tricky things it takes to grow up, step by step, into an anxious and unsettling world.

I smelt a mingling of Pablum and sour milk and salt-cod-stinky diapers and felt sorrowful and tender. How easy having babies seemed to the women around me! Why was I so unmaternal and apart? Why couldn't I dream of devoting myself to baby after fat puling baby like Dodo Conway? If I had to wait on a baby all day, I would go mad. I looked at the baby in the lap of the woman opposite. I had no idea how old it was, I never did, with babies—for all I knew it could talk a blue streak and had twenty teeth behind its pursed, pink lips. It held its little wobby head up on its shoulders—it didn't seem to have a neck—and observed me with a wise, Platonic expression.

The baby's mother smiled and smiled, holding that baby as if it were the first wonder of the world. I watched the mother and the baby for some clue to their mutual satisfaction, but before I had discovered anything, the doctor called me in.

“You'd like a fitting,” he said cheerfully, and I thought with relief that he wasn't the sort of doctor to ask awkward questions. I had toyed with the idea of telling him I planned to be married to a sailor as soon as his ship docked at the Charlestown Navy Yard, and the reason I didn't have an engagement ring was because we were too poor, but at the last moment I rejected that appealing story and simply said “Yes.”

I climbed up on the examination table, thinking: “I am climbing to freedom, freedom from fear, freedom from marrying the wrong person, like Buddy Willard, just because of sex, freedom from the Florence Crittenden Homes where all the poor girls go who should have been fitted out like me, because what they did, they would do anyway, regardless…”

As I rode back to the asylum with my box in the plain brown paper wrapper on my lap. I might have been Mrs. Anybody coming back from a day in town with a Schrafft's cake for her maiden aunt or a Filene's Basement hat. Gradually the suspicion that Catholics had X-ray eyes diminished, and I grew easy. I had done well by my shopping privileges, I thought.

I was my own woman.

The next step was to find the proper sort of man.

Nineteen

“I'm going to be a psychiatrist.”

Joan spoke with her usual breathy enthusiasm.We were drinking apple cider in the Belsize lounge.

“Oh,” I said dryly, “that's nice.”

“I've had a long talk with Doctor Quinn, and she thinks it's perfectly possible.” Doctor Quinn was Joan's psychiatrist, a bright, shrewd, single lady, and I often thought if I had been assigned to Doctor Quinn I would be still in Caplan or, more probably,Wymark. Doctor Quinn had an abstract quality that appealed to Joan, but it gave me the polar chills.

Joan chattered on about Egos and Ids, and I turned my mind to something else, to the brown, unwrapped package in my bottom drawer. I never talked about Egos and Ids with Doctor Nolan. I didn't know just what I talked about really.

“…I'm going to live out, now.”

I tuned in on Joan then. “Where?” I demanded, trying to hide my envy.

Doctor Nolan said my college would take me back for the second semester, on her recommendation and Philomena Guinea's scholarship, but as the doctors vetoed my living with my mother in the interim, I was staying on at the asylum until the winter term began.

Even so, I felt it unfair of Joan to beat me through the gates.

“Where?” I persisted. “They're not letting you live on your own, are they?” Joan had only that week been given town privileges again.

“Oh no, of course not. I'm living in Cambridge with Nurse Kennedy. Her roommate's just got married, and she needs someone to share the apartment.”

“Cheers.” I raised my apple cider glass, and we clinked. In spite of my profound reservations, I thought I would always treasure Joan. It was as if we had been forced together by some overwhelming circumstance, like war or plague, and shared a world of our own. “When are you leaving?”

“On the first of the month.”

“Nice.”

Joan grew wistful, “You'll come visit me, won't you, Esther?”

“Of course.”

But I thought, “Not likely.”

“It hurts,” I said. “Is it supposed to hurt?”

Irwin didn't say anything. Then he said, “Sometimes it hurts.”

I had met Irwin on the steps of the Widener Library. I was standing at the top of the long flight, overlooking the red brick buildings that walled the snow-filled quad and preparing to catch the trolley back to the asylum, when a tall young man with a rather ugly and bespectacled, but intelligent face, came up and said, “Could you please tell me the time?”

I glanced at my watch. “Five past four.”

Then the man shifted his arms around the load of books he was carrying before him like a dinner tray and revealed a bony wrist.

“Why, you've a watch yourself!”

The man looked ruefully at his watch. He lifted it and shook it by his ear. “Doesn't work.” He smiled engagingly. “Where are you going?”

I was about to say, “Back to the asylum,” but the man looked promising, so I changed my mind. “Home.”

“Would you like some coffee first?”

I hesitated. I was due at the asylum for supper and I didn't want to be late so close to being signed out of there for good.

“A very small cup of coffee?”

I decided to practice my new, normal personality on this man who, in the course of my hesitations, told me his name was Irwin and that he was a very well-paid professor of mathematics, so I said, “All right,” and, matching my stride to Irwin's, strolled down the long, ice-encrusted flight at his side.

It was only after seeing Irwin's study that I decided to seduce him.

Irwin lived in a murky, comfortable basement apartment in one of the rundown streets of outer Cambridge and drove me there—for a beer, he said—after three cups of bitter coffee in a student cafe. We sat in his study on stuffed brown leather chairs, surrounded by stacks of dusty, incomprehensible books with huge formulas inset artistically on the page like poems.

While I was sipping my first glass of beer—I have never really cared for cold beer in midwinter, but I accepted the glass to have something solid to hold on to—the doorbell rang.

Irwin seemed embarrassed. “I think it may be a lady.”

Irwin had a queer, old-world habit of calling women ladies.

“Fine, fine,” I gestured largely. “Bring her in.”

Irwin shook his head. “You would upset her.”

I smiled into my amber cylinder of cold beer.

The doorbell rang again with a peremptory jab. Irwin sighed and rose to answer it. The minute he disappeared, I whipped into the bathroom and, concealed behind the dirty, aluminum-colored Venetian blind, watched Irwin's monkish face appear in the door crack.

A large, bosomy Slavic lady in a bulky sweater of natural sheep's wool, purple slacks, high-heeled black overshoes with Persian lamb cuffs and a matching toque, puffed white, inaudible words into the wintry air. Irwin's voice drifted back to me through the chilly hall.

“I'm sorry, Olga…I'm working, Olga…no, I don't think so, Olga,” all the while the lady's red mouth moved and the words, translated to white smoke, floated up among the branches of the naked lilac by the door. Then, finally, “Perhaps, Olga…good-bye, Olga.”

I admired the immense, steppelike expanse of the lady's wool-clad bosom as she retreated a few inches from my eye, down the creaking wooden stair, a sort of Siberian bitterness on her vivid lips.

“I suppose you have lots and lots of affairs in Cambridge,” I told Irwin cheerily, as I stuck a snail with a pin in one of Cambridge's determinedly French restaurants.

“I seem,” Irwin admitted with a small, modest smile, “to get on with the ladies.”

I picked up my empty snail shell and drank the herb-green juice. I had no idea if this was proper, but after months of wholesome, dull asylum diet, I was greedy for butter.

I had called Doctor Nolan from a pay phone at the restaurant and asked for permission to stay overnight in Cambridge with Joan. Of course, I had no idea whether Irwin would invite me back to his apartment after dinner or not, but I thought his dismissal of the Slavic lady—another professor's wife—looked promising.

I tipped back my head and poured down a glass of Nuits-St.-Georges.

“You do like wine,” Irwin observed.

“Only Nuits-St.-Georges. I imagine him…with the dragon…”

Irwin reached for my hand.

I felt the first man I slept with must be intelligent, so I would respect him. Irwin was afull professor at twenty-six and had the pale, hairless skin of a boy genius. I also needed somebody quite experienced to make up for my lack of it, and Irwin's ladies reassured me on this head. Then, to be on the safe side, I wanted somebody I didn't know and wouldn't go on knowing—a kind of impersonal, priestlike official, as in the tales of tribal rites.

By the end of the evening I had no doubts about Irwin whatsoever.

Ever since I'd learned about the corruption of Buddy Willard my virginity weighed like a millstone around my neck. It had been of such enormous importance to me for so long that my habit was to defend it at all costs. I had been defending it for five years and I was sick of it.

It was only as Irwin swung me into his arms, back at the apartment, and carried me, wine-dazed and limp, into the pitch-black bedroom, that I murmured, “You know, Irwin, I think I ought to tell you, I'm a virgin.”

Irwin laughed and flung me down on the bed.

A few minutes later an exclamation of surprise revealed that Irwin hadn't really believed me. I thought how lucky it was I had started practicing birth control during the day, because in my winey state that night I would never have bothered to perform the delicate and necessary operation. I lay, rapt and naked, on Irwin's rough blanket, waiting for the miraculous change to make itself felt.

But all I felt was a sharp, startlingly bad pain.

“It hurts,” I said. “Is it supposed to hurt?”

Irwin didn't say anything. Then he said, “Sometimes it hurts.”

After a little while Irwin got up and went into the bathroom, and I heard the rushing of shower water. I wasn't sure if Irwin had done what he planned to do, or if my virginity had obstructed him in some way. I wanted to ask him if I was still a virgin, but I felt too unsettled. A warm liquid was seeping out between my legs. Tentatively, I reached down and touched it.

When I held my hand up to the light streaming in from the bathroom, my fingertips looked black.

“Irwin,” I said nervously, “bring me a towel.”

Irwin strolled back, a bathtowel knotted around his waist, and tossed me a second, smaller towel. I pushed the towel between my legs and pulled it away almost immediately. It was half black with blood.

“I'm bleeding!” I announced, sitting up with a start.

“Oh, that often happens,” Irwin reassured me. “You'll be all right.”

Then the stories of blood-stained bridal sheets and capsules of red ink bestowed on already deflowered brides floated back to me. I wondered how much I would bleed, and lay down, nursing the towel. It occurred to me that the blood was my answer. I couldn't possibly be a virgin any more. I smiled into the dark. I felt part of a great tradition.

Surreptitiously, I applied a fresh section of white towel to my wound, thinking that as soon as the bleeding stopped, I would take the late trolley back to the asylum. I wanted to brood over my new condition in perfect peace. But the towel came away black and dripping.

“I…think I better go home,” I said faintly.

“Surely not so soon.”

“Yes, I think I better.”

I asked if I could borrow Irwin's towel and packed it between my thighs as a bandage.Then I pulled on my sweaty clothes. Irwin offered to drive me home, but I didn't see how I could let him drive me to the asylum, so I dug in my pocketbook for Joan's address. Irwin knew the street and went out to start the car. I was too worried to tell him I was still bleeding. I kept hoping every minute that it would stop.

But as Irwin drove me through the barren, snow-banked streets I felt the warm seepage let itself through the dam of the towel and my skirt and onto the car seat.

As we slowed, cruising by house after lit house, I thought how fortunate it was I had not discarded my virginity while living at college or at home, where such concealment would have been impossible.

Joan opened the door with an expression of glad surprise. Irwin kissed my hand and told Joan to take good care of me.

I shut the door and leaned back against it, feeling the blood drain from my face in one spectacular flush.

“Why, Esther,” Joan said, “what on earth's the matter?”

I wondered when Joan would notice the blood trickling down my legs and oozing, stickily, into each black patent leather shoe. I thought I could be dying from a bullet wound and Joan would still stare through me with her blank eyes, expecting me to ask for a cup of coffee and a sandwich.

“Is that nurse here?”

“No, she's on night duty at Caplan…”

“Good.” I made a little bitter grin as another soak of blood let itself through the drenched padding and started the tedious journey into my shoes. “I mean…bad.”

“You look funny,” Joan said.

“You better get a doctor.”

“Why?”

“Quick”

“But…”

Still she hadn't noticed anything.

I bent down, with a brief grunt, and slipped off one of my winter-cracked black Bloomingdale shoes. I held the shoe up, before Joan's enlarged, pebbly eyes, tilted it, and watched her take in the stream of blood that cascaded onto the beige rug.

“My God!What is it?”

“I'm hemorrhaging.”

Joan half led, half dragged me to the sofa and made me lie down. Then she propped some pillows under my blood-stained feet. Then she stood back and demanded, “Who was that man?”

For one crazy minute I thought Joan would refuse to call a doctor until I confessed the whole story of my evening with Irwin and that after my confession she would still refuse, as a sort of punishment. But then I realized that she honestly took my explanation at face value, that my going to bed with Irwin was utterly incomprehensible to her, and his appearance a mere prick to her pleasure at my arrival.

“Oh somebody,” I said, with a flabby gesture of dismissal. Another pulse of blood released itself and I contracted my stomach muscles in alarm. “Get a towel.”

Joan went out and came back almost immediately with a pile of towels and sheets. Like a prompt nurse, she peeled back my blood-wet clothes, drew a quick breath as she arrived at the original royal red towel, and applied a fresh bandage. I lay, trying to slow the beating of my heart, as every beat pushed forth another gush of blood.

I remembered a worrisome course in the Victorian novel where woman after woman died, palely and nobly, in torrents of blood, after a difficult childbirth. Perhaps Irwin had injured me in some awful, obscure way, and all the while I lay there on Joan's sofa I was really dying.

Joan pulled up an Indian hassock and began to dial down the long list of Cambridge doctors. The first number didn't answer. Joan began to explain my case to the second number, which did answer, but then broke off and said “I see” and hung up.

“What's the trouble?”

“He'll only come for regular customers or emergencies. It's Sunday.”

I tried to lift my arm and look at my watch, but my hand was a rock at my side and wouldn't budge. Sunday—the doctor's paradise! Doctors at country clubs, doctors at the seaside, doctors with mistresses, doctors with wives, doctors in church, doctors in yachts, doctors everywhere resolutely being people, not doctors.

“For God's sake,” I said, “tell them I'm an emergency.”

The third number didn't answer and, at the fourth, the party hung up the minute Joan mentioned it was about a period. Joan began to cry.

“Look, Joan,” I said painstakingly, “call up the local hospital. Tell them it's an emergency. They'll have to take me.”

Joan brightened and dialed a fifth number. The Emergency Service promised her a staff doctor would attend to me if I could come to the ward. Then Joan called a taxi.

Joan insisted on riding with me. I clasped my fresh padding of towels with a sort of desperation as the cabby, impressed by the address Joan gave him, cut corner after corner in the dawn-pale streets and drew up with a great squeal of tires at the Emergency Ward entrance.

I left Joan to pay the driver and hurried into the empty, glaringly lit room. A nurse bustled out from behind a white screen. In a few swift words, I managed to tell her the truth about my predicament before Joan came in the door, blinking and wide-eyed as a myopic owl.

The EmergencyWard doctor strolled out then, and I climbed, with the nurse's help, on to the examining table. The nurse whispered to the doctor, and the doctor nodded and began unpacking the bloody toweling. I felt his fingers start to probe, and Joan stood, rigid as a soldier, at my side, holding my hand, for my sake or hers I couldn't tell.

“Ouch!” I winced at a particularly bad jab.

The doctor whistled.

“You're one in a million.”

“What do you mean?”

“I mean it's one in a million it happens to like this.”

The doctor spoke in a low, curt voice to the nurse, and she hurried to a side table and brought back some rolls of gauze and silver instruments. “I can see,” the doctor bent down, “exactly where the trouble is coming from.”

“But can you fix it?”

The doctor laughed. “Oh, I can fix it, all right.”

I was roused by a tap on my door. It was past midnight, and the asylum quiet as death. I couldn't imagine who would still be up.

“Come in!” I switched on the bedside light. The door clicked open, and Doctor Quinn's brisk, dark head appeared in the crack. I looked at her with surprise, because although I knew who she was, and often passed her, with a brief nod, in the asylum hall, I never spoke to her at all.

Now she said, “Miss Greenwood, may I come in a minute?”

I nodded.

Doctor Quinn stepped into the room, shutting the door quietly behind her. She was wearing one of her navy blue, immaculate suits with a plain, snow-white blouse showing in the V of the neck.

“I'm sorry to bother you, Miss Greenwood, and especially at this time of night, but I thought you might be able to help us out about Joan.”

For a minute I wondered if Doctor Quinn was going to blame me for Joan's return to the asylum. I still wasn't sure how much Joan knew, after our trip to the Emergency Ward, but a few days later she had come back to live in Belsize, retaining, however, the freest of town privileges.

“I'll do what I can,” I told Doctor Quinn.

Doctor Quinn sat down on the edge of my bed with a grave face. “We would like to find out where Joan is. We thought you might have an idea.”

Suddenly I wanted to dissociate myself from Joan completely. “I don't know,” I said coldly. “Isn't she in her room?”

It was well after the Belsize curfew hour.

“No, Joan had a permit to go to a movie in town this evening, and she's not back yet.”

“Who was she with?”

“She was alone.” Doctor Quinn paused. “Have you any idea where she might be likely to spend the night?”

“Surely she'll be back. Something must have held her up.” But I didn't see what could have held Joan up in tame night Boston.

Doctor Quinn shook her head. “The last trolley went by an hour ago.”

“Maybe she'll come back by taxi.”

Doctor Quinn sighed.

“Have you tried the Kennedy girl?” I went on. “Where Joan used to live?”

Doctor Quinn nodded.

“Her family?”

“Oh, she'd never go there…but we've tried them, too.”

Doctor Quinn lingered a minute, as if she could sniff out some clue in the still room. Then she said, “Well, we'll do what we can,” and left.

I turned out the light and tried to drop back to sleep, but Joan's face floated before me, bodiless and smiling, like the face of the Cheshire cat. I even thought I heard her voice, rustling and hushing through the dark, but then I realized it was only the night wind in the asylum trees…

Another tap woke me in the frost-gray dawn.

This time I opened the door myself.

Facing me was Doctor Quinn. She stood at attention, like a frail drill sergeant, but her outlines seemed curiously smudged.

“I thought you should know,” Doctor Quinn said. “Joan has been found.”

Doctor Quinn's use of the passive slowed my blood.

“Where?”

“In the woods, by the frozen ponds…”

I opened my mouth, but no words came out.

“One of the orderlies found her,” Doctor Quinn continued, “just now, coming to work…”

“She's not…”

“Dead,” said Doctor Quinn. “I'm afraid she's hanged herself.”

Twenty

A fresh fall of snow blanketed the asylum grounds—not a Christmas sprinkle, but a man-high January deluge, the sort that snuffs out schools and offices and churches, and leaves, for a day or more, a pure, blank sheet in place of memo pads, date books and calendars.

In a week, if I passed my interview with the board of directors, Philomena Guinea's large black car would drive me west and deposit me at the wrought-iron gates of my college.

The heart of winter!

Massachusetts would be sunk in a marble calm. I pictured the snowflaky, Grandma Moses villages, the reaches of swampland rattling with dried cattails, the ponds where frog and hornpout dreamed in a sheath of ice, and the shivering woods.

But under the deceptively clean and level slate the topography was the same, and instead of San Francisco or Europe or Mars I would be learning the old landscape, brook and hill and tree. In one way it seemed a small thing, starting, after a six months' lapse,where I had so vehemently left off.

Everybody would know about me, of course.

Doctor Nolan had said, quite bluntly, that a lot of people would treat me gingerly, or even avoid me, like a leper with a warning bell. My mother's face floated to mind, a pale, reproachful moon, at her last and first visit to the asylum since my twentieth birthday. A daughter in an asylum! I had done that to her. Still, she had obviously decided to forgive me.

“We'll take up where we left off, Esther,” she had said, with her sweet, martyr's smile. “Well act as if all this were a bad dream.”

A bad dream.

To the person in the bell jar, blank and stopped as a dead baby, the world itself is the bad dream.

A bad dream.

I remembered everything.

I remembered the cadavers and Doreen and the story of the fig tree and Marco's diamond and the sailor on the Common and Doctor Gordon's wall-eyed nurse and the broken thermometers and the Negro with his two kinds of beans and the twenty pounds I gained on insulin and the rock that bulged between sky and sea like a gray skull.

Maybe forgetfulness, like a kind of snow, should numb and cover them.

But they were part of me. They were my landscape.

“A man to see you!”

The smiling, snow-capped nurse poked her head in through the door, and for a confused second I thought I really was back in college and this spruce white furniture, this white view over trees and hills, an improvement on my old room's nicked chairs and desk and outlook over the bald quad. “A man to see you!” the girl on watch had said, on the dormitory phone.

What was there about us, in Belsize, so different from the girls playing bridge and gossiping and studying in the college to which I would return? Those girls, too, sat under bell jars of a sort.

“Come in!” I called, and Buddy Willard, khaki cap in hand, stepped into the room.

“Well, Buddy,” I said.

“Well, Esther.”

We stood there, looking at each other. I waited for a touch of emotion, the faintest glow. Nothing. Nothing but a great, amiable boredom. Buddy's khaki-jacketed shape seemed small and unrelated to me as the brown posts he had stood against that day a year ago, at the bottom of the ski run.

“How did you get here?” I asked finally.

“Mother's car.”

“In all this snow?”

“Well,” Buddy grinned, “I'm stuck outside in a drift. The hill was too much for me. Is there anyplace I can borrow a shovel?”

“We can get a shovel from one of the groundsmen.”

“Good.” Buddy turned to go.

“Wait, I'll come and help you.”

Buddy looked at me then, and in his eyes I saw a flicker of strangeness—the same compound of curiosity and wariness I had seen in the eyes of the Christian Scientist and my old English teacher and the Unitarian minister who used to visit me.

“Oh, Buddy,” I laughed. “I'm all right.”

“Oh, I know, I know, Esther,” Buddy said hastily.

“It's you who oughtn't to dig out cars, Buddy. Not me.”

And Buddy did let me do most of the work.

The car had skidded on the glassy hill up to the asylum and backed, with one wheel over the rim of the drive, into a steep drift.

The sun, emerged from its gray shrouds of clouds, shone with a summer brillance on the untouched slopes. Pausing in my work to overlook that pristine expanse, I felt the same profound thrill it gives me to see trees and grassland waist-high under flood water—as if the usual order of the world had shifted slightly, and entered a new phase.

I was grateful for the car and the snowdrift. It kept Buddy from asking me what I knew he was going to ask, and what he finally did ask, in a low, nervous voice, at the Belsize afternoon tea. DeeDee was eyeing us like an envious cat over the rim of her teacup. After Joan's death, DeeDee had been moved to Wymark for a while, but now she was among us once more.

“I've been wondering…” Buddy set his cup in the saucer with an awkward clatter.

“What have you been wondering?”

“I've been wondering…I mean, I thought you might be able to tell me something.” Buddy met my eyes and I saw, for the first time, how he had changed. Instead of the old, sure smile that flashed on easily and frequently as a photographer's bulb, his face was grave, even tentative—the face of a man who often does not get what he wants.

“I'll tell you if I can, Buddy.”

“Do you think there's something in me that drives women crazy?”

I couldn't help myself, I burst out laughing—maybe because of the seriousness of Buddy's face and the common meaning of the word “crazy” in a sentence like that.

“I mean,” Buddy pushed on, “I dated Joan, and then you, and first you…went, and then Joan…”

With one finger I nudged a cake crumb into a drop of wet, brown tea.

“Of course you didn't do it!” I heard Doctor Nolan say. I had come to her about Joan, and it was the only time I remember her sounding angry. “Nobody did it. She did it.” And then Doctor Nolan told me how the best of psychiatrists have suicides among their patients, and how they, if anybody, should be held responsible, but how they, on the contrary, do not hold themselves responsible…

“You had nothing to do with us, Buddy.”

“You're sure?”

“Absolutely.”

“Well,” Buddy breathed. “I'm glad of that.”

And he drained his tea like a tonic medicine.

“I hear you're leaving us.”

I fell into step beside Valerie in the little, nurse-supervised group. “Only if the doctors say yes. I have my interview tomorrow.”

The packed snow creaked underfoot, and everywhere I could hear a musical trickle and drip as the noon sun thawed icicles and snow crusts that would glaze again before nightfall.

The shadows of the massed black pines were lavender in that bright light, and I walked with Valerie awhile, down the familiar labyrinth of shoveled asylum paths. Doctors and nurses and patients passing on adjoining paths seemed to be moving on casters, cut off at the waist by the piled snow.

“Interviews!” Valerie snorted. “They're nothing! If they're going to let you out, they let you out.”

“I hope so.”

In front of Caplan I said good-bye to Valerie's calm, snow-maiden face behind which so little, bad or good, could happen, and walked on alone, my breath coming in white puffs even in that sun-filled air. Valerie's last, cheerful cry had been “So long! Be seeing you.”

“Not if I know it,” I thought.

But I wasn't sure. I wasn't sure at all. How did I know that someday—at college, in Europe, somewhere, anywhere—the bell jar, with its stifling distortions, wouldn't descend again?

And hadn't Buddy said, as if to revenge himself for my digging out the car and his having to stand by, “I wonder who you'll marry now, Esther.”

“What?” I'd said, shoveling snow up onto a mound and blinking against the stinging backshower of loose flakes.

“I wonder who you'll marry now, Esther. Now you've been,” and Buddy's gesture encompassed the hill, the pines and the severe, snow-gabled buidlings breaking up the rolling landscape, “here.”

And of course I didn't know who would marry me now that I'd been where I had been. I didn't know at all.

“I have a bill here, Irwin.”

I spoke quietly into the mouthpiece of the asylum pay phone in the main hall of the administration building. At first I suspected the operator, at her switchboard, might be listening, but she just went on plugging and unplugging her little tubes without batting an eye.

“Yes,” Irwin said.

“It's a bill for twenty dollars for emergency attention on a certain date in December and a checkup a week thereafter.”

“Yes,” Irwin said.

“The hospital says they are sending me the bill because there was no answer to the bill they sent to you.”

“All right, all right, I'm writing a check now. I'm writing them a blank check.” Irwin's voice altered subtly. “When am I going to see you?”

“Do you really want to know?”

“Very much.”

“Never,” I said, and hung up with a resolute click.

I wondered, briefly, if Irwin would send his check to the hospital after that, and then I thought, “Of course he will, he's a mathematics professor—he won't want to leave any loose ends.”

I felt unaccountably weak-kneed and relieved.

Irwin's voice had meant nothing to me.

This was the first time, since our first and last meeting, that I had spoken with him and, I was reasonably sure, it would be the last. Irwin had absolutely no way of getting in touch with me, except by going to Nurse Kennedy's flat, and after Joan's death Nurse Kennedy had moved somewhere else and left no trace.

I was perfectly free.

Joan's parents invited me to the funeral.

I had been, Mrs. Gilling said, one of Joan's best friends.

“You don't have to go, you know,” Doctor Nolan told me. “You can always write and say I said it would be better not to.”

“I'll go,” I said, and I did go, and all during the simple funeral service I wondered what I thought I was burying.

At the altar the coffin loomed in its snow pallor of flowers—the black shadow of something that wasn't there. The faces in the pews around me were waxen with candlelight, and pine boughs, left over from Christmas, sent up a sepulchral incense in the cold air.

Beside me, Jody's cheeks bloomed like good apples, and here and there in the little congregation I recognized other faces of other girls from college and my home town who had known Joan. Dee-Dee and Nurse Kennedy bent their kerchiefed heads in a front pew.

Then, behind the coffin and the flowers and the face of the minister and the faces of the mourners, I saw the rolling lawns of our town cemetery, knee-deep in snow now, with the tombstones rising out of it like smokeless chimneys.

There would be a black, six-foot-deep gap hacked in the hard ground. That shadow would marry this shadow, and the peculiar, yellowish soil of our locality seal the wound in the whiteness, and yet another snowfall erase the traces of newness in Joan's grave.

I took a deep breath and listened to the old brag of my heart.

I am, I am, I am.

The doctors were having their weekly board meeting—old business, new business, admissions, dismissals and interviews. Leafing blindly through a tatty National Geographic in the asylum library, I waited my turn.

Patients, with accompanying nurses, made their rounds of the stocked shelves, conversing in low tones, with the asylum librarian, an alumna of the asylum herself. Glancing at her—myopic, spinsterish, effaced—I wondered how she knew she had graduated at all, and, unlike her clients, was whole and well.

“Don't be scared,” Doctor Nolan had said. “I'll be there, and the rest of the doctors you know, and some visitors, and Doctor Vining, the head of all the doctors, will ask you a few questions, and then you can go.”

But in spite of Doctor Nolan's reassurances, I was scared to death.

I had hoped, at my departure, I would feel sure and knowledgeable about everything that lay ahead—after all, I had been “analyzed.” Instead, all I could see were question marks.

I kept shooting impatient glances at the closed boardroom door. My stocking seam swere straight, my black shoes cracked, but polished, and my red wool suit flamboyant as my plans. Something old, something new…

But I wasn't getting married. There ought, I thought, to be a ritual for being born twice— patched, retreaded and approved for the road, I was trying to think of an appropriate one when Doctor Nolan appeared from nowhere and touched me on the shoulder.

“All right, Esther.”

I rose and followed her to the open door.

Pausing, for a brief breath, on the threshold, I saw the silver-haired doctor who had told me about the rivers and the Pilgrims on my first day, and the pocked, cadaverous face of Miss Huey, and eyes I thought I had recognized over white masks.

The eyes and the faces all turned themselves toward me, and guiding myself by them, as by a magical thread, I stepped into the room.

THE BURNING SECRET

A PARTNER

THE engine gave a hoarse shriek as the express drew up at Semmering station. A moment of silence followed, during which the carriages rested in the translucent mountain air. The train belched forth a traveller or two and swallowed down a couple of fresh arrivals. Peppery exclamations shuttlecocked to and fro. Again the locomotive uttered a raucous cry as it started off, dragging a dark serpent behind it, to disappear into the tunnel’s maw. A healing peace once more pervaded the landscape, and the windswept atmosphere was good to breathe.

One of the men who had stepped out of the train was young, and of agreeable aspect. He was stylishly dressed and debonair, with an elasticity of gait which brought him to the cabstand well in advance of the other passengers. He engaged the solitary vehicle, and was conveyed without haste to the hotel he had selected. Spring was in the air. A few white clouds, glinting and glowing in the sky, such clouds as are seen only in the months of May and June, seemed to be playing at catch-ascatch-can in the blue, only to hide themselves from the observer’s eye behind the scaling mountains, there to embrace and flee, to wave a lilywhite hand, as it were, then to melt away into nothingness, reappear, and finally to settle down as night-caps on the neighbouring hills.

A restless, insurgent wind rustled among the lean and raindrenched trees, so that their limbs groaned, and thousands of waterdrops were scattered on the ground. Chill currents of snow-laden air descended from the peaks, until one caught one’s breath in the keen, sharp atmosphere. The heavens and the earth were both in a yeasty ferment of impatience. The cab rattled along to the accompaniment of the leisurely trot of the horses and the silvery tinkle of the bells with which the harness was adorned.

On arriving at the hotel the young man’s first move was to consult the list of guests. Not a name that he knew was to be found!

“What the devil have I come here for?” he communed. “No office could be worse than this lonesome place with not a soul for company. Obviously I am too early in the season or too late. My vacations never seem to strike it lucky. Not a creature of my acquaintance among the whole bally lot of them. At least one or two women might have graced the list, so that I could have whiled away my one short week in a mild flirtation.”

The youth, a scion of the minor Austrian nobility and employeem the Treasury, had decided to give himself this week’s holiday, not because he was in need of a rest but because his colleagues were off on a jaunt and he did not see why he should not follow their example. Though by no means lacking in philosophical capacity, Baron Otto von Sternfeldt was essentially of a sociable disposition, and was popular in the circles he frequented. He found solitude irksome, soon tired of his own company, and avoided every occasion for being alone since he felt scant inclination to get to know himself better. If his talents were to flourish, the warmth of his heart to glow into a flame, and his natural high spirits to find vent, he needed constantly to rub shoulders with men and women. By himself he felt cold and lifeless like a match unlighted in a box.

He now wandered aimlessly about in the empty lounge, disconsolately fingering the papers and magazines; then he tried the music-room and strummed a waltz on the piano, but his fingers were stiff and clumsy, refusing to impart the necessary swing and rhythm to the tune. Utterly depressed, he threw himself into an easy-chair and stared out of the window. The evening was drawing in, and grey mistwreaths lurked among the pines. For a full hour, he remained drearily watching the gathering shadows. Then he decided to go into the diningroom.

Very few tables were laid; and he cast a hasty glance at the persons sitting over their meal. Not a friend or an acquaintance to be seen! Ah, yes, over there was a face he knew—but it was merely that of a professional trainer to whom he gave a nod. Women there were none; not a sign of anything worth the attention of a charming young gentleman on pleasure bent. His vexation swelled into impatience.

Sternfeldt belonged to the category of those whose face is a fortune; one took a liking to him at first sight. He was always eager for new experiences, fresh adventures; he was never taken off his guard, because he kept perpetually on the alert to seize the skirts of happy chance; Cupid stood ready at his elbow to give him a hint at the first approach of amorous possibilities; he looked at every woman, be she the wife of a friend or the chambermaid who opened his bedroom door for him, with a searching eye which seemed to unclothe her. It is customary to call such men “Women hunters,” and there is much penetrating wisdom in the appellation, for they actually do possess many of the instincts of the huntsman, passionately stalking their prey, enjoying the excitement of bringing the quarry to bay, and revelling in the spiritual cruelty of the kill. They are perpetually ambushed for the spring, and refuse to give up the chase until the game is theirs. Passion swamps their whole being; not the passion of a lover, but the passion of a gambler, which is cool, calculating, and dangerous. Some continue thus their whole life long, persistent adventurers in the field of“love,” persons whose days are divided into countless petty and lustful episodes—a significant glance in passing, a suggestive smile, a touch of the knee to a neighbour at table—and the year is made up of hundreds of such days wherein sensuality is the main ingredient.

That evening, the baron found no one to take a hand in his favourite sport; and there is nothing so exasperating to the temper of a gamester as to sit with the cards in his hand awaiting the arrival of a partner. Otto asked the waiter to bring him a newspaper. His eyes ran down the columns and over the headlines; but his mind was elsewhere, and he read as though his senses were benumbed by drink.

Then a skirt rustled behind him, and he heard a clear voice say somewhat irritably and with an affectation of culture:

“Mais tais-toi donc, Edgar!”

A tall, finely built woman in a silk dress passed followed by a boy with a pale face and eyes filled with vague curiosity which seemed to caress his companion’s form. The couple sat down at a table reserved for them. Edgar was obviously on his best behaviour, and yet the restlessness in his dark eyes betrayed his real feelings. The lady—and she it was who absorbed the whole of the baron’s interest—was well groomed and dressed with taste. She was a type that the young man admired being a not too buxom Jewess just past the prime but not as yet blowzy, a woman still capable of passion, though keeping her natural sensuousness veiled behind an outward decorum. At first he was denied a look into her eyes, for she kept the lids resolutely lowered; but he could contemplate at leisure the arch of her brows meeting delicately over her finely chiselled nose, which, though it betrayed her race, gave a noble grace to a clear-cut and interesting profile. Her hair was as abundant and feminine as the other charms of the flesh, and swept in opulent waves over her head. She possessed the assurance of a woman whose beauty has been the open delight of everyone with whom she has come in contact. Her voice was soft and low as she gave her orders to the waiter and told her son, who was fiddling with his spoon and fork, to remember his manners and to sit still. Seemingly indifferent to what was going on around her she appeared to ignore the baron’s cautious scrutiny—though in reality her masked interest in him had been awakened by the fact that he was frankly interested in her.

The cloud upon the young man’s spirit had dispersed, and his face was serene. Lines and wrinkles of annoyance were smoothed away, his muscles became taut, the blood flooded his skin and gave it renewed life, his eyes sparkled. Having many a feminine attribute in his nature, he responded to the presence of an attractive woman, as a woman responds to the presence of a man. Sensuous pleasure stretched his energies to the full. The hunter scented the game. His eyes challenged hers to the tourney. But she, though giving him a furtive glance, refused to look him in the face and thus to pick up the gauntlet. It seemed to him, however, that a hint of a smile might be detected flitting around the corners of her mouth. He could not be sure, and this excited him the more. What contented him was the fact that she deliberately avoided his eyes. A good sign, he thought, for it might be interpreted as defiance and at the same time as embarrassment. Besides, her preoccupation with the child was too meticulous, and must undoubtedly be aimed at the onlooker. Nor was her conversation with the lad quite natural; she seemed, rather, to be talking at her observant neighbour. The forced repose of her manner was, Otto felt, the mark of an initial uneasiness.

His feelings were roused. The hunt was on. He lingered over his meal, staring at the woman incessantly during a full hour until at length he could have drawn every curve of her face, while his eyes had secretly caressed each nook and fold of her splendid body. A heavy shroud of darkness had fallen over the countryside, blotting out the forest whose trees continued to sob as though they were frightened children, for the rainclouds were stretching eager fingers towards them grey and full of menace. Shadows had gathered in the corners of the room, and an oppressive silence hung like a pall upon the groups clustered round the dining-tables. Sternfeldt noticed that the lady’s chatter with her son became more and more forced under the burden of this silence, became more and more artificial and soon would have to cease. A test occurred to his mind. He got up, and, walking very slowly, with his eyes glued on the window, he passed close to her without giving her a glance, and disappeared through the doorway. Suddenly he reappeared as if he had forgotten something and had come back to fetch it. She was caught in the trap, for he found that she had been gazing with lively interest at his retreating figure.

Baron Otto von Sternfeldt was enchanted at the success of his ruse, and waited patiently in the entrance hall. She soon came out of the dining-room holding her boy by the hand, fluttering the pages of some magazines as she passed the big hall table, and showed a few of the illustrations to the little boy. As if by chance, the baron too, approached the table, pretending he wanted to read a paper but in reality that he might get another glimpse into those lustrous eyes, perhaps, even, say a word or two....However, the woman turned abruptly away not deigning to give him so much as a glance. She tapped her son lightly on the shoulder, saying with affectionate decision.

“Viens, Edgar. Au lit!”

A trifle crestfallen, Otto stared after her. He had fully expected to make acquaintance that very night. The postponement was a disappointment. And yet, it must be agreed, the situation was not lacking in charm. A zest had been added to the adventure. The incident goaded him to enhance desire. He had to admit that a partner had come his way, and he could now play his hand.

FRIENDSHIP

When the baron stepped into the hall next morning, he saw the boy engaged in conversation with the two lift attendants who were showing him the pictures in one of Karl May’s juvenile books. Since his mother was not present, it might be inferred that she was still engrossed in the cares of her person. For the first time, Sternfeldt took conscious notice of the child, who appeared to be about twelve years old, underdeveloped, shy, nervous, jerky in his movements, and possessed of a pair of dark, roving eyes. Like so many youngsters of his age, he gave the impression of being scared, as if he had suddenly been roused from sleep and placed in unfamiliar surroundings. He was by no means plain, but his face was still undifferentiated; the struggle between the man that was to be and the child that had been was hardly begun; his features were moulded but not finally set; there was no clear line, no striking silhouette, only a pale and somewhat uncouth mass. In addition, being at the awkward age, his clothes did not seem to belong to him; his thin arms and frail legs were lost in the folds of jacket and trousers; he lacked interest in his appearance.

The lad created a very poor impression. He was constantly getting in the way. At one moment it was the hall-porter who pushed him aside; at another he would be mixed up in the revolving door. The outer world was unfriendly. But he tried to compensate for this by futile and incessant chatter with the hotel servants. When they had time they would endeavour to answer his numerous questions, but would break off as soon as possible and go about their business. The baron contemplated the boy, a compassionate smile curling his lips. Poor child, he examined everything with curiosity, only to be fobbed off with roughness. If another human eye caught his inquisitive look, he would cringe away, unhappy at being observed, miserable that he had been detected in the act of investigating. Sternfeldt was amused; he began to feel his interest waxing. Then a thought struck him: why not make friends with the lad and utilize this friendship in order to get acquainted with the mother? It was only fear that made the youngster so shy. Well, a fellow could try. Unobtrusively he followed Edgar, who had gone outside and was stroking the soft nose of a cab-horse. Ill-luck dogged him even in this innocent pastime, for the cabby unceremoniously ordered him to leave the beast alone. Ruffled and bored, Edgar was again reduced to standing about with his vacant expression of countenance, not knowing what next to be at.

The baron seized his chance, and said in a jovial voice:

“Well, young man, how do you like this place?”

The boy flushed, and looked up anxiously. He rubbed his hands on the seat of his trousers in his embarrassment. This was his first experience of a gentleman opening conversation with him.

“Very much, thank you,” he answered awkwardly, gulping down the last two words.

“You surprise me. I should say it was a rotten hole, especially for a young man such as you. What on earth can you find to do all day?”

The boy was still too flustered to find a speedy response. How was it possible that this stranger should take notice of a small boy about whom nobody ever bothered? He felt immensely shy and immensely proud likewise of what was happening to him. With an effort he pulled himself together.

“I like reading, and we go for walks. Sometimes we hire a carriage for a drive. I’ve been ill, and Mother brought me here for my health. The doctor said I was to sit about a lot in the sun.”

As he spoke, an accent of self-confidence came into his voice. Children are invariably proud of their illnesses, for they guess that the danger makes them doubly important to their relatives.

“Yes the sun is most beneficial for a young gentleman in your state of health. You ought to burn to a fine brown. But it’s not good to be sitting about all day. A big boy like you would do better to go for rambles on his own, to be a bit uppish, and to play all kinds of pranks. It seems to me you are too obedient and well behaved. You look like a regular bookworm, always going about with a ponderous tome tucked under your arm. When I think of the young scamp I was at your age...Why, d’you know, every evening I came home with torn breeches;a terrible pickle I was in. No use for a man to be too good.”

In spite of himself Edgar smiled, and on the instant his shyness vanished. He would have loved to respond to the baron’s advances, but was afraid of appearing cheeky. How friendly this smartly tailored gentleman was! It was splendid to be talking on equal terms with him. The boy’s pleasure in the encounter tied his tongue for very happiness. What would he not have given to find suitable words to continue the conversation! But his thoughts were in a whirl. As luck would have it, the hotel manager’s Saint Bernard loped by at this crucial moment. Then it stopped still, came to sniff both boy and man, allowed itself to be patted and fondled.

“D’you like dogs?” the baron inquired abruptly.

“Very much. Grandma has one at her place in Baden, and when we go there on a visit he spends the whole day with me. It’s topping. But we’re only there in summer.”

“I’ve a couple of dozen dogs on my estate, and maybe I’ll give you one, a brown chap with white ears, little more than a puppy, but well trained. How’d you like that?”

The lad blushed with delight.

“Fine!” he exclaimed spontaneously. But then a revulsion of feeling overtook him, and he stuttered bashfully: “But Mother will never agree. She hates dogs about the house, they make so much work.”

The baron chuckled, well pleased, for he had at length guided the talk on to the lady who interested him.

“Is your mother very strict?”

Edgar reflected for a moment, looked up at his new friend questioningly as if to see whether the stranger could be trusted, and then answered cautiously:

“No, can’t exactly say she’s strict. She lets me do anything I like just now because I’ve been ill. Perhaps she’d let me have a dog...”

“Shall I put in a good word for you?”

“Oh, golly!” cried the boy delightedly. “She’d be sure to agree. What’s the dog like? White ears, did you say? Can he beg and retrieve?”

“He can do any and every trick you can think of.”

It was tickling to Otto’s vanity to watch the spark he had kindled in the youngster’s eyes. All trace of shyness disappeared; and the child’s spontaneity, no longer crippled by anxiety and fear, bubbled up like a spring of fresh water. The awkward boy had been replaced by a natural and exuberant creature. If only the mother could prove similar to her son, thought the baron. A score of questions were showered upon him at this instant by the youth.

“What’s it called?”

“Caro.”

“Caro! Caro!”

Edgar seemed to revel in the word, and to be intoxicated with delight at having acquired a friend so unexpectedly. The baron himself was no little surprised at his easy conquest, and decided to strike while the iron was hot. He invited Edgar to go for a stroll, and the lad, who for weeks had hungered after companionship, was in the seventh heaven of delight. He gave free rein to his tongue, responding innocently to his new friend’s subtle questions and assumed interest. It was not long before the baron knew all he needed concerning the family: that Edgar was the only son of a Viennese lawyer belonging to the well-to-do Jewish stratum. Plying the boy with adroit questions, he further learned that the mother was not particularly pleased with their stay in Semmering, that she had grumbled at the lack of society. Moreover, it would appear from the evasive answers given by Edgar that Mother was not particularly fond of Father, so that Sternfeldt surmised the situation to a nicety. He felt almost ashamed of himself for extracting these scraps of information thus easily from his decoy who, unused to finding anyone interested in what he had to say, allowed himself to be inveigled into confidence after confidence. Edgar’s youthful heart beat quick with pride, especially when, in the course of the walk the baron took his arm affectionately. It was an infinite delight for the child to be seen in such company. Soon he forgot his juvenility, and prattled disingenuously as to an equal. His conversation proved him to be a bright lad, somewhat precocious intellectually as is usual with sickly children who pass a large part of their time among elders, and prone to like or to dislike persons and things to excess. He seemed, so far as his emotional life was concerned, to be unbalanced, feeling either hatred towards or passionate love for objects and individuals. The golden mean did not exist for him and his tender face would at times become contorted with the excess of his emotions. There was something wild and resilient in his mode of expression which coloured his words with fanatical ardour, and his gawkiness might possibly be explained as an outcome of a painfully repressed anxiety at the violence of his own passions.

The baron soon won Edgar’s confidence. In half an hour he held the child’s warm and palpitating heart in his hand. Children are so easily hoaxed, for grown-ups seldom try to ingratiate themselves and when they do they catch the innocents unawares. Sternfeldt merely had to think himself back into his own boyhood, and the puerile conversation immediately seemed the most natural in the world. Edgar, for his part, had by now quite accepted the elder man as a chum, and very soon lost any sense of inferiority. All he was aware of was that he had found a friend—and what a friend! His relatives and friends in Vienna were forgotten, his pals with their squeaky voices, their idiotic chatter, might never have existed! They were submerged beneath this new and unprecedented experience. He had become an intimate of the stranger, his wonderful friend; and he swelled with pride when at parting, he was invited to a further ramble on the morrow. They separated as brothers and this farewell was, perhaps, the most glorious of Edgar’s life. Children are so easily hoaxed....

Baron Otto von Sternfeldt grinned as Edgar ran off. An intermediary had been found. The boy would doubtless regale his mother to satiety with every word, every gesture of this amazing encounter. The woman-hunter preened himself upon the subtle compliments he had conveyed through the son to the mother. He had invariably spoken of her as “Your lovely mother”—Edgar would do what was necessary; he, the baron, need make no further advances. The charming unknown would come to him. Not requisite to lift a finger. The baron could muse over the landscape from morning to night, from night till morning...A child’s warm hands, he knew, were building a bridge between his heart and the heart of the woman he coveted.

TRIO

As was clearly demonstrated a few hours later, the baron’s plan proved highly successful. Intentionally he came rather late to luncheon;and the boy, who was already seated at table, sprang up to greet his new friend with enthusiasm. He plucked his mother’s sleeve, whispered a few words in her ear, and drew her attention to the baron with hands and eyes. The lady reproved him for his unseemly behaviour, blushing the while and evidently put out of countenance. Yet she could not help glancing in the young gentleman’s direction, and this gave her suitor an opportunity. He bowed respectfully—henceforward they “knew” one another, the necessary introduction had been made. She, in her turn, felt obliged to recognize his civility with a gracious nod, but for the remainder of the meal she kept her eyes glued to her plate. With Edgar it was otherwise. He was constantly spying in the baron’s direction, and once even went so far as to address his newly-found friend—for which piece of effrontery his mother reproved him smartly. So soon as luncheon was over, he was ordered to go upstairs and lie down. Edgar begged and prayed to be let off. In the end his mother permitted him to take leave of the baron. The latter spoke a few pleasant words to the lad, and Edgar’s eyes glistened with joy. Then, with a nonchalant air, the young man stood up, turned towards the neighbouring table, and, addressing the lady, complimented her upon having so intelligent and jolly a little chap as son, and referred to the pleasant morning he and Edgar had passed in one another’s company. Meanwhile the boy stood by, blushing with delight. The baron plied the lady with questions concerning Edgar’s health, so that in the end she was compelled to reply. Gradually, as the barriers were broken down, the two elders engaged in a lengthy conversation to which the boy listened entranced. Then Sternfeldt introduced himself formally, mentioning his name and title—to which, it would seem, the lady was not wholly indifferent. Take it all in all, she was most gracious in her manner towards her new acquaintance. Nevertheless, she soon moved to withdraw, excusing herself from further conversation because of her son’s delicate health.

The boy entered a lively protest, saying that he was not in the least tired, and was quite prepared to sit up throughout the afternoon and far into the night. But his mother had already proffered her hand to the baron who deferentially bent his head over it and kissed it gallantly.

That night Edgar slept badly. His brain was in a whirl of ecstasy and despair. Something new had suddenly entered his life. For the first time in his experience he had participated in the destinies of fully grown persons. As he swayed between sleep and waking he forgot his own childhood and deemed himself an adult. So far, his existence had not been a particularly happy one, since he was an only child and his health was constantly giving trouble. His parents had been the only target for his affections, and they paid little heed to him. The boy’s other companions were the household servants. Thus his feelings had been pent up to bursting point, and at the first chance were likely to overwhelm the object which seemed worthy of a great love. Edgar lay in the dark, happy but puzzled, wishing to laugh aloud and finding the tears streaming down his face. He loved his new friend more deeply than father, mother, or even God Almighty. An intense and passionate longing went up from his heart, and wove a glamour around the image of this fascinating companion.

“I’m certainly not worthy of his friendship,” he thought. “A kid like me, barely twelve, all my schooldays before me, sent off to bed long before anyone else thinks of going...What can I ever be to him? What have I to offer him?...”

This torturing sense of inability to show his friend what he felt made Edgar miserable. Before, when he had chummed up with a schoolfellow, he had always been able to show his liking by the gift of a stamp from his album, or some other object dear to a youthful heart. But now things of the sort seemed idiotic, utterly valueless. How could he present such paltry tokens of affections to his new friend? What means could he employ to show his regard? He was tormented by the recognition of his immaturity. How rotten to be nothing more than a kid of twelve! Never had he so yearned to be grown up, to be big and strong, to be a real man.

These uneasy musings were interwoven with premonitions of an awakening manhood, rosy dreams which passed gradually into the realm of sleep. But even as he slept, a contented smile played about his lips....Tomorrow he would see his friend again....Had they not fixed it up for a walk together?...

At seven he awoke with a start. Had he overslept himself? Quickly he got into his clothes, and ran to bid his mother the customary good morning. She was amazed to find him up so early. Usually it was all she could do to drag him out of his bed and get him washed and dressed in time for breakfast.

Before she could question him as to his unwonted behaviour, he had already bolted from the room. Forgetting all about breakfast, Edgar prowled up and down the lounge till nine eagerly watching the lift, determined not to miss his friend and the promised walk....

At last, a little before ten, Baron Otto von Sternfeldt strolled unconcernedly into the hall. The tryst had long since escaped his memory. But when the boy rushed up to him and passionately recalled the previous day’s promise, the baron proved affable, and cordially entered into Edgar’s plan, smiling the while at so excessive a demonstration of friendliness. Linking his arm in that of his companion, he sauntered to and fro, quietly but firmly refusing to quit the hall immediately. He seemed to be waiting for someone, and scanned both lift and doors attentively. Of a sudden he stiffened. Edgar’s mother sailed towards the twain with a smile of greeting. She fell in with the idea of a walk, and the three set out together.

This was far from being the treat Edgar had expected. He had reckoned upon a tete-a-tete, and was sorely disappointed. Biting his lips, the boy slouched sulkily in their wake. The promised walk, he thought, was his own special privilege. It had only been out of kindness that he had introduced his mother to this wonderful friend, but he could not conceive why he should share the baron’s friendship with anyone. A dash of jealousy intermingled with his loving adoration. He could not help noticing how attentive and considerate the man was towards this interloper....

As the trio made tracks for the woods, the talk was almost wholly directed towards Edgar. His frail health, his paleness, were commented upon by the woman with loving anxiety, while the baron insisted upon the sprightly wit and pleasant ways of his “Friend”, as it pleased him to call the lad. This created an idea of his own importance in Edgar’s mind, contributing to his sense of self-esteem—a dangerous feeling to arouse in a child’s heart. Thus flattered, he regained his good humour. Never before had people conceded him any rights. Now he felt he had been given his due. He was allowed to enter into the conversation on equal terms, instead of being told that little boys were to be seen but not heard. Moreover, he spoke of certain wishes he had long been forced to repress, and they were now given serious consideration. What was there to be surprised at that such treatment should make him feel grown up? Childhood with its artless dreams lay behind him, a relic of the past, discarded like a worn-out garment.

The lady invited Sternfeldt to share her table at luncheon. A casual acquaintanceship had ripened into friendship. Our trio was now in full swing, the voices of woman, man, and child mingling harmoniously together.

ATTACK

The hunter began to think that the time had come when he could bring his quarry to bay. A trio was not to his liking. Very pleasant as a temporary convenience doubtless, but it had served its turn and was not the object of his maneuvering. He knew that, as the saying runs, “Two’s company, three’s none”—that the presence of a third party makes it necessary for Eros to wear a mask, that, except in a duet, loving words lose their tang and the fire of an onslaught is chilled. Throughout their conversation she must never be allowed to forget what he was aiming at. He was sure she had already understood....

It did not seem to Otto at all improbable that his preoccupation with the lady would be crowned with success. She had reached an age when a woman may well regret having remained faithful to a husband she has never loved, an age when her mature beauty craves for one last acknowledgment, when a choice has to be made between the antagonistic forces constituted by motherhood and womanhood.Life, whose riddles had long since appeared to be solved, in this fateful hour poses a fresh question, and the magnetic needle of the will hovers between the hope of a final love-experience and quiet resignation. A matron has then to decide whether she is to live for herself or for her children, whether she is to be the devoted mother or the beloved woman. The baron, who credited himself with a profound knowledge of feminine psychology, believed he had struck up acquaintance with the lady precisely at the perilous hour when she would be obliged to decide the issue as between pleasure and duty. He noticed that in their talks she rarely mentioned her husband, who plainly could satisfy no more than the most superficial of her needs. She had expected marriage to give her an outstanding position in the world, but it had failed to do so; and, worse than this, her husband had little interest in their boy. A shade of melancholy and boredom veiled her lustrous eyes, darkening her life and blunting the edges of her sensibilities.

The baron made up his mind to set about his business of conquest without further ado, but he realized that he must not betray undue haste. Like an angler playing a fish, he wished to land his catch and at the same time to postpone the moment of netting, so as to be sure that his prey did not escape him. He would assume indifference, entice her into making the first advances; whereas in reality it was he who wooed her favours. Taking advantage of his social position, he resolved to treat her somewhat arrogantly so that she would feel her inferiority. It tickled his fancy, this thought that the glamour of an aristocratic name, the gloss of distinguished manners, would enable him to overcome her scruples and to clasp her beautiful body in his embrace.

The game was becoming an exciting one, and called for discretion. Otto spent that afternoon in his own room, well aware that he would be missed and his presence looked for. Yet, truth to tell, this deliberate absence did not so much affect the lady, who hardly noticed it, as the boy, for whom it constituted a martyrdom. Edgar felt utterly lost, utterly at a loose end. With boyish obstinacy he waited, throughout the creeping, dreary hours, for a glimpse of his friend. To have sought other recreations would have seemed to him a betrayal. He haunted the passages and stairs, and, as evening approached, his heart was filled with anguish. He began to imagine that some misfortune had overtaken the baron, or that he had given unwitting offense to his big friend. Impatient and alarmed, the boy felt his eyes brimming over with scalding tears.

At dinner, Baron Otto von Sternfeldt received a warm welcome. Edgar sprang up to greet him, and, to the astonishment of the other guests and to the distress of his mother, flung his arms passionately round the baron’s neck, exclaiming:

“Oh, where have you been? We’ve been looking for you everywhere.”

Frau Blumental reddened with vexation at being dragged into the business in this tactless fashion. She called her son to order.

“Sois sage, Edgar. Assieds-toi!”

The child obeyed, but continued to ply his questions, so that his mother again reprimanded him.

“You must remember that Baron von Sternfeldt is his own master and can do as he likes. Perhaps he finds our society boring.”

Admirable, thought Otto, she had included herself in the company, so that the reproach to her child became an indirect compliment to himself.

Our huntsman was again on the alert. He was indeed in luck to have thus easily found the spoor! With bright eyes, with a flush which brought the bloom on to his cheeks, he now talked easily and wittily. Like all strongly erotic persons, his eloquence grew as he felt himself appreciated by the object of his desire. He had a gift for anecdote and sprightly repartee which, after a couple of glasses of the champagne he had ordered in honour of the occasion, outstripped even his own expectations. Big-game hunts in India with an English nobleman—here, forsooth, was a splendid subject to captivate the interest of a woman for whom such exotic experiences were unattainable. Nevertheless, it was the boy who was the most impressed by these personal experiences, and not the woman. He sat enthralled, forgetting to eat or drink, lapping up every word that dropped from Sternfeldt’s lips. Who could ever have hoped to meet in the flesh a hero of dangerous exploits, and to hear the account of adventures so enchanting? Tiger hunts, brownskinned natives, Juggernaut cars crushing thousands of human bodies beneath their weight—of these Edgar had read in books. But he had never believed that such things actually existed. They had seemed no more than fairy-tales. Now they were proved to be true. Edgar’s eyes could not leave his friend’s face, or, alternatively, those marvelous hands whose fingers had pressed the trigger and had killed tigers. The boy hardly ventured a question, and, when he did, his voice trembled with excitement. His lively imagination quickly called up a picture of the baron perched aloft upon an elephant’s back, sitting in a purple howdah, to right and left swarthy men wearing magnificent turbans;the tiger snarling and showing its teeth; the jungle; blood oozing from the elephant’s neck where the great cat clawed. Even more interesting narratives were in store, for Sternfeldt told of how old and well-trained elephants were used as decoys to entrap wild ones. Edgar’s eyes sparkled....

Then, shattering his magic world, came the voice of his mother, saying, as she glanced at her watch:

“Neuf heures? Au lit, Edgar!”

The boy went pale with alarm. Bedtime is for every child a bugaboo, for it implies a putting to shame, is a public demonstration that adults look upon a boy or a girl of tender years as an inferior, as a creature in need of more sleep than their Olympian selves. Doubly poignant was the disgrace of such an implication at so unique, so interesting a moment as that which Edgar was experiencing.

“Oh, Mother, do let me hear just one more story about the elephant who...”

He was ready to beg and pray for her leniency, when it dawned upon him that the role of suppliant little accorded with his new status as grown-up. Too late! His mother, brushing his request aside, said severely:

“Non, Edgar, il se fait tard. Monte. Sois sage. Je te raconterai toutes les histoires de Monsieur le Baron demain.”

The child hesitated. Usually his mother saw him into bed. Still, he was not going to demean himself by begging a favour in front of this stranger. Not he! So Edgar merely asked:

“Promise, Mother, you’ll tell me everything, you won’t forget? All about the elephants...”

“Yes, yes.”

“To-night, when you come up?”

“Yes. Now run along with you.”

How Edgar managed to bid them good night without breaking down, he did not know. His throat ached with suppressed tears. Sternfeldt pulled a comical face which brought a grin to the lad’s mouth, but he had to make quick tracks for the exit in order to conceal the sobs which could no longer be kept in check.

ELEPHANTS

Frau Blumental remained below in converse with the baron, but their talk was no longer about elephants and big-game hunting. After Edgar had vanished through the doorway, they were both troubled, embarrassed, and the conversation began to flag. Otto suggested they should transfer to the lounge. Here they found a quiet corner. The young man ordered more champagne; and, after they had sipped a glass or two, their oppression evaporated and the talk took a dangerous turn. Baron Otto von Sternfeldt was not handsome. His youthful appearance and manly bearing, his energetic, sunburned face, his short-cropped hair, and his sprightly manner were, however, undeniably in his favour;and these were the characteristics which exercised their spell upon the lady. She allowed her gaze to dwell upon this comely companion, and no longer feared to meet his eyes.

Gradually a certain boldness entered his speech, which ruffled her sense of security as if a hand had been laid upon her, palpating her body desirously, so that the blood raced up into her face and beat feverishly in her temples. Then she would be reassured as he flung back his head and gave vent to a boyish laugh, scattering to the winds as a childish joke any suggestion of sensuousness that might have lurked in his words. At times she thought it advisable to reprove him for, his delicate effrontery but, coquettish by nature, she rather enjoyed the implication, and eagerly looked forward to his next move. The game caught her,too, in its meshes; and in the end she was led to follow his lead. Her eyes spoke flattering promises, her lips uttered encouraging words. She even allowed him to sit closer beside her, and she felt his warm breath upon her naked shoulder. Like all those who engage upon a game, they become so engrossed that they forgot the passage of time, and it was not until the hall-clock struck midnight that the woman rose in alarm.

Then only did she realize how far the young man’s advances had gone. This was not the first time she had played with fire, but hitherto she had never permitted things to reach such a stage. With horror it was borne in upon her that she was no longer fully mistress of herself, that something intangible was slipping from her grasp, that her senses were in a whirl. Her brain reeled, what with the wine, the momentary shock of anxiety, the ardent talk....

“Good night,” she said hastily. “See you to-morrow.”

Already she was stretching forth her hand in farewell. He, however, was not inclined to let her get away so easily. He retained her hand in his with gentle mastery, and bent his lips to it ceremoniously. But the conventional act of politeness assumed ampler form as he kissed her slender finger-tips and followed up his advantage as far as her wrist. When his moustache brushed the back of her hand, she shivered slightly and a feeling of warmth invaded her being, anguishing and ravishing at one, and the same time. Again the tell-tale blood coursed swiftly, setting her pulses throbbing. Anxiety, senseless anxiety, deprived her of selfcommand and she wrenched her hand away from his grasp.

“Stay a little while longer,” Otto pleaded.

But she was already half-way to the door, walking clumsily with an excess of speed. He was more than satisfied at this display of ungainliness, for it was a sure and certain sign that the excitement he had wished to arouse was responsible for her inelegant movements. For her part, all she could think of was to get away as quickly as possible from this man who might pursue and catch her. Yet another personality within made her sorry that he did not follow....What for years she had hoped might one day happen might very well have taken place at that perilous moment: an adventure. How she loved the hazard that word implied. Often before she had been on the brink, but always she had pulled up in time. Yet she desired nothing better than to be swept off her feet by a great passion. A mere flirtation seemed to her a paltry experience.

But Sternfeldt was too proud to seize the first favorable opportunity. He knew that his victory was secured, so why take advantage of a momentary weakness when a woman’s mind was confused by liquor to make a piratical onslaught and secure the prize? No, he must play fair; she should come to him of her own accord and when in full possession of her faculties. She could not escape him now, for the sweet intoxication had entered her soul.

As she got out of the lift, she pressed her hand upon her heart to stay its furious beating. She breathed a sigh that was partly one of relief at eluding a danger and partly one of regret that danger had not overtaken her. She felt dazed. With eyes downcast, swaying slightly like a drunken person, she groped her way along the passage to her room. Another sigh of relief as she felt the cold door-handle and turned it....Safe at last!

With stealthy tread she entered, and softly closed the door so as not to disturb the child. Then she shrank back in terror. What was that, stirring over there in the darkness? She twitched all over in alarm, was about to cry for help, when a sleep-weary voice asked:

“Is that you, Mummy?”

“What on earth are you up to there?” she cried, witching on the light and running towards the sofa.

Edgar lay huddled up among the cushions, but as she advanced he sat up drowsily. Her first thought was that her child was ill, and had crept into her room for aid. But Edgar said sleepily with a note of reproach in his voice:

“I waited and waited for you to come, and then I went to sleep.”

“What did you want?”

“To hear about the elephants.”

“Elephants? What elephants?”

But even as she spoke she remembered her promise. Poor innocent, he had slipped into her room so confident that she would be true to her word and tell him about the baron’s exploits, but she had failed him,and he had fallen asleep....No, this was absurd, after all; extravagantly foolish. She was outraged. Yet at bottom she was angry with herself, feeling ashamed and guilty.

“Go to your bed at once, you young scallawag,” she cried fiercely.

Edgar looked at her in amazement. What had he done to put her into such a tantrum? The child’s bewilderment only served to infuriate her the more.

“I told you to go to your own room. Go, at once,” she said savagely, feeling all the while how unjust she was.

Without a word, Edgar slunk away. He was desperately tired and only dimly realized that his mother had broken her promise and for some unaccountable reason was angry with him. The mists of sleep encompassed his mind, and he was in no state to rebel. Every sensation was blunted by fatigue, yet he was alert enough to blame himself for having fallen asleep when it was so important to keep awake, “like a silly kid,” he told himself reproachfully, as he drifted off into the Land of Nod. Since yesterday morning his childhood had become detestable to him.

SKIRMISHING

It was Sternfeldt’s turn to sleep badly that night. An interrupted love-adventure is not favourable to repose. A restless, dream-laden night made him regret not having seized the propitious moment...The shades of sleeplessness and discontent still shrouded his mind when, next morning, he came down on his way to breakfast. The boy, who for some time had been lying in ambush, made a passionate assault, flung his lean arms round his friend, and volleyed forth questions. How jolly to have this big friend all to himself and not have to share his treasure with Mother! She did not need to tell him the wonderful stories, she had broken faith; the hero himself would give an account of those enthralling adventures.

The baron was put out. He found the child’s constant spying most incommodious. The deluge of questions was intolerable. The passionate love bestowed on him by the boy was becoming a burden.It was a nuisance to have a twelve-year-old jackanapes perpetually at one’s heels. What he wanted was to get hold of the mother before she had cooled off. How could this aim be realized if the child was always hanging around? Uneasiness germinated in his mind. Had he done wisely to arouse Edgar’s tender emotions? Certainly it was going to prove difficult to free himself from this ubiquitous youth!

Still, it was up to him to try. He was expecting Frau Blumental to appear at about ten o’clock, and meanwhile he allowed the boy to besiege him with questions. They flowed over him like an avalanche, and he needed merely to put in a word here and there to keep the child happy. When the minute-hand was at the hour he made as if he suddenly recollected an appointment, and begged Edgar to run over to the opposite hotel to ask whether Count Grundheim, the baron’s cousin, had arrived.

Radiant that the message should be confided to his care Edgar sped off to inquire. How splendid to be of use to his friend! Eager to carry out his mission worthily, the boy bustled along—to the inconvenience and surprise of other visitors. He was keen on showing how smart a messenger he could be, and took no notice of their exasperated stares. The porter informed him that Count Grundheim had not yet arrived, and that, indeed, the gentleman’s coming had not, so far, ever been announced. Edgar returned on winged feet, bringing the tidings—but the lounge was empty, the baron was nowhere to be found. No answer came to a knock at his friend’s door. Dashing from hall to diningroom, from music-room to bar, he inquired from all and sundry whether they had seen Baron von Sternfeldt. Then he ran helter-skelter to his mother’s quarters—but she, too, had vanished. Coming downstairs once more, he asked the porter, who told him that the pair had gone out together a few minutes earlier. The child was dumbfounded.

Edgar awaited their return with all the patience he could muster. In his innocence, he suspected nothing untoward. They’d only be gone a very short while he was sure, for the baron would want to know whether Count Grundheim had come or not. Hour followed hour, and, as they did not return, the boy grew increasingly uneasy. Ever since the morning when his seductive stranger had entered his young life, he had been in suspense. The child mind is a fragile mechanism, and every passion leaves its imprint like a seal upon wax. Edgar’s eyelids began to quiver, his face became wan. He waited and waited; at first patiently, but anon becoming more and more excited, until at last he burst into tears. Even now his suspicions were not aroused. He possessed so blind a confidence in his new friend that he attributed everything to a misunderstanding. A doubt entered his mind. Might he not have interpreted the message falsely?

At last they came back, and stood talking pleasantly in the hall just as if nothing unusual had happened. They did not seem to have missed him. Without asking for the answer to his message, the baron said:

“We thought we’d meet you on the way, Eddie.”

Overcome with confusion at the thought that they had looked for him vainly, the child protested that he had run straight back along High Street. What direction had they taken? But Frau Blumental cut her son’s indiscreet questions short, saying:

“There, there now! Children must not try to put their fingers into every pie.”

Edgar went scarlet with mortification. It was the second time she had humiliated him in the presence of his friend. Why did she do this? What was the object’ of making him out to be the child he no longer felt himself to be? She must envy him so wonderful a friend and had probably planned to capture the baron for herself. How mean! Yes;and it was she, doubtless, who had deliberately led Sternfeldt in the wrong direction. But he was not going to let her misuse him whenever the fancy seized her. He’d show her! He made up his mind not to say a word to her during luncheon but only to address his friend.

This plan was difficult of execution. What he most feared happened: neither of them noticed his fit of the sulks. Worse still, they seemed to be unaware of his presence, though yesterday he had been the focus around which had concentrated their attention and interest. They talked over his head, joked and laughed as if he were non-existent. The blood welled up into his cheeks, he felt a lump in his throat which nearly suffocated him. Keenly aware of his impotence to create a more favourable atmosphere around his person, he sat mumchance while his mother stole his only friend away under his nose. He would have given almost anything to have the courage to stand up and thump the table with his fist—just to make them realize that he was there. But he did not dare to assert himself. He had to be content with laying down his knife and fork, and refusing to eat. In this demonstration, too, he was foiled for they were not aware of his self-imposed fast until the final course was being served. Then his mother inquired if he was not feeling well.“Ugh,” he thought, “She’s always fussing about my health. Otherwise she doesn’t care a scrap.” His answer was curt. “Not hungry,” was all he said—and she appeared satisfied. Still they continued to ignore him. The baron seemed totally to have forgotten his existence. Anyway, he never addressed a single word to the boy. Edgar’s eyes burned with partially suppressed tears, and he was forced to adopt the childish subterfuge of wiping his mouth in order to mop up with his table—napkin the water which coursed down his face. At last the meal was over; and, with a sigh of relief, he pushed back his chair, prepared to rush away from the table.

While they had been eating, his mother had proposed an excursion to Maria-Schutz. “So she’s determined not to leave me a minute alone with the baron,” thought the child. But worse was in store. As Edgar was making for the door, his mother called him back, saying:

“Edgar, you’ll be forgetting all you ever learned if you don’t set to work on your holiday tasks. You had better stay quietly at home, and get on with your schoolwork for an hour or so.”

Why was she set upon humiliating him before his friend, perpetually recalling him to the fact that he was a child? Edgar clenched his fists and turning on his heel, again made for the exit.

“Huffy? You take offence too easily, my son,” she said, smiling indulgently. Then, addressing the baron she added: “Do you find me too severe when I ask him to attend to his studies for an hour now and again?”

The baron’s reply was like an icy morsel of steel plunged into Edgar’s heart.

“Can’t for the life of me see what harm a few hours’ study could do.”

Was it a plot to get rid of him? Were they leagued against him? Edgar’s gorge rose.

“Dad said I wasn’t to do any lessons while I was here,” he declared. “Dad said I was to get well and strong.”

The child’s threatening aspect—or was it the reference to paternal authority?—seemed to produce an effect upon his antagonists. His mother drummed with her fingers on the table, and stared out through the window. An oppressive silence weighed upon the trio. After a prolonged pause, the baron said with a forced smile:

“Just as you please, Eddie. It’s not for me to preach; I was as lazy as you make ’em at your age, and failed in all my exams.”

But Edgar was long past being in a mood to respond to such pleasantries. He looked up at Sternfeldt with searching eyes, as though he would fain have penetrated to his friend’s innermost thoughts. What was happening? Something had changed. They were no longer the intimates they had been. Why! The child was too young to unravel the mystery. He lowered his eyes while his heart beat like a sledge-hammer. Doubt had entered his mind.

However, the mother relented, and said:

“All right, Edgar, lie down for half an hour. Then get ready to start. You shall come with us on the drive.”

THE BURNING SECRET

“How account for the change?” mused Edgar, as the three of them rolled along in a hired landau. “Why are they no longer the same to me as they were? Mother avoids my eves. I wonder why. Why is the baron always up to some foolery as if he wanted to amuse me? But I don’t want to be amused, I want him to treat me as he did man to man. They both seem to have got quite other faces. They don’t speak to me as they did yesterday and the day before. Mother’s lips are so red she must have painted them. She’s never done that. And he’s always frowning as though he were put out. But I can’t remember saying a single word that could have been taken amiss. Can’t think of any reason why...Besides, they’re not behaving to one another in the old way. One could think they were up to some game they were ashamed of. They’re hiding something. I feel sure. They’re not talking naturally as they did, they don’t laugh any more. There’s a secret they don’t want me to know about. I must, at any cost, find out what this secret is. Perhaps I know what it is already. It must be the one people are always trying to hide from me; the same as is hidden in books they forbid me to read, the same as when we go to the opera and a man and a woman hold out their arms to one another, hug one another. Then there was that French governess who did not hit it off with Dad and was given notice and sent away. All these things seem to hang together; but why, I wonder? Oh, if I could only know, just get hold of the key to the secret. Then I should no longer be a child, and have interesting things hidden from me. It’s a case of now or never. I’m going to snatch their secret from them....”

His brow puckered, giving his juvenile visage a quaintly old appearance. The beautiful landscape might just as well not have existed so far as he was concerned, for his whole mental energy was absorbed in trying to unravel the enigma. And yet the scene was an enchanting one. Mountains encircled with a ring of emerald trees, tender with their early spring foliage; valleys filled with wisps of iridescent mists dappled with golden sunshine. Edgar could only see his two companions opposite him, lolling on the comfortable seat of the carriage. He glared at them as though by the very force of his concentrated stare he could extract the secret from their eyes and hearts. Nothing is guaranteed to sharpen the intelligence quicker than a passion-laden suspicion; nothing is better calculated to ripen the infantile mind prematurely than the feeling that one is on the right scent without knowing what one is hunting. Children are often separated from what adults call “The real world” by a tenuous partition which a zephyr may blow down.

Edgar was convinced that he was nearer elucidating the mystery than he had ever been before; the solution seemed to be just under his hand. He was excited at the approach of discovery, and the solemnity of the occasion made him grave beyond his years. In his unconscious, he was aware that he had reached the frontiers of his childhood.

The couple ensconced in the back seat sensed opposition in the air without realizing that it emanated from Edgar. The roomy vehicle had suddenly grown too small for the three passengers. The intense scrutiny of the boy’s dark eyes made the two elders uncomfortable. They hardly ventured to utter a word, to exchange a glance. They could not get back to the gossamer-light tone of their previous discourse. No matter what topic they started, the conversation soon flagged.

The woman was more sensitive to the child’s mutism than Baron von Sternfeldt. She was alarmed at Edgar’s morose expression and started back in disgust when she detected upon the callow visage of her son the self-same grimace as that which her husband made when he was put out. Never before had Edgar shown any resemblance to his father. Particularly at such a moment as this was she loathed to be reminded of her husband. The child sitting there huddled upon the tiny seat seemed like a ghost, a reproachful guardian of her ways. She felt conscience-stricken. Suddenly Edgar glanced up, and looked her full in the eyes. Mother and son instantaneously lowered their lids. For the first time in their life together they were watching one another. This they both realized with anguish squeezing their hearts. Up till now they had blindly trusted each other; now a hedge of doubt and suspicion rose up between them. A latent hatred invaded them, a sensation so novel that neither admitted as yet that it existed.

All three were genuinely relieved when the horses drew up in front of the hotel. The drive had been wretched from start to finish, but none of them was frank enough to say so. Edgar was the first to jump out of the landau. Frau Blumental, saying she had a headache, made straight for her room. The boy and Otto were thus left alone. After paying the driver, Baron von Sternfeldt strode off towards the lounge, passing close to Edgar without so much as noticing the child’s presence. He had forgotten his little friend’s existence, and left the poor lad behind as if such an insignificant creature was of no more concern to him any more than the coachman on the box or the horses harnessed to the carriage.

Something broke inside Edgar’s head as that beloved and slender figure receded. Despair filled his heart at the thought that this wonderful friend had brushed past without a glance or a word. What could he have done to cause displeasure? The mantle of his newly acquired dignity slipped from his frail shoulders; he was no more than a small and helpless boy, as childlike and immature as he had been yesterday and during all the years that went before. With hesitating footsteps, his legs quailing beneath him, he followed in the baron’s wake, caught up the older man who was about to engage in the revolving door, and stuttered:

“What have I done? Please tell me. Why don’t you look at me any more? And Mother, too? Why are you and she always trying to get rid of me now? Am I a nuisance? Have I been naughty?”

Otto was alarmed at the tone of the child’s voice; it troubled him strangely, and he felt moved.

“Eddie, you silly old fool, don’t worry. I’m out of temper to-day, that’s all. You’ve not done anything. You’re a jolly little fellow, and I’m very fond of you.”

He rumpled the boy’s hair affectionately, but at the same time he averted his head so as not to look into those huge, imploring eyes which were now brimming over with tears. The game he was playing seemed to him paltry and unworthy. He was ashamed of having wrought havoc with a child’s innocent adoration. That was a mean thing to have done.

“Run along now, Eddie. We’ll meet again this evening on the old terms, and this misunderstanding will be forgotten.”

“And you won’t allow Mother to send me to bed so early, will you? Promise.”

“No, Eddie, trust me. But you’d better be getting to your room now. The dinner gong will be sounding soon, and we shan’t have washed and changed.”

For the time being, Edgar was comforted. He felt quite happy as he went upstairs. But soon his heart misgave him. He had grown years older since yesterday, and an unknown guest had taken up quarters in his mind: mistrust.

He waited. This was to be the ultimate test. The three of them sat together at the little dining-table. Nine o’clock struck, but Mother did not send him to bed. He became uneasy. Why to-day in particular was she allowing him to sit up beyond his wonted hour? Had the baron betrayed him? Bitterly did he now repent having run after his sometime friend and put in so urgent a plea. At ten his mother got up, and took leave of the baron. Strange, but the man, too, seemed in nowise taken aback by her breaking up the party thus early, and made no endeavour to keep her as he had done before. The child’s heart beat to suffocation.

Now for the test, thought Edgar. He made as if he had noticed nothing, and docilely followed his mother to the door. Arrived there, he suddenly raised his eyes and caught his mother in the act. She was smiling at the baron, an enigmatical smile, a smile of mutual understanding. So this was the explanation of her early withdrawal from the dining-room. The baron had cheated him. He was to be cajoled into obedience so that they might enjoy one another’s company unmolested.

“Cad,” muttered Edgar.

“What was that you said?” inquired his mother.

“Nothing,” he replied, between clenched teeth.

He too held a secret within his heart. Its name? Hatred, unbounded hatred for the two of them.

SILENCE

Edgar henceforward felt easy. His heart was overflowing with one undivided emotion: hatred, open enmity. He was now absolutely single-minded. Since he knew that his presence was irksome, he took a voluptuous pleasure in sticking to them like a leech. His energies were concentrated upon making their lives a burden to them. The baron was the first to feel the boy’s fangs.

Next morning, when Sternfeldt passed through the lounge throwing a friendly “Good morning, Eddie” to the child, the latter did not look up but muttered a cold, hard “Good morning” in return.

“Mother down yet?”

Edgar remained buried in the newspaper. “Don’t know,” he said carelessly.

The baron was surprised. What could this mean?

“Slept badly, Eddie?” he asked, facetiously.

“No,” answered the boy curtly, and buried his head still deeper in the periodical.

“Silly young ass,” murmured Otto, shrugging, and passing on his way.

War had been declared.

Towards his mother Edgar behaved with exaggerated politeness. A suggestion that it would be good for his health to play a game of tennis was courteously thrust aside. A fixed and rather bitter smile showed that he was no longer to be duped by such ruses. With assumed friendliness he remarked: “I’d rather go for a walk with you and Baron von Sternfeldt, Mummy.”

He glanced up at her as he spoke, and noticed her embarrassment. At length she said:

“Wait for me here,” and passed into the dining-room where breakfast was served for her.

He waited; but as he waited mistrust grew stronger within him. At last he decided to go outside where he could keep the front door under observation and all the other exits likewise. His instinct told him his enemies were likely to betray him again, and he was determined not to be caught napping. Books on Red Indians had taught him how to take cover, and he crept behind a wood-pile. He chuckled contentedly when, half an hour later his mother came stealthily out of one of the side with a superb bunch of red roses in her hand, and, close at her heels, the baron, the traitor.

Both appeared to be in fine fettle, to be enjoying the fact that they had given Edgar the slip, and could now relish their secret together, without the boy’s watchful eye perpetually upon them.

The moment had come for the young spy to act. He sauntered along the path towards the hotel as if he had not observed them, pretending he was engrossed in the bushes and birds, giving them ample time to compose their features after their initial surprise. Very deliberately the child drew nearer, and, when a few yards away, lifted mocking eyes towards them. Frau Blumental was the first to recover.

“Ah, there you are at last, Edgar. We’ve been hunting for you all over the place.”

“What a whopper,” thought the boy, as the lie slid easily off her tongue. But he kept himself in hand, and drew a veil over the intensity of his hate. They stood in a bunch, not knowing what to do next, each watching the other.

“Well, we’d better be starting,” said the woman, nervously plucking the head off one of the beautiful roses. Her sensitive nostrils quivered, and Edgar knew this was a sign that she was angry. The boy did not move. He continued to gaze indifferently aloft, into the blue firmament. At length they passed onward down the path, and he followed. One more endeavour on the baron’s part.

“There’s a tennis tournament this afternoon, Eddie. Don’t you want to be there?”

The boy looked at his interlocutor with unconcealed disgust, and did not deign to answer. He pursed up his lips as if about to whistle.

His presence weighed upon the two elders. They walked like convicts under guard. The child said nothing and did nothing, and yet his presence became more and more irksome as the minutes went by. He repelled their advances, their essays at conciliation. His eyelids stung with suppressed tears, his lips were drawn and sullen. Suddenly, feeling she could bear this furtive observation no longer, the mother ordered Edgar to go on in front.

“I can’t stand your dogging my steps like this. It makes me nervous.”

Obediently, the boy took the lead, but every once in a while he looked back to see if they were following, and would wait for them to catch up with him if they dawdled on the way.

His obstinate silence poisoned any pleasure they had hoped to derive from this stroll, and his hostile eyes dried up the words on their lips. Baron Otto von Sternfeldt did not venture to woo, and it was with impotent fury that he sensed the woman slipping from his grasp as the passion he had been at such pains to evoke cooled under the observation of this nerve-racking and detestable child. Every time they started to converse they became tongue-tied. In the end, the trio wandered aimlessly through the forest, wrapped in a shroud of silence, while the trees rustled above their heads and the sound of their own footsteps beat upon the air. The boy had successfully wet-blanketed their conversation.

A malevolent spirit had taken up its abode in the heart of each one of them. But the child was armed and invulnerable; he took a wild delight in the fact that he, whom they despised, remained unscathed by their wrath. It was sheer delight to see how mortified the baron was, how he resented such treatment. Edgar could guess the tenor of the curses that lay unuttered upon the man’s lips; he knew that his mother’s temper rising; he realized that they would have given almost anything to fall upon him tooth and nail, to get rid of him by hook or by crook. But he gave them no occasion to treat him harshly, behaving civilly, walking sedately before them. His hatred had reckoned upon hours of this martyrdom, and he was determined not to yield an iota of his advantage.

“let’s go back,” said Frau Blumental at last, exasperated, feeling she would have to scream if the tension continued.

“What a pity,” rejoined her son placidly, “It’s such a lovely afternoon.”

Both the elders noted that the lad was making fun of them. But neither dared a rebuke, for the youngster’s outward conduct was exemplary. In two days he had acquired a self-mastery beyond his years. Not a sign could be read upon that tender face...Without further discussion the trio made their way home. Alone in their suite, mother and son let fall the mask of reserve. She threw down her sunshade and gloves in a pet, thus revealing to Edgar’s watchful eyes that her nerves were on edge and that her emotions craved an outlet. Nothing better, thought the boy, than that she should give way to her exasperation. In order to provoke her he remained fidgeting about in her room. She walked feverishly to and fro, sat down, drummed with her fingers on the table, sprang to her feet again.

“How untidy your hair is,” she scolded. “Your hands are grubbywash them at once. It’s disgusting to go about in such a state. A boy of your age, too; aren’t you ashamed?”

Edgar grinned as he betook himself to the bathroom. “She can’t stand my being with her,” he reflected maliciously.

He knew now that they were frightened of him and his relentless eyes, that they dreaded the moment when the three of them were forced to share one another’s company. Proportionally as they grew uneasy, the boy grew happy and content. They were defenceless against the child’s tactics. Sternfeldt, still hoping to gain his end, was furious,and determined to pay the boy back at the first suitable opportunity. Frau Blumental was fast losing control. It was a relief to her feelings to rebuke Edgar and find fault at every turn. “Don’t fidget with your spoon,” she would say at table. “Where are your manners? You are not fit to take your meals among grown-ups.”

The boy grinned, and continued to grin with his head a little to one side. He knew well enough what lay behind such reproofs, and was proud at having provoked them. His expression was as calm and collected as that of a doctor by a patient’s bedside. Hate is an excellent master for teaching the young self-discipline. A day or two ago Edgar would have made scenes under such trying circumstances. Now he kept silent and always silent, until they both squirmed under his silence.

The meal over, Frau Blumental got up, and Edgar prepared to follow her in the most natural way in the world. She turned on him with the irritation of a horse pestered with flies, and said vehemently:

“Why do you cling to me in this silly fashion as if you were a baby of three? I don’t want you constantly hanging around, d’you hear? Children should not always be with their elders. Go and amuse yourself on your own for a bit. Read, or do anything else you have a fancy for, but for heaven’s sake leave me in peace. I’m fed up with you and your stupid, tiresome ways.”

So he had got her to speak frankly at last! Edgar continued to grin, whereas the baron and she seemed at a loss. The woman turned her back, furious with herself for having given the show away to the child, while Edgar said complacently:

“Dad does not wish me to wander about here alone. Dad made me promise to be careful and to stick by you.”

The word “Dad” seemed to exercise a paralysing effect upon the couple, and Edgar, therefore, took a fresh delight in stressing it. His father, he felt, must also have a place in this burning secret, must wield power over the twain from a distance, otherwise why should they look so distressed at the mere mention of his name. Without deigning to answer, the woman led the way from the dining-room. The baron followed. The boy brought up the rear, not humbly as an inferior, but with the air of a warder, hard, severe, ruthless. In fancy he held them on a chain whose links he could hear rattling and which was indestructible. Hate had steeled his childish strength. He, the innocent, was more invulnerable than they who were under the ban of their secret.

THE LIARS

Time pressed. No more than a few days remained of the baron’s holiday, and these he wished to use to the full. Open conflict with an obstinate and determined child was unthinkable. The only way out of their dilemma was through flight. An ignominious surrender, undoubtedly, but what other alternative could be found if they were to escape for a couple of hours from the boy’s tyrannical observation?

“Just run along to the post and get this letter registered there’s a dear,” said Frau Blumental affably to her son.

They were standing inside, while the baron was with-out, engaging the services of a cabby.

Edgar took the missive gingerly. His heart misgave him. Could this be another trap? Usually his mother sent the porter on such errands. He hesitated and then asked:

“You’ll wait for me, won’t you? Where shall I find you?”

“Here.”

“Honour bright?”

“Of course.”

“Promise not to start without me.”

This smacked rather of command than of supplication. Fancy his ordering his mother about! Their relationship had certainly altered considerably since the day before yesterday. He scampered off with the letter and collided with Otto as the latter was entering the hotel through the revolving door. For the first time since their estrangement the boy took the initiative and addressed the baron:

“I’m just going to the post. Back in half a tick. Mummy’s waiting for me. Please don’t start before I get back.”

“Naturally we shan’t,” murmured Sternfeldt, squeezing by.

Edgar made for the post office. Here he was held up by having to wait in line for a considerable time. Then the gentleman in front had a dozen or more questions to ask. At last came his turn. He did his business with the utmost dispatch and rushed back to the hotel, the receipt fluttering between his fingers. Just as he arrived, panting, within sight of the front door, he saw his mother and the baron driving off in the cab.

Anger arrested his headlong progress. He felt like throwing stones after the retreating pair. They had eluded his vigilance. How mean! What a beastly lie! He knew that his mother fibbed occasionally. But that she should break her pledged word—that was too much. His trust in her was shattered. Life had become an enigma. Words and promises were no better than soap bubbles; the merest prick annihilated them. The secret must be a terrible one, Edgar thought, if it made two grownups break faith with a child, if it made them lie, steal away as though they were criminals. The books he had read had told him of people who had cheated in order to gain wealth or power or a throne. But what could these two be after? Why did they try to elude him? What were they endeavouring to hide behind this veil of lies? Cudgel his brains as he might, Edgar could discover no solution. And yet he felt dimly that if he could answer the riddle he would find the “Open sesame” out of the realm of childhood and would enter the kingdom of an adult man. His fury at their behaviour made it impossible for him to think clearly, otherwise....

The forest, the dark and silent forest, would furnish an answer to his perplexities. He sought refuge in its cool shade, gave free vent to his sorrow, allowed the tears he had so far restrained to flow.

“liars. Rotters. Traitors. Cads.”

He felt that if he did not let go he would suffocate.

All the anger, the impatience, the inquisitiveness, the helplessness, the treason of the last few days burst through the dam of his childish controls and found relief in tears. But this fit of unrestrained weeping closed the door forever upon his childhood. The flood carried away all the trust, the love, the reliance, and the respect which had so far been the essential constituents of his life.

The boy who later re-entered the hotel was a changed being. He was collected and purposeful. First of all he sought his own room, and washed the traces of tears from eyes and cheeks. Then he made ready for a settlement of accounts as between himself and his two foes. This satisfactorily arranged, he was prepared to wait patiently for their return.

The lounge was full of guests when the culprits alighted from the cab. Two gentlemen were playing chess. A little coterie of ladies were chatting. Various other individuals were reading papers and periodicals. The child, alert, a trifle pale, had taken an armchair among these grownups. His mother and the baron were annoyed at meeting him so soon, and were about to proffer their excuses when Edgar cut them short with:

“Sir, I should like a few words with you.”

The baron was nonplussed. He felt as though he had fallen into a trap.

“Yes, yes,” he said, flustered. “later, a little later.”

But Edgar protested in a high-pitched voice, so that everyone could hear:

“No, I want to have a talk with you now. You’ve behaved like a cad. You told me a lie. You knew very well that my mother had promised to wait for me till I got back from the post. But...”

“Edgar,” cried his mother, rushing towards him.

All eyes were now concentrated upon the trio, and the child, feeling that his hour had come continued:

“I say it again so that everyone may hear. You lied, both of you—and that’s a mean thing, a caddish thing to do.”

Baron Otto von Sternfeldt went white under the barrage of eyes. Frau Blumental seized her son by the arm, saying hoarsely:

“Come, come up to your room at once or I’ll spank you in front of all these people....”

Edgar had by now quieted down. A pity, he thought, that his excitement had got the better of him. He felt annoyed with himself, for he had intended to keep more than usually calm while challenging the baron, whereas in actual fact his anger had overmastered him. Avoiding any display of haste, he now turned towards the lift in order to seek his own quarters. His mother, embarrassed by the scrutiny of so many quizzical eyes was stammering:

“Please excuse his execrable behaviour...I’m awfully sorry...After all, he is no more than a child....”

She detested scandal or even the lightest breath of gossip associated with her name, and she knew that the situation needed the utmost tact if she was to come out of it unscathed. To save her face, she was careful not to beat a hasty retreat, but inquired whether there were any letters for her. Then, calmly and deliberately, she made her way to the lift and went to her room. Nevertheless, she was aware of the fact that her withdrawal was accompanied by giggles and malicious whispers.

A serious situation invariably took her unawares and made her anxious. She recognized that in the circumstances she had been remiss, and she dreaded a confrontation with her child. So she loitered on the way. Edgar had donned a new visage since yesterday, a visage which paralysed her. Fear counselled her to have recourse to gentleness when dealing with her son. She realized that, if the issue was forced into the open, Edgar would prove the stronger....

Opening the door quietly, she found the boy sitting in her room. There was no sign of fear in the eyes he raised to the encounter; there was not even inquisitiveness. He appeared to be absolutely sure of himself. Assuming her most motherly manner, she asked:

“Edgar, what could you have been thinking of? You made me blush. A child has no business to behave so outrageously to a grown-up person. You’ll have to ask the baron’s pardon....”

“No,” he answered indifferently, gazing at the trees outside.

This involved her in a quandary. Nevertheless, she continued valiantly:

“What’s up, Edgar? You are so changed I hardly recognize you. You have always been such a sensible and well-mannered boy that it was a pleasure to be with you. And now, all of a sudden, you behave as if you were possessed of the devil. What’s your grievance against Baron von Sternfeldt? You seemed very fond of him, and he has been so kind to you....”

“Yes; but that was merely to get to know you.”

“Nonsense,” she said, much perturbed. “What maggot’s got hold of you?”

“He’s a liar and a cad. Everything he does is calculated beforehand. He is a vulgar beast. He wanted to get to know you and thought that the easiest way was to be civil to me, and to catch me by promising to give me a dog. I don’t know what he has promised you, nor why he is so friendly towards you. But I’m certain that he hopes to get something out of you, Mummy. He’s a rotter, a liar. You need only look at him to know what kind of beast he is. I hate him, yes, I hate him for his lies, his caddishness, his— ”

“But, Edgar, you must not speak like that...” she protested, while her heart told her that the child was right.

“You’ll never make me believe that he is anything but a cad. Can’t you see it for yourself? He’s afraid of me. Why should he be? He tries to hide his real motives from me. Why? Because he knows very well that I see through him, that I know him for what he is—a cad.”

“It’s not fair to say such things; really, it’s not fair.” Her mind had become a blank, and she could only reiterate the words “It’s not fair.”Panic seized her, but whether on the baron’s account or on the boy’s, she would have found it difficult to decide.

Edgar was well aware that he had made an impression.

He was tempted to lure her to his side and thus acquire a comrade to share in his hatred. He went over to where his mother was, put his arms round her, and said gently:

“Mummy darling, can’t you see for yourself that he’s a rotter? He has succeeded in changing you, in making you angry with me, because he wants you for himself alone. I’m sure he means to cheat you. Whatever he may have promised, he won t give—of that I am certain. Don’t trust him, Mummy. He’s cheated me, and he’ll cheat you. He’s a rotter, and no one ought to trust him.”

The child’s voice broke on the last words. It seemed as if she herself were speaking. And yet she felt ashamed to acknowledge that this youngster was right. She tried to maintain her dignity, as so many adults do, by assuming a lofty tone.

“Children are not the best judges in such matters. They don’t understand. This is no business of yours. All you have to do is to behave like a little gentleman...”

The tenderness vanished from Edgar’s countenance. He drew himself up, and said:

“Very well. You can’t say I failed to warn you.”

“So you are determined not to apologize?”

“Yes. Absolutely.”

They stood facing one another, and the woman felt that her authority was at stake.

“As you will, Edgar. You will have your meal served here. You will eat alone. And I shall not allow you to share our table until you have made suitable excuses. I’ll teach you your manners. You’ll not move from this room until I give you leave. Understand?”

Edgar grinned. This sardonic smile seemed to have become part of him. But he was vexed with himself for having warned her (who was just as flagrant a liar as the baron) against that “Vulgar beast’s”advances.

Meanwhile the lady had slammed the door behind her without a glance in his direction. She was awed by the child’s wrathful eyes. He had become uncanny, he knew too much, far more than it was desirable for him to know and to hear. He seemed to be an embodiment of her own conscience, a reproach and an admonition. Edgar had always been a plaything, an ornament to her life, a sweet and lovable object. Occasionally, it is true, he had proved a bit of a burden and a nuisance, but, taking the rough with the smooth, she had enjoyed his company, and their lives had run placidly side by side. For the first time the child had set up his will in opposition to her own. A breath of hate was now part of their relationship.

Yet even at this moment, as she made her way downstairs, she could hear the boy’s tender voice raised in warning against the man she was about to meet. She was unable to silence the inward monitor. As she passed a mirror on the landing, she stopped and contemplated her reflection. For long she looked at herself, deep, deep into her soul. Then she became aware of a smile playing about her lips, of her lips rounding themselves to pronounce a particular word—in the circumstances a dangerous word. Still the voice sounded within her; but she shrugged her shoulders as if shaking off an incubus, cast a bright glance at the answering image, smoothed her skirt, and marched off to her fate with the determination of a gambler staking his last gold piece upon the hazards of the game.

SHADOWS IN THE MOONLIGHT

A waiter brought up Edgar’s supper on a tray, made the boy as comfortable as possible, and then withdrew, closing the door behind him and turning the key in the lock. “Insufferable,” thought the boy, springing to his feet. To be bolted in as though he were a wild beast was too great an indignity. Could his mother really have brought this degradation upon him? His mind darkened as he meditated.

“I wonder what can be going on down there while I’m caged in this room. What are they talking about? Will their secret be disclosed, when I’m not there to share it with them? It’s awful to feel there’s a secret in the air, always when I’m with grown-ups. They shut me out, especially at night and talk in whispers if I drop in and take them unawares. I feel I’m on the track of their secret, and yet I just miss guessing what it’s all about. This isn’t the first time I’ve tried to understand. Those books I sneaked from Dad’s table and shelves! Only the trouble was that even when I had read them from cover to cover I never understood what they were driving at. There’s something that escapes me every time. How Emma, our parlourmaid, laughed at me when I begged her to explain a passage! Oh, I think it’s dreadful to be a child full of curiosity and not daring to ask questions. Grown-ups merely grin, and look down on a fellow as if he were a fool. But something tells me I’ll soon know everything there is to know. I’m not going to give in until I do....”

He strained his ears to catch a possible footstep. But only the breeze murmured in the foliage, swaying the branches and breaking the moonbeams into a thousand facets of light scattered among the shadows.

“They must be up to something they are ashamed of, otherwise why should they trouble to tell me such idiotic lies? I expect they’re having a good laugh at getting rid of me. Never fear, my turn will come. I’ve been a silly ass to allow them to lock me in. Ought to have stuck to them and never let them out of my sight. Grownups aren’t very clever at hiding what they are doing, and they’d be sure to give themselves away before long. They fancy we children go to sleep, and they forget that we know all kinds of dodges so as to overhear what they say and see what they do. We’re not so stupid as they imagine. When Aunt Clara had a baby two months ago they pretended to be ever so much surprised. But they had known about its coming ages before, and I knew too, because I heard them talking. This time also I’ll find out what Mother and the baron are hiding. I wish the doors were transparent so that I could watch them when they thought no one could see. I wonder if it would be a good move to ring for the chambermaid? She’d have to unlock the door to ask what I wanted. Then, before she knew what I was doing, I’d slip out...” No better not. That might give me away and show the servants how meanly I’m treated. No one must know, it would hurt too much, I couldn’t stand it. But to-morrow...”

A woman’s laugh floated up to him on the spring air, was that his mother? It might well be. She had plenty of reasons for being gay. Had she not locked him up, small and defenceless as he was, got rid of him thrown him into a corner like a bundle of dirty clothes? Stealthily creeping to the window, he peered out. A couple of girls were strolling by with their young men—no one else.

As he leaned on the sill, he noticed how close the window was to the ground; and, before he realized what he was doing, he had taken the plunge and landed in a bed of flowers. The slight noise he made passed unnoticed. He was free. Now he could go and spy upon his foes. In two days, this attitude of spying had become second nature to him who hitherto had been so candid and innocent. Careful to avoid making a sound, he prowled round the hotel, his heart beating furiously lest he should be discovered. Here was the dining-room. With the utmost precaution he pressed his face close to a window-pane: The pair were not there. He passed from window to window, not daring to enter the building in case he should stumble upon them in a passage or on the stair. He failed in his search and was in despair. Then, of a sudden, he saw two shadows issuing from a side door. He ducked so as not to be discovered. Yes, it was his mother accompanied by the inevitable baron.“Just in time,” thought the boy. “What are they talking about? Wish this rotten wind wouldn’t make such a row among the trees!” His mother laughed audibly. He had never heard her laugh like that; it sounded shrill, a trifle excited; most peculiar. Though Edgar felt alarmed at this unusual mirth, he was likewise reassured for, if she felt merry, there certainly could be no immediate danger threatening her. Nor could the matter the twain had in hand be anything of grave importance. Why, then, were they at such pains to hide it from him? Edgar felt rather disappointed at the thought that the secret was not something big, and worthy of the trouble he was taking to unravel it.

Whither could they be going at this hour of the night? High up in the sky a strong wind must be blowing for the clouds were racing by, obscuring the moon. So dark was it at times that one could not see the path, and then all at once the earth was radiant with clarity, and a silver sheen lay on leaf and blade. How strange, how eerie was the interplay of light and shade—like a nymph unveiling and veiling her beauties ere you could feast your eyes on her nakedness. Again the moon shone out, and Edgar saw two silhouettes—or, rather, one only, so closely were the couple walking together—making towards the forest. Why? Whither? The wind was busy among the firs.

“I’ll follow,” thought the child. “They’ll never hear my footsteps in such a din.”

Thrice blessed wind thus to muffle his movements! He slid from tree to tree, from shadow to shadow. Thrice cursed wind thus to muffle their words so that he could not hear what the enemy was talking about. If he once caught the subject of their conversation, he felt convinced that the secret would be his.

Unconcernedly, Frau Blumental and her cavalier went on their way, little suspecting the presence of a spy in their wake. They were entirely happy, and were lost to everything but the splendour of the night and their own growing interest in one another. How could they know that every step they took was dogged, and that eager eyes were watching them with hatred and curiosity?

Suddenly they stopped in the middle of the path. Edgar pressed his frail body against a tree. He gasped with anxiety. “Suppose they turn back, and Mother doesn’t find me in my room? She’ll guess I’ve been watching her, and then she’ll be so wary that I shall never discover their secret.” Happily at that moment the clouds scurried by, the moon shone, and the clearing was flooded with light. The boy saw that the baron was trying to entice the lady into a smaller and darker path which led up a little ravine. Edgar’s mother seemed to be saying “No,” but Sternfeldt urged her to consent. Why? What did he want of her? The books Edgar had read told of “Murders under cover of darkness”, of “Abduction”, of crimes innumerable. Could the baron be planning to kill her? Then here was the explanation, this was Sternfeldt had wanted to be alone with Mother, this was the reason he had induced Mother to turn the key on her own son. Should he seek help? Should he cry, “Murder”? He could not utter the syllables, for his lips were parched with excitement. So intense was his emotion that he found it difficult to keep his footing. He swayed; and, in order to steady himself, seized hold of a branch. It snapped with a loud report.

The two swung round in alarm and stared into the gloom. Edgar stood motionless, hardly daring to breathe. The silence of death lay upon the forest, for neither wind nor creature stirred. Then the woman said:

“Let us turn back.”

How scared she seemed. The baron, too, was frightened and fell in with her wishes. Linked in a close embrace they retraced their steps, slowly, engrossed in their own thoughts. Edgar, profiting by their absorption ran on all fours through the undergrowth, and arrived breathless at the hotel. Turning the key, he entered his room, undressed, and got into bed. He lay quiet for a while, recovering. Then he got up and went to the window, determined to witness their return. They must have walked very, very slowly. At long last he saw their shadows. They looked ghostly in the moonlight. Was the baron really a murderer in disguise? And had he, Edgar, prevented the bloody deed by breaking a dried and rotted branch? Again the moon shone brightly. Edgar had never seen an expression of such rapture on his mother’s face before. But the baron looked wooden and disappointed—probably because his wicked scheme had come to naught, thought the boy.

As they drew near to the hotel they wrenched themselves apart. Would they glance up? No! “They have quite forgotten me!” Then with a mixture of triumph and bitterness Edgar muttered: “But I haven’t forgotten you. You may fancy I am asleep or that I simply don’t exist at all. Just wait; I’ll show you how mistaken you are. I’m not going to let you out of my sight until I have snatched your secret from you. I’ll keep awake all right.”

The two stepped into the doorway. Again their shadows were united to form but one dark patch. Then the moonlight invaded the courtyard, until it looked like a field of untrodden snow.

A MIDNIGHT TUSSLE

With a catch in his breath, Edgar withdrew from the window. He was terribly shaken. Never had he been so near to discovering the riddle. Excitement, adventure, murder, betrayal, these had been no more than tales a boy reads of in books, dream events, unreal, unattainable. Now, of a sudden, he felt that this awful world of risk and enterprise had roped him in, had made of him a participant. He was alarmed and pleased at so unexpected an initiation.

“I wonder what kind of a man this is who has come into our lives....Can he really be a murderer? If not, why does he want to lure my mother into dark and lonely places?”

Something terrible seemed impending, and yet the boy did not know what steps to take in order to avert the evil. Of one thing he was certain: To-morrow he would write or wire to his father. But might not that be too late? Who could tell what would happen this very night? Mother had not come up to her room; she must still be with that wretch....

Between one door and the other of their rooms, which were in suite, was a small lobby. Here Edgar ensconced himself, determined not to miss his chance of hearing whatever happened in the corridor. At length he heard their steps. He strained every nerve to catch what they were saying and doing.

How slow they were—just as though they were climbing a mountain, not in the least as if they were making for their rooms, tired, after a pleasant evening together. They were constantly stopping and whispering. The boy trembled with mental torment. He would have given almost anything to hear what they were saying. Still, he knew they were coming his way. But, oh, how slowly! Now he could hear the baron pleading. Now his mother’s voice saying: “No. Not to-night. No.”

Edgar shivered. Every step that brought them nearer him caused him fresh agony. Then he heard the detested voice pleading:

“Please, please. Don’t say no. You’ve been so adorable the whole evening....”

And his mother, frightened, on the defensive, answering:

“I dare not. No, really, not to-night. I beg you, let me go.”

Again Edgar wondered what the baron wanted her to do and why his mother was so alarmed. Now they came to a standstill opposite the door behind which the child was lurking. He could hear them so clearly that they might have been in the same room with him.

“Come along, Mathilde, do! Please, please.”

His mother sighed; her protests became weaker. Hullo! What was happening? Frau Blumental did not enter her room, she passed along the passage. What did this mean? Why were they no longer talking together? Was it possible that the wretch had gagged her and was now in the act of throttling her?

Maddened with alarm, the child opened the door only a crack, but through this he could see what was going on. The baron had his arm round his mother’s waist and was cajoling her into acquiescence. She seemed to be nothing loath. Arrived at Sternfeldt’s door they stopped.

“Now he’s going to commit the crime,” thought the boy, his head filled with reminiscences of penny dreadful stories.

Banging the door behind him, he stampeded down the passage and butted in upon the lovers. His mother drew abruptly aside, alarmed by the sudden onslaught. Then she dropped as if in a faint, and was caught in the baron’s arms. At the same time, the baron became aware of two small fists pummelling his face, bashing his lips against his teeth, and nails scratching him like a cat’s claws. The alarmed woman quickly took to her heels, while the man hit back at his assailant before grasping who it was.

Edgar was only too conscious of the fact that his puny strength could not hold out against the vigorous onslaught of a man in the prime of life. Nevertheless he determined to do his best, and at least to show the intensity of his hatred. He banged away with all his might, his lips set firm, his teeth clenched. By now the baron had recognized the spy, and gave the lad a generous drubbing. He was furious at having his holiday ruined by this tiresome young monkey. Edgar suffered without uttering a sound. The struggle continued for several minutes in the dimly lighted passage until Sternfeldt, growing aware how ludicrous was this encounter between a man and a child, tried to seize Edgar by the nape and hold the boy at arm’s length. Feeling that he would be overpowered by the man’s superior strength and longer reach, the youngster turned savagely and clenched his teeth in Sternfeldt’s right hand. A low growl issued from the baron’s throat he relaxed his grip, and before he could recover his presence of mind Edgar was back in his own room and had bolted the door.

No one had been aware of this midnight affray. All were asleep. Everything was as still and silent as the tomb. Otto wiped the blood from his hand with a handkerchief. He peered uneasily into the dark recesses of the corridor. Not a soul to be seen! And yet, up there, was there not a light, flickering in the draught and a low, mocking laugh?

STORM

“Was it all a terrible dream?” Edgar asked himself when he awoke next morning. His head ached and as his eyes travelled down his body he saw that he had gone to sleep in his clothes. He jumped up, and ran to the looking-glass. There he was confronted with a pale, drawn face, tousled hair, a red swelling upon a smudgy forehead. With an effort the child collected his thoughts, trying to remember what had happened. Yes, he had come to fisticuffs with his enemy, out there in the passage, sometime after midnight; had then rushed back to his room; had thought of decamping; had been overwhelmed by fatigue; had thrown himself on to his bed without undressing; and had fallen into a restless sleep,full of nightmares and the stench of freshly spilled blood.

In the garden below he could hear the sound of foot-steps on the gravel; voices floated up to him; the sun was high in the heavens. It must be late. He consulted his watch, but found it had stopped.

In his excitement he had forgotten to wind it up. Curiously enough this uncertainty as to the hour disquieted him more than anything else. He quickly undressed, washed, and dressed himself again. Then he went downstairs, feeling slightly guilty and very much disturbed.

He found his mother sitting in the dining-room over her breakfast. Alone, thank goodness. It was a relief not to have to look upon that hated countenance....But Edgar was not quite sure of himself as he stepped up to the table and wished his mother “Good morning.”

She gave no response, continuing to stare fixedly out of the window. Her face was very pale, deep shadows lay around her eyes, and her delicate nostrils quivered as they invariably did when she was greatly moved. Edgar bit his lips. Her silence puzzled him. Did she know who had attacked Otto von Sternfeldt in the passage? Had he seriously damaged the baron? Doubts assailed him and tortured him. Her sightless, staring eyes alarmed him even more profoundly; he was afraid to move lest they should suddenly be turned upon him; he drank his coffee and ate his roll with as little movement as possible so as not to attract her attention. He thought she must be exceedingly angry. A quarter of an hour went by, while he waited for something to happen. Not a word was spoken. Then, still behaving as though he were not present, his mother got up and went out. What was he to do? Remain sitting at the table, or follow her? In the end, he decided upon the latter course. She continued to ignore him, so that he felt more and more humiliated. He lagged behind, not knowing whither to go. In the end, he went up to the suite he and his mother occupied—but found the outer door locked against him.

Yesterday’s hardihood had completely disappeared; he had not a notion what to do. Perhaps he had acted badly when he fell upon the baron tooth and nail. Could they be preparing some terrible retribution or a fresh humiliation? He was convinced they were concocting a plan, setting a trap for unwary feet. There was a feeling about these two as when a storm is brewing and flashes of lightning speed from cloud to cloud. This burden of misgiving weighed heavily upon his spirit throughout the morning, and it was a very small and diminished Edgar who finally presented himself at the luncheon table.

“Good day,” he said, once more endeavouring to break the silence which hung like a threatening cloud over his head.

She looked through him, and again made no answer. Edgar now recognized how terribly angry she was, so angry, indeed, that she did not venture to speak. Never had he roused her to such a pitch of exasperation. The boy’s heart sank; he was genuinely frightened. Hitherto when she had scolded him it was, rather, an affair of the nerves than of the emotions, a summer storm that was quickly over and followed by an indulgent laugh. To-day he felt that he had stirred her to the depths, had aroused something wild and untamed in her nature, and he trembled in face of the forces he had unleashed. Hardly a morsel of food could he swallow; his throat as dry, his lips were cracked. His mother seemed unaware of his desperate plight. But when the horrible meal at last came to an end and they rose from table, Frau Blumental turned casually to her son and said:

“Come to my room, Edgar. I wish to have a few words with you.”

No threat in her voice, thank goodness! But, oh, how icy and aloof was her demeanour. Her words fell over Edgar like a cold douche and made him shiver. His defiance oozed away. Like a whipped cur, the child followed his mother in silence to her room.

She prolonged Edgar’s martyrdom by sitting for a while without uttering a word. Through the open window came the joyous laughter of children at play; but Edgar’s heart beat to suffocation. Frau Blumental, too, was ill at ease, avoiding her son’s eyes even when she began to speak to him.

“I don’t intend to tell you what I think of your conduct, Edgar. The mere thought of it horrifies me. You will pay for the consequences. But you are certainly not fit to mix with grown-ups and sensible people. I have written to your father and told him that your unruly behaviour needs stricter discipline than I am able to provide. I have suggested he find you a tutor, or that he send you to a boarding-school, where you will be taught your manners. That is all. I myself shall not bother about you any more.”

Edgar’s head sank on his breast. He knew that this was only a prologue, and that worse was in store. Frau Blumental continued:

“You will have to apologize to Baron von Sternfeldt....”

The boy trembled; but she was adamant, and refused him a moment’s pause for a protest.

“The baron left this morning and you will write him a letter to my dictation....”

Again Edgar made as though to speak, and again his mother went on precipitately:

“Not a word! Sit down. There is a sheet of paper and a pen....”

Edgar looked up at her. He read decision in her hard eyes. Never had she looked like this. He seated himself at the table, took up the pen, and bowed his head low over the paper.

“Date it. Done? Leave a line. Good. Now write ‘dear Baron von Sternfeldt.’ Comma. Leave another line. A little to the right, begin, ‘I am sorry to learn that you have left Semmering,’ two m’s in Semmering. Got that? Very well. Continue the sentence, after a comma, and that ‘I cannot say good-bye to you personally but only by letter’; hurry up, no need to write as if you were doing a copy. Full stop. ‘Also, I want to ask your pardon for my unseemly conduct last night. Mother told you that I am convalescent after a severe illness and am easily overwrought. That makes me do things for which I am very sorry afterwards....’”

The bowed back straightened; Edgar turned round, defiance blazing up anew.

“That’s not true; I won’t write...”

“Edgar,” cried his mother threateningly.

“It’s not true. I’ve done nothing to be sorry for. I’ve done nothing naughty for which I need beg anyone’s pardon. All I did was to run to your side when you called for help.”

Her lips blanched; her nostrils quivered. “I called for help? You’re crazy.” Edgar sprang fiercely to his feet.

“Yes, you did, out there in the passage, last night, when he caught hold of you. ‘Let go of me. Leave me,’ you said so loud that I could hear the words quite plainly from my room.”

“You are lying, my poor child. The baron and I were not in the passage. He merely saw me to the landing.”

Such a brazen falsehood took the boy’s breath away. He was stunned, looking at her with scared eyes, and stammering:

“You...were...not in...the passage? And he...did not...take...hold of you? Forcibly....against your will...?”

She laughed; a cold, dry laugh.

“Must have been dreaming, my boy.”

This was too much for Edgar. He knew that grownups lied, that they used funny words to express what was not true, told fibs, had recourse to strange ambiguities. But anything as bold-faced as this he was utterly unprepared for.

“And is this huge bump on my forehead also a dream?”

“How am I to know what other young jackanapes you’ve been fighting with? Come now, I don’t want any back-talk from you. Sit down and write.”

She had gone very pale, and was making a great effort to remain calm.

But Edgar crumpled up; a last faint ember of credulity and trust in his elders was quenched. How could anyone trample on truth so ruthlessly? He would not believe that a monstrous lie such as this could go unscathed. He rallied his forces, became cool and collected and bitter. An ironical, bantering, and sarcastic tone entered his voice.

“So I’ve been dreaming, have I? All that happened in the passage, this bump on my forehead-just a dream! And of course you and he did not go for a walk in the moonlight. Neither did he try to get you down a small dark path in the forest. Oh, no, nothing of that is true, is it? But did you really fancy I was going to allow myself to be locked into my room like a naughty child? Not such an ass. I know what I know.”

He looked her squarely and pertly in the face, and this saucy expression cowed her for a moment. It was dreadful to see hatred gleaming from the eyes of her only child. Then her anger broke loose.

“Enough! Write what I tell you, immediately otherwise...”

“Otherwise what?” he demanded peremptorily.

“Otherwise I’ll beat you as if you were in very fact a little child.”

Edgar stepped close up to his mother a jeering and challenging laugh issuing from his mouth.

Her hand was already raised and came down in a resounding smack upon his head. He uttered a yell of rage and surprise. Then, like a drowning man whose ears are buzzing, whose hands vainly strive to find some flotsam whereon to cling, he struck out blindly. Something soft and yielding countered his fists. Again he struck, this time upwards towards a blanched face. A cry...

The scream of pain brought him to his senses. What had he done? Something terrible, something unforgivable. He had struck his mother. Frightened, ashamed, disgusted, he wished the floor would open and swallow him up. He must get away from those horrified eyes. Away...away. Edgar stumbled towards the door, down the stairs, through the hall, into the forest. Oh, to get away, far away! He rushed along as if pursued by a pack of hounds giving tongue.

REVELATION

At length Edgar halted. His limbs, his body trembled violently that he had to support himself against a tree. His breath came quickly and spasmodically. What was he to do? Where could he go? Impossible to remain here, almost within sight of the house which had been his temporary home. He was forsaken, helpless. The world was a harsh and unfeeling place. Even the trees which but yesterday afforded shelter from the sun and had clustered round him in brotherly affection, now stood aloof and looked down grimly. The unknown lay ahead of him. His loneliness amid the vastness of nature filled him with dread. Such solitude could not be borne, he must go somewhere and find a companion. He dared not seek out his father in Vienna, for Herr Blumental was a martinet and would insist upon Edgar’s prompt return to Semmering. This thought was intolerable. Better by far to be alone and to journey forth into the unexplored. He felt as if never again could he look his mother in the face without remembering that he had struck her with his fist.

But what about Grandma? She had always made much of him—such a kind old lady. Invariably she had been on his side when he had got into trouble at home. He could hide in her house in Baden until his parents’ anger had cooled off. From there he would write a long letter, begging Dad and Mummy to forgive him. All the pride had seeped out of him. He felt very small and helpless in the midst of this huge and antagonistic universe, and wanted nothing better than to become once again the child he had been a few days ago.

How did one get to Baden, he wondered. Pulling out a shabby purse which was his inseparable companion, he extracted a gold piece that had been given him for his birthday. How he had polished it every day with his grubby handkerchief, until it shone and shone again! He had never been able to make up his mind to spend it. Like a little sun it was. Lovely. Bright. Beautiful. Would it suffice to pay for his railway fare? Often and often he had travelled by train! Yet never had it entered his head to inquire how much a journey cost. For the first time in his short life he was up against reality. Things he had taken for granted apparently possessed a value of their own and could not be had for the asking. They needed to be paid for in hard cash. A short hour ago he thought himself so wonderfully clever, knowing all there was to know. But there were hundreds of problems and secrets that were a sealed book to him. He realized his shortcomings now. More and more did the sense of humiliation master him as he made his way to the station. Often and often he had dreamed of setting forth into the world to win his laurels, to become an emperor, a king, a famous soldier, a poet. Now that he had finally realized part of this dream, he felt exceeding small, and, as he fixed his eyes on the station building, his mind was wholly preoccupied with the question: “Shall I have enough to pay for my ticket?” The shining rails ran away into the infinite; not a soul could be seen on the platform or in the waiting-room. Edgar tiptoed up to the ticket office and asked softly and modestly how much it cost to go to Baden. A pair of surprised eyes looked through the little hole, and smiled not unkindly at the timid youngster.

“Half fare, or a whole?”

“Whole,” stammered Edgar, every atom of conceit punched out of him.

“Six crowns.”

“Please give me a ticket.”

He shoved the shining treasure across the diminutive counter, picked up the ticket and change. The piece of cardboard spelled freedom. He thrust the silver coins into his pocket, and listened well satisfied to the muffled clinking as they rattled together.

Only twenty minutes till the train was due. Edgar crept into a doorway so that no one should catch sight of him. A few passengers trailed in and wandered aimlessly about the platform. They failed to notice the runaway, though he himself felt as if all eyes were upon him. A whistle in the distance came as an immense relief to his suspense. Here was the train destined to convey him right away into the world. It was not until he had already stepped into a first-class carriage that he noticed he had been given a third-class ticket. So there were differences between travellers, he thought. Another initiation! His neighbours, when he had rectified his mistake, were a couple of Italian workmen, with calloused hands and rough voices. They had slung their tools on to the rack, and were sitting relaxed and listless. “They must have been working very hard, mused the child as one of them nodded off to sleep. I suppose they earned money for what they did. How much I wonder?”Money, then, was a thing one had to earn, that one was not automatically provided with. So far Edgar had taken his comfortable circumstances for granted, and had never given a thought to those abysses of misery which beset him on either hand. There were professions and trades to be followed, incomes to be earned—so many secrets he had never even noticed. He had learned much during his hour of solitude; and, as he cogitated these problems yet further and gazed at the fleeing landscape through the window, greater and greater illumination came to him. Gradually amid his gloomy anxiety, something seemed to grow, up and to blossom as he became conscious of the amazing kaleidoscope presented to him by life. He had run away because he was a coward and had been scared: true, but through his poltroonery he had come to taste the sweets of independence, he had come into contact with a reality he had hitherto completely ignored. Was he himself not just as great an enigma to his father and mother as the world had been to him? Quite possible. He saw with a new vision, as if manifold veils had been torn away from his eyes, as if the inside of things was being revealed to him, as if the secret of secrets was being disclosed. Houses flew past as though borne on the wings of the wind. Who were the people dwelling inside all these cottages and farmsteads, Edgar wondered. Were they rich or poor, happy or unhappy; were they full of uneasy longing as he was; did they want to know everything; were the children, like himself so far, merely playing with life? At the level crossings, the switchmen with their little flags were no longer the puppets he had always thought them, toy men, objects set up at those particular spots by chance. Edgar understood now that they had a function to perform, that they were fulfilling their destiny, had entered upon the struggle for life. The train gained in speed as it wound its way down the valley, leaving the high mountains behind. The contours were softened with the tender green of springtime. Only once did the fugitive look back at the high country he had left. The hills were blue distant, unattainable. As they receded more and more, and were swallowed up in the late afternoon fogs, it seemed to him that he had left childhood behind for ever in those remote and austere regions.

BEWILDERING DARKNESS

When at length he stood alone on the platform at Baden, watched the signal lights, and realized that night was upon him, his more hopeful and cheery mood petered out, and he felt an immense desolation descending upon him. While daylight lasted he had been surrounded by human beings; there were all manner of interesting things a small boy could do, sit on a bench and watch the passers-by, wander along streets looking into shop windows. But what was going to happen when everyone withdrew behind closed doors, when they retired to bed, went to sleep, while he, feeling guilty of wrong-doing, slunk about the empty streets, unwontedly alone and forsaken? He must seek shelter at once, not a minute to waste; of that he was profoundly convinced.

Without casting a look to right or to left he made a bee-line towards his grandmother’s villa. It lay back from the road in a garden sheltered by shrubberies and covered with ivy and other creepers. It peeped out white within its framework of green, a friendly, old-fashioned abode. Edgar looked over the hedge, feeling almost like a stranger. Nothing stirred, no lights shone from the windows; Grannie and her guests were probably sitting over their coffee on the lawn to the rear.

He already had his hand on the bell-pull, when an alarming thought entered his mind. So far his resolve to ask his dear Grannie for shelter had seemed quite natural to him. But suddenly he had a doubt. What excuse could he furnish for his unexpected arrival? How was he to answer her inevitable questions? He saw in fancy the old lady’s look of surprise when he told her that he had run away from his mother. Besides, he would have to confess having hit his mother, and the enormity of this crime weighed heavily upon him. A door banged. He started violently, and panic seized him. Suppose someone came out and caught him loitering! He scampered off, hardly knowing where his legs were taking him.

Arrived at the town-park gates, he came to a stop. Here it was very dark, and no one was to be seen. Perhaps he could find a vacant seat, sit down quietly, and think over the situation undisturbed. He slunk along a deserted alley-way. The trees looked ghostly in the dim light of the lamps, but farther on, up a little hill which he climbed, everything lay in darkness, the mist-laden gloom of a spring night. A solitary couple or two sat absorbed. He passed quickly by, for he wanted to be alone. But no solitude was to be found. Whispers could be heard coming from the shadowy depths of trees and bushes, borne upon the wind, mingling with the rustle of leaves and grass-blades; stealthy footsteps sounded along the paths, a sigh, a low laugh, mysterious, voluptuous. Did these murmurs come from human beings or from the beasts? Nature seemed wrapped in sleep, and yet all things were astir. A ferment of living matter was at work disquieting in the extreme to a highly-strung child. Could It all be part of the springtime?

Never had he felt smaller and more impotent, as he huddled upon a bench and tried to think out what he should do, and how explain his flight. But he found it impossible to concentrate his thoughts. In spite of his best endeavours, his ears were always pricked to catch the sound of those mysterious voices issuing from the gloom. The darkness was terrible and perplexing? yet how enigmatically beautiful! This rustling and soughing, this whirring and allurement, did it emanate from animals or from men? Or was it merely the breeze among the boughs? Edgar listened. Yes it was the wind shaking the leaves....No, it came from that couple over there, held in a tight embrace. Man and woman. They had strolled hither from the glare of the town, in order to be alone in the darkness. What were they up to? If he could only find an answer to that question he would find peace, and his tortured mind would be at rest. Two people, but so closely pressed together as to form but a single shadow-just as it had been with his mother and the baron...So the fateful secret clung to this place too? Footsteps drew nearer, a soft gurgle of laughter could be heard. Supposing this approaching couple should catch sight of him? He cowered farther back into the darkness. But they did not see him. They passed quietly by, wrapped in one another’s embrace. Edgar was beginning to breathe freely once more when they stopped, pressing their faces together, and a sigh of content escaped from the woman’s mouth. The man spoke a few rapid words. Edgar felt horribly frightened, and at the same time he thrilled with an unknown pleasure. A minute later the gravel crunched beneath their feet; the pair were swallowed up in the shadows. .

Edgar’s pulses beat furiously, and a sense of solitude gripped him. He longed to hear the sound of a friendly voice; to feel an affectionate hug; to see a lighted and familiar room, people he knew and loved. The uncanny darkness of the night had sunk into his very marrow. He would burst if he did not shake himself free.

Home! Home! A warm and lighted room! Persons he knew! All would be well, then. Nothing bad could happen if he were once with his own people. They might scold him or even beat him, he did not care so long as he had no more to dwell in darkness and solitude.

Hardly knowing what he did he ran on and on, till again he found himself in front of Grandma's house, with his hand ready to pull the bell. Through the curtain of greenery, he saw that the windows were alight;in imagination he pictured the familiar rooms, and their occupants. This proximity was a pleasure; and if he still hesitated to ring, it was merely to revel in his happiness, in the knowledge that he was near to those he loved and who loved him.

A shrill voice behind him brought him back to earth.

“Master Edgar, why, here you are at last!”

It was his Grannie’s housemaid who had come out for an airing. She ran up to the boy and gave him a hearty embrace. The doors, magically, swung open, the dogs dashed down the drive to bark a welcome, people were coming from the house with candles and lanterns, voices of mingled alarm and delight sounded in his ears, a friendly tumult of noises, shapes of persons he knew....His grandmother, who hugged him tight, and behind her—could he be dreaming?—his mother. Abashed, trembling, on the verge of tears, the boy stood stockstill, not knowing which way to turn or what to do. Was he frightened? Or was he happy?

THE LAST DREAM

Yes, it was his mother. Through inquiries made at Simmering station, she had traced the direction of his flight. She had wired to her husband in Vienna, to Grannie in Baden. He was expected. Why had he not arrived ? Frau Blumental, taking the express, had outstripped him. They led him in subdued triumph to the sitting-room. True, he was scolded; but the scoldings did not wound him, for in the eyes of those that scolded he saw nothing but joy and love. Even their assumed anger could not last; it fizzled out almost before the reprimand had been made. Now Grannie was hugging him again, and crying over him. No one reproached him. Wonderful! He felt as though he were a prisoner of love. The maid pulled off his thin coat and muffled him in a warm shawl; asked him if he were not hungry, or if there was anything she could bring him. He had hated being looked upon as a child; but now he revelled in the bliss of being cared for. The arrogance and presumption of the last few days vanished.

The telephone buzzed in the neighbouring room. His mother answered the call. “Yes...Edgar’s come...it’s all right... Why was she not furious with him, he wondered. Her dear eyes caressed him with a strange expression. His immediate impulse was to disregard all the coddling his Grannie and his Aunt Bertha were lavishing upon him and to throw himself into Mummy’s arms, to tell her how sorry he was, to promise anything she liked. He got up. But Grannie asked in alarm:

“Where are you going, pet?”

Anxious, were they, if he so much as moved? They fancied he was running away again. So he had given them all a jolly good fright? How could he ever make them understand that no one regretted this flight so much as he.

They served him an impromptu supper. Grannie sat by him, and never took her eyes off him. She and Auntie and the maid formed a loving circle round him. The warmth of their affection solaced him marvellously. But why was his mother not present? He felt uneasy at her absence. If she could only guess how utterly crushed he was...

A carriage drew up outside. Grannie left the room. Amid a medley of voices he recognized his father’s. Auntie and the maid had also gone out into the hall. Edgar was again alone, and again he was frightened by solitude. His father had always treated the boy with the utmost severity, and had made himself feared. Now Edgar listened to his father’s voice on the other side of the door. He appeared to be excited, and spoke in loud and angry tones. Grannie and Mummy seemed to be using their best endeavours to appease him. Resolute footsteps approached. The door opened.

Herr Blumental was a very tall man, so that Edgar felt as tiny as a doll when he was asked, in a harsh voice:

“What possessed you to run away and give your mother such a fright, you young scoundrel?”

The man was genuinely angry; but Mummy came in directly behind her husband. Her face was in shadow so that the boy could not take his cue from her and therefore, did not answer.

“Well? Lost your tongue? What was wrong? Own up, don’t be afraid. There must be some reason for running away. Anybody hurt your feelings?”

Edgar hesitated to reply. Anger and pique revived in him. Should he justify himself? He raised his eyes and looked at his mother. She was still in her husband’s huge shadow, but the boy saw her make an unwonted gesture. She slowly raised a finger to her lips, and her eyes implored silence.

The child’s heart warmed. He understood that she was begging him to keep her secret. How proud and happy he felt that she should ask him this service. Pulling himself together, he said:

“No, Dad! I was having a lovely time. Mummy was ever so good to me. But suddenly I felt I had to do something thoroughly naughty. So I ran away.”

Herr Blumental looked at his son dubiously. He had expected anything but this, and was disarmed by so abject a confession.

“Well,” he answered, “If you’re sorry, there’s no more to be said. Another time I trust you will reflect before behaving so rashly.” He gazed kindly down at the boy and his voice took on a softer tone. “You’re looking a bit pale, but you’ve grown a lot since you left home. Don’t be up to any more childish pranks. You are no longer a kid, and must try in future to be reasonable....”

Edgar gazed fixedly at his mother. There was a gleam in her eyes he had never seen before, they were moist and bright, while round her mouth played an elfin smile which seemed full of gratitude.

He was now sent off to bed, but he felt no resentment, neither did he mind being left alone once more. His head buzzed with thoughts. All the suffering of the last few days was swallowed up in the freshness and delight of this first real experience, and he looked forward undauntedly to further encounters with reality. The trees without soughed and swayed in the wind, but he was not saddened by the noise. Life was rich and manifold; he had seen it naked before him, bereft of lies and subterfuges, full of a perilous beauty. Hatred for persons or things seemed to him now a childish stupidity and misapprehension. Even the baron, his enemy, shared in the boy’s exuberant gratitude, because it had been through this false friend that the door into a wonderland of the emotions had been opened.

He lay in the dark, contented, proud, and happy. Sleep had almost enfolded him, when he became aware of someone moving softly in the room and of a hand gently stroking his hair. Tears dropped on to his cheeks...and, without a word, his mother kissed him fondly. Not until many years later did Edgar understand the full meaning of these tears and kisses. They were a vow that henceforward Mummy would devote all her energies, all her love to him; that there would be no more adventures in her life; that she had said farewell to the pleasures of the flesh. She was grateful to her child for saving her from a futile and unworthy liaison; and, in a bitter-sweet compunction, she pledged herself to her boy’s service. Though Edgar could not, child that he still was, grasp the significance of all this at the time, he nevertheless felt that it was glorious to be loved so much, and he surmised that in some incomprehensible manner such love was inextricably interwoven with the major secret of life.

After she had withdrawn and closed the door behind her, Edgar felt her presence and the warm glow of her lips upon his cheek. As he gradually dropped off to sleep, he drowsily wished he might often feel the pressure of soft lips against his own. A final and confused vision of the last eventful days swept before him; fate turned the pages of the Book of Youth; the child fell asleep, and the profound dream of life began to unfold itself.

THE GOVERNESS

THE two girls were alone in their room. The light had been extinguished, and all was dark except for a faint shimmer from the two beds. They were both breathing so quietly that they might have been supposed to be asleep.

“I say,” came a gentle, hesitating whisper from one of the beds. The twelve-year-old girl was speaking.

“What is it?” asked her sister, who was a year older. “I’m so glad you’re still awake. I’ve something to tell you.”

There was no answer in words, only a rustle from the other bed. The elder girl had sat up, and was waiting, her eyes a sparkle in the dim light.

“Look here, this is what I want to tell you. But, first of all, have you noticed anything funny about Miss Mann lately?”

“Yes,” said the other after a moment’s silence. “There is something, but I hardly know what. She’s not so strict as she used to be. For two days I haven’t done my exercises, and she never scolded me about it. I don’t know what’s happened, but she doesn’t seem to bother about us any more. She sits all by herself, and doesn’t join in our games as she used to.”

“I think she’s unhappy, and tries not to show it. She never plays the piano now.”

There was a pause, and then the elder girl spoke once more:

“You said you had something to tell me.”

“Yes, but you must keep it to yourself. You mustn’t breathe a word about it to Mother, or to your friend, Lottie.”

“Of course I won’t,” answered the other indignantly. “Do get on!”

“Well, after we’d come up to bed, it suddenly struck me that I’d never said good night to Miss Mann. I didn’t bother to put on my shoes again, and I tiptoed across to her room, meaning to give her a surprise.So I opened her door quietly, and for a moment I thought she wasn’t there. The light was on, but I couldn’t see her. Then suddenly—I was quite startled—I heard someone crying, and I saw that she was lying dressed on her bed, her head buried in the pillows. She was sobbing so dreadfully that it made me feel all queer, but she never noticed me. Then I crept out and shut the door as softly as I could. I stood outside there for a moment, for I could hardly walk, and through the door I could still hear her sobbing. Then I came back.”

Neither of them spoke for a moment. Then the elder girl said with a sigh:

“Poor Miss Mann!” and there was another pause.

“I wonder what on earth she was crying about,” resumed the younger girl. “She hasn’t been in any row lately, for Mother hasn’t been nagging at her as she always used to, and I’m sure we’ve not been troublesome. What can there be to make her cry?”

“I think I can guess,” said the elder.

“Well, out with it!”

The answer was delayed, but at length it came:

“I believe she’s in love.”

“In love?” The younger girl started up. “In love? Who with?”

“Haven’t you noticed?”

“You can’t mean Otto?”

“Of course I do! And he’s in love with her. All the three years he’s been living with us he never came for a walk with us until two or three months ago. But now he doesn’t miss a day. He hardly noticed either of us until Miss Mann came. Now he’s always fussing round. Every time we go out, we seem to run across him, either in the Park or in the Gardens or somewhere—wherever Miss Mann takes us. Surely you’ve noticed?”

“Yes, of course I’ve noticed,” answered the younger. “But I just thought...”

She did not finish her sentence.

“Oh, I didn’t want to make too much of it either. But after a time I was sure that he was only using us as an excuse.”

There was a long silence, while the girls were thinking things over.The younger was the first to resume the conversation. “But if so, why should she cry? He’s very fond of her. I’ve always thought it must be so jolly to be in love.”

“So have I,” said the elder dreamily. “I can’t make it out.”

Once more came the words, in a drowsy voice:“ Poor Miss Mann!”

So their talk ended for that night.

They did not allude to the matter again in the morning, but each knew that the other’s thoughts were full of it. Not that they looked meaningly at one another, but in spite of themselves they would exchange glances when their eyes had rested on the governess. At meals they contemplated their cousin Otto aloofly, as if he had been a stranger. They did not speak to him, but scrutinized him furtively, trying to discover if he had a secret understanding with Miss Mann. They had no heart in their amusements, for they could think of nothing but this urgent enigma. In the evening, with an assumption of indifference, one of them asked the other:

“Did you notice anything more to-day?”

“No,” said the sister, laconically.

They were really afraid to discuss the subject. Thus matters continued for several days. The two girls were silently taking notes, uneasy in mind and yet feeling that they were on the verge of discovering a wonderful secret.

At length, it was at supper, the younger girl noticed that the governess made an almost imperceptible sign to Otto, and that he nodded in answer. Trembling with excitement, she gave her sister a gentle kick under cover of the table. The elder looked inquiringly at the younger, who responded with a meaning glance. Both were on tenterhooks for the rest of the meal. After supper the governess said to the girls:

“Go to the schoolroom and find something to do. My head is aching, and I must lie down for half an hour.”

The instant they were alone, the younger burst out with:

“You’ll see, Otto will go into her room!”

“Of course,” said the other, “That’s why she sent us in here.”

“We must listen outside the door.”

“But suppose someone should come...”

“Who?”

“Mother.”

“That would be awful,” exclaimed the younger in alarm.

“look here, I’ll listen, and you must keep cavy in the passage.”

The little one pouted.

“But then you won’t tell me everything.”

“No fear!”

“Honour bright?”

“Honour bright! You must cough if you hear anyone coming.”They waited in the passage, their hearts throbbing with excitement. What was going to happen? They heard a footstep, and stole into the dark schoolroom. Yes, it was Otto. He went into Miss Mann’s room and closed the door. The elder girl shot to her post, and listened at the keyhole, hardly daring to breathe. The younger looked enviously. Burning with curiosity, she too stole up to the door, but her sister pushed her away, and angrily signed to her to keep watch at the other end of the passage. Thus they waited for several minutes, which to the younger girl seemed an eternity. She was in a fever of impatience, and fidgeted as if she had been standing on hot coals. She could hardly restrain her tears because her sister was hearing everything. At length a noise startled her, and she coughed. Both the girls fled into the schoolroom, and a moment passed before they had breath enough to speak. Then the younger said eagerly:

“Now then, tell me all about it.”

The elder looked perplexed, and said, as if talking to herself:

“I don’t understand.”

“What?”

“It’s so extraordinary.”

“What? What?” said the other furiously.

The elder made an effort:

“It was extraordinary, quite different from what I expected. I think when he went into the room he must have wanted to put his arms round her or to kiss her, for she said: ‘Not now, I’ve something serious to tell you.’ I couldn’t see anything, for the key was in the way, but I could hear all right. ‘what’s up?’ asked Otto, in a tone I’ve never heard him use before. You know how he generally speaks, quite loud and cheekily, but now I am sure he was frightened. She must have noticed that he was humbugging, for all she said was: ‘I think you know well enough.’—‘Not a bit.’—‘If so,’ she said in ever so sad a tone, ‘why have you drawn away from me? For a week you’ve hardly spoken to me; you avoid me whenever you can; you are never with the girls now;you don’t come to meet us in the Park. Have you ceased to care for me all of a sudden? Oh, you know only too well why you are drawing back like this.’ There was no answer for a moment. Then he said: ‘Surely you realize how near it is to my examination. I have no time for anything but my work. How can I help that?’ She began to cry, and while sobbing, she said to him gently: ‘Otto, do speak the truth. What have I done that you should treat me like this? I have not made any claim on you, but we must talk things out frankly. Your expression shows me plainly that you know all about...’”

The girl began to shake, and could not finish her sentence. The listener pressed closer, and asked:

“All about what?”

“All about our baby!”

“Their baby!” the younger broke out. “A baby! Impossible!”

“That’s what she said.”

“You can’t have heard right.”

“But I did. I’m quite sure. And he repeated it: ‘Our baby!’ After a time she went on: ‘what are we to do now?’ Then...”

“Well?”

“Then you coughed, and I had to bolt for it.” The younger was frightfully perplexed.

“But she can’t have a baby. Where can the baby be?”

“I don’t understand any more than you.”

“Perhaps she’s got it at home. Of course, Mother would not let her bring it here. That must be why she is so unhappy.”

“Oh, rot, she didn’t know Otto then!”

They pondered helplessly. Again the younger girl said:

“A baby, it’s impossible. How can she have a baby? She’s not married, and only married people have children.” “Perhaps she is married.”

“Don’t be an idiot. She never married Otto, any-how.”

“Well, then?”

They stared at one another.

“Poor Miss Mann,” said one of them sorrowfully.

They always seemed to come back to this phrase, which was like a sigh of compassion. But always their curiosity blazed up once more.

“Do you think it’s a boy or a girl?”

“How on earth can I tell?”

“What if I were to ask her, tactfully?”

“Oh, shut up!”

“Why shouldn’t I? She’s so awfully nice to us.”

“What’s the use. They never tell us that sort of thing. If they are talking about them when we come into the room they immediately dry up, and begin to talk rot to us as if we were still kids—though I’m thirteen. What’s the use of asking her, just to be humbugged?”

“But I want to know.”

“Well, of course, I should like to know too.”

“What bothers me is that Otto pretended not to know anything about it. One must know when one has a baby, just as one knows one has a father and mother.”

“Oh, he was only putting it on. He’s always kidding!”

“But not about such a thing. It’s only when he wants to pull our leg.”

They were interrupted by the governess coming in at that moment, and they pretended to be hard at work. But it did not escape them that her eyelids were red, and that her voice betrayed deep emotion. They sat perfectly quiet, regarding her with a new respect. “She has a baby,” they kept on thinking; “That is why she is so sorrowful.” But upon them, too, sorrow was stealing unawares.

At dinner next day, they learned a startling piece of news. Otto was going away. He had told his uncle that he had to work extra hard just before examination, and that there were too many interruptions in the house. He was going into lodgings for the next two months.

The girls were bubbling with excitement. They felt sure that their cousin’s departure must be connected in some way with the previous day’s conversation. Instinct convinced them that this was a coward’s flight. When Otto came to say good-bye to them they were deliberately rude, and turned their backs on him. Nevertheless, they watched his farewell to Miss Mann. She shook hands with him calmly, but her lips twitched.

The girls were changed beings these days. They seldom laughed, could not take pleasure in anything, were sad-eyed. They prowled restlessly about, and distrusted their elders, suspecting that an intention to deceive was lurking behind the simplest utterance. Ever on the watch, they glided like shadows, and listened behind doors, eager to break through the net which shut them off from the mystery—or at least to catch through its meshes a glimpse into the world of reality. The faith, the contented blindness of childhood, had vanished. Besides, they were continually expecting some new revelation, and were afraid they might miss it. The atmosphere of deceit around them made them deceitful. Whenever their parents were near, they pretended to be busily engaged in childish occupations. Making common cause against the world of grown-ups, they were drawn more closely together. A caressive impulse would often make them embrace one another when overwhelmed by a sense of their ignorance and impotence; and sometimes they would burst into tears. Without obvious cause, their lives had passed into a critical phase.

Among their manifold troubles, one seemed worse than all the rest. Tacitly, quite independently of one another, they had made up their minds that they would give as little trouble as they could to Miss Mann, now that she was so unhappy. They were extremely diligent, helping one another in their lessons; were always quiet and well behaved; tried to anticipate their teacher’s wishes. But the governess never seemed to notice, and that was what hurt them more than anything. She was so different now. When one of the girls spoke to her, she would start as though from slumber, and her gaze seemed to come back to them as if it had been probing vast distances. For hours she would sit musing, and the girls would move on tiptoe lest they should disturb her, for they fancied she was thinking of her absent child. In their own awakening womanhood, they had become fonder than ever of the governess, who was now so gentle towards them. Miss Mann, who had been lively, and at times a trifle overbearing, was more thoughtful and considerate, and the girls felt that all her actions betrayed a secret sorrow. They never actually saw her weeping, but her eyelids were often red. It was plain she wanted to keep her troubles to herself, and they were deeply grieved not to be able to help her.

One day, when the governess had turned away towards the window to wipe her eyes, the younger girl plucked up courage to seize her hand and say: “Miss Mann, you are so sad. It’s not our fault, is it?”

The governess looked tenderly at the child, stroked her hair, and answered:

“No, dear. Of course it is not your fault.” She kissed the little maid’s forehead.

Thus the girls were continually on the watch, and one of them, coming unexpectedly into the sitting-room, caught a word or two that had not been intended for her ears. Her parents promptly changed the conversation, but the child had heard enough to set her thinking.

“Yes, I have been struck by the same thing,” the mother had been saying. “I shall have to speak to her.”

At first the little girl had fitted the cap on her own head, and had run to consult her sister.

“What do you think the row can be about?”

But at dinner-time they noticed how their father and mother were scrutinizing the governess, and how they then looked significantly at one another. After dinner, their mother said to Miss Mann:

“Will you come to my room please? I want to speak to you.”

The girls were tremulous with excitement. Something was going to happen! By now, eavesdropping had become a matter of course. They no longer felt any shame; their one thought was to discover what was being hidden from them. They were at the door in a flash, directly Miss Mann had entered.

They listened, but all they could hear was a faint murmur of conversation. Were they to learn nothing after all? Then one of the voices was raised. Their mother said angrily:

“Did you suppose we were all blind—that we should never notice your condition? This throws a pretty light upon your conception of your duties as a governess. I shudder to think that I have confided my daughters’ education to such hands. No doubt you have neglected them shamefully...”

The governess seemed to break in here with a protest, but she spoke softly, so that the girls could not hear.

“Talk, talk! Every wanton finds excuses. A woman such as you gives herself to the first comer without a thought of the consequences. God will provide! It’s monstrous that a hussy like you should become a governess. But I suppose you don’t flatter yourself that I shall let you stay in the house any longer?”

The listeners shuddered. They could not fully understand, but their mother’s tone seemed horrible to them. It was answered only by Miss Mann’s sobs. The tears burst from their own eyes. Their mother grew angrier than ever.

“That’s all you can do now, cry and snivel! Your tears won’t move me. I have no sympathy with such a person as you are. It’s no business of mine, what will happen to you. No doubt you know where to turn for help, and that’s your affair. All I know is that you shan’t stay another day in my house.”

Miss Mann’s despairing sobs were still the only answer. Never had they heard anyone cry in this fashion. Their feeling was that no one who cried so bitterly could possibly be in the wrong. Their mother waited in silence for a little while, and then said sharply: “Well, that’s all I have to say to you. Pack up your things this afternoon, and come to me for your salary to-morrow morning. You can go now.”

The girls fled back to their own room. What could have happened? What was the meaning of this sudden storm? In a glass darkly, they began to have some suspicion of the truth. For the first time, their feeling was one of revolt against their parents.

“Wasn’t it horrid of Mother to speak to her like that ?” said the elder.

The younger was a little alarmed at such frank criticism, and stammered:

“But...but...we don’t know what she’s done.”

“Nothing wrong, I’m certain. Miss Mann would never do anything wrong. Mother doesn’t know her as well as we do.”

“Wasn’t it awful, the way she cried? It did make me feel so bad.”

“Yes, it was dreadful. But the way Mother shouted at her was sickening, positively sickening!”

The speaker stamped angrily, and tears welled up into her eyes.

At this moment Miss Mann came in, looking utterly worn out.

“Girls, I have a lot to do this afternoon. I know you will be good, if I leave you to yourselves? We’ll have the evening together.”

She turned, and left the room, without noticing the children’s forlorn looks.

“Did you see how red her eyes were? I simply can’t understand how Mother could be so unkind to her.”

“Poor Miss Mann!”

Again this lament, in a voice broken with tears. Then their Mother came to ask if they would like to go for a walk with her.

“Not to-day, Mother.”

In fact, they were afraid of their mother, and they were angry because she did not tell them that she was sending Miss Mann away. It suited their mood better to be by themselves. They fluttered about the room like caged swallows, crushed by the atmosphere of falsehood and silence. They wondered if they could not go to Miss Mann and ask her what was the matter; tell her they wanted her to stay, that they thought Mother had been horribly unfair. But they were afraid of distressing her. Besides they were ashamed, for how could they say a word about the matter when all they knew had been learned by eavesdropping? They had to spend the interminable afternoon by themselves, moping, crying from time to time, and turning over in their minds memories of what they had heard through the closed door—their mother’s heartless anger and Miss Mann’s despairing sobs.

In the evening, the governess came to see them, but only to say good night. As she left the room, the girls longed to break the silence, but could not utter a word. At the door, as if recalled by their dumb yearning, Miss Mann turned back, her eyes shining with emotion. She embraced both the girls, who instantly burst out crying. Kissing them once more, the governess hurried away.

It was obvious to the children that this was a final leave taking.

“We shall never see her again,” sobbed one.

“I know. She’ll be gone when we come back from school tomorrow.”

“Perhaps we shall be able to visit her after a time. Then she’ll show us the baby.”

“Yes, she’s always such a dear.”

“Poor Miss Mann!”

The sorrowful phrase seemed to hold a foreboding of their own destiny.

“I can’t think how we shall get on without her!”

“I shall never be able to stand another governess, after her.”

“Nor shall I.”

“There’ll never be anyone like Miss Mann. Besides...”

She did not venture to finish her sentence. An unconscious womanliness had made them feel a sort of veneration for Miss Mann, ever since they had known she had a baby. This was continually in their thoughts, and moved them profoundly.

“I say,” said one.

“Yes?”

“I’ve got an idea. Can’t we do something really nice for Miss Mann before she goes away, something that will show her how fond we are of her, and that we are not like Mother? Will you join in?”

“Rather!”

“You know how much she likes white roses. Let’s go out early tomorrow and buy some, before we go to school. We’ll put them in her room.”

“But when?”

“After school.”

“That’s no use, she’ll be gone then. Look here, I’ll steal out quite early, before breakfast, and bring them back here. Then we’ll take them to her.”

“All right, we must get up early.”

They raided their money-boxes. It made them almost cheerful, once more, that they would be able to show Miss Mann how much they loved her.

Early in the morning, roses in hand, they knocked at Miss Mann’s door. There was no answer.

Thinking the governess must be asleep, they peeped in. The room was empty; the bed had not been slept in. On the table lay two letters. The girls were startled. What had happened?

“I shall go straight to Mother,” said the elder girl. Defiantly, without a trace of fear, she accosted her mother with the words:

“Where’s Miss Mann?”

“In her room, I suppose.”

“There’s no one in her room; she never went to bed. She must have gone away last night. Why didn’t you tell us anything about it?”

The mother hardly noticed the challenging tone. Turning pale, she sought her husband, who went into Miss Mann’s room.

He stayed there some time, while the girls eyed their mother with gloomy indignation, and she seemed unable to meet their gaze.

Now their father came back, with an open letter in his hand. He, too, was agitated. The parents retired into their own room, and conversed in low tones. This time, the girls were afraid to try and overhear what was said. They had never seen their father look like that before.

When their mother came out, they saw she had been weeping. They wanted to question her, but she said sharply:

“Be off with you to school, you’ll be late.”

They had to go. For hours they sat in class without attending to a single word. Then they rushed home. There, a dreadful thought seemed to dominate everyone’s mind. Even the servants had a strange look. Their mother came to meet them, and began to speak in carefully rehearsed phrases:

“Children, you won’t see Miss Mann any more; she is...”

The sentence was left unfinished. So furious, so menacing, was the girls’ expression that their mother could not lie to them. She turned away, and sought refuge in her own room.

That afternoon, Otto put in an appearance. One of the two letters had been addressed to him, and he had been summoned. He too, was pale and uneasy. No one spoke to him. Everybody shunned him. Catching sight of the two girls sitting disconsolate in a corner of the room, he went up to them.

“Don’t you come near us!” both screamed, regarding him with horror.

He paced up and down for a while, and then vanished. No one spoke to the girls and they said nothing to one another. They wandered aimlessly from room to room, looking silently into one another’s tearstained faces when their paths crossed. They knew everything now. They knew that they had been cheated; they knew how mean people could be. They did not love their parents any more, did not trust Father or Mother any longer. They were sure they would never trust anyone again. All the burden of life pressed heavily upon their frail young shoulders. Their careless, happy childhood lay behind them; unknown terrors awaited them. The full significance of what had happened was still beyond their grasp, but they were wrestling with its dire potentialities., They were drawn together in their isolation, but it was a dumb communion, for they could not break the spell of silence. From their elders they were completely cut off. No one could approach them, for the portals of their souls had been closed—perhaps for years to come. They were at war with all around them. For, in one brief day, they had grown up!

Not till late in the evening, when they were alone in their bedroom, did there reawaken in them the child’s awe of solitude, the haunting fear of the dead woman, the terror of dread possibilities. It was bitterly cold; in the general confusion the heating apparatus had been forgotten They both crept into one bed, and cuddled closely together, for mutual encouragement as well as for warmth. They were still unable to discuss their trouble. But now, at length, the younger’s pent-up emotion found relief in a storm of tears, and the elder, too, sobbed convulsively. Thus they lay weeping in one another’s arms. They were no longer bewailing the loss of Miss Mann, or their estrangement from their parents. They were shaken by the anticipation of what might befall them in this unknown world into whose realities they had to-day looked for the first time. They shrank from the life into which they were growing up; from the life which seemed to them like a forest full of threatening shapes, a forest they had to cross. But by degrees this sense of anxiety grew visionary; their sobs were less violent, and came at longer intervals. They breathed quietly, now, in a rhythmical unison of peace. They slept.

LETTER FROM AN UNKNOWN WOMAN

R. the famous novelist, had been away on a brief holiday in the mountains. Reaching Vienna early in the morning, he bought a newspaper at the station, and when he glanced at the date was reminded that it was his birthday. “Forty-one!”—the thought came like a flash. He was neither glad nor sorry at the realization. He hailed a taxi, and skimmed the newspaper as he drove home. His man reported that there had been a few callers during the master’s absence, besides some telephone messages. A bundle of letters was awaiting him. Looking indifferently at these, he opened one or two because he was interested in the senders, but laid aside for the time a bulky packet addressed in a strange handwriting. At ease in an armchair, he drank his morning tea, finished the newspaper, and read a few circulars. Then, having lighted a cigar, he turned to the remaining letter.

It was a manuscript rather than an ordinary letter, comprising several dozen hastily penned sheets in a feminine handwriting. Involuntarily he examined the envelope once more, in case he might have overlooked a covering letter. But there was nothing of the kind, no signature, and no sender’s address on either envelope or contents.“Strange,” he thought, as he began to read the manuscript. The first words were a superscription:

“To you, who have never known me.” He was perplexed. Was this addressed to him, or to some imaginary being? His curiosity suddenly awakened he, read as follows:

My boy died yesterday. For three days and three nights I have been wrestling with Death for this frail little life. During forty consecutive hours, while the fever of influenza was shaking his poor burning body I sat beside his bed. I put cold compresses on his fore head; day and night, night and day. I held his restless little hands. The third evening,my strength gave out. My eyes closed without my being aware of it, and for three or four hours I must have slept on the hard stool. Meanwhile, Death took him. There he lies, my darling boy, in his narrow cot, just as he died. Only his eyes have been closed, his wise, dark eyes; and his hands have been crossed over his breast. Four candles are burning, one at each corner of the bed. I cannot bear to look, I cannot bear to move; for when the candles flicker, shadows chase one another over his face and his closed lips. It looks as if his features stirred, and I could almost fancy that he is not dead after all, that he will wake and with his clear voice will say something childishly loving. But I know that he is dead; and I will not look again, to hope once more, and once more to be disappointed. I know, now, my boy died yesterday. Now I have only you left in the world; only you, who do not know me; you, who are enjoying yourself all unheeding, sporting with men and things. Only you, who have never known me, and whom I have never ceased to love.

I have lighted a fifth candle, and am sitting at the table writing to you. I cannot stay alone with my dead child without pouring my heart out to someone; and to whom should I do that in this dreadful hour if not to you, who have been and still are all in all to me? Perhaps I shall not be able to make myself plain to you. Perhaps you will not be able to understand me. My head feels so heavy my temples are throbbing;my limbs are aching. I think I must be feverish. Influenza is raging in this quarter and probably I have caught the infection. I should not be sorry if I could join my child in that way, instead of making short work of myself. Sometimes it seems dark before my eyes, and perhaps I shall not be able to finish this letter; but I shall try with all my strength, this one and only time, to speak to you, my beloved, to you who have never known me.

To you only do I want to speak, that I may tell you everything for the first time. I should like you to know the whole of my life, of that life which has always been yours, and of which you have known nothing. But you shall only know my secret after I am dead, when there will be no one whom you will have to answer; you shall only know it if that which is now shaking my limbs with cold and with heat should really prove, for me, the end. If I have to go on living, I shall tear up this letter and shall keep the silence I have always kept. If you ever hold it in your hands, you may know that a dead woman is telling you her lifestory; the story of a life which was yours from its first to its last fully conscious hour. You need have no fear of my words. A dead woman wants nothing; neither love, nor compassion, nor consolation. I have only one thing to ask of you, that you believe to the full what the pain in me forces me to disclose to you. Believe my words, for I ask nothing more of you; a mother will not speak false beside the deathbed of her only child.

I am going to tell you my whole life, the life which did not really begin until the day I first saw you. What I can recall before that day is gloomy and confused, a memory as of a cellar filled with dusty, dull and cob-webbed things and people—a place with which my heart has no concern. When you came into my life, I was thirteen, and I lived in the house where you live to-day, in the very house in which you are reading this letter; the last breath of my life. I lived on the same floor, for the door of our flat was just opposite the door of yours. You will certainly have forgotten us. You will long ago have forgotten the accountant’s widow in her threadbare mourning, and the thin, half-grown girl. We were always so quiet, characteristic examples of shabby gentility. It is unlikely that you ever heard our name, for we had no plate on our front door, and no one ever came to see us. Besides, it is so long ago, fifteen or sixteen years. Impossible that you should remember. But I, how passionately I remember every detail. As if it had just happened, I recall the day, the hour, when I first heard of you, first saw you. How could it be otherwise, seeing that it was then the world began for me? Have patience awhile, and let me tell you everything from first to last. Do not grow weary of listening to me for a brief space, since I have not been weary of loving you my whole life long.

Before you came, the people who lived in your flat were horrid folk, always quarrelling. Though they were wretchedly poor themselves, they hated us for our poverty because we held aloof from them. The man was given to drink, and used to beat his wife. We were often wakened in the night by the clatter of falling chairs and breaking plates. Once, when he had beaten her till the blood came, she ran out on the landing with her hair streaming, followed by her drunken husband abusing her, until all the people came out on to the staircase and threatened to send for the police. My mother would have nothing to do with them. She forbade me to play with the children, who took every opportunity of venting their spleen on me for this refusal. When they met me in the street, they would call me names; and once they threw a snowball at me which was so hard that it cut my forehead. Everyone in the house detested them, and we all breathed more freely when something happened and they had to leave—I think the man had been arrested for theft. For a few days there was a “To Let” notice at the the main door. Then it was taken down, and the caretaker told us that the flat had been rented by an author, who was a bachelor, and was sure to be quiet. That was the first time I heard your name.

A few days later, the flat was thoroughly cleaned, and the painters and decorators came. Of course they made lot of noise, but my mother was glad, for she said that would be the end of the disorder next door. I did not see you during the move. The decorations and furnishings were supervised by your servant, the little greyhaired man with such a serious demeanour, who had obviously been used to service in good families. He managed everything in a most businesslike way, and impressed us all very much. A high-class domestic of this kind was something quite new in our suburban flats. Besides, he was extremely civil, but was never hail-fellow-well-met with the ordinary servants. From the outset he treated my mother respectfully, as a lady; and he was always courteous even to little me. When he had occasion to mention your name, he did so in a way which showed that his feeling towards you was that of a family retainer. I used to love good old John for this, though I envied him at the same time because it was his privilege to see you constantly and to serve you.

Do you know why I am telling you these trifles? I Want you to understand how it was that from the very beginning your personality came to exercise so much power over me when I was still a shy and timid child. Before I had actually seen you, there was a halo round your head. You were enveloped in an atmosphere of wealth, marvel and mystery. People whose lives are narrow, are avid of novelty; and in this little suburban house we were all impatiently awaiting your arrival. In my own case, curiosity rose to fever point when I came home from school one afternoon and found the furniture van in front of the house. Most of the heavy things had gone up, and the furniture removers were dealing with the smaller articles. I stood at the door to watch and admire, for everything belonging to you was so different from what I had been used to. There were Indian idols, Italian sculptures, and great, brightly-coloured pictures. Last of all came books, such lovely books, many more than I should have thought possible. They were piled by the door. The manservant stood there carefully dusting them one by one. I greedily watched the pile as it grew. Your servant did not send me away, but he did not encourage me either, so I was afraid to touch any of them, though I should have so liked to stroke the smooth leather bindings. I did glance timidly at some of the titles; many of them were in French and in English, and in languages of which I did not know a single word. I should have liked to stand there watching for hours, but my mother called me and I had to go in.

I thought about you the whole evening, although I had not seen you yet. I had only about a dozen cheap books, bound in worn cardboard. I loved them more than anything else in the world, and was continually reading and re-reading them. Now I was wondering what the man could be like who had such a lot of books, who had read so much, who knew so many languages, who was rich and at the same time so learned. The idea of so many books aroused a kind of unearthly veneration. I tried to picture you in my mind. You must be an old man with spectacles and a long, white beard, like our geography master, but much kinder, nicer-looking, and gentler. I don’t know why I was sure that you must be handsome, for I fancied you to be an elderly man. That very night, I dreamed of you for the first time.

Next day you moved in; but though I was on the watch I could not get a glimpse of your face, and my failure inflamed my curiosity. At length I saw you, on the third day. How astounded I was to find that you were quite different from the ancient godfather conjured up by my childish imagination. A bespectacled, good-natured old fellow was what I had anticipated; and you came looking just as you still look, for you are one on whom the years leave little mark. You were wearing a beautiful suit of light-brown tweeds, and you ran upstairs two steps at a time with the boyish ease that always characterizes your movements. You were hat in hand, so that, with indescribable amazement, I should see your bright and lively face and your youthful hair. Your handsome, slim, and spruce figure was a positive shock to me. How strange it was that in this first moment I should have plainly realized that which I and all others are continually surprised at in you. I realized that you are two people rolled into one: that you are an ardent, lighthearted youth devoted to sport and adventure; and at the same time, in your art, a deeply read and highly cultured man, grave, and with a keen sense of responsibility. Unconsciously I perceived what everyone who knew you came to perceive, that you led two lives. One of these was known to all, it was the life open to the whole world; the other was turned away from the world, and was fully known only to yourself. I, a girl of thirteen, coming under the spell of your attraction, grasped this secret of your existence, this profound cleavage of your two lives, at the first glance.

Can you understand, now, what a miracle, what an alluring enigma, you must have seemed to me, the child? Here was a man whom everyone spoke of with respect because he wrote books, and because he was famous in the great world. Of a sudden he had revealed himself to me as a boyish, cheerful young man of five-and-twenty. I need hardly tell you that henceforward in my restricted world, you were the only thing that interested me; that my life revolved round yours with the fidelity proper to a girl of thirteen. I watched you, watched your habits, watched the people who came to see you—and all this increased instead of diminishing my interest in your personality, for the two-sidedness of your nature was reflected in the diversity of your visitors. Some of them were young men, comrades of yours, carelessly dressed students with whom you laughed and larked. Some of them were ladies who came in motors. Once the conductor of the opera—the great man whom before this I had seen only from a distance, baton in hand-called on you. Some of them were girls, young girls still attending the commercial school, who shyly glided in at the door. A great many of your visitors were women. I thought nothing of this, not even when, one morning,as I was on my way to school, I saw a closely veiled lady coming away from your flat. I was only just thirteen, and in my immaturity I did not in the least realize that the eager curiosity with which I scanned all your doings was already love.

But I know the very day and hour when I consciously gave my whole heart to you. I had been for a walk with a schoolfellow, and we were standing at the door chattering. A motor drove up. You jumped out, in the impatient, springy fashion which has never ceased to charm me, and were about to go in. An impulse made me open the door for you, and this brought me in your path, so that we almost collided. You looked at me with a cordial, gracious, all-embracing glance, which was almost a caress. You smiled at me tenderly—yes, tenderly is the word—and said gently, nay, confidentially: “Thanks so much.”

That was all. But from this moment, from the time when you looked at me so tenderly, so tenderly, I was yours. Later, before long indeed, I was to learn that this was a way you had of looking at all women with whom you came in contact. It was a caressive and alluring glance, at once enfolding and disclothing, the glance of the born seducer. Involuntarily you looked in this way at every shopgirl who served you, at every maidservant who opened the door to you. It was not that you consciously longed to possess all these women, but your impulse towards the sex unconsciously made your eyes melting and warm whenever they rested on a woman. At thirteen, I had no thought of this; and I felt as if I had been bathed in fire. I believed that the tenderness was for me, for me only; and in this one instant the woman was awakened in the half-grown girl, the woman who was to be yours for all future time.

“Who was that?” asked my friend. At first, I could not answer. I found it impossible to utter your name. It had suddenly become sacred to me, had become my secret. “Oh, it’s just someone who lives in the house,” I said awkwardly. “Then why did you blush so fiery red when he looked at you?” inquired my school fellow with the malice of an inquisitive child. I felt that she was making fun of me, and was reaching out towards my secret, and this coloured my cheeks more than ever. I was deliberately rude to her: “You silly idiot,” I said angrily—I should have liked to throttle her. She laughed mockingly, until the tears came into my eyes from impotent rage. I left her at the door and ran upstairs.

I have loved you ever since. I know full well that you are used to hearing women say that they love you. But I am sure that no one else has ever loved you so slavishly, with such doglike fidelity, with such devotion, as I did and do. Nothing can equal the unnoticed love of a child. It is hopeless and subservient; it is patient and passionate;it is something which the covetous love of a grown woman, the love that is unconsciously exacting can never be. None but lonely children can cherish such a passion. The others will squander their feelings in companionship, will dissipate them in confidential talks. They have heard and read much of love, and they know that it comes to all. They play with it like a toy; they flaunt it as a boy flaunts his first cigarette. But I had no confidant; I had been neither taught nor warned, I was inexperienced and unsuspecting. I rushed to meet my fate. Everything that stirred in me, all that happened to me, seemed to be centred upon you, upon my imaginings of you. My father had died long before. My mother could think of nothing but her troubles, of the difficulties of making ends meet upon her narrow pension, so that she had little in common with a growing girl. My school fellows, half-enlightened and half-corrupted, were uncongenial to me because of their frivolous outlook upon that which to me was a supreme passion. The upshot was that everything which surged up in me, all which in other girls of my age is usually scattered, was focused upon you. You became for me—what simile can do justice to my feelings? You became for me the whole of my life. Nothing existed for me except in so far as it related to you. Nothing had meaning for me unless it bore upon you in some way. You had changed everything for me. Hitherto I had been indifferent at school, and undistinguished. Now, of a sudden, I was the first. I read book upon book, far into the night, for I knew that you were a booklover. To my mother’s astonishment, I began, almost stubbornly, to practise the piano, for I fancied that you were fond of music. I stitched and mended my clothes, to make them neat for your eyes. It was a torment to me that there was a square patch in my old school-apron (cut down from one of my mother’s overalls). I was afraid you might notice it and would despise me, so I used to cover the patch with my satchel when I was on the staircase. I was terrified lest you should catch sight of it. What a fool I was! You hardly ever looked at me again.

Yet my days were spent in waiting for you and watching you. There was a judas in our front door, and through this a glimpse of your door could be had. Don’t laugh at me, dear. Even now, I am not ashamed of the hours I spent at this spy-hole. The hall was icy cold, and I was afraid of exciting my mother’s suspicions. But there I would watch through the long afternoons, during those months and years, book in hand, tense as a violin string, and vibrating at the touch of your nearness. I was ever near you, and ever tense; but you were no more aware of it than you were aware of the tension of the main spring of the watch in your pocket, faithfully recording the hours for you, accompanying your footsteps with its unheard ticking and vouchsafed only a hasty glance for one second among millions. I knew all about you, your habits, the neckties you wore; I knew each one of your suits. Soon I was familiar with your regular visitors, and had my likes and dislikes among them. From my thirteenth to my sixteenth year, my every hour was yours. What follies did I not commit? I kissed the door-handle you had touched; I picked up a cigarette-end you had thrown away, and it was sacred to me because your lips had pressed it. A hundred times, in the evening, on one pretext or another, I ran out into the street in order to see in which room your light was burning, that I might be more fully conscious of your invisible presence. During the weeks when you were away (my heart always seemed to stop beating when I saw John carry your portmanteau downstairs), life was devoid of meaning. Out of sorts, bored to death, and in an ill-humour, I wandered about not knowing what to do, and had to take precautions lest my tear-dimmed eyes should betray my despair to my mother.

I know that what I am writing here is a record of grotesque absurdities, of a girl’s extravagant fantasies. I ought to be ashamed of them; but I am not ashamed, for never was my love purer and more passionate than at this time. I could spend hours, days, in telling you how I lived with you though you hardly knew me by sight. Of course you hardly knew me, for if I met you on the stairs and could not avoid the encounter, I would hasten by with lowered head, afraid of your burning glance, hasten like one who is jumping into the water to avoid being singed. For hours, days, I could tell you of those years you have long since forgotten; could unroll all the calendar of your life: but I will not weary you with details. Only one more thing I should like to tell you dating from this time, the most splendid experience of my childhood. You must not laugh at it, for, trifle though you may deem it, to me it was of infinite significance.

It must have been a Sunday. You were away, and your man was dragging back the heavy rugs, which he had been beating, through the open door of the flat. They were rather too much for his strength, and I summoned up courage to ask whether he would let me help him. He was surprised, but did not refuse. Can I ever make you understand the awe, the pious veneration, with which I set foot in your dwelling, with which I saw your world—the writing-table at which you were accustomed to sit (there were some flowers on it in a blue crystal vase), the pictures, the books? I had no more than a stolen glance, though the good John would no doubt have let me see more had I ventured to ask him. But it was enough for me to absorb the atmosphere, and to provide fresh nourishment for my endless dreams of you in waking and sleeping.

This swift minute was the happiest of my childhood. I wanted to tell you of it, so that you who do not know me might at length begin to understand how my life hung upon yours. I wanted to tell you of that minute, and also of the dreadful hour which so soon followed. As I have explained, my thoughts of you had made me oblivious to all else. I paid no attention to my mother’s doings, or to those of any of our visitors. I failed to notice that an elderly gentleman, an Innsbruck merchant, a distant family connection of my mother, came often and stayed for a long time. I was glad that he took mother to the theatre sometimes, for this left me alone, undisturbed in my thoughts of you, undisturbed in the watching which was my chief, my only pleasure. But one day my mother summoned me with a certain formality, saying that she had something serious to talk to me about. I turned pale, and felt my heart throb. Did she suspect anything? Had I betrayed myself in some way? My first thought was of you, of my secret, of that which linked me with life. But my mother was herself embarrassed. It had never been her way to kiss me. Now she kissed me affectionately more than once, drew me to her on the sofa, and began hesitatingly and rather shamefacedly to tell me that her relative, who was a widower, had made her a proposal of marriage, and that, mainly for my sake, she had decided to accept. I palpitated with anxiety, having only one thought, that of you. “We shall stay here, shan’t we?” I stammered out. “No, we are going to Innsbruck, where Ferdinand has a fine villa.” I heard no more. Everything seemed to turn black before my eyes. I learned afterwards that I had fainted. I clasped my hands convulsively, and fell like a lump of lead. I cannot tell you all that happened in the next few days; how I, a powerless child, vainly revolted against the mighty elders. Even now, as I think of it, my hand shakes so that I can scarcely write. I could not disclose the real secret, and therefore my opposition seemed ill-tempered obstinacy. No one told me anything more. All the arrangements were made behind my back. The hours when I was at school were turned to account. Each time came home some new article had been removed or sold. My life seemed falling to pieces; and at last one day, when I returned to dinner, the furniture removers had cleared the flat. In the empty rooms there were some packed trunks, and two camp-beds for Mother and myself. We were to sleep there one night more, and were then to go to Innsbruck.

On this last day I suddenly made up my mind that I could not live without being near you. You were all the world to me. It is difficult to say what I was thinking of and whether in this hour of despair I was able to think at all. My mother was out of the house. I stood up, just as I was, in my school dress, and went over to your door. Yet I can hardly say that I went. With stiff limbs and trembling joints, I seemed to be drawn towards your door as by a magnet. It was in my mind to throw myself at your feet, and to beg you to keep me as a maid, as a slave. I cannot help feeling afraid that you will laugh at this infatuation of a girl of fifteen. But you would not laugh if you could realize how I stood there on the chilly landing, rigid with apprehension, and yet drawn onward by an irresistible force; how my arm seemed to lift itself in spite of me. The struggle appeared to last for endless, terrible seconds;and then I rang the bell. The shrill noise still sounds in my ears. It was followed by a silence in which my heart well-nigh stopped beating, and my blood stagnated, while I listened for your coming.

But you did not come. No one came. You must have been out that afternoon, and John must have been away too. With the dead note of the bell still sounding in my ears, I stole back into our empty dwelling, and threw myself exhausted upon a rug, tired out by these few paces as if I had been wading through deep snow for hours. Yet beneath this exhaustion there still glowed the determination to see you, to speak to you, before they carried me away. I can assure you that there were no sensual longings in my mind; I was still ignorant, just because I never thought of anything but you. All I wanted was to see you once more, to cling to you. Throughout that dreadful night I waited for you. Directly my mother had gone to sleep, I crept into the hall to listen for your return. It was a bitterly cold night in January. I was tired, my limbs ached, and there was no longer a chair on which I could sit; so I lay upon the floor, scourged by the draught that came under the door. In my thin dress I lay there, without any covering. I did not want to be warm, lest I should fall asleep and miss your footstep. Cramps seized me, so cold was it in the horrible darkness; again and again I had to stand up. But I waited, waited, waited for you, as for my fate.

At length (it must have been two or three in the morning) I heard the house-door open, and footsteps on the stair. The sense of cold vanished, and a rush of heat passed over me. I softly opened the door, meaning to run out, to throw myself at your feet....I cannot tell what I should have done in my frenzy. The steps drew nearer. A candle flickered. Tremblingly I held the door-handle. Was it you coming up the stairs?

Yes, it was you, beloved; but you were not alone. I heard a gentle laugh, the rustle of silk, and your voice, speaking in low tones. There was a woman with you....

I cannot tell how I lived through the rest of the night. At eight next morning, they took me with them to Innsbruck. I had no strength left to resist.

My boy died last night. I shall be alone once more, if I really have to go on living. To-morrow, strange men will come, black-clad and uncouth, bringing with them a coffin for the body of my only child. Perhaps friends will come as well, with wreaths—but what is the flowers on a coffin? They will offer consolation in one phrase or another. Words, words, words! What can words help? All I know is that I shall be alone again. There is nothing more terrible than to be alone among. human beings. That is what I came to realize during those interminable two years in Innsbruck, from my sixteenth to my eighteenth year, when I lived with people as a prisoner and an outcast. My stepfather, a quiet, taciturn man, was kind to me. My mother as if eager to atone for an unwitting injustice, seemed ready to meet all my wishes. Those of my own age would have been glad to befriend me. But I repelled their advances with angry defiance. I did not wish to be happy, I did not wish to live content away from you; so I buried myself in a gloomy world of self-torment and solitude. I would not wear the new and gay dresses they bought for me. I refused to go to concerts or to the theatre, and I would not take part in cheerful excursions. I rarely left the house. Can you believe me when I tell you that I hardly got to know a dozen streets in this little town where I lived for two years? Mourning was my joy; I renounced society and every pleasure, and was intoxicated with delight at the mortification I thus super added to the lack of seeing you. Moreover, I would let nothing divert me from my passionate longing to live only for you. Sitting alone at home, hour after hour and day after day, I did nothing but think of you, turning over in my mind unceasingly my hundred petty memories of you, renewing every movement and every time of waiting, rehearsing these episodes in the theatre of my mind. The countless repetitions of the years of my childhood from the day in which you came into my life have so branded the details on my memory that I can recall every minute of those long-passed years as if they were yesterday.

Thus my life was still entirely centred in you. I bought all your books. If your name was mentioned in the newspaper the day was a red-letter day. Will you believe me when I tell you that I have read your books so often that I know them by heart? Were anyone to wake me in the night and quote a detached sentence, I could continue the passage unfalteringly even to-day, after thirteen years. Your every word was Holy Writ to me. The world existed for me only in relationship to you. In the Viennese newspapers I read the reports of concerts and first nights, wondering which would interest you most. When evening came, I accompanied you in imagination, saying to myself: “Now he is entering the hall; now he is taking his seat.” Such were my fancies a thousand times, simply because I had once seen you at a concert.

Why should I recount these things? Why recount the tragic hopelessness of a forsaken child? Why tell it to you, who have never dreamed of my admiration or of my sorrow? But was I still a child? I was seventeen; I was eighteen; young fellows would turn to look after me in the street, but they only made me angry. To love anyone but you, even to play with the thought of loving anyone but you, would have been so utterly impossible to me, that the mere tender of affection on the part of another man seemed to me a crime. My passion for you remained just as intense, but it changed in character as my body grew and my senses awakened, becoming more ardent, more physical, more unmistakably the love of a grown woman. What had been hidden from the thoughts of the uninstructed child, of the girl who had rung your doorbell, was now my only longing. I wanted to give myself to you.

My associates believed me to be shy and timid. But I had an absolute fixity of purpose. My whole being was directed towards one end—back to Vienna, back to you. I fought successfully to get my own way, unreasonable, incomprehensible though it seemed to others. My step father was well-to-do, and looked upon me as his daughter. I insisted, however, that I would earn my own living, and at length got him to agree to my returning to Vienna as employee in a dressmaking establishment belonging to a relative of his.

Need I tell you whither my steps first led me that fog autumn evening when, at last, at last, I found myself back in Vienna? I left my trunk in the cloak-room, and hurried to a tram. How slowly it moved! Every stop was a renewed vexation to me. In the end, I reached the house. My heart leapt when I saw a light in your window. The town, which had seemed so alien, so dreary, grew suddenly alive for me. I myself lived once more, now that I was near you, you who were my unending dream. When nothing but the thin, shining pane of glass was between you and my uplifted eyes, I could ignore the fact that in reality I was as far from your mind as if I had been separated by mountains and valleys and rivers. Enough that I could go on looking at your window. There was a light in it; that was your dwelling; you were there; that was my world. For two years I had dreamed of this hour, and now it had come. Throughout that warm and cloudy evening I stood in front of your windows, until the light was extinguished. Not until then did I seek my own quarters.

Evening after evening I returned to the same spot.

Up to six o’clock I was at work. The work was hard, and yet I liked it, for the turmoil of the show-room masked the turmoil in my heart. The instant the shutters were rolled down, I flew to the beloved spot. To see you once more, to meet you just once, was all I wanted; simply from a distance to devour your face with my eyes. At length, after a week, I did meet you, and then the meeting took me by surprise. I was watching your window, when you came across the street. In an instant, I was a child once more, the girl of thirteen. My cheeks flushed. Although I was longing to meet your eyes, I hung my head and hurried past you as if someone had been in pursuit. Afterwards I was ashamed of having fled like a schoolgirl, for now I knew what I really wanted. I wanted to meet you; I wanted you to recognize me after all these weary years, to notice me, to love me.

For a long time you failed to notice me, although I took up my post outside your house every night, even when it was snowing, or when the keen wind of the Viennese winter was blowing. Sometimes I waited for hours in vain. Often, in the end, you would leave the house in the company of friends. Twice I saw you with a woman, and the fact that I was now awakened, that there was something new and different in my feeling towards you, was disclosed by the sudden heart-pang when I saw a strange woman walking confidently with you arm-in-arm. It was no surprise to me, for I had known since childhood how many such visitors came to your house; but now the sight aroused in me a definite bodily pain. I had a mingled feeling of enmity and desire when I witnessed this open manifestation of fleshly intimacy with another woman. For a day, animated by the youthful pride from which, perhaps, I am not yet free, I abstained from my usual visit; but how horrible was this empty evening of defiance and renunciation! The next night I was standing, as usual, in all humility, in front of your window; waiting, as I have ever waited, in front of your closed life.

At length came the hour when you noticed me. I marked your coming from a distance, and collected all my forces to prevent myself shrinking out of your path. As chance would have it, a loaded dray filled the street, so that you had to pass quite close to me. Involuntarily your eyes encountered my figure, and immediately, though you had hardly noticed the attentiveness in gaze, there came into your face that expression with which you were wont to look at women. The memory of it darted through me like an electric shock—that caressive and alluring glance, at once enfolding and disclothing, with which, years before, you had awakened the girl to become the woman and the lover. For a moment or two your eyes thus rested on me, for a space during which I could not turn my own eyes away, and then you had passed. My heart was beating so furiously that I had to slacken my pace; and when, moved by irresistible curiosity, I turned to look back, I saw that you were standing and watching me. The inquisitive interest of your expression convinced me that you had not recognized me. You did not recognize me, either then or later. How can I describe my disappointment? This was the first of such disappointments: the first time I had to endure what has always been my fate; that you have never recognized me. I must die, unrecognized. Ah, how can I make you understand my disappointment? During the years at Innsbruck I had never ceased to think of you. Our next meeting in Vienna was always in my thoughts. My fancies varied with my mood, ranging from the wildest possibilities to the most delightful. Every conceivable variation had passed through my mind. In gloomy moments it had seemed to me that you would repulse me, would despise me, for being of no account, for being plain, or importunate. I had had a vision of every possible form of disfavour, coldness, or indifference. But never, in the extremity of depression, in the utmost realization of my own insignificance, had I conceived this most abhorrent of possibilities—that you had never become aware of my existence. I understand, now (you have taught me!) that a girl’s or a woman’s face must be for a man something extraordinarily mutable. It is usually nothing more than the reflection of moods which pass as swiftly as an image vanishes from a mirror. A man can readily forget a woman’s face, because age modifies its lights and shades, and because at different times the dress gives it so different a setting. Resignation comes to a woman as her knowledge grows. But I, who was still a girl, was unable to understand your forgetfulness. My whole mind had been full of you ever since I had first known you, and this had produced in me the illusion that you must have often thought of me and waited for me. How could I have borne to go on living had I realized that I was nothing to you, that I had no place in your memory? Your glance that evening, showing me as it did that on your side there was not even : gossamer thread connecting your life with mine, meant for me a first plunge into reality, conveyed to me the first intimation of my destiny.

You did not recognize me. Two days later, when our paths again crossed, and you looked at me with an approach to intimacy, it was not in recognition of the girl who had loved you so long and whom you had awakened to womanhood; it was simply that you knew the face of the pretty lass of eighteen whom you had encountered at the same spot two evenings before. Your expression was one of friendly surprise, and a smile fluttered about your lips. You passed me as before, and as before you promptly slackened your pace. I trembled, I exulted, I longed for you to speak to me. I felt that for the first time I had become alive for you; I, too, walked slowly, and did not attempt to evade you. Suddenly, I heard your step behind me. Without turning round, I knew that I was about to hear your beloved voice directly addressing me. I was almost paralysed by the expectation, and my heart beat so violently that I thought I should have to stand still. You were at my side. You greeted me cordially, as if we were old acquaintances—though you did not really know me, though you have never known anything about my life. So simply charming was your manner that 1 was able to answer you without hesitation. We walked along the street and you asked me whether we could not have supper together. I agreed. What was there I could have refused you?

We supped in a little restaurant. You will not remember where it was. To you it will be one of many such. For what was I? One among hundreds; one adventure, one link in an endless chain. What happened that evening to keep me in your memory? I said very little, for I was so intensely happy to have you near me and to hear you speak to me. I did not wish to waste a moment upon questions or foolish words. I shall never cease to be thankful to you for that hour, for the way in which you justified my ardent admiration. I shall never forget the gentle tact you displayed. There was no undue eagerness, no hasty offer of a caress. Yet from the first moment you displayed so much friendly confidence, that you would have won me even if my whole being had not long ere this been yours. Can I make you understand how much it meant to me that my five years of expectation were so perfectly fulfilled?

The hour grew late, and we came away from the restaurant. At the door you asked me whether I was in any hurry, or still had time to spare. How could I hide from you that I was yours? I said I had plenty of time. With a momentary hesitation, you asked me whether I would not come to your rooms for a talk. “I shall be delighted,” I answered with alacrity, thus giving frank expression to my feelings. I could not fail to notice that my ready assent surprised you. I am not sure whether your feeling was one of vexation or pleasure, but it was obvious to me that you were surprised. To-day, of course, I understand your astonishment. I know now that it is usual for a woman, even though she may ardently desire to herself to a man, to feign reluctance, to simulate alarm in indignation. She must be brought to consent by urgent pleadings, by lies, adjurations, and promises. I know that only professional prostitutes are accustomed to answer such an invitation with a perfectly frank assent-prostitutes, or simple-minded, immature girls. How could you know that, in my case, the frank assent was but the voicing of an eternity of desire, the uprush of yearnings that had endured for a thousand days and more?

In any case, my manner aroused your attention; I had become interesting to you. As we were walking along together, I felt that during our conversation you were trying to sample me in some way. Your perceptions, your assured touch in the whole gamut of human emotions,made you realize instantly that there was something unusual here;that this pretty, complaisant girl carried a secret about with her. Your curiosity had been awakened, and your discreet questions showed that you were trying to pluck the heart out of my mystery. But my replies were evasive. I would rather seem a fool than disclose my secret to you.

We went up to your flat. Forgive me, beloved, for saying that you cannot possibly understand all that it meant to me to go up those stairs with you—how I was mad, tortured, almost suffocated with happiness. Even now I can hardly think of it without tears, but I have no tears left. Everything in that house had been steeped in my passion; everything was a symbol of my childhood and its longing. There was the door behind which a thousand times I had awaited your coming; the stairs on which I had heard your footsteps, and where I had first seen you; the judas through which I had watched your comings and goings; the doormat on which I had once knelt; the sound of a key in the lock, which had always been a signal to me. My childhood and its passions were nested within these few yards of space. Here was my whole life, and it surged around me like a great storm, for all was being fulfilled, and I was going with you, I with you, into your, into our house. Think (the way I am phrasing it sounds trivial, but I know no better words) that up to your door was the world of reality, the dull everyday world which had been that of all my previous life. At this door began the magic world of my childish imaginings. Aladdin’s realm. Think how a thousand times, I had had my burning eyes fixed upon this door through which I was now passing, my head in a whirl, and you will have an inkling—no more—of all that this tremendous minute meant to me.

I stayed with you that night. You did not dream that before you no man had ever touched or seen my body. How could you fancy it, when I made no resistance, and when I suppressed every trace of shame, fearing lest I might betray the secret of my love? That would certainly have alarmed you; you care only for what comes and goes easily, for that which is light of touch, is imponderable. You dread being involved in anyone else’s destiny. You like to give yourself freely to all the world but not to make any sacrifices. When I tell you that I gave myself to you as a maiden, do not misunderstand me. I am not making any charge against you. You did not entice me, deceive me, seduce me. I threw myself into your arms; went out to meet my fate. I have nothing but thankfulness towards you for the blessedness of that night. When I opened my eyes in the darkness and you were beside me, I felt that I must be in heaven, and I was amazed that the stars were not shining on me. Never, beloved, have I repented giving myself to you that night. When you were sleeping beside me, when I listened to your breathing, touched your body, and felt myself so near you, I shed tears for very happiness.

I went away early in the morning. I had to go to my work and I wanted to leave before your servant came. When I was ready to go, you put your arm round me and looked at me for a very long time. Was some obscure memory stirring in your mind; or was it simply that my radiant happiness made me seem beautiful to you? You kissed me on the lips, and I moved to go. You asked me: “Would you not like to take a few flowers with you?” There were four white roses in the blue crystal vase on the writing-table (I knew it of old from that stolen glance of childhood), and you gave them to me. For days they were mine to kiss.

We had arranged to meet on a second evening. Again it was full of wonder and delight. You gave me a third night. Then you said that you were called away from Vienna for a time—oh, how I had always hated those journeys of yours!—and promised that I should hear from you as soon as you came back. I would only give you a poste-restante address, and did not tell you my real name. I guarded my secret. Once more you gave me roses at parting—at parting.

Day after day for two months I asked myself...no, I will not describe the anguish of my expectation and despair. I make no complaint. I love you just as you are, ardent and forgetful, generous and unfaithful. I love you just as you have always been. You were back long before the two months were up. The light in your windows showed me that, but you did not write to me. In my last hours I have not a line in your handwriting, not a line from you to whom my life was given. I waited, waited despairingly. You did not call me to you, did not write a word, not a word....

My boy who died yesterday was yours too. He was your son, the child of one of those three nights. I was yours, and yours only from that time until the hour of his birth. I felt myself sanctified by your touch, and it would not have been possible for me then to accept any other man’s caresses. He was our boy, dear; the child of my fully conscious love and of your careless, spendthrift, almost unwitting tenderness. Our child, our son, our only child. Perhaps you will be startled, perhaps merely surprised. You will wonder why I never told you of this boy; and why, having kept silence throughout the long years, I only tell you of him now, when he lies in his last sleep, about to leave me for all time—never, never to return. How could I have told you? I was a stranger, a girl who had shown herself only too eager to spend those three nights with you. Never would you have believed that I, the nameless partner in a chance encounter, had been faithful to you, the unfaithful. You would never without misgivings, have accepted the boy as your own. Even if, to all appearance, you had trusted my word, you would still have cherished the secret suspicion that I had seized an opportunity of fathering upon you, a man of means, the child of another lover. You would have been suspicious. There would always have been a shadow of mistrust between you and me. I could not have borne it. Besides, I know you. Perhaps I know you better than you know yourself. You love to be care-free, light of heart, perfectly at ease; and that is what you understand by love. It would have been repugnant to you to find yourself suddenly in the position of father; to be made responsible, all at once, for a child’s destiny. The breath of freedom is the breath of life to you, and you would have felt me to be a tie. Inwardly, even in defiance of your conscious will, you would have hated me as an embodied claim. Perhaps only now and again, for an hour or for a fleeting minute, should I have seemed a burden to you, should I have been hated by you. But it was my pride that I should never be a trouble or a care to you all my life long. I would rather take the whole burden on myself than be a burden to you; I wanted to be the one among all the women you had intimately known of whom you would never think except with love and thankfulness. In actual fact, you never thought of me at all. You forgot me.

I am not accusing you. Believe me, I am not coming. You must forgive me if for a moment, now and again, it seems as if my pen had been dipped in gall. You must forgive me; for my boy, our boy, lies dead there beneath the flickering candles. I have clenched my fists against God, and have called him a murderer, for I have been almost beside myself with grief. Forgive me for complaining. I know that you are kindhearted, and always ready to help. You will help the merest stranger at a word. But your kindliness is peculiar. It is unbounded. Anyone may have of yours as much as he can grasp with both hands. And yet, I must own, your kindliness works sluggishly. You need to be asked. You help those who call for help; you help from shame, from weakness, and not from sheer joy in helping. Let me tell you openly that those who are in affliction and torment are not dearer to you than your brothers in happiness. Now, it is hard, very hard, to ask anything of such as you, even of the kindest among you. Once, when I was still a child, I watched through the judas in our door how you gave something to a beggar who had rung your bell. You gave quickly and freely, almost before he spoke. But there was a certain nervousness and haste in your manner, as if your chief concern were to be speedily rid of him; you seemed to be afraid to meet his eye. I have never forgotten this uneasy and timid way of giving help, this shunning of a word of thanks. That is why I never turned to you in my difficulty. Oh, I know that you would have given me all the help I needed, in spite of a doubt that my child was yours. You would have offered me comfort, and have given me money, an ample supply of money; but always with a masked impatience, a secret desire to shake off trouble. I even believe that you would have advised me to rid myself of the coming child. This was what I dreaded above all, for I knew that I should do whatever you wanted. But the child was all in all to me. It was yours; it was you reborn—not the happy and carefree you, whom I could never hope to keep; but you, given to me for my very own, flesh of my flesh, intimately intertwined with my own life. At length I held you fast; I could feel your life-blood flowing through my veins; I could nourish you, caress you, kiss you, as often as my soul yearned. That was why I was so happy when I knew that I was with child by you and that is why I kept the secret from you. Hence forward you could not escape me; you were mine.

But you must not suppose that the months of waiting passed so happily as I had dreamed in my first transports. They were full of sorrow and care, full of loathing for the baseness of mankind. Things went hard with me. I could not stay at work during the later months, for my stepfather’s relatives would have noticed my condition, and would have sent the news home. Nor would I ask my mother for money; so until my time came I managed to live by the sale of some trinkets. A week before my confinement, the few crown-pieces that remained to me were stolen by my laundress, so I had to go to the maternity hospital. The child, your son, was born there, in that asylum of wretchedness, among the very poor, the outcast, and the abandoned. It was a deadly place. Everything was strange, was alien. We were all alien to one another, as we lay there in our loneliness, filled with mutual hatred, thrust together only by our kinship of poverty and distress into this crowded ward, reeking of chloroform and blood, filled with cries and moaning. A patient in these wards loses all individuality, except such as remains in the name at the head of the clinical record. What lies in the bed is merely a piece of quivering flesh, an object of study....

I ask your forgiveness for speaking of these things. I shall never speak of them again. For eleven years I have kept silence, and shall soon be dumb for evermore. Once, at least, I had to cry aloud, to let you know how dearly bought was this child, this boy who was my delight, and who now lies dead. I had forgotten those dreadful hours, forgotten them in his smiles and his voice, forgotten them in my happiness. Now, when he is dead, the torment has come to life again; and I had, this once, to give it utterance. But I do not accuse you; only God, only God who is the author of such purposeless affliction. Never have I cherished an angry thought of you. Not even in the utmost agony of giving birth did I feel any resentment against you; never did I repent the nights when I enjoyed your love; never did I cease to love you or to bless the hour when you came into my life. Were it necessary for me, fully aware of what was coming, to relive that time in hell, I would do it gladly, not once, but many times.

Our boy died yesterday, and you never knew him. His bright little personality has never come into the most fugitive contact with you, and your eyes have never rested on him. For a long time after our son was born, I kept myself hidden from you. My longing for you had become less overpowering. Indeed, I believe I loved you less passionately. Certainly, my love for you did not hurt so much, now that I had the boy. I did not wish to divide myself between you and him, and so I did not give myself to you, who were happy and independent of me, but to the boy who needed me, whom I had to nourish, whom I could kiss and fondle. I seemed to have been healed of my restless yearning for you. The doom seemed to have been lifted from me by the birth of this other you, who was truly my own. Rarely, now, did my feelings reach out towards you in your dwelling. One thing only—on your birthday I have always sent you a bunch of white roses, like the roses you gay after our first night of love. Has it ever occurred to you, during these ten or eleven years, to ask yourself who sent them? Have you ever recalled having given such roses to a girl? I do not know, and never shall know. For me it was enough to send them to you out of the darkness; enough, once a year, to revive my own memory of that hour.

You never knew our boy. I blame myself to-day for having hidden him from you, for you would have loved him. You have never seen him smile when he first opened his eyes after sleep, his dark eyes that were your eyes, the eyes with which he looked merrily forth at me and the world. He was so bright, so lovable. All your lightheartedness and your mobile imagination were his likewise—in the form in which these qualities can show themselves in a child. He would spend entranced hours playing with things as you play with life; and then, grown serious, would sit long over his books. He was you, reborn. The mingling of sport and earnest, which is so characteristic of you, was becoming plain in him; and the more he resembled you, the more I loved him. He was good at his lessons, so that he could chatter French like a magpie. His exercise books were the tidiest in the class. And what a fine, upstanding little man he was! When I took him to the seaside in the summer, at Grado, women used to stop and stroke his fair hair. At Semmering, when he was tobogganing, people would turn round to gaze after him. He was so handsome, so gentle, so appealing. Last year, when he went to college as a boarder, he began to wear the collegiates’ uniform of an eighteenth-century page, with a little dagger stuck in his belt—now he lies here in his shift, with pallid lips and crossed hands.

You will wonder how I could manage to give the boy so costly an upbringing, how it was possible for me to provide for him an entry into this bright and cheerful life of the well-to-do. Dear one, I am speaking to you from the darkness. Unashamed, I will tell you. Do not shrink from me. I sold myself. I did not become a streetwalker, a common prostitute, but I sold myself. My friends, my lovers, were wealthy men. At first I sought them out, but soon they sought me, for I was (did you ever notice it?) a beautiful woman. Everyone to whom I gave myself was devoted to me. They all became my grateful admirers. They all loved me—except you, except you whom I loved.

Will you despise me now that I have told you what I did? I am sure you will not. I know you will understand everything, will understand that what I did was done only for you, for your other self, for your boy. In the lying-in hospital I had tasted the full horror of poverty. I knew that, in the world of the poor, those who are downtrodden are always the victims. I could not bear to think that your son, your lovely boy, was to grow up in that abyss, amid the corruptions of the street, in the poisoned air of a slum. His delicate lips must not learn the speech of the gutter; his fine, white skin must not be chafed by the harsh and sordid underclothing of the poor. Your son must have the best of everything, all the wealth and all the lightheartedness of the world. He must follow your footsteps through life, must dwell in the sphere in which you had lived.

That is why I sold myself. It was no sacrifice to me, for what are conventionally termed “Honour” and “Disgrace” were unmeaning words to me. You were the only one to whom my body could belong, and you did not love me, so what did it matter what I did with that body? My companions’ caresses, even their most ardent passion, never sounded my depths, although many of them were persons I could not but respect, and although the thought of my own fate made me sympathize with them in their unrequited love. All these men were kind to me; they all petted and spoiled me; they all paid me every deference.One of them, a widower, an elderly man of title, used his utmost influence until he secured your boy’s nomination to the college. This man loved me like a daughter. Three or four times he urged me to marry him. I could have been a countess to-day, mistress of a lovely castle m Tyrol. I could have been free from care, for the boy would have had a most affectionate father and I should have had a sedate, distinguished, and kind-hearted husband. But I persisted in my refusal though I knew it gave him pain. It may have been foolish of me. Had I yielded, I should have been living a safe and retired life somewhere, and my child would still have been with me. Why should I hide from you the reason for my refusal? I did not want to bind myself. I wanted to remain free—for you. In my innermost self in the unconscious, I continued to dream the dream of my childhood. Some day, perhaps you would call me to your side, were it only for an hour. For the possibility of this one hour I rejected everything else, simply that I might be free to answer your call. Since my first awakening to womanhood, what had my life been but waiting, a waiting upon your will?

In the end, the expected hour came. And still you never knew that it had come! When it came, you did not recognize me. You have never recognized me, never, never. I met you often enough, in theatres, at concerts, in the Prater, and elsewhere. Always my heart leapt but always you passed me by, unheeding. In outward appearance I had become a different person. The timid girl was a woman now; beautiful, it was said; decked out in fine clothes; surrounded by admirers. How could you recognize in me one whom you had known as a shy girl in the subdued light of your bedroom? Sometimes my companion would greet you, and you would acknowledge the greeting as you glanced at me. But your look was always that of a courteous stranger, a look of deference, but not of recognition—distant, hopelessly distant. Once, I remember, this non-recognition, familiar as it had become, was a torture to me. I was in a box at the opera with a friend, and you were in the next box. The lights were lowered when the Overture began. I could no longer see your face, but I could feel your breathing quite close to me, just as when I was with you in your room; and on the velvet-covered partition between the boxes your slender hand was resting. I was filled with an infinite longing to bend down and kiss this hand, whose loving touch I had once known. Amid the turmoil of sound from the orchestra, the craving grew even more intense. I had to hold myself in convulsively, to keep my lips away from your dear hand. At the end of the first act, I told my friend I wanted to leave. It was intolerable to me to have you sitting there beside me in the darkness, so near, and so estranged.

But the hour came once more, only once more. It was all but a year ago, on the day after your birthday. My thoughts had been dwelling on you more than ever, for I used to keep your birthday as a festival. Early in the morning I had gone to buy the white roses which I sent you every year in commemoration of an hour you had forgotten. In the afternoon I took my boy for a drive and we had tea together. In the evening we went to the theatre. I wanted him to look upon this day as a sort of mystical anniversary of his youth, though he could not know the reason. The next day I spent with my intimate of that epoch, a young and wealthy manufacturer of Brunn, with whom I had been living for two years. He was passionately fond of me, and he, too, wanted me to marry him. I refused, for no reason he could understand, although he loaded me and the child with presents, and was lovable enough in his rather stupid and slavish devotion. We went together to a concert, where we met a lively company. We all had supper at a restaurant in the Ringstrasse. Amid talk and laughter, I proposed that we should move on to a dancing-hall. In general, such places, where the cheerfulness is always an expression of partial intoxication, are repulsive to me, and I would seldom go to them. But on this occasion some elemental force seemed at work in me, leading to make the proposal, which was hailed with acclamation by the others. I was animated by an inexplicable longing, as if some extraordinary experience were awaiting me. As usual, everyone was eager to accede to my whims. We went to the dancing hall, drank some champagne, and I had a sudden access of almost frenzied cheerfulness such as I had never known. I drank one glass of wine after another, joined in the chorus of a suggestive song, and was in a mood to dance with glee. Then, all in a moment, I felt as if my heart had been seized by an icy or a burning hand. You were sitting with some friends at the next table, regarding me with an admiring and covetous glance, that glance which had always thrilled me beyond expression. For the first time in ten years you were looking at me again under the stress of all the unconscious passion in your nature. I trembled, and my hand shook so violently that I nearly let my wineglass fall. Fortunately my companions did not notice my condition, for their perceptions were confused by the noise of laughter and music.

Your look became continually more ardent, and touched my own senses to fire. I could not be sure whether you had at last recognized me, or whether your desires had been aroused by one whom you believed to be a stranger. My cheeks were flushed, and I talked at random. You could not help noticing the effect your glance had on me. You made an inconspicuous movement of the head, to suggest my coming into the ante-room for a moment. Then, having settled your bill, you took leave of your associates and left the table, after giving me a further sign that you intended to wait for me outside. I shook like one in the cold stage of a fever. I could no longer answer when spoken to, could no longer control the tumult of my blood. At this moment, as chance would have it, a couple of Negroes with clattering heels began a barbaric dance to the accompaniment of their own shrill cries. Everyone turned to look at them, and I seized my opportunity. Standing up, I told my friend that I would be back in a moment, and followed you.

You were waiting for me in the lobby, and your face lighted up when I came. With a smile on your lips, you hastened to meet me. It was plain that you did not recognize me, neither the child nor the girl of old days. Again, to you, I was a new acquaintance. “Have you really got an hour to spare for me?” you asked in a confident tone, which showed that you took me for one of the women whom anyone can buy for a night. “Yes,” I answered; the same tremulous but perfectly acquiescent“Yes” that you had heard from me in my girlhood, more than ten years earlier, in the darkling street. “Tell me when we can meet,” you said.“Whenever you like,” I replied, for I knew nothing of shame where you were concerned. You looked at me with a little surprise, with a surprise which had in it the same flavour of doubt mingled with curiosity which you had shown before when you were astonished at the readiness of my acceptance. “Now?” you inquired, after a moment’s hesitation. “Yes,” I replied, “let us go.”

I was about to fetch my wrap from the cloak-room, When I remembered that my Brunn friend had handed in our things together, and that he had the ticket. It was impossible to go back, and ask him for it, and it seemed to me even more impossible to renounce this hour with you to which I had been looking forward for years. My choice was instantly made. I gathered my shawl around and went forth into the misty night, regardless not only, of my cloak, but regardless, likewise, of the kind—hearted man with whom I had been living for years—regardless of the fact that in this public way, before his friends I was putting him into the ludicrous position of one whose mistress abandons him at the first nod of a stranger. Inwardly, I was well aware how basely and ungratefully I was behaving towards a good friend. I knew that my outrageous folly would alienate him from me for ever and that I was playing havoc with my life. But what was his friendship, what was my own life, to me when compared with the chance of again feeling your lips on mine of again listening to the tones of your voice. Now that all is over and done with I can tell you this, can let you know how I loved you. I believe that were you to summon me from my death-bed I should find strength to rise in answer to your call.

There was a taxi at the door, and we drove to your rooms. Once more I could listen to your voice, once more I felt the ecstasy of being near you, and was almost as intoxicated with joy and confusion as I had been so long before. I cannot describe it all to you, how what I had felt ten years earlier was now renewed as we went up the wellknown stairs together; how I lived simultaneously in the past and in the present, my whole being fused as it were with yours. In your rooms, little was changed. There were a few more pictures, a great many more books, one or two additions to your furniture—but the whole had the friendly look of an old acquaintance. On the writing-table was the vase with the roses—my roses, the ones I had sent you the day before as a memento of the woman whom you did not remember, whom you did not recognize, not even now when she was close to you, when you were holding her hand and your lips were pressed on hers. But it comforted me to see my flowers there, to know that you had cherished something that was an emanation from me, was the breath of my love for you.

You took me in your arms. Again I stayed with you for the whole of one glorious night. But even then you did not recognize me. While I thrilled to your caresses it was plain to me that your passion knew no difference between a loving mistress and a meretrix, that your spendthrift affections were wholly concentrated in their own expression. To me, the stranger picked up at a dancing-hall, you were at once affectionate and courteous. You would not treat me lightly, and yet you were full of an enthralling ardour. Dizzy with the old happiness, I was again aware of the two-sidedness of your nature, of that strange mingling of intellectual passion with sensual, which had already enslaved me to you in my childhood. In no other man have I ever known such complete surrender to the sweetness of the moment. No other has for the time being given himself so utterly as did you who, when the hour was past, were to relapse into an interminable and almost inhuman forgetfullness. But I, too, forgot myself. Who was I, lying in the darkness beside you? Was I the impassioned child of former days; was I the mother of your son; was I a stranger? Everything in this wonderful night was at one and the same time entrancingly familiar and entrancingly new. I prayed that the joy might last for ever.

But morning came. It was late when we rose, and you asked me to stay to breakfast. Over the tea, which an unseen hand had discreetly served in the dining-room, we talked quietly. As of old, you displayed a cordial frankness; and, as of old, there were no tactless questions, there was no curiosity about myself. You did not ask my name, nor where I lived. To you I was as before a casual adventure, a nameless woman, an ardent hour which leaves no trace when it is over. You told me that you were about to start on a long journey, that you were going to spend two or three months in northern Africa. The words broke in upon my happiness like a knell: “Past, past, past and forgotten!” I longed to throw myself at your feet, crying: “Take me with you, that you may at length come to know me, at length after all these years!” But I was timid, cowardly, slavish, weak. All I could say was: “What a pity!” You looked at me with a smile: “Are you really sorry?”

For a moment I was as if frenzied. I stood up and looked at you fixedly. Then I said: “The man I love has always gone on a journey.” I looked you straight in the eyes. “Now, now,” I thought, “Now he will recognize me!” You only smiled, and said consolingly: “One comes back after a time.” I answered: “Yes, one comes back, but one has forgotten by then.”

I must have spoken with strong feeling, for my tone moved you. You, too, rose, and looked at me wonderingly and tenderly. You put your hands on my shoulders:

“Good things are not forgotten, and I shall not forget you.” Your eyes studied me attentively, as if you wished to form an enduring image of me in your mind. When I felt this penetrating glance, this exploration of my whole being, I could not but fancy that the spell of your blindness would at last be broken. “He will recognize me! He will recognize me!”My soul trembled with expectation.

But you did not recognize me. No, you did not recognize me. Never had I been more of a stranger to you than I was at that moment, for had it been otherwise you could not possibly have done what you did a few minutes later. You had kissed me again, had kissed me passionately. My hair had been ruffled, and I had to tidy it once more. Standing at the glass, I saw in it—and as I saw, I was overcome with shame and horror—that you were surreptitiously slipping a couple of banknotes into my muff. I could hardly refrain from crying out; I could hardly refrain from slapping your face. You were paying me for the night I had spent with you, me who had loved you since childhood, me the mother of your son. To you I was only a prostitute picked up at a dancing hall. It was not enough that you should forget me; you had to pay me, and to debase me by doing so.

I hastily gathered up my belongings, that I might escape as quickly as possible; the pain was too great. I looked round for my hat. There it was, on the writing table, beside the vase with the white roses, my roses. I had an irresistible desire to make a last effort to awaken your memory. “Will you give me one of your white roses?”—“Of course,”you answered, lifting them all out of the vase. “But perhaps they were given you by a woman, a woman who loves you?”—“Maybe,” you replied, “I don’t know. They were a present, but I don’t know who sent them; that’s why I’m so fond of them.” I looked at you intently: “Perhaps they were sent you by a woman whom you have forgotten!”

You were surprised. I looked at you yet more intently. “Recognize me, only recognize me at last!” was the clamour of my eyes. But your smile, though cordial, had no recognition in it. You kissed me yet again, but you did not recognize me.

I hurried away, for my eyes were filling with tears, and I did not want you to see. In the entry, as I precipitated myself from the room, I almost cannoned into John, your servant. Embarrassed but zealous, he got out of my way, and opened the front door for me. Then, in this fugitive instant, as I looked at him through my tears, a light suddenly flooded the old man’s face. In this fugitive instant, I tell you, he recognized me, the man who had never seen me since my childhood. I was so grateful that I could have kneeled before him and kissed his hands. I tore from my muff the banknotes with which you had scourged me, and thrust them upon him. He glanced at me in alarm—for in this instant I think he understood more of me than you have understood in your whole life. Everyone, everyone, has been eager to spoil me;everyone has loaded me with kindness. But you, only you, forgot me. You, only you, never recognized me.

My boy, our boy, is dead. I have no one left to love; no one in the world, except you. But what can you be to me—you who have never, never recognized me, you who stepped across me as you might step across a stream, you who trod on me as you might tread on a stone, you who went on your way unheeding, while you left me to wait for all eternity? Once I fancied that I could hold you for my own; that I held you, the elusive, in the child. But he was your son! In the night, he cruelly slipped away from me on a journey; he has forgotten me, and will never return. I am alone once more, more utterly alone than ever. I have nothing, nothing from you. No child, no word, no line of writing, no place in your memory. If anyone were to mention my name in your presence, to you it would be the name of a stranger. Shall I not be glad to die, since I am dead to you? Glad to go away, since you have gone away from me?

Beloved, I am not blaming you. I do not wish to intrude my sorrows into your joyful life. Do not fear that I shall ever trouble you further. Bear with me for giving way to the longing to cry out my heart to you this once, in the bitter hour when the boy lies dead. Only this once I must talk to you. Then I shall slip back into obscurity, and be dumb towards you as I have ever been. You will not even hear my cry so long as I continue to live. Only when I am dead will this heritage come to you from one who has loved you more fondly than any other has loved you, from one whom you have never recognized, from one who has always been awaiting your summons and whom you have never summoned. Perhaps, perhaps when you receive this legacy you will call to me; and for the first time I shall be unfaithful to you, for I shall not hear you in the sleep of death. Neither picture nor token do I leave you, just as you left me nothing, for never will you recognize me now. That was my fate in life, and it shall be my fate in death likewise. I shall not summon you in my last hour; I shall go my way leaving you ignorant of my name and my appearance. Death will be easy to me, for you will not feel it from afar. I could not die if my death were going to give you pain.

I cannot write any more. My head is so heavy; my limbs ache; I am feverish. I must lie down. Perhaps all will soon be over. Perhaps, this once, fate will be kind to me, and I shall not have to see them take away my boy....I cannot write any more. Farewell, dear one, farewell. All my thanks go out to you. What happened was good in spite of everything. I shall be thankful to you till my last breath. I am so glad that I have told you all. Now, you will know, though you can never fully understand, how much I have loved you; and yet my love will never be a burden to you. It is my solace that I shall not fail you. Nothing will be changed in your bright and lovely life. Beloved, my death will not harm you. This comforts me.

But who, ah who, will now send you white roses on your birthday? The vase will be empty. No longer will come that breath, that aroma, from my life, which once a year was breathed into your room. I have one last request—the first, and the last. Do it for my sake. Always on your birthday—a day when one thinks of oneself—get some roses and put them in the vase. Do it just as others, once a year, have a Mass said for the beloved dead. I no longer believe in God, and therefore I do not want a Mass said for me. I believe in you alone. I love none but you. Only in you do I wish to go on living – just one day in the year, softly, quietly, as I have always lived near you. Please do this, my darling, please do it...My first request, and my last....Thanks, thanks...I love you, I love you....Farewell.....

The letter fell from his nerveless hands. He thought long and deeply. Yes, he had vague memories of a neighbour’s child, of a girl, of a woman in a dancing-hall—all was dim and confused, like a flickering and shapeless view of a stone in the bed of a swiftly running stream. Shadows chased one another across his mind, but would not fuse into a picture. There were stirrings of memory in the realm of feeling, and still he could not remember. It seemed to him that he must have dreamed of all these figures, must have dreamed often and vividly—and yet they had only been the phantoms of a dream. His eyes wandered to the blue vase on the writing-table. It was empty. For years it had not been empty on his birthday. He shuddered, feeling as if an invisible door had been suddenly opened, a door through which a chill breeze from another world was blowing into his sheltered room. An intimation of death came to him, and an intimation of deathless love. Something welled up within him; and the thought of the dead woman stirred in his mind, bodiless and passionate, like the sound of distant music.

MOONBEAM ALLEY

STORMY weather had delayed the ship, so that the evening was far advanced before she came to port on the French coast. Having missed the train which was to have carried me farther on my journey, I had a whole twenty-four hours on my hands. How could I best while away the time, marooned as I was in this unknown coast-town? There did not seem to be much doing. Melancholy strains of dance music issued from a dubious looking haunt—not particularly attractive, I thought. The alternative would be to spend the interlude in desultory converse with my fellow-passengers. In the dining-room of the third-rate hotel where we put up, the air was thick with the smell of burned fat and tobacco smoke. Besides, it was an ill-kept and dirty place, its filthiness rendered all the more intolerable since for many days now I had enjoyed the pure ocean breezes and felt the salt, sweet taste of sea-spume upon my lips. I decided to go for a stroll along the broad main street leading to a square where the local band was giving a concert. It was pleasant to allow oneself to be carried gently along by the stream of idlers who, having done their work for the day, were taking the air after a wash and brush-up followed by a cosy meal at a provincial fireside. After a while, however, the jostling of the crowd and its empty laughter vexed me sorely; I found it exasperating to be gaped at because I happened to be a stranger in their midst; the physical proximity of so many unknown human beings was nauseating in the extreme.

The voyage had been far from calm, and the movement of swelling waters was still in my veins. Under foot the earth seemed to be heaving and rolling, the whole street and the skies swayed like a see-saw. I felt giddy and in order to escape, I ducked my head and plunged down a side street without taking the trouble to decipher its name. This led me into an even narrower thoroughfare where the din of music and mob was muffled almost to extinction. One street opened out of another like the anastomoses of arteries and veins. They were less well lighted the farther I withdrew from the central square which was brightly illuminated with arc-lamps. Overhead the stars could be distinguished, now that my eyes were no longer dazzled by the glare. How dark the intervening spaces of heaven appeared as I gazed upward!

This must be “Sailor-town,” quite near the harbour for my nostrils were tickled with the stench of rotting fish and seaweed and tar, with the indescribable odour issuing from badly ventilated houses wherein the air remains stagnant until it is swept away by a health bringing gale. Such twilight as hung over these alleyways was healing to my mind. It was delightful to be alone. I slackened my pace, studied the narrow streets each of which was different from the others, being here coquettish or amorous, there wrapped in inviolable peace. All, however, were dark, and filled with the soft murmur of voices and music which arose from nowhere in particular, but from unseen springs deep within the houses. Doors and windows were tightly shut, and the only lights were red or yellow lanterns hanging from a porch at rare intervals.

I have a special predilection for such quarters in unknown towns, these foul market-places of the passions, filled with temptations for men who sail the seas and who turn in here for a night of pleasure, hoping to realize their dreams in one short hour on land. These places are obliged to tuck themselves away out of sight in the less “respectable”areas of the town, because they tell a plain tale which the snug and well-built houses of the elect hide behind a hundred veils. Tiny rooms are crowded with dancing couples; glaring placards lure into the picture-houses, square-faced lanterns twinkle in doorways and beckon unambiguously to the passerby. Drunken voices clamour from behind the red-curtained windows of drinking booths. Sailors grin at one another when they meet, their eyes are greedy with expectation, for here they may find women and gambling, drink and display, adventure that is sordid or worth the risk. But these allurements are discreetly housed behind drawn blinds. You have to go inside to find them out, and the mystery only serves to enhance the lure. Similar streets and alleys exist in Hamburg and Colombo and Havana and Liverpool, just as in these cities the broad avenues and boulevards where the wealthy forgather are likewise to be found, for the upper stratum of life and the lower bear a close resemblance everywhere in the matter of form. These disorderly streets are strange vestiges of an unregulated world of the senses, where impulses continue to discharge themselves brutally and without rein;they are a gloomy forest of the passions, a covert full of manifestations of our instinctive and animal existence; they stimulate by what they disclose, and allure by the suggestion of what they hide. They haunt our dreams.

A sensation of being trapped in this maze overwhelmed me. I had chanced to follow a couple of cuirassiers who, with swords clanking along the uneven pavement, were taking a stroll. Some women on the booze in a bar shouted coarse jokes as the pair sauntered by; shrieks of laughter, a finger knocking on the window, an oath from within—and then the men went on. Soon the ribald mirth grew so faint that I could barely catch the sound. Silence closed round me, a few windows were dimly lighted, the watery moon shone through the mist. I breathed my fill of the stillness, which was almost uncanny, seeing that behind it lurked a universe of mystery, sensuousness, and peril. The silence was a lie, for it covered the accumulated filth of a whole world. I stood listening, and peering into the void. All sense of the town, the street, its name, and even my own name vanished; I was cut adrift, my body in some miraculous way had been taken possession of by a stranger, I had no activity in view, no reason for being where I was, no relationship to my surroundings—and yet I was acutely conscious of the seething life that beset me on all sides; it flowed through my veins as if it were my own blood. Nothing that was happening was doing so on my account, though everything was germane to myself. An inexpressibly delightful, feeling that I was not a participator was accompanied by the conviction that I was in for an experience which would bore down into the deepest springs of my being—a feeling which, whenever it comes to me, suffuses me with a pleasure that emanates from communion with the unconscious.

As I stood thus expectant, listening into the void, a voice came to me from a distance, muffled by intervening walls, but unmistakably singing in German. A simple melody, indeed; the “Schoner, gruner Jungfernkranz” from Weber’s Freischutz. A woman’s voice badly trained, but German, yes indeed, German. Strange to hear one’s own tongue in so out-of-the-way a corner; and friendly, homely, at the same time. Poorly as the air was sung, it held a greeting from the land of my birth. Who can speak German here, who can be moved to hum this innocent refrain? Straining my ears against house after house, I reached one where there was a glimmer in one of the windows, and the shadow of a hand silhouetted against the blind. All doors were shut, and yet invitation to enter was to be deciphered on every brick and lintel. Nearer and nearer I approached the sound. This was the house! I hesitated a moment, and then pushed my shoulder against the door, having drawn aside a curtain which shielded the interior from draughts. On the threshold I entered a man whose face was reddened by the hanging lamp, and was livid with fury. He scowled at me, murmured an apology, and thrust past me into the alley. “Queer customer,” thought I, gazing after him. Meanwhile the voice continued singing; clearer than before it seemed to me. I boldly entered.

The song was cut off sharp, as with a knife. A terrible silence compassed me about, giving me the impression that I had destroyed something. Gradually my eyes grew accustomed to the dim lighting, and I found that the room was scantily furnished with a little bar at one end, a table, a couple of chairs—obviously a mere waiting-room for the true business of the establishment which went on in the background. Nor was it difficult to guess what the real business was, for along a passage there were many doors, some of them ajar, leading into bedrooms in which beneath deeply shaded lamps double beds were to be discerned. A girl was seated on a bench leaning her elbows on the table; she was heavily made up, and appeared extremely tired. Behind the bar was a blowzy woman, slatternly and fat, with a second girl, a rather pretty lass, at her side. My good evening fell flat and was not echoed back to me for a considerable time. It was eerie to have stepped into this silence of the desert, and I wished to get clear away. Yet, since there did not seem to be adequate reason for absconding, I took a place at the table and resigned myself to the inevitable.

Suddenly remembering her business in life, the girl got up and asked me what I wished to drink, and I recognised at once by her guttural pronunciation of the French words that she hailed from Germany. I ordered beer, which she fetched and brought to me, shuffling her feet in slovenly fashion, thus betraying even greater indifference than did her lack-lustre eyes. Following the custom of such haunts, she placed another glass next mine and sat down before it. She raised her glass with a nod of greeting in my direction, but she gazed through and beyond me. I had a good look at her. A beautiful face still, with regular features; but it had grown like a mask, since the inner fires were quenched. There was a touch of coarseness about it, the skin and muscles were lax, the lids heavy, the hair unkempt, and two furrows had already formed on either side of the mouth. Her dress was disorderly, her voice husky from too much smoking and beer-drinking. Here undubitably was a fellow-mortal who was weary unto death, and who only continued having out of long-established habit. Embarrassed and horrified, I asked her a question. She answered without looking at me and scarcely moving her lips. I guessed that my coming was unwelcome. The elder woman behind the bar yawned prodigiously, the younger girl slouched in a corner, as if waiting for me to call her. If I could have got away, I should have done so precipitately. But my limbs were like lead and I sat on inert, chained by disgust and curiosity, for, to speak frankly, this indifference stirred me strangely.

The girl next me suddenly burst into a fit of shrill laughter. Simultaneously, the flame of the lamp flickered in a draught of cold air coming through the open doorway.

“So you’ve come back,” said the girl in German.

“Creeping round the house again, you mean skunk. Oh, come along in—I shan’t do you any harm.”

I turned first to the speaker whose mouth seemed to be spewing forth fire, and then to the door. Slinking in was the individual who had scuttled away on my entry. He was a cringing creature holding his hat in his hand like a beggar, trembling under the douche of words that had greeted him, writhing beneath the torrential flow of mirthless laughter, and rendered even more uneasy by the way in which, from behind the bar, the hostess was whispering to the girl.

“Go and sit down beside Francoise,” the young woman said hectoringly. “Can’t you see I’ve got a gentleman customer?”

She spoke to him exclusively in the German tongue, while the hostess and the younger girl split their sides with laughter though they could not understand a word she said. The man was evidently a habitue.

“Give him a bottle of champagne, Francoise, the most expensive brand,” she yelled mockingly. “And if it’s too dear for you, my man, you’ve only got to stay outside and not come bothering us. You’d like to have me for nothing I know, and anything else you could get without paying you’d grab. Ugh, you filthy beast.”

The tall figure crumbled under the lash of this tongue. Like a whipped cur, he sidled up to the counter and with a trembling hand he poured the wine into a glass. He evidently wanted to look at the slattern who was abusing him, and yet he was unable to lift his gaze from the floor. The lamplight caught his face, and I saw before me an emaciated visage, with damp locks of hair sticking in wisps on the brow. His limbs were slack, as if broken at the joints. He was a pitiable object, devoid of strength and yet not wholly lacking in a kind of vicious courage. Everything about him was askew; and the eyes he raised for a flash did not look straight, but were shifty and full of a wicked light.

“Don’t bother about him,” said the girl to me in her ponderous French and seizing me roughly by the arm as though she wanted me to turn away from my contemplation. “It’s an old story between him and me. Doesn’t date from yesterday!” She bared her teeth like a vixen ready to bite, and snarled: “You just listen to what I tell you, old fox. I’d rather fling myself into the sea than go with you. Got it?”

Again the sally was applauded by shouts of laughter from behind the bar. The pleasantry seemed to be a joy which was daily renewed. Then a horrible thing happened. The younger wench put her arms round the man in simulated affection and caressed him tenderly. He winced under her touch, and glanced at me, anxious and cringing. At the same moment the woman next me threw off her inertia as if she had just awakened from profound sleep, and her countenance was so contorted with malevolence, her hands trembled so violently, that I could bear the scene no longer. Throwing some coins upon the table, I rose to go. But she detained me, saying:

“If he’s bothering you, I’ll chuck him out, the swine. He’s jolly well got to do what he’s told. Come, let’s drink another glass together.”

She pressed up against me with assumed ardour, and I knew at once that she was playing a game in order to torment the man, for she kept on glancing in his direction out of the corner of her eyes. Disgust filled me when I saw how, with every endearment she lavished upon me, the poor wretch shrank together as if branded with a red-hot iron. I could not take my eyes off him, and I shivered when it became evident what a storm of rage, jealousy, and desire was brewing within him. Yet, every time the girl looked towards him, he ducked his head in fear. She sidled closer, and I could feel her body quivering with pleasure as she pursued her wicked game. The scent of cheap powder and unwashed skin was sickening, and in order to keep her at a distance I took a cigar out of my case. Before I had time to light it, the girl was screaming.

“Here, you, bring a light, and be quick about it.”

It was horrible to make myself a party to her machinations by allowing the man to serve me, and I made what haste I could to find a match for myself. But her orders has already whipped the poor devil into activity, and he shuffled up to the table with the necessary kindling material. Our eyes crossed, and in his I read abysmal shame mingled with pusillanimous bitterness. This look touched a brotherly chord in me and made me vibrate in sympathy with his humiliation. I said in German:

“Thank you, Sir; but you should not have bothered.”

I offered him my hand. He hesitated for a moment, then my fingers were squeezed between his bony fists. Gratitude shone from his eyes during the second he fixed me, but soon he lowered his puffy lids. Defiance made me want to invite him to sit with us, and I had probably made a gesture of invitation for, ere the words dropped from my lips, the woman had said harshly:

“Back to your place, at once, and don’t come bothering round here again.”

I was nauseated by her strident voice and her whole demeanour. Why should I worry my head about this repulsive harlot, this weak-minded wench, this sewer of beer and cheap scent and tobacco-smoke? I longed for a breath of fresh air. I pushed the money towards her, stood up, and, when she tried to detain me with her endearments, I moved resolutely towards the exit. I could not participate in the humiliation of a fellow creature, and I made it clear to the girl that her charms had no attractions for me. An angry flush spread over her face and neck, fierce words trembled on her lips; but she did not speak. She merely turned to the man and looked at him so meaningly that with the utmost speed he sought to do her unspoken bidding. His fingers shot down into his pocket, and he drew forth a purse. He was evidently frightened at being left alone with her, and in his excitement fumbled with the opening. I guessed that he was not accustomed to spending money freely, he had none of the generous way of a sailor who flings his coins carelessly about. This man was used to counting money carefully, and to testing the pieces between his fingers before paying them away—as he now paid for his champagne.

“look how he’s trembling because he has to part with some of his beloved pence,” she cried tauntingly, stepping nearer to him. “Too slow, I tell you. Just wait till I...”

He shrank back in fear. When she saw how frightened he was, she shrugged her shoulders and said jeeringly, and with an indescribable expression of disgust on her face:

“I’m not going to take anything away from you. I spit on your money. It is all counted beforehand I know; never a farthing too much must be allowed to leave your purse. But,” and she tapped him on the chest, “What about the bit of paper you’ve so carefully stitched into your waistcoat lining?”

His hand went to his side as if he were seized with a spasm of the heart. Having felt the place, his face, which had gone ashen pale, resumed its normal hue and his hand dropped away again.

“Miser,” she screamed.

At this the martyr turned, flung the purse and its contents into the younger girl’s lap, and rushed out as if the place were on fire. At first the girl gave a shriek of alarm, then, realizing what the man had done she broke into peal upon peal of piercing laughter.

The woman stood for a moment rigid, her eyes sparkling with wrath. Then her lids closed, and her body went limp. She looked old and tired. A forlorn and dipping figure swayed before me.

“He’ll be weeping over his lost money, out there. May even go to the police-station and tell them we’ve stolen it To-morrow he’ll be here again. But he won’t get me, no that he won’t. I’ll give myself to anyone who offers, but never to him.”

She stepped up to the bar and gulped down a glass of neat brandy. The wickedness still glinted in her eyes but it was misty now as if shining from behind a veil of tears. My gorge rose as I looked at her, so that I could find no compassion in my heart.

“Good evening,” I said as I took my leave.

“Bon soir,” answered the hostess, without a glance in my direction.

Shrill and mocking laughter followed me into the street.

As I stepped forth into the alley, it seemed to me darker than ever, closed in by the starless sky and the night; but soon the pale moon shone down again, bringing me infinite alleviation. I took a deep breath, and the horror left me. Now I could once more relish the amazing tangle of human destinies; and a feeling of beatitude, akin to tears, filled me at the thought that behind every window fate was waiting, that at the opening of every door an experience was ready for the taking, that the multitudinous happenings of this world are ever present for those who choose to observe them, that even the foulest hovel is bursting with newly generated life like dung filled with the larvae that will become shining beetles. The unsavoury encounter was no longer repulsive to me. On the contrary, the suspense it had produced in my mind now relaxed into an agreeable sensation of lassitude, and my sole desire was to convert my adventure into beautiful dreams. I cast a searching eye up and down the narrow street, wondering which direction would lead me back to the hotel. A shadow fell across my path.

“Beg pardon, Sir,” said a familiar whining voice in my native tongue, “But I’m afraid you will have some difficulty in finding your way out of the maze. May I act as guide, Sir? Your hotel, Sir?”

I gave him the name.

“Yes, Sir, I know it, Sir. Will you allow me to accompany you,Sir?” he asked apologetically.

A shudder crept over me. It was horrible to have this slouching, ghostlike creature walking by my side, noiselessly, as if on stockinged feet. My perception of the gloom in the alleyways of the sailors’ quarter, the memory of my recent experience, were spontaneously replaced by a state of confused reverie. I knew that my companion’s eyes still held the same meek expression, that his lips still twitched nervously, that he wanted to talk. But I did not wish to rouse myself from the inertia of mind which enfolded me, in order to take any active interest in the fellow. He hemmed, words choked in his throat, and I felt a cruel pleasure in not coming to his aid. Repulsion at the recollection of that dreadful woman spread through me like a miasma, and I was glad the man’s shame should be wrestling with his spiritual need for explanation. No, I did not help him; but allowed a heavy curtain of silence to hang black and awesome between us. My footsteps rang out clear and youthful in contrast to his muffled and aged tread. The tension between his soul and mine grew stronger every minute. The silence became strident with unspoken words. At last the string, stretched to breaking-point, snapped, and he blurted out:

“You have...you have just witnessed a strange scene, Sir. I beg you to forgive me, Sir, if I refer to it...but it must have appeared very peculiar to you, Sir, and you must think me a ludicrous fellow, but you see, Sir, the woman...well, she is....”

He had got stuck again. His throat worked. Then, in a very small voice, he said hastily:

“She’s my wife, Sir...”

I must have shown surprise, for he hurriedly continued as if wishing to excuse himself.

“That is to say, Sir, she was my wife, five, no four years ago at Geratzheim in Hesse where I have my home. Please, Sir, you really must not think badly of her. It’s probably my fault that she has become what she is.. She was not always thus. But I...I teased and plagued her. You see, Sir, I married her in spite her abject poverty. Why, she had hardly a chemise to her back, nothing, nothing at all. Whereas I am well-to-do, or rather I am comfortably off...at least I had a pretty competence in those days...and I was, perhaps—she is right—I was thrifty...yes, I was thrifty even before our great misfortune. But you see, Sir, my father and mother were so, and the whole family a bit on the stingy side. Besides, I worked hard for every penny I earned. She was fond of pretty things, and, being poor, she had nothing but what I gave her. I was constantly reminding her of this. Oh, I know it was wrong of me—I’ve had time to learn that since the catastrophe—for she was proud, very proud. Please don’t run away with the idea that she is naturally of such a disposition as you witnessed this evening. Far from it, Sir; that’s all make-believe. She hurts herself in order to make me suffer in order to torture me, and because she is ashamed of her own doings, of her present mode of life. Maybe she has gone to the bad, but I...I refuse to accept such a notion...for I remember how good, how very good she used to be, Sir.”

His excitement made him pause, both in speech and walk, while he wiped his eyes. I looked at him in spite of myself. He no longer appeared to be a figure of fun, and I was no longer annoyed by his constant repetition of the obsequious “Sir.” The energy he had put into phrasing his explanation had transfigured his countenance. We started forward again, and he kept his eyes downcast as if reading his story printed upon the pavement. He sighed heavily, and his voice took on a sonorous tone very different from the querulous sound I had come to expect from him.

“Yes, Sir, she was good—good, and kind to me as well—she was grateful for having been raised out of her misery. I knew how thankful she was...but I wanted to hear her say so...always and always again...I could not listen too often to the verbal expression of her gratitude. You see, Sir, it is so wonderful to feel that someone considers you to be better than you really are. I would willingly have parted with all my money just to hear her say those few words, everlastingly renewed...but she had her proper pride, and she found it increasingly difficult to acknowledge her debt to me, especially when I made a claim upon her in the matter and almost ordered her point-blank to pronounce the words I longed to hear....And so, Sir, I insisted that she ask me for everything she wanted, for every dress, for every scrap of ribbon....Three years I tortured her thus, and her martyrdom grew worse as the time went by. And believe me, Sir, it was all because I loved her so desperately. I loved her proud bearing, and yet I wished to humiliate her. Oh, fool that I was! I pretended to be vexed when she asked for a hat, or any other trifle she took a fancy for; while all the time I was in the seventh heaven of delight at being given an opportunity to gratify her—and at the same time to make her eat humble-pie. In those days, Sir, I did not realize how dear she was to me....”

Again he stopped, and reeled in his gait. He had forgotten my existence, and spoke henceforward as if in a hypnotic trance.

“I only discovered how greatly I loved her on the day—the accursed day—when she begged me to give her something to help her mother out of a difficulty, and I refused. It was an insignificant sum....I had actually put the money aside for the purpose...but I longed for her to ask me again...and then, when I came home I found a letter on the table and learned that she had gone...All she wrote was: ‘Keep your damned money. I’ll never ask you for another penny.’ That’s all. Nothing more. I was like one demented for three days and three nights. I had the river dragged and the forest scoured; indeed I paid hundreds over to the authorities in the hope of discovering her whereabouts. I even confided my troubles to the neighbours—but they merely laughed me to scorn. No trace, no trace at all. Months later, I learned that someone had seen her in the train, accompanied by a soldier...a train going to Berlin. That very day I went to the capital, leaving my business to take care of itself. Thousands did I lose in the process. My farm labourers, my manager, my...oh, everyone profited by my absence to line his pockets. But I assure you, Sir, I remained indifferent to these losses...I stayed a week in Berlin...and, at last, I found her....”

He panted slightly, and then continued:

“I assure you, Sir, I never said a harsh word to her...I wept...I knelt before her...I offered her anything she pleased....She would hence forward be the mistress of all I possessed—for I had come to realize that life without her was impossible....I loved every hair on her head, her mouth, her body, every part and particle of her being. I bribed the landlady (she was, in fact, a procuress, what they call a ‘white-slave trader’) generously and thus managed to see poor Lise alone. Her face was like chalk; but she listened to me, oh, Sir I believe she really listened to me as if pleased, pleased to see me. But when I began to speak of the money it was necessary to pay—and after all, Sir, you will agree that we were obliged to discuss such practical issues—she merely called her fancy—man on to the scene, and the two of them laughed me out of countenance. I did not lose sight of her, Sir, but returned to the charge day after day. The other lodgers told me that the cur had left her, utterly unprovided for. So I sought her out yet again; but she tore up the notes I gave her, and the next time I came—she was gone. Oh, Sir, you can have no idea of what I did to trace her. I followed her for a year, paying agents here and agents there. At last I discovered that she had gone to Argentina...and...and...that she was in...a house...of ill-fame.”

Again he hesitated, and the last two words seemed to stick in his throat. His voice became sombre as he went on:

“At first I could hardly believe my ears...then I reflected that I was to blame, I, only I, because I had humiliated her. And I thought how terribly she must be suffering, she so proud, as I well knew her to be. I got my solicitor to write to the consul out there and I sent money. But she was not to be told from whom it came. The sum was more than sufficient to bring her home again. Soon I got a cable that the scheme had worked, and that the boat would reach Amsterdam on such a date. Well, so great was my impatience that I got there three days too soon. When I saw the smoke in the distance, it seemed to me I could not wait till the ship slowly entered port and came alongside the quay. At last I caught a glimpse of her at the tail of the other passengers, hardly recognizable at first, so heavily was she made up. When she saw me waiting for her, she blanched even under her paint, and tottered so that two ‘Sailors had to support her. No sooner had she stepped to land than I was at her side. I could not speak, my throat felt so dry. She, too, said nothing, and did not look at me. I motioned to a porter to carry the luggage, and we started for the hotel. Suddenly she turned to me and said...oh, Sir, if you could have heard her voice, so sad I thought my heart would break...‘do you want me still as your wife, after...?’ I could only clasp her hand...She trembled violently, but spoke no more. I felt that now all would be well....Ah, Sir, how happy I was. When we got to our room, I danced for joy, I knelt at her feet babbling out the most absurd things—at least I fancy my words must have been rather funny, for she smiled through her tears and stroked my hair—hesitatingly, of course. Her endearments did me good, my heart overflowed. I rushed up and down stairs ordering dinner—I called it our wedding feast. I helped her to change her dress, and then we went down and ate and drank, a merry meal I assure you, Sir. She was like a child, so warm and affectionate, speaking of our home and how everything would start fresh....Then...”

The man’s voice became rasping, and he made a gesture as if he were strangling someone.

“Then...the waiter...a mean and vulgar cur...believed me to be the worse for drink because I laughed so much and had carried on in such a boyish fashion and all because I was so happy, oh, so happy....Well, I paid the bill and he, as I said, thinking me drunk, cheated me out of twenty francs in giving me the change. I called the fellow back, and demanded my due. He looked sheepish, and laid the money by my plate...” Then...quite suddenly...Lise began to laugh. I stared at her perplexed...and her face was completely changed...mocking, hard, angry. ‘The same as ever...even after our wedding feast,’ she said coldly—and yet her voice was full of pity. I cursed myself for having been so particular...but I tried to laugh the matter off....Her gaiety had disappeared...It was dead and gone....She insisted upon being given a separate room....I was in a mood to grant every request...and lay alone, open-eyed, through the night, thinking what I should get her on the morrow...a handsome gift, that would show her I was no longer stingy...at least where she was concerned. Early next morning I was abroad...I bought a bracelet...and took it to her in her room...but she was no longer there...she had gone...as she had gone before. I looked round for a note...praying it would not be there, yet knowing that it would inevitably be awaiting me and there it was, sure enough, on the dressing-table and on it was scribbled...”

He hesitated. I stood still, looking into his martyred face. The man bowed his head, and whispered hoarsely:

“She had written...‘Leave me in peace. You are utterly repulsive to me.’”

Our walk had led us to the harbour; and, in the distance, the silence was broken by the roar of the Atlantic breakers on the coast. The vessels, their lights shining like the eyes of huge animals, swung at their anchors. A song floated to me from afar. Nothing was very clear. I seemed to feel presences rather than see them. The town was sleeping and dreaming an immense dream. By my side I distinguished the ghostly shadow of the man growing uncannily large and then dwindling to dwarfed proportions in the flickering lamp-light. I was not inclined to speak, or to offer consolation, or to ask questions. The silence stuck to me heavy and oppressive. Suddenly he seized my arm and said quaveringly:

“But I’m determined not to leave this town without her....After many months of search I found her....I am invulnerable to the martyrdom she is putting me through...I beseech you, Sir, to have a word with her...she refuses to listen if I speak...I must get her to come back....Oh, won’t you tell her she ought to? Please, Sir, have a try....I can’t go on living like this. I can’t bear any longer to see other men go in there, knowing she is giving herself to them, while I wait in the street till they come down again, laughing and tipsy. The whole neighbourhood knows me by now, and the people make mock of me when they see me waiting out on the pavement....I shall go mad, but I must keep my vigil without fail....Oh, Sir, I do beg of you to speak to her....You are a stranger, I know, but for God’s sake, Sir, have a word with her. Someone from her own country might influence her in this foreign land.”

I wished to free my arm from the man’s convulsive grip. Loathing and disgust alienated my sympathies. When he felt that I was trying to get away, he flung himself on to his knees in the middle of the street and clasped my legs.

“I conjure you, Sir, to speak to her; you must, you must—or something terrible will happen. All my money’s gone in tracing her, and I’m not going to leave her here...not alive. I’ve bought a knife. Yes, Sir, I’ve got a knife. I won’t let her stay here; at least not alive; I could not bear it. Oh, speak to her, Sir, I beg and pray you to have a talk with her....”

He crouched like a maniac before me. At that moment two policemen turned into the street. I dragged him violently to his feet. He looked at me blankly for a moment, and then said in an utterly changed voice: “Take the first turning on your right, and the hotel is about halfway down.”

Once more he stared at me with eyes wherein the pupils seemed to have melted away into a bleak, white void. Then he vanished.

I hugged myself in my coat, for I was shivering. I was tired; and sleep, a kind of drunken sleep, black and feelingless, claimed me. I wanted to think, to turn these things over in my mind, but sleep was ruthless and would not be put off. I got to my hotel, fell on to the bed, and slept like an animal.

In the morning it was hard to disentangle dream from reality, and something within me urged me not to try and find out. I woke late, a stranger in a strange city, and visited a church far-famed for its mosaics. But my eyes were blind to such sights. The night’s adventure rose vividly before my mind, and unconsciously my feet sought that alleyway and that house. But such thoroughfares do not become alive until after dark. During the daytime they wear cold, grey masks, and it is only those who know them well who are able to recognize one from another. Search as I might, I did not find the street I wanted. Weary and disappointed I returned to the hotel, followed by pictures that were either the figment of a disordered brain, or the remembrance of reality.

The train was scheduled to leave at nine o’clock that evening. I felt sorry to quit. A porter carried my bags to the station. Then, at a crossing, I recognized the street leading to that house. Telling the man to wait a minute, I went to cast a final glance at the site of my adventure, leaving the fellow smirking in a knowing way.

Yes, here it was, dark as last night, with the moonlight shining on the window-panes, and outlining the door. I was drawing nearer, when a figure emerged from the shadows. I recognized the German cowering on the threshold. He beckoned for me to approach. But mingled horror and fear made me take to my heels. I did not wish to be delayed, and to miss my train.

At the corner I turned for another look. As my eyes fell upon the poor devil he sprang up and made for the entry. He pushed the door open, and a piece of metal shone in his hand. Was it money or a knifeblade that glittered so treacherously in the moon beams?

THE INVISIBLE COLLECTION

AN EPISODE OF THE INFLATION PERIOD IN GERMANY

AT the first junction beyond Dresden, an elderly gentleman entered our compartment, smiled genially to the company, and gave me a special nod, as if to an old acquaintance. Seeing that I was at a loss, he mentioned his name. Of course I knew him! He was one of the most famous connoisseurs and art-dealers in Berlin. Before the war, I had often purchased autographs and rare books at his place. He took the vacant seat opposite me, and for a while we talked of matters not worth relating. Then, changing the conversation, he explained the object of the journey from which he was returning. It had, he said, been one of the strangest of his experiences in the thirty-seven years he had devoted to the occupation of art-pedlar. Enough introduction. I will let him tell the story in his own words, without using quote-marks—to avoid the complication of wheels within wheels.

You know [he said] what has been going on in my trade since the value of money began to diffuse into the void like gas. War-profiteers have developed a taste for old masters (Madonnas and so on), for incunabula, for ancient tapestries. It is difficult to satisfy their craving;and a man like myself, who prefers to keep the best for his own use and enjoyment, is hard put to it not to have his house stripped bare. If I let them, they would buy the cuff-links from my shirt and the lamp from my writing-table. Harder and harder to find wares to sell. I’m afraid the term “Wares” may grate upon you in this connexion, but you must excuse me. I have picked it up from customers of the new sort. Evil communications....Through use and wont I have come to look upon an invaluable book from one of the early Venetian presses much as the philistine looks upon an overcoat that cost so or so many hundred dollars, and upon a sketch by Guercino as animated by nothing more worthy of reverence than the transmigrated soul of a banknote for a few thousand francs.

Impossible to resist the greed of these fellows with money to burn. As I looked round my place the other night, it seemed to me that there was so little left of any real value that I might as well put up the shutters. Here was a fine business which had come down to me from my father and my grandfather; but the shop was stocked with rubbish which, before 1914, a street-trader would have been ashamed to hawk upon a hand-cart.

In this dilemma, it occurred to me to flutter the pages of our old ledgers. Perhaps I should be put on the track of former customers who might be willing to resell what they had bought in prosperous days. True, such a list of sometime purchasers has considerable resemblance to a battlefield laden with the corpses of the slain; and in fact I soon realized that most of those who had purchased from the firm when the sun was shining were dead or would be in such low water that it was probable they must have sold anything of value among their possessions. However, I came across a bundle of letters from a man who was presumably the oldest yet alive—if he was alive. But he was so old that I had forgotten him, since he had bought nothing after the great explosion in the summer of 1914. Yes, very, very old. The earliest letters were dated more than half a century back, when my grandfather was head of the business. Yet I could not recall having had any personal relationships with him during the thirty-seven years in which I had been an active worker in the establishment.

All indications showed that he must ave been one of those antediluvian eccentrics, a few of whom survive in those German provincial towns. His writing was copperplate, and every item in his orders was underlined in red ink. Each price was given in words as well as figures, so that there could be no mistake. These peculiarities, and his use of torn-out fly-leaves as writing paper, enclosed in a scratch assortment of envelopes, hinted at the penuriousness of a confirmed backwoodsman. His signature was always followed by his style and title in full: “Forest Ranger and Economic Councillor, Retired; Lieutenant,Retired; Holder of the Iron Cross First Class.” Since he was obviously a veteran of the war of 1870-71, he must by now be close on eighty.

For all his cheese-paring and for all his eccentricities, he had manifested exceptional shrewdness, knowledge, and taste as collector of prints and engravings. A careful study of his orders, which had at first totalled very small sums indeed, disclosed that in the days when a thaler could still pay for a pile of lovely German woodcuts, this country bumpkin had got together a collection of etchings and the like outrivalling the widely trumpeted acquisitions of war profiteers. Merely those which, in the course of decades, he had brought from us for trifling sums should be worth a large amount of money to-day; and I had no reason to suppose that he had failed to pick up similar bargains elsewhere. Was his collection dispersed? I was too familiar with what had been going on in the art trade since the date of his last purchase not to feel confident that such a collection could scarcely have changed hands entire without my getting wind of the event. If he was dead, his treasures had probably remained intact in the hands of his heirs.

The affair seemed so interesting that I set forth next day (yesterday evening) on a journey to one of the most out-of-the-way towns in Saxony. When I left the tiny railway station and strolled along the main street, it seemed to me impossible that anyone inhabiting one of these gimcrack houses, furnished in a way with which you are doubtless familiar, could possibly own a full of magnificent Rembrandt etchings together with an precedented number of Durer wood cuts and a complete collection of Mantegnas. However, I went to the post office to inquire, and was astonished to learn that sometime Forest Ranger and Economic Councillor of name I mentioned was still living. They told me how to find his house, and I will admit that my heart beat faster than usual as I made my way thither. It was well before noon.

The connoisseur of whom I was in search lived on the second floor of one of those jerry-built houses which were run up in such numbers by speculators during the sixties of the last century. The first floor was occupied by master tailor. On the second landing to the left was the name-plate of the manager of the local post-office while the porcelain shield on the right-hand door bore the name of my quarry. I had run him to earth! My ring was promptly answered by a very old, white-haired woman wearing a black lace cap. I handed her my card and asked whether the master was at home. With air of suspicion she glanced at me, at the card, and then back at my face once more. In this God-forsaken little town a visit from an inhabitant of the metropolis was a disturbing event. However, in as friendly a tone as she could muster, she asked me to be good enough to wait a minute or two in the hall, and vanished through doorway. I heard whispering, and then a loud, hearty, masculine voice: “Herr Rackner from Berlin, you say, the famous dealer in antiquities? Of course I shall be delighted to see him.” Thereupon the old woman reappeared and invited me to enter.

I took off my overcoat, and followed her. In the middle of the cheaply furnished room was a man standing up to receive me. Old but hale, he had a bushy moustache and was wearing a semi-military frogged smoking-jacket. In the most cordial way, he held out both hands towards me. But though this gesture was spontaneous and in no wise forced, it was in strange contrast with the stiffness of his attitude. He did not advance to meet me, so that I was compelled (I must confess I was a trifle piqued) to walk right up to him before I could shake. Then I noticed that his hand, too, did not seek mine, but was waiting for mine to clasp it. At length I guessed what was amiss. He was blind.

Ever since I was a child I have been uncomfortable in presence of the blind. It embarrasses me, produces in me a sense of bewilderment and shame to encounter anyone who is thoroughly alive, and yet has not the full use of his senses. I feel as if I were taking an unfair advantage, and I was keenly conscious of this sensation as I glanced into the fixed and sightless orbs beneath the bristling white eyebrows. The blind man, however, did not leave me time to dwell upon this discomfort. He exclaimed, laughing with boisterous delight:

“A red-letter day, indeed! Seems almost a miracle that one of the big men of Berlin should drop in as you have done. There’s need for us provincials to be careful, you know, when a noted dealer such as yourself is on the war-path. We’ve a saying in this part of the world:‘Shut your doors and button up your pockets if there are gipsies about!’ I can guess why you’ve taken the trouble to call. Business doesn’t thrive, I’ve gathered. No buyers or very few, so people are looking up their old customers. I’m afraid you’ll draw a blank. We pensioners are glad enough to find there’s still some bread for dinner. I’ve been a collector in my time, but now I’m out of the game. My buying days are over.”

I hastened to tell him he was under a misapprehension, that I had not called with any thought of effecting sales. Happening to be in the neighbourhood I felt loath to miss the chance of paying my respects to a long standing customer who was at the same time one of the most famous among German collectors. Hardly had the phrase passed my lips when a remarkable change took place in the old man’s expression. He stood stiffly in the middle of the room, but his face lighted up and his whole aspect was suffused with pride. He turned in the direction where he fancied his wife to be, and nodded as if to say, “D’you hear that?”Then, turning back to me, he resumed—having dropped the brusque, drill-sergeant tone he had previously used, and speaking in a gentle, nay, almost tender voice:

“How charming of you....I should be sorry, however, if your visit were to result in nothing more than your making the personal acquaintanceship of an old buffer like myself. At any rate I’ve something worth while for you to see-more worth while than you could find in Berlin in the Albertina at Vienna, or even in the Louvre (God’s curse on Paris!) A man who has been a diligent collector for fifty years, with taste to guide him, gets hold of treasures that are not to be picked up at every street-corner. Lisbeth, give me the key of the cupboard, please.”

Now a strange thing happened. His wife, who had been listening with a pleasant smile, was startled. She raised her hands towards me, clasped them imploringly, and shook her head. What these gestures signified was a puzzle to me. Next she went up to her husband and touched his shoulder, saying:

“Franz, dear, you have forgotten to ask our visitor whether he may not have another appointment; and, anyhow, it is almost dinner-time.—I am sorry,” she went on, looking at me, “That we have not enough in the house for an unexpected guest. No doubt you will dine at the inn.If you will take a cup of coffee with us afterwords, my daughter Anna Maria will be here, and she is much better acquainted than I am with the contents of the portfolios.”

Once more she glanced piteously at me. It was plain that she wanted me to refuse the proposal to examine the collection there and then. Taking my cue, I said that in fact I had a dinner engagement at the Golden Stag, but should be only too delighted to return at three, when there would be plenty of time to examine anything Herr Kronfeld wanted to show me. I was not leaving before six o’clock.

The veteran was as pettish as a child deprived of a favourite toy.

“Of course,” he growled, “I know you mandarins from Berlin have extensive claims on your time. Still, I really think you will do well to spare me a few hours. It is not merely two or three prints I want to show you, but the contents of twenty-seven portfolios, one for each master, and all of them full to bursting. However, if you come at three sharp, I dare say we can get through by six.”

The wife saw me out. In the entrance hall, before she opened the front door, she whispered:

“Do you mind if Anna Maria comes to see you at the hotel before you return? It will be better for various reasons which I cannot explain just now.”

“Of Course, of course, a great pleasure. Really, I am dining alone, and your daughter can come along directly you have finished your own meal.”

An hour later, when I had removed from the dining-room to the parlour of the Golden Stag, Anna Maria Kronfeld arrived. An old maid, wizened and diffident, plainly dressed, she contemplated me with embarrassment. I did my best to put her at her ease, and express my readiness to go back with her at once, if her father was impatient, though it was short of the appointed hour. At this she reddened, grew even more confused and then stammered a request for a little talk before we set out.

“Please sit down,” I answered. “I am entirely at your service.”

She found it difficult to begin. Her hands and her lips trembled. At length: “My mother sent me. We have to ask a favour of you. Directly you get back, Father will want to show you his collection; and the collection...the collection. Well, there’s very little of it left.”

She panted, almost sobbed, and went on breathlessly:

“I must be frank...” You know what troublous times we are passing through, and I am sure you will understand. Soon after the war broke out, my father became completely blind. His sight had already been failing. Agitation, perhaps, contributed. Though he was over seventy, he wanted to go to the front, remembering the fight in which he had taken part so long ago. Naturally there was no use for his services. Then, when the advance of our armies was checked, he took the matter very much to heart, and the doctor thought that may have precipitated the oncoming of blindness. In other respects, as you will have noticed, he is vigorous. Down to 1914 he could take long walks, and go out shooting. Since the failure of his eyes, his only pleasure is in his collection. He looks at it every day. ‘Looks at it,’ I say, though he sees nothing. Each afternoon he has the portfolios on the table, and fingers the prints one by one, in the order which many years have rendered so familiar. Nothing else interests him. He makes me read reports of auctions; and the higher the prices, the more enthusiastic does he become.

“There’s the dreadful feature of the situation. Father knows nothing about the inflation; that we are ruined; that his monthly pension would not provide us with a day’s food. Then we have others to support. My sister’s husband was killed at Verdun, and there are four children. These money troubles have been kept from him. We cut down expenses as much as we can, but it is impossible to make ends meet. We began to sell things, trinkets and so on, without interfering with his beloved collection. There was very little to sell, since Father had always spent whatever he could scrape together upon woodcuts, copperplate engravings, and the like. The collector’s mania! Well, at length it was a question whether we were to touch the collection or to let him starve. We didn’t ask permission. What would have been the use? He hasn’t the ghost of a notion how hard food is to come by, at any price; has never heard that Germany was defeated and surrendered Alsace-Lorraine. We don’t read him items of that sort from the newspapers!

“The first piece we sold was a very valuable one, a Rembrandt etching, and the dealer paid us a long price, a good many thousand marks. We thought it would last us for years. But you know how money was melting away in 1922 and 1923. After we had provided for our immediate needs, we put the rest in a bank. In two months it was gone! We had to sell another engraving, and then another. That was during the worst days of inflation and each time the dealer delayed settlement until the price was not worth a tenth or a hundredth of what he had promised to pay. We tried auction-rooms, and were cheated there too, though the bids were raised by millions. The million- or milliard-mark notes were waste-paper by the time we got them. The collection was scattered to provide daily bread, and little of that.

“That was why Mother was so much alarmed when you turned up to-day. Directly the portfolios are opened, our pious fraud will be disclosed. He knows each item by touch. You see, every print we disposed of was immediately replaced by a sheet of blank cartridge-paper of the same size and thickness, so that he would notice no difference when he handled it. Feeling them one by one, and counting them, he derives almost much pleasure as if he could actually see them. He never tries to show them to anyone here, where there is no connoisseur, no one worthy to look at them; but he loves each of them so ardently that I think his heart would break if he knew they had been dispersed. The last time he asked someone to look at them, it was the curator of the copper-plate engravings in Dresden, who died years ago.

“I beseech you”—her voice broke—“Not to shatter his illusion, not to undermine his faith, that the treasures he will describe to you are there for the seeing. He would not survive the knowledge of their loss. Perhaps we have wronged him; yet what could we do? One must live. Orphaned children are more valuable than old prints. Besides, it has been life and happiness to him to spend three hours every afternoon going through his imaginary collection, and talking to each specimen as if it were a friend. To-day may be the most enthralling experience since his sight failed. How he has longed for the chance of exhibiting his treasures to an expert! If you will lend yourself to the deception...”

In my cold recital, I cannot convey to you how poignant was this appeal. I have seen many a sordid transaction in my business career,have had to look on supinely while persons ruined by inflation have been diddled out of cherished heirlooms which they were compelled to sacrifice for a crust. But my heart has not been utter calloused, and this tale touched me to the quick. I need hardly tell you that I promised to play up.

We went to her house together. On the way I was grieved (though not surprised) to learn for what preposterously small amounts these ignorant though kind-hearted women had parted with prints many of which were extremely valuable and some of them unique. This confirmed my resolve to give all the help in my power. As we mounted the stairs we heard a jovial shout: “Come in! Come in!” With the keen hearing of the blind he had recognized the footsteps for which he had been eagerly waiting.

“Franz usually takes a siesta after dinner, but excitement kept him awake to-day,” said the old woman, with a smile as she let us in. A glance at her daughter showed her that all was well. The stack of portfolios was on the table. The blind collector seized me by the arm and thrust me into a chair which was placed ready for me.

“Let’s begin at once. There’s a lot to see, and time presses. The first portfolio contains Durers. Nearly a full set, and you’ll think each cut finer than the others. Magnificent specimens. Judge for yourself.”

He opened the portfolio as he spoke saying:

“We start with the Apocalypse series, of course.” Then, tenderly, delicately (as one handles fragile and precious objects), he picked up the first of the blank sheets of cartridge-paper and held it admiringly before my sighted eyes and his blind ones. So enthusiastic was his gaze that it was difficult to believe he could not see. Though I knew it to be fancy, I found it difficult to doubt that there was a glow of recognition in the wrinkled visage.

“Have you ever come across a finer print? How sharp the impression. Every detail crystal-clear. I compared mine with the one at Dresden; a good one, no doubt, but ‘fuzzy’ in contrast with the specimen you are looking at. Then I have the whole pedigree.”

He turned the sheet over and pointed at the back so convincingly that involuntarily I leaned forward to read the non-existent inscriptions.

“The stamp of the Nagler collection, followed by those of Remy and Esdaille. My famous predecessors never thought that their treasure would come to roost in this little room.”

I shuddered as the unsuspecting enthusiast extolled the blank sheet of paper; my flesh crept when he placed a finger-nail on the exact spot where the alleged imprints had been made by long-dead collectors. It was as ghostly as if the disembodied spirits of the men he named had risen from the tomb. My tongue clave to the roof of my mouth—until once more I caught sight of distraught countenances of Kronfelds’ wife and daughter. Then I pulled myself together and resumed my role. With forced heartiness, I exclaimed:

“Certainly you are right. This specimen is peerless.”

He swelled with triumph.

“But that’s nothing,” he went on. “Look at these two the Melancholia, and the illuminated print of the Passion. The latter, beyond question, has no equal. The freshness of the tints! Your colleagues in Berlin and the custodians of the public galleries would turn green with envy at the sight.”

I will not bore you with details. Thus it went on, a paean, for more than two hours, as he ransacked portfolio after portfolio. An eerie business to watch handling of these two or three hundred blanks, to chime in at appropriate moments with praise of merits which for the blind collector were so eminently real that again and again (this was my salvation) his faith kindled my own.

Once only did disaster loom. He was “Showing” me first proof of Rembrandt’s Antiope, which must have been of inestimable value and which had doubtless been sold for a song. Again he dilated on the sharpness of the print as he passed his fingers lightly over it the sensitive tips missed some familiar indentation. His face clouded, his mouth trembled, and he said:

“Surely, surely it’s the Antiope? No one touches the wood-cuts and etchings but myself. How can it have got misplaced?”

“Of course it’s the Antiope, Herr Kronfeld,” I said, hastening to take the “Print” from his hand to expatiate upon various details which my own remembrance enabled me to conjure up upon the blank surface.

His bewilderment faded. The more I praised, the more gratified he became, until at last he said exultantly to the two women:

“Here’s a man who knows what’s what! You have been inclined to grumble at my ‘Squandering’ money upon the collection. It’s true that for half a century and more I denied myself beer, wine, tobacco, travelling, visits to the theatre, books, devoting all I could spare to these purchases you have despised. Well, Herr Rackner confirms my judgment. When I am dead and gone, you’ll be richer than anyone in the town, as wealthy as the wealthiest folk in Dresden, and you’ll have good reason for congratulating yourself on my ‘craze’. But so long as I’m alive, the collection must be kept together. After I’ve been boxed and buried, this expert or another will help you to sell. You’ll have to, since my pension dies with me.”

As he spoke, his fingers caressed the despoiled portfolios. It was horrible and touching. Not for years, not since 1914, had I witnessed an expression of such unmitigated happiness on the face of a German. His wife and daughter watched him with tear-dimmed eyes, yet ecstatically, like those women of old who—affrighted and rapturous—found the stone rolled away and the sepulchre empty in the garden outside the wall of Jerusalem. But the man could not have enough of my appreciation. He went on from portfolio to portfolio from “Print” to “Print”, drinking in my words, until, outwearied, I was glad when the lying blanks were replaced in their cases and room was made to serve coffee on the table.

My host, far from being tired, looked rejuvenated. He had story after story to tell concerning the way he had chanced upon his multifarious treasures, wanting in this connexion, to take out each relevant piece once more. He grew peevish when I insisted, when his wife and daughter insisted, that I should miss my train if he delayed me any longer....

In the end he was reconciled to my going, and we said good-bye. His voice mellowed; he took both my hands in his and fondled them with the tactile appreciation of the blind.

“Your visit has given me immense pleasure,” he said with a quaver in his voice. “What a joy to have been able at long last to show my collection to one competent to appreciate it. I can do something to prove my gratitude, to make your visit to a blind old man worth while. A codicil to my will shall stipulate that your firm, whose probity everyone knows, will be entrusted with the auctioning of my collection.”

He laid a hand lovingly upon the pile of worthless portfolios.

“Promise me they shall have a handsome catalogue. I could ask no better monument.”

I glanced at the two women, who were exercising the utmost control, fearful lest the sound of their trembling should reach his keen ears. I promised the impossible, and he pressed my hand in response.

Wife and daughter accompanied me to the door. They did not venture to speak, but tears were flowing down their cheeks. I myself was in little better case. An art dealer, I had come in search of bargains. Instead, as events turned out, I had been a sort of angel of good-luck, lying like a trooper in order to assist in a fraud which kept an old man happy. Ashamed of lying, I was glad that I had lied. At any rate I had aroused an ecstasy which seems foreign to this period of sorrow and gloom.

As I stepped forth into the street, I heard a window and my name called. Though the old fellow could not see me, he knew in which direction I should walk, and his sightless eyes were turned thither. He leaned out so far that his anxious relatives put their arms round him lest he should fall. Waving a handkerchief, he shouted:

“A pleasant journey to you, Herr Rackner.”

His voice rang like a boy’s. Never shall I forget that cheerful face, which contrasted so grimly with the careworn aspect of the passers-by in the street. The illusion I had helped to sustain made life good for him. Was it not Goethe who said:

“Collectors are happy creatures”?

BUCHMENDEL

HAVING just got back to Vienna, after a visit to an out-of-theway part of the country, I was walking home from the station when a heavy shower came on, such a deluge that the passers-by hastened to take shelter in doorways, and I myself felt it expedient to get out of the downpour. Luckily there is a cafe at almost every street corner in the metropolis, and I made for the nearest, though not before my hat was dripping wet and my shoulders were drenched to the skin. An old-fashioned suburban place, lacking the attractions (copied from Germany) of music and a dancing-floor to be found in the centre of the town; full of small shopkeepers and working folk who consumed more newspapers than coffee and rolls. Since it was already late in the evening, the air, which would have been stuffy anyhow, was thick with tobacco-smoke. Still, the place was clean and brightly decorated, had new satin-covered couches, and a shining cash-register, so that it looked thoroughly attractive. In my haste to get out of the rain I had not troubled to read its name-but what matter? There I rested, warm and comfortable, though looking rather impatiently through the blue-tinted window panes to see when the shower would be over, and I should be able to get on my way.

Thus I sat unoccupied, and began to succumb to that inertia which results from the narcotic atmosphere of the typical Viennese cafe. Out of this void, I scanned various individuals whose eyes, in the murky room, had a greyish look in the artificial light; I mechanically contemplated the young woman at the counter as, like an automaton, she dealt out sugar and a teaspoon to the waiter for each cup of coffee; with half an eye and a wandering attention I read the uninteresting advertisements on the walls—and there was something agreeable about these dull occupations. But suddenly, and in a peculiar fashion, I was aroused from what had become almost a doze. A vague internal movement had begun; much as a toothache sometimes begins, without one’s being able to say whether it is on the right side or the left, in the upper jaw or the lower. All I became aware of was a numb tension, an obscure sentiment of spiritual unrest. Then, without knowing why, I grew fully conscious. I must have been in this cafe once before, years ago, and random associations had awakened memories of the walls, the tables, the chairs, the seemingly unfamiliar smoke-laden room.

The more I endeavoured to grasp this lost memory, the more obstinately did it elude me; a sort of jellyfish glistening in the abysses of consciousness, slippery and unseizable. Vainly did I scrutinize every object within the range of vision. Certainly when I had been here before the counter had had neither marble top nor cash register; the walls had not been panelled with imitation rosewood; these must be recent acquisitions. Yet I had indubitably been here, more than twenty years back. Within these four walls, as firmly fixed as a nail driven up to the head in a tree, there slung a part of my ego, long since overgrown. Vainly I explored, not only the room, but my own inner man, to grapple the lost links. Curse it all, I could not plumb the depths!

It will be seen that I was becoming vexed, as one is always out of humour when one’s grip slips in this way, and reveals the inadequacy, the imperfections, of one’s spiritual powers. Yet I still hoped to recover the clue. A slender thread would suffice, for my memory is of a peculiar type, both good and bad; on the one hand stubbornly untrustworthy, and on the other incredibly dependable. It swallows the most important details, whether in concrete happenings or in faces, and no voluntary exertion will induce it to regurgitate them from the gulf. Yet the most trifling indication—a picture postcard, the address on an envelope, a newspaper cutting—will suffice to hook up what is wanted as an angler who has made a strike and successfully imbedded his hook reels in a lively, struggling, and reluctant fish. Then I can recall the features of a man seen once only, the shape of his mouth and the gap to the left where he had an upper eye-tooth knocked out, the falsetto tone of his laugh, and the twitching of the moustache when he chooses to be merry, the entire change of expression which hilarity effects in him. Not only do these physical traits rise before my mind’s eye, but I remember,years afterwards, every word the man said to me, and the tenor of my replies. But if I am to see and feel the past thus vividly, there must be some material link to start the current of associations. My memory will not work satisfactorily on the abstract plane.

I closed my eyes to think more strenuously, in the attempt to forge the hook which would catch my fish. In vain! In vain! There was no hook, or the fish would not bite. So fierce waxed my irritation with the inefficient and mulish thinking apparatus between my temples that I could have struck myself a violent blow on the forehead, much as an irascible man will shake and kick a penny-in-the-slot machine which when he has inserted his coin, refuses to render him his due.

So exasperated did I become at my failure, that I could no longer sit quiet, but rose to prowl about the room. The instant I moved, the glow of awakening memory began. To the right of the cash-register, I recalled, there must be a doorway leading into a windowless room, where the only light was artificial. Yes, the place actually existed. The decorative scheme was different, but the proportions were unchanged. A square box of a place, behind the bar—the card room. My nerves thrilled as I contemplated the furniture, for I was on the track, I had found the clue, and soon I should know all. There were two small billiard-tables, looking like silent ponds covered with green scum. In the corners, card-tables, at one of which two bearded men of professorial type were playing chess. Beside the iron stove, close to a door labelled“Telephone,” was another small table. In a flash, I had it! That was Mendel’s place, Jacob Mendel’s. That was where Mendel used to hang out, Buchmendel. I was in the Cafe Gluck! How could I have forgotten Jacob Mendel. Was it possible that I had not thought about him for ages, a man so peculiar as well nigh to belong to the Land of Fable, the eighth wonder of the world, famous at the university and among a narrow circle of admirers, magician of book-fanciers, who had been wont to sit there from morning till night, an emblem of bookish lore, the glory of the Cafe Gluck? Why had I had so much difficulty in hooking my fish? How could I have forgotten Buchmendel?

I allowed my imagination to work. The man’s face and form pictured themselves vividly before me. I saw him as he had been in the flesh, seated at the table with its grey marble top, on which books and manuscripts were piled. Motionless he sat, his spectacled eyes fixed upon the printed page. Yet not altogether motionless, for he had a habit (acquired at school in the Jewish quarter of the Galician town from which he came) of rocking his shiny bald pate backwards and forwards and humming to himself as he read, There he studied catalogues and tomes, crooning and rocking, as Jewish boys are taught to do when reading the Talmud. The rabbis believe that, just as a child is rocked to sleep in its cradle, so are the pious ideas of the holy text better instilled by this rhythmical and hypnotizing movement of head and body. In fact, as if he had been in a trance, Jacob Mendel saw and heard nothing while thus occupied. He was oblivious to the click of billiard-balls, the coming and going of waiters, the ringing of the telephone bell; he paid no heed when the floor was scrubbed and when the stove was refilled. Once a red-hot coal fell out of the latter, and the flooring began to blaze a few inches from Mendel’s feet; the room was full of smoke, and one of the guests ran for a pail of water to extinguish the fire. But neither the smoke, the bustle, nor the stench diverted his attention from the volume before him. He read as others pray, as gamblers follow the spinning of the roulette board, as drunkards stare into vacancy; he read with such profound absorption that ever since I first watched him the reading of ordinary mortals has seemed a pastime. This Galician second-hand book dealer, Jacob Mendel, was the first to reveal to me in my youth the mystery of absolute concentration which characterizes the artist and the scholar, the sage and the imbecile; the first to make me acquainted with the tragical happiness and unhappiness of complete absorption.

A senior student introduced me to him. I was studying the life and doings of a man who is even to-day too little known, Mesmer the magnetizer. My researches were bearing scant fruit, for the books I could lay my hands on conveyed sparse information, and when I applied to the university librarian for help he told me, uncivilly, that it was not his business to hunt up references for a freshman. Then my college friend suggested taking me to Mendel.

“He knows everything about books, and will tell you where to find the information you want. The ablest man in Vienna, and an original to boot. The man is a saurian of the book-world, an antediluvian survivor of an extinct species.”

We went, therefore, to the Cafe Gluck, and found Buchmendel in his usual place, bespectacled, bearded, wearing a rusty black suit, and rocking as I have described. He did not notice our intrusion, but went on reading, looking like a nodding mandarin. On a hook behind him hung his ragged black overcoat, the pockets of which bulged with manuscripts, catalogues, and books. My friend coughed loudly, to attract his attention, but Mendel ignored the sign. At length Schmidt rapped on the table-top, as if knocking at a door, and at this Mendel glanced up, mechanically pushed his spectacles on to his forehead, and from beneath his thick and untidy ashen-grey brows there glared at us two dark, alert little eyes. My friend introduced me, and I explained my quandary, being careful (as Schmidt had advised) to express great annoyance at the librarian’s unwillingness to assist me. Mendel leaned back, laughed scornfully, and answered with a strong Galician accent:

“Unwillingness, you think? Incompetence, that’s what’s the matter with him. He’s a jackass. I’ve known him (for my sins) twenty years at least, and he’s learned nothing in the whole of that time. Pocket their wages that’s all such fellows can do. They should be mending the road, instead of sitting over books.”

This outburst served to break the ice, and with a friendly wave of the hand the bookworm invited me to sit down at his table. I reiterated my object in consulting him; to get a list of all the early works on animal magnetism, and of contemporary and subsequent books and pamphlets for and against Mesmer. When I had said my say, Mendel closed his left eye for an instant, as if excluding a grain of dust. This was, with him, a sign of concentrated attention. Then, as though reading from an invisible catalogue, he reeled out the names of two or three dozen titles, giving in each case place and date of publication and approximate price. I was amazed, though Schmidt had warned me what to expect. His vanity was tickled by my surprise, for he went on to strum the keyboard of his marvellous memory, and to produce the most astounding bibliographical marginal notes. Did I want to know about sleepwalkers, Perkins’s metallic tractors, early experiments in hypnotism, Braid, Gassner, attempts to conjure up the devil, Christian Science, theosophy, Madame Blavatsky? In connexion with each item there was a hailstorm of book-names, dates and appropriate details. I was beginning to understand that Jacob Mendel was a living lexicon, something like the general catalogue of the British Museum Reading Room, but able to walk about on two legs. I stared dumbfounded at this bibliographical phenomenon, which masqueraded in the sordid and rather unclean domino of a Galician second-hand book dealer, who after rattling off some eighty titles (with assumed indifference but really with the satisfaction of one who plays an unexpected trump), proceeded to wipe his spectacles with a handkerchief which might long before have been white.

Hoping to conceal my astonishment, I inquired:

“Which among these works do you think you could get for me without too much trouble?”

“Oh, I’ll have a look round,” he answered. “Come here to-morrow and I shall certainly have some of them. As for the others, it’s only a question of time, and of knowing where to look.”

“I’m greatly obliged to you,” I said; and, then, wishing to be civil, I put my foot in it, proposing to give him a list of the books I wanted. Schmidt nudged me warningly, but too late. Mendel had already flashed a look at me—such a look, at once triumphant and affronted, scornful and overwhelmingly superior—the royal look with which Macbeth answers Macduff when summoned to yield without a blow. He laughed curtly. His Adam’s apple moved excitedly. Obviously he had gulped down a choleric, an insulting epithet.

Indeed he had good reason to be angry. Only a stranger, an ignoramus, could have proposed to give him, Jacob Mendel, a memorandum, as if he had been a bookseller’s assistant or an underling in a public library. Not until I knew him better did I fully understand how much my would-be politeness must have galled this aberrant genius—for the man had and knew himself to have, a titanic memory wherein, behind a dirty and undistinguished-looking forehead, was indelibly recorded a picture of the title-page of every book that had been printed. No matter whether it had issued from the press yesterday or hundreds of years ago, he knew its place of publication, its author’s name and its price. From his mind, as if from the printed page, he could read off the contents, could reproduce the illustrations; could visualize, not only what he had actually held in his hands, but also what he had glanced at in a bookseller’s window; could see it with the same vividness as an artist sees the creations of fancy which he has not yet reproduced upon canvas. When a book was offered for six marks by a Regensburg dealer, he could remember that, two years before, a copy of the same work had changed hands for four crowns at a Viennese auction and he recalled the name of the purchaser. In a word: Jacob Mendel never forgot a title or a figure; he knew every plant, every infusorian, every star, in the continually revolving and incessantly changing cosmos of the book-universe. In each literary speciality, he knew more than the specialists; he knew the contents of the libraries better than the librarians; he knew the book-lists of most publishers better than the heads of the firms concerned—though he had nothing to guide him except the magical powers of his inexplicable but invariably accurate memory.

True this memory owed its infallibility to the man’s limitations, to his extraordinary power of concentration. Apart from books, he knew nothing of the world. The phenomena of existence did not begin to become real for him until they had been set in type, arranged upon a composing stick, collected and, so to say, sterilized in a book. Nor did he read books for their meaning, to extract their spiritual or narrative substance. What aroused his passionate interest, what fixed his attention, was the name, the price, the format, the title-page Though in the last analysis unproductive and uncreative, this specifically antiquarian memory of Jacob Mendel, since it was not a printed book-catalogue but was stamped upon the grey matter of a mammalian brain, was, in its unique perfection, no less remarkable a phenomenon than Napoleon’s gift for physiognomy, Mezzofanti's talent for languages, Lasker’s skill at chess-openings, Busoni's musical genius. Given a public position as teacher, this man with so marvellous a brain might have taught thousands and hundreds of thousands of students, have trained others to become men of great learning and of incalculable value to those communal treasure-houses we call libraries. But to him, a man of no account, a Galician Jew, a book-pedlar whose only training had been received in a Talmudic school, this upper world of culture was a fenced precinct he could never enter; and his amazing faculties could only find application at the marble-topped table in the inner room of the Cafe Gluck. When, some day, there arises a great psychologist who shall classify the types of that magical power we term memory as effectively as Buffon classified the genera and species of animals, a man competent to give a detailed description of all the varieties, he will have to find a pigeon-hole for Jacob Mendel, forgotten master of the lore of bookprices and book-titles, the ambulatory catalogue alike of incunabula and the modern commonplace.

In the book-trade and among ordinary persons, Jacob Mendel was regarded as nothing more than a secondhand book dealer in a small way of business. Sunday after Sunday, his stereotyped advertisement appeared in the “Neue Freie Presse” and the “Neues Wiener Tagblatt.”It ran as follows: “Best prices paid for old books, Mendel, Obere Alserstrasse.” A telephone number followed, really that of the Cafe Gluck. He rummaged every available corner for his wares, and once a week, with the aid of a bearded porter, conveyed fresh booty to his headquarters, and got rid of old stock—for he had no proper bookshop. Thus he remained a petty trader, and his business was not lucrative. Students sold him their textbooks, which year by year passed through his hands from one “Generation” to another; and for a small percentage on the price he would procure any additional book that was wanted. He charged little or nothing for advice. Money seemed to have no standing in his world. No one had ever seen him better dressed than in the threadbare black coat. For breakfast and supper he had a glass of milk and a couple of rolls, while at midday a modest meal was brought him from a neighbouring restaurant. He did not smoke; he did not play cards; one might almost say he did not live, were it not that his eyes were alive behind his spectacles, and unceasingly fed his enigmatic brain with words, titles, names. The brain, like a fertile pasture, greedily sucked in this abundant irrigation. Human beings did not interest him, and of all human passions perhaps one only moved him, the most universal—vanity.

When someone, wearied by a futile hunt in countless other places, applied to him for information, and was instantly put on the track, his self-gratification was overwhelming; and it was unquestionably a delight to him that in Vienna and elsewhere there existed a few dozen persons who respected him for his knowledge and valued him for the services he could render. In every one of these monstrous aggregates we call towns, there are here and there facets which reflect one and the same universe in miniature—unseen by most, but highly prized by connoisseurs, by brethren of the same craft, by devotees of the same passion. The fans of the book-market knew Jacob Mendel. Just as anyone encountering a difficulty in deciphering a score would apply to Eusebius Mandyczewski of the Musical Society, who would be found wearing a grey skull-cap and seated among multifarious musical MSS., ready, with a friendly smile, to solve the most obstinate crux;and just as, to-day, anyone in search of information about the Viennese theatrical and cultural life of earlier times will unhesitatingly look up the polyhistor Father Glossy; so, with equal confidence did the bibliophiles of Vienna, when they had a particularly hard nut to crack, make a pilgrimage to the Cafe Gluck and lay their difficulty before Jacob Mendel.

To me, young and eager for new experiences, it became enthralling to watch such a consultation. Whereas ordinarily, when a would-be seller brought him some ordinary book, he would contemptuously clap the cover to and mutter, “Two crowns”; if shown a rare or unique volume, he would sit up and take notice, lay the treasure upon a clean sheet of paper; and, on one such occasion, he was obviously ashamed of his dirty, ink-stained fingers and mourning finger-nails. Tenderly, cautiously, respectfully, he would turn the pages of the treasure. One would have been as loath to disturb him at such a moment as to break in upon the devotions of a man at prayer; and in very truth there was a flavour of solemn ritual and religious observance about the way in which contemplation, palpation, smelling, and weighing in the hand followed one another in orderly succession. His rounded hack waggled while he was thus engaged, he muttered to himself, exclaimed “Ah”now and again to express wonder or admiration, or “Oh, dear” when a page was missing or another had been mutilated by the larva of a bookbeetle. His weighing of the tome in his hand was as circumspect as if books were sold by the ounce, and his snuffling at it as sentimental as a girl’s smelling of a rose. Of course it would have been the height of bad form for the owner to show impatience during this ritual of examination.

When it was over, he willingly, nay enthusiastically, tendered all the information at his disposal, not forgetting relevant anecdotes, and dramatized accounts of the prices which other specimens of the same work had fetched at auctions or in sales by private treaty. He looked brighter, younger, more lively at such times, and only one thing could put him seriously out of humour. This was when a novice offered him money for his expert opinion. Then he would draw back with an affronted air, looking for all the world like the skilled custodian of a museum gallery to whom an American traveller has offered a tip—for to Jacob Mendel contact with a rare book was something sacred, as is contact with a woman to a young man who has not had the bloom rubbed off. Such moments were his platonic love-nights. Books exerted a spell on him, never money. Vainly, therefore, did great collectors (among them one of the notables of Princeton University) try to recruit Mendel as librarian or book-buyer. The offer was declined with thanks. He could not forsake his familiar headquarters at the Cafe Gluck. Thirty-three years before, an awkward youngster with black down sprouting on his chin and black ringlets hanging over his temples, he had come from Galicia to Vienna, intending to adopt the calling of rabbi; but ere long he forsook the worship of the harsh and jealous Jehovah to devote himself to the more lively and polytheistic cult of books. Then he happened upon the Cafe Gluck, by degrees making it his workshop, headquarters, post-office—his world. Just as an astronomer, alone in an observatory, watches night after night through a telescope the myriads of stars, their mysterious movements, their changeful medley, their extinction and their flaming-up anew, so did Jacob Mendel, seated at his table in the Cafe Gluck, look through his spectacles into the universe of books, a universe that lies above the world of our everyday life, and, like the stellar universe, is full of changing cycles.

It need hardly be said that he was highly esteemed in the Cafe Gluck, whose fame seemed to us to depend far more upon his unofficial professorship than upon the godfathership of the famous musician, Christoph Willibald Gluck, composer of Alcestis and Iphigenia. He belonged to the outfit quite as much as did the old cherry wood counter, the two billiard-tables with their cloth stitched in many places, and the copper coffee-urn. His table was guarded as a sanctuary. His numerous clients and customers were expected to take a drink “For the good of the house,” so that most of the profit of his far-flung knowledge flowed into the big leathern pouch slung round the waist of Deubler, the waiter. In return for being a centre of attraction, Mendel enjoyed many privileges. The telephone was at his service for nothing. He could have his letters directed to the cafe, and his parcels were taken in there. The excellent old woman who looked after the toilet brushed his coat, sewed on buttons, and carried a small bundle of underlinen every week to the wash. He was the only guest who could have a meal sent in from the restaurant; and every morning Herr Standhartner, the proprietor of the cafe, made a point of coming to his table and saying “Good morning!”—though Jacob Mendel, immersed in his books, seldom noticed the greeting. Punctually at half-past seven he arrived, and did not leave till the lights were extinguished. He never spoke to the other guests, never read a newspaper, noticed no changes; and once, when Herr :Standhartner civilly asked him whether he did not find the electric light more agreeable to read by than the malodorous and uncertain kerosene lamps they had replaced, he stared in astonishment at the new incandescent bulbs. Although the installation had necessitated several days’ hammering and bustle, the introduction of the glow-lamps had escaped his notice. Only through the two round apertures of the spectacles, only through these two shining and sucking lenses, did the milliards of black infusorians which were the letters filter into his brain. Whatever else happened in his vicinity was disregarded as unmeaning noise. He had spent more than thirty years of his waking life at this table, reading, comparing, calculating, in a continuous waking dream, interrupted only by intervals of sleep.

A sense of horror overcame me when, looking into the inner room behind the bar of the Cafe Gluck, I saw that the marble-top of the table where Jacob Mendel used to deliver his oracles was now as bare as a tombstone. Grown older since those days, I understood how much disappears when such a man drops out of his place in the world, were it only because, amid the daily increase in hopeless monotony, the unique grows continually more precious. Besides, in my callow youth a profound intuition had made me exceedingly fond of Buchmendel. It was through the observation of him that I had first become aware of the enigmatic fact that supreme achievement and outstanding capacity are only rendered possible by mental concentration, by a sublime monomania that verges on lunacy. Through the living example of this obscure genius of a second-hand book dealer, far more than through the flashes of insight in the works of our poets and other imaginative writers, had been made plain to me the persistent possibility of a pure life of the spirit, of complete absorption in an idea, an ecstasy as absolute as that of an Indian yogi or a medieval monk; and I had learned that this was possible in an electric-lighted cafe and adjoining a telephone box. Yet I had forgotten him, during the war years, and through a kindred immersion in my own work. The sight of the empty table made me ashamed of myself, and at the same time curious about the man who used to sit there.

“What had become of him?” I called the waiter and inquired.

“No, Sir,” he answered, “I’m sorry, but I never heard of Herr Mendel. There is no one of that name among the frequenters of the Cafe Gluck. Perhaps the head-waiter will know.”

“Herr Mendel?” said the head-waiter dubiously, after a moment’s reflection. “No, Sir, never heard of him. Unless you mean Herr Mandl, who has a hardware store in the Florianigasse?”

I had a bitter taste in the mouth, the taste of an irrecoverable past. What is the use of living, when the wind obliterates our footsteps in the sand directly we have gone by? Thirty years, perhaps forty, a man had breathed, read, thought, and spoken within this narrow room;three or four years had elapsed, and there had arisen a new king over Egypt, which knew not Joseph. No one in the Cafe Gluck had ever heard of Jacob Mendel, of Buchmendel. Somewhat pettishly I asked the headwaiter whether I could have a word with Herr Standhartner, or with one of the old Staff.

“Herr Standhartner, who used to own the place? He sold it years ago, and has died since....The former head-waiter? He saved up enough to retire, and lives upon a little property at Krems. No, Sir, all of the old lot are scattered. All except one, indeed, Frau Sporschil, who looks after the toilet. She’s been worked under the late owner, I know. likely to remember your Herr Mendel. hardly know one guest from another.”

I dissented in thought.

“One does not forget a Jacob Mendel so easily!”

What I said was:

“Still, I should like to have a word with Frau Sporschil, if she has a moment to spare.”

The “Toilettenfrau” (known in the Viennese vernacular as the“Schocoladefrau”) soon emerged from the basement, white-haired, run to seed, heavy-footed wiping her chapped hands upon a towel as she came. She had been called away from her task of cleaning up, and was obviously uneasy at being summoned into the strong light of the guestrooms—for common folk in Vienna, where an authoritative tradition has lingered on after the revolution, always think it must be a police matter when their “Superiors” want to question them. She eyed me suspiciously, though humbly. But as soon as I asked her about Jacob Mendel, she braced up, and at the same time her eyes filled with tears.

“Poor Herr Mendel...so there’s still someone who bears him in mind?”

Old people are commonly much moved by anything which recalls the days of their youth and revives the memory of past companionships. I asked if he was still alive.

“Good Lord, no. Poor Herr Mendel must have died five or six years ago. Indeed, I think it’s fully seven since he passed away. Dear, good man that he was; and how long I knew him, more than twentyfive years; he was already sitting every day at his table when I began to work here. It was a shame, it was the way they let him die.”

Growing more and more excited, she asked if I was a relative. Didn’t I know what had happened to him?

“No,” I replied, “And I want you to be good enough to tell me all about it.”

She looked at me timidly, and continued to wipe her damp hands. It was plain to me that she found it embarrassing, with her dirty apron and her tousled white hair, to be standing in the full glare of the cafe. She kept looking round anxiously, to see if one of the waiters might be listening.

“let’s go into the card-room,” I said, “Mendel’s old room. You shall tell me your story there.”

She nodded appreciatively, thankful that I understood and led the way to the inner room, a little shambling in her gait. As I followed, I noticed that the waiters and the guests were staring at us as a strangely assorted pair. We sat down opposite one another at the marble topped table, and there she told me the story of Jacob Mendel’s ruin and death. I will give the tale as nearly as may be in her own words, supplemented here and there by what I learned afterwards from other sources.

“Down to the outbreak of war, and after the war had begun, he continued to come here every morning at half past seven, to sit at this table and study all day just as before. We had the feeling that the fact of a war going on had never entered his mind. Certainly didn’t read the newspapers, and didn’t talk to anyone except about books. He paid no attention when (in the early days of the war, before the authorities put a stop to such things) the newspaper-vendors ran through the streets shouting, ‘Great Battle on the Eastern Front’ (or wherever it might be),‘Horrible Slaughter,’ and so on; when people gathered in knots to talk things over, he kept himself to himself; he did not know that Fritz, the billiard-marker, who fell in one of the first battles, had vanished from this place; he did not know that Herr Standhartner’s son had been taken prisoner by the Russians at Przemysl; never said a word when the bread grew more and more uneatable and when he was given bean-coffee to drink at breakfast and supper instead of hot milk. Once only did he express surprise at the changes, wondering why so few students came to the cafe. There was nothing in the world that mattered to him except his books.

“Then disaster befell him. At eleven one morning, two policemen came, one in uniform, and the other a plainclothes man. The latter showed the red rosette under the lapel of his coat and asked whether there was a man named Jacob Mendel in the house. They went straight to Herr Mendel’s table. The poor man, in his innocence, supposed they had books to sell, or wanted some information; but they told him he was under arrest, and took him away at once. It was a scandal for the cafe. All the guests flocked round Herr Mendel, as he stood between the two police officers, his spectacles pushed up under his hair, staring from each to the other bewildered. Some ventured a protest, saying there must be a mistake—that Herr Mendel was a man who wouldn’t hurt a fly; but the detective was furious, and told them to mind their own business. They took him away, and none of us at the Cafe Gluck saw him again for two years. I never found out what they had against him, but I would take my dying oath that they must have made a mistake. Herr Mendel could never have done anything wrong. It was a crime to treat an innocent man so harshly.”

The excellent Frau Sporschil was right. Our friend Jacob Mendel had done nothing wrong. He had merely (as I subsequently learned) done something incredibly stupid, only explicable to those who knew the man’s peculiarities. The military censorship board, whose function it was to supervise correspondence passing into and out of neutral lands, one day got its clutches upon a postcard written and signed by a certain Jacob Mendel, properly stamped for transmission abroad. This postcard was addressed to Monsieur Jean Labourdaire, Librairie, Quai de Grenelle, Paris—to an enemy country, therefore. The winter complained that the last eight issues of the monthly “Bulletin bibliographique de la France” had failed to reach him, although his annual subscription had been duly paid in advance. The jack-in-office who read this missive (a high-school teacher with a bent for the study of the Romance languages, called up for “War-service” and sent to employ his talents at the censorship board instead of wasting them in the trenches) was astonished by its tenor. “Must be a joke,” he thought. He had to examine some two thousand letters and postcards every week, always on the alert to detect anything that might savour of espionage, but never yet had he chanced upon anything so absurd as that an Austrian subject should unconcernedly drop into one of the imperial and royal letterboxes a postcard addressed to someone in an enemy land, regardless of the trifling detail that since August 1914 the Central Powers had been cut off from Russia on one side and from France on the other by barbed-wire entanglements and a network of ditches in which men armed with rifles and bayonets, machine-guns and artillery, were doing their utmost to exterminate one another like rats. Our schoolmaster enrolled in the Landsturm did not treat this first postcard seriously, but pigeon-holed it as a curiosity not worth talking about to his chief. But a few weeks later there turned up another card, again from Jacob Mendel, this time to John Aldridge, Bookseller, Golden Square, London, asking whether the addressee could send the last few numbers of the “Antiquarian” to an address in Vienna which was clearly stated on the card, The censor in the blue uniform began to feel uneasy. Was his “Class” trying to trick the schoolmaster? Were the cards written in cipher? Possible, anyhow; so the subordinate went over to the major’s desk, clicked his heels together, saluted, and laid the suspicious documents before“Properly constituted authority.” A strange business, certainly. The police were instructed by telephone to see if there actually was a Jacob Mendel at the specified address, and, if so, to bring the fellow along. Within the hour, Mendel had been arrested, and (still stupefied by the shock) brought before the major, who showed him the postcards, and asked him with drill sergeant roughness whether he acknowledged their authorship. Angered at being spoken to so sharply, and still more annoyed because his perusal of an important catalogue had been interrupted, Mendel answered tartly:

“Of course I wrote the cards. That’s my handwriting and signature. Surely one has a right to claim the delivery of a periodical to which one has subscribed?”

The major swung half-round in his swivel-chair and exchanged a meaning glance with the lieutenant seated at the adjoining desk.

“The man must be a double-distilled idiot,” was what they mutely conveyed to one another.

Then the chief took counsel within himself whether he should discharge the offender with a caution, or whether he should treat the case more seriously. In all offices, when such doubts arise, the usual practice is, not to spin a coin, but to send in a report. Thus Pilate washes his hands of responsibility. Even if the report does no good, it can do no harm, and is merely one useless manuscript or typescript added to a million others.

In this instance, however, the decision to send in a report did much harm, alas, to an inoffensive man of genius, for it involved asking a series of questions, and the third of them brought suspicious circumstances to light.

“Your full name?”

“Jacob Mendel.”

“Occupation ?”

“Book-pedlar” (for, as already explained, Mendel had no shop, but only a pedlar’s licence).

“Place of birth?”

Now came the disaster. Mendel’s birthplace was not far from Petrikau. The major raised his eyebrows. Petrikau, or Piotrkov, was across the frontier, in Russian Poland.

“You were born a Russian subject. When did you acquire Austrian nationality? Show me your papers.”

Mendel gazed at the officer uncomprehendingly through his spectacles.

“Papers? Identification papers? I have nothing but my hawker’s licence.”

“What’s’ your nationality, then? Was your father Austrian or Russian?”

Undismayed, Mendel answered:

“A Russian, of course.”

“What about yourself?”

“Wishing to evade Russian military service, I slipped across the frontier thirty-three years ago,

and ever since I have lived in Vienna.”

The matter seemed to the major to be growing worse and worse.

“But didn’t you take steps to become an Austrian subject?”

“Why should I?” countered Mendel. “I never troubled my head about such things.”

“Then you are still a Russian subject?”

Mendel, who was bored by this endless questioning, answered simply:

“Yes, I suppose I am.”

The startled and indignant major threw himself back in his chair with such violence that the wood cracked protestingly. So this was what it had come to! In Vienna, the Austrian capital, at the end of 1915, after Tarnow, when the war was in full blast, after the great offensive, a Russian could walk about unmolested, could write letters to France and England, while the police ignored his machinations. And then the fools who wrote in the newspapers wondered why Conrad von Hotzendorf had not advanced in seven-leagued boots to Warsaw, and the general staff was puzzled because every movement of the troops was immediately blabbed to the Russians.

The lieutenant had sprung to his feet and crossed the room to his chief’s table. What had been an almost friendly conversation took a new turn, and degenerated into a trial.

“Why didn’t you report as an enemy alien directly the war began?”

Mendel, still failing to realize the gravity of his position, answered in his singing Jewish jargon:

“Why should I report? I don’t understand.”

The major regarded this inquiry as a challenge, and asked threateningly:

“Didn’t you read the notices that were posted up everywhere ?”

“No.”

“Didn’t you read the newspapers?”

“No.”

The two officers stared at Jacob Mendel (now sweating with uneasiness) as if the moon had fallen from the sky into their office. Then the telephone buzzed, the typewriters clacked, orderlies ran hither and thither, and Mendel was sent under guard to the nearest barracks, where he was to await transfer to a concentration camp. When he was ordered to follow the two soldiers, he was frankly puzzled, but not seriously perturbed. What could the man with the gold-lace collar and the rough voice have against him? In the upper world of books, where Mendel lived and breathed and his being, there was no warfare, there were no misunderstandings, only an ever-increasing knowledge of words and figures, of book-titles and authors’ names. He walked good-humouredly enough downstairs between the soldiers, whose first charge was to take him to the police station. Not until, there, the books were taken out of his overcoat pockets, and the police impounded the portfolio containing a hundred important memoranda and customers’ addresses, did he lose his temper, and begin to resist and strike blows. They had to tie his hands. In the struggle, his spectacles fell off, and those magical telescopes, without which he could not see into the wonder world of books, were smashed into a thousand pieces. Two days later, insufficiently clad (for his only wrap was a light summer cloak), he was sent to the internment camp for Russian civilians at Komorn.

I have no information as to what Jacob Mendel suffered during these two years of internment, cut off from his beloved books, penniless, among roughly nurtured men, few of whom could read or write, in a huge human dunghill. This must be left to the imagination of those who can grasp the torments of a caged eagle. By degrees, however, our world, grown sober after its fit of drunkenness, has become aware that, of all the cruelties and wanton abuses of power during the war, the most needless and therefore the most inexcusable was this herding together behind barbed-wire fences of thousands upon thousands of persons who had outgrown the age of military service, who had made homes for themselves in a foreign land, and who (believing in the good faith of their hosts) had refrained from exercising the sacred right of hospitality granted even by the Tunguses and Araucanians-the right to flee while time permits. This crime against civilization was committed with the same unthinking hardihood in France, Germany, and Britain, in every belligerent country of our crazy Europe.

Probably Jacob Mendel would, like thousands as innocent as he, have perished in this cattle-pen, have gone stark mad, have succumbed to dysentery, asthenia, softening of the brain, had it not been that, before the worst happened, a chance (typically Austrian) recalled him to the world in which a spiritual life became again possible. Several times after his disappearance, letters from distinguished customers were delivered for him at the Cafe Gluck. Count Schonberg, sometime lord lieutenant of Styria, an enthusiastic collector of works on heraldry; Siegenfeld, the former dean of the theological faculty, who was writing a commentary on the works of St. Augustine; Edler von Pisek, an octogenarian admiral on the retired list, engaged in writing his memoirs—these and other persons of note, wanting information from Buchmendel, had repeatedly addressed communications to him at his familiar haunt, and some of these were duly forwarded to the concentration camp at Komorn. There they fell into the hands of the commanding officer, who happened to be a man of humane disposition, and was astonished to find what notables were among the correspondents of this dirty little Russian Jew, who, half-blind now that his spectacles were broken and he had no money to buy new ones, crouched in a corner like a mole, grey, eyeless, and dumb. A man who had such patrons must be a person of importance, whatever he looked like. The C.O. therefore read the letters to the short-sighted Mendel, and penned answers for him to sign—answers which were mainly requests that influence should be exercised on his behalf. The spell worked, for these correspondents had the solidarity of collectors. Joining forces and pulling strings they were able (giving guarantees for the “Enemy alien’s” good behaviour) to secure leave for Buchmendel’s return to Vienna in 1917, after more than two years at Komorn—on the condition that he should report daily to the police. The proviso mattered little. He was a free man once more, free to take up his quarters in his old attic, free to handle books again, free (above all) to return to his table in the Cafe Gluck. I can describe the return from the underworld of the camp in the good Frau Sporschil’s own words:

“One day—Jesus, Mary, Joseph; I could hardly believe my eyes—the door opened (you remember the way he had) little wider than a crack, and through this opening he sidled, poor Herr Mendel. He was wearing a tattered and much-darned military cloak, and his head was covered by what had perhaps once been a hat thrown away by the owner as past use. No collar. His face looked like a death’s head, so haggard it was, and his hair was pitifully thin. But he came in as if nothing had happened, went straight to his table, and took off his cloak, not briskly as of old, for he panted with the exertion. Nor had he any books with him. He just sat there without a word, staring straight in front of him with hollow, expressionless eyes. Only by degrees, after we had brought him the big bundle of printed matter which had arrived for him from Germany, did he begin to read again: But he was never the same man.”

No, he was never the same man, not now the miraculum mundi, the magical walking book-catalogue. All who saw him in those days told me the same pitiful story. Something had gone irrecoverably wrong;he was broken; the blood-red comet of the war had burst into the remote, calm atmosphere of his bookish world. His eyes, accustomed for decades to look at nothing but print, must have seen terrible sights in the wire-fenced human stockyard, for the eyes that had formerly been so alert and full of ironical gleams were now almost completely veiled by the inert lids, and looked sleepy and red-bordered behind the carefully repaired spectacle-frames. Worse still, a cog must have broken somewhere in the marvellous machinery of his memory, so that the working of the whole was impaired; for so delicate is the structure of the brain (a sort of switchboard made of the most fragile substances, and as easily jarred as are all instruments of precision) that a blocked arteriole, a congested bundle of nerve-fibres, a fatigued group of cells, even a displaced molecule, may put the apparatus out of gear and make harmonious working impossible. In Mendel’s memory, the keyboard of knowledge, the keys were stiff, or—to use psychological terminology—the associations were impaired. When, now and again, someone came to ask for information, Jacob stared blankly at the inquirer, failing to understand the question, and even forgetting it before he had found the answer. Mendel was no longer Buchmendel, just as the world was no longer the world. He could not now become wholly absorbed in his reading, did not rock as of old when he read, but sat bolt upright, his glasses turned mechanically towards the printed page, but perhaps not reading at all, and only sunk in a reverie. Often, said Frau Sporschil, his head would drop on to his book and he would fall asleep in the daytime, or he would gaze hour after hour at the stinking acetylene lamp which (in the days of the coal famine) had replaced the electric lighting. No, Mendel was no longer Buchmendel, no longer the eighth wonder of the world, but a weary, worn-out, though still breathing, useless bundle of beard and ragged garments, which sat, as futile as a potato-bogle, where of old the Pythian oracle had sat; no longer the glory of the Cafe Gluck, but a shameful scarecrow, evil-smelling, a parasite.

That was the impression he produced upon the new proprietor, Florian Gurtner from Retz, who (a successful profiteer in flour and butter) had cajoled Standhartner into selling him the Cafe Gluck for eighty thousand rapidly depreciating paper crowns. He took everything into his hard peasant grip, hastily arranged to have the old place redecorated, bought fine-looking satin-covered seats, installed a marble porch, an was in negotiation with his next-door neighbour to buy a place where he could extend the cafe into a dancing-hall. Naturally while he was making these embellishments, he was not best pleased by the parasitic encumbrance of Jacob Mendel, a filthy old Galician Jew, who had been in trouble with the authorities during the war, was still to be regarded as an “Enemy alien,” and, while occupying a table from morning till night, consumed no more than two cups of coffee and four or five rolls. Standhartner, indeed, had put in a word for this guest of long standing, had explained that Mendel was a person of note, and, in the stock-taking, had handed him over as having a permanent lien upon the establishment, but as an asset rather than a liability. Florian Gurtner, however, had brought into the cafe, not only new furniture, and an upto-date cash register, but also the profit-making and hard temper of the post-war era, and awaited the first pretext for ejecting from his smart coffee-house the last troublesome vestige of suburban shabbiness.

A good excuse was not slow to present itself. Jacob Mendel was impoverished to the last degree. Such banknotes as had been left to him had crumbled away to nothing during the inflation period; his regular clientele had been killed, ruined, or dispersed. When he tried to resume his early trade of book-pedlar, calling from door to door to buy and to sell, he found that he lacked strength to carry books up and down stairs. A hundred little signs showed him to be a pauper. Seldom, now, did he have a midday meal sent in from the restaurant, and he began to run up a score at the Cafe Gluck for his modest breakfast and supper. Once his payments were as much as three weeks overdue. Were it only for this reason, the head-waiter wanted Gurtner to “Give Mendel the sack.” But Frau Sporschil intervened, and stood surety for the debtor. What was due could be stopped out of her wages!

This staved off disaster for a while, but worse was to come. For some time the head-waiter had noticed that rolls were disappearing faster than the tally would account for. Naturally suspicion fell upon Mendel, who was known to be six months in debt to the tottering old porter whose services he still needed. The head-waiter, hidden behind the stove, was able, two days later, to catch Mendel red-handed. The unwelcome guest had stolen from his seat in the card-room, crept behind the counter in the front room, taken two rolls from the bread basket, returned to the card-room, and hungrily devoured them. When settling-up at the end of the day, he said he had only had coffee; no rolls. The source of wastage had been traced, and the waiter reported his discovery to the proprietor. Herr Gurtner, delighted to have so good an excuse for getting rid of Mendel, made a scene, openly accused him of theft, and declared that nothing but the goodness of his own heart prevented his sending for the police.

“But after this,” said Florian, “You’ll kindly take yourself off for good and all. We don’t want to see your face again at the Cafe Gluck.”

Jacob Mendel trembled, but made no reply. Abandoning his poor belongings, he departed without a word.

“It was ghastly,” said Frau Sporschil. “Never shall I forget the sight. He stood up, his spectacles pushed on to his forehead, and his face white as a sheet. He did not even stop to put on his cloak, although it was January, and very cold. You’ll remember that severe winter, just after the war. In his fright, he left the book he was reading open upon the table. I did not notice it at first, and then, when I wanted to pick it up and take it after him, he had already stumbled out through the doorway. I was afraid to follow him into the street, for Herr Gurtner was standing at the door and shouting at him, so that a crowd had gathered. Yet I felt ashamed to the depths of my soul. Such a thing would never have happened under the old master. Herr Standhartner would not have driven Herr Mendel away for pinching one or two rolls when he was hungry, but would have let him have as many as he wanted for nothing,to the end of his days. Since the war, people seem to have grown heartless. Drive away a man who had been a guest daily for so many, many years. Shameful! I should not like to have to answer before God for such cruelty!”

The good woman had grown excited, and, with the passionate garrulousness of old age, she kept on repeating how shameful it was, and that nothing of the sort would have happened if Herr Standhartner had not sold the business. In the end I tried to stop the flow by asking her what had happened to Mendel, and whether she had ever seen him again. These questions excited her yet more.

“Day after day, when I passed his table, it gave me the creeps, as you will easily understand. Each time I thought to myself: ‘where can he have got to, poor Herr Mendel?’ Had I known where he lived, I would have called and taken him something nice and hot to eat-for where could he get the money to cook food and warm his room? As far as I knew, he had no kinsfolk in the wide world. When, after a long time, I had heard nothing about him, I began to believe that it must be all up with him, and that I should never see him again. I had made up my mind to have a mass said for the peace of his soul, knowing him to be a good man, after twenty-five years’ acquaintance.

“At length one day in February, at half-past seven in the morning, when I was cleaning the windows, the door opened, and in came Herr Mendel. Generally, as you know, he sidled in, looking confused, and not ‘quite all there’; but this time, somehow, it was different. I noticed at once the strange look in his eyes; they were sparkling, and he rolled them this way and that, as if to see everything at once; as for his appearance, he seemed nothing but beard and skin and bone. Instantly it crossed my mind: ‘He’s forgotten all that happened last time he was here; it’s his way to go about like a sleepwalker noticing nothing; he doesn’t remember about the rolls, and how shamefully Herr Gurtner ordered him out of the place, half in mind to set the police on him.’ Thank goodness, Herr Gurtner hadn’t come yet, and the head-waiter was drinking coffee. I ran up to Herr Mendel, meaning to tell him he’d better make himself scarce, for otherwise that ruffian” [she looked round timidly to see if we were overheard, and hastily amended her phrase], “Herr Gurtner, I mean, would only have him thrown into the street once more. ‘Herr Mendel,’ I began. He started, and looked at me. In that very moment (it was dreadful), he must have remembered the whole thing, for he almost collapsed, and began to tremble, not his fingers only, but to shiver and shake from head to foot. Hastily he stepped back into the street, and fell in a heap on the pavement as soon as he was outside the door. We telephoned for the ambulance, and they carried him off to hospital, the nurse who came saying he had high fever directly she touched him. He died that evening. ‘double pneumonia,’ the doctor said, and that he never recovered consciousness—could not have been fully conscious when he came to the Cafe Gluck. As I said, he had entered like a man walking in his sleep. The table where he had sat day after day for thirty-six years drew him back to it like a home.”

Frau Sporschil and I went on talking about him for a long time, the two last persons to remember this strange creature, Buchmendel:I to whom in youth the book-pedlar from Galicia had given the first revelation of a life wholly devoted to the things of the spirit; she, the poor old woman who was caretaker of a cafe-toilet, who had never read a book in her life, and whose only tie with this strangely matched comrade in her subordinate, poverty-stricken world had been that for twenty-five years she had brushed his overcoat and had sewn on buttons for him. We, too, might have been considered strangely assorted, but Frau Sporschil and I got on very well together, linked, as we sat at the forsaken marble topped table, by our common memories of the shade our talk had conjured up—for joint memories, and above all loving memories, always establish a tie. Suddenly, while in the full stream of talk, she exclaimed:

“lord Jesus, how forgetful I am. I still have the book he left on the table the evening Herr Gurtner gave him the key of the street. I didn’t know where to take it. Afterwards, when no one appeared to claim it, I ventured to keep it as a souvenir. You don’t think it wrong of me, Sir?”

She went to a locker where she stored some of the requisites for her job: and produced the volume for my inspection. I found it hard to repress a smile, for I was face to face with one of life’s little ironies. It was the second volume of Hayn’s Bibliotheca Germanorum erotica et curiosa, a compendium of gallant literature known to every bookcollector. “Habent sua fata libelli!” This scabrous publication, as legacy of the vanished magician had fallen into toil worn hands which had perhaps never held any other printed work than a prayer-book. Maybe I was not wholly successful in controlling my mirth, for the expression on my race seemed to perplex the worthy soul, and once more she said:

“You don t think it wrong of me to keep it, Sir?”

I shook her cordially by the hand.

“Keep it, and welcome,” I said. “I am absolutely sure that our old friend Mendel would be only too delighted to know that someone among the many thousands he has provided with books, cherishes his memory.”

Then I took my departure, feeling a trifle ashamed when I compared myself with this excellent old woman, who, so simply and so humanely, had fostered the memory of the dead scholar. For she, uncultured though she was, had at least preserved a book as a memento;whereas I, a man of education and a writer, had completely forgotten Buchmendel for years—I, who at least should have known that one only makes books in order to keep in touch with one’s fellows after one has ceased to breathe, and thus to defend oneself against the inexorable fate of all that lives—transitoriness and oblivion.

LEPORELLA

CRESCENTIA ANNA ALOISIA FINKENHUBER was thirty-nine years of age, and had been born (an illegitimate child) in a mountain hamlet not far from Innsbruck. Under the rubric “Special Peculiarities”in her identity paper as servant-maid was drawn a line signifying“None”; but if the officials who fill in such documents were obliged to enter characterological details, there would certainly have been written here: “looks like an over-driven, bony, lean mountain nag.” Beyond question there was something horse-like in the aspect of the cumbrous lower lip; in the elongated and sharply bounded oval of the brownish visage; in the dull eyes almost denuded of lashes; and, above all, in the coarse hair, plastered on to the forehead with pomade. Her gait, too, was as stiff and reluctant as that of a mule, one of those unhappy beasts which winter after summer and summer after winter, have to carry loads of wood up and down the same rough and stony or muddy track way. When freed from the halter of toil, Crescenz, clasping her bony fingers and sticking out her elbows in ungainly fashion, would usually sit down and fall into a doze, no more lightened by intelligence than that of one of the aforesaid mules standing patiently in its stable when the day’s work was done. Everything about her was hard, wooden and heavy. Thought, with her, was a slow process. A new idea made its way into her mind with much difficulty, as if it had to traverse the meshes of a choked sieve; but, once she had grasped it, she retained it as a miser clings to a coin. She never read, not even the newspaper or her prayerbook. Writing was a great labour to her, and the awkwardly-formed letters in her marketing-book reminded one of her own clumsy and angular figure, which was utterly lacking in feminine charm. As hard as her bones, her forehead, her hips, and her knuckles, was her voice, which, despite the guttural Tyrolese accent, creaked like the hinges of a rusty iron gate. Nor was this rustiness surprising, for Crescenz never uttered a superfluous word. No one had seen her laugh. In this respect, likewise, she resembled the lower animals; for more cruel even than the denial of speech to those we term “Dumb beasts” is the denial of laughter, that free and joyful vent to the emotions.

Being a bastard, she had been brought up at the charge of the community, and at the age of twelve had been sent out to service, at first as maid-of-all-work in a restaurant; but then, having gained a good character by her indomitable and almost bestial diligence, as cook-general to a second-rate hotel on one of the main routes of travel. Rising daily at five, Crescenz slaved, swept, scrubbed, did the rooms, lighted fires, cooked, kneaded and baked, washed and ironed, till late at night. She never asked for a day out; never went into the street, except to church and back. The kitchen-fire was her sun, and her only acquaintance with the forest came from splitting thousands upon thousands of billets every year in order to feed the flames.

Men did not trouble her: maybe because, as previously explained, twenty-five years spent as a robot had rubbed off the very inadequate feminine graces which Mother Nature had bestowed on her; maybe because she so fiercely repelled any amorous advances. Her only pleasure was found in the amassing of money, for she had the magpie hoarding-instincts of the peasant, and dreaded lest, when she grew old, she would once more be forced to accept the unwelcome lot of being dependent upon the community. The bitter bread of public charity would have choked her.

Nothing but the lust for gain had, when she was thirty-seven lured this dull being from her Tyrolese homeland. The manageress of an employment agency, spending a summer holiday in the Tyrol, was amazed by Crescenz’s berserker rage for work, and told her that in Vienna she could get twice her present earnings.

On the railway journey, Crescenz maintained her usual taciturnity, seated in solemn silence while holding in her lap the wicker basket which contained all her worldly possessions, though her knees ached beneath its weight. Some of her fellow-travellers, friendly and companionable, offered to put it in the rack, but the dour woman snapped a refusal, for, in her peasant mind, cheating and theft were the only associations with the great city to which she was journeying. In Vienna it was some days before she could make her way alone to market, for at first the traffic frightened her almost out of her poor wits. But once she had grown familiar with the four streets she had to traverse, she became independent, and trotted safely to the market and back carrying a basket on her arm. In her new place, she swept, scrubbed, lighted the fires, and did the rooms, just as before. At nine, the customary hour in the Tyrol, she went to bed, and slept like an animal with her mouth wide open, until she was called in the morning. No one could tell whether she liked her new situation; perhaps she herself did not know. Her reserve was unbroken. She acknowledged orders with a monosyllabic “Right” ; or, if in a refractory mood with a shrug of the shoulders. She ignored her fellow-servants, being, as a rule absolutely indifferent to their inclination to tease and to make fun of her. Once only, when another maid, a cheerful Viennese girl, persistently mocked her Tyrolese accent, Crescenz lost patience. In a fury she snatched a burning log from the stove, and, brandishing this dangerous weapon, rushed at her tormentress, who fled shrieking with dismay. Thenceforward no one ventured to gibe.

Every Sunday morning, dressed in her voluminous skirt and wearing a Tyrolese head-dress, she went to Mass. Once only, being given a day off, she tried a walk through Vienna. She would not take a tram, and her peregrinations in the bewildering streets brought her, at length, to the Danube. After staring at the current as if it were a familiar friend, she turned about and retraced her steps, sedulously avoiding the busier highways. This first excursion must have been a disappointment, for it was never repeated. She preferred to spend her free Sundays doing needlework, or sitting idly at a window. Thus her coming to the metropolis wrought no change in the treadmill of her life, except that at the end of each month four blue bank notes instead of two were put into her toilworn, withered, and calloused hands. These notes were always suspiciously scrutinized. Each was separately folded and smoothed out, before being stacked with the others and laid to rest in the yellow box of carved wood which she had brought with her from the village. This clumsy little treasure-chest contained the innermost purpose of her life.At night she always had the key under her pillow. No one in the house knew where it was kept in the daytime.

Such were the characteristics of this weird human being (for“Human being” we must call her, although the human attributes were queerly obscured); and perhaps a more normal woman could not have long endured to stay as a servant in the remarkable household of young Baron von Ledersheim. The atmosphere was so quarrelsome that in general the domestics were quick to give notice. The hysterical scoldings of their mistress were more than they could bear. The elderly daughter of an more extremely rich manufacturer, she had made the baron’s acquaintance at a health-resort. Though he was many years younger than herself, and his birth was nothing to boast of, while he was up to his ears in debt he was a handsome fellow, with distinguished manners and willing enough to marry money. Things were speedily arranged between the pair, notwithstanding the strenuous opposition of the lady’s parents, who were on the look-out for more solid advantages than Baron von Ledersheim could offer. Before the honeymoon was over, Baroness von Ledersheim was to learn that her father and mother had been right. The young husband had by no means finished sowing his wild oats, and was more interested in this form of agriculture than in the fulfillment of his conjugal duties. Nor had he even made a clean breast of it as to the amount of his debts.

Good-natured in a way, a pleasant companion like most libertines, he had no principles, and considered any attempt to regulate his expenditure to be the outcome of plebeian prejudices. The husband wanted to remain a dissolute spendthrift, after marriage as before; the wife wanted an orderly domestic life such as she had been used to in her parental home at Essen. This bourgeoisdom jarred on his aristocratic nerves. Since, wealthy though she was, she tried to draw the pursestrings tight, and refused to finance his pet scheme of building and running a racing-stable, his response to her “Meanness” was, as far as husbandly relations went, to ignore his North-German bride, whose dictatorial ways and harsh voice became increasingly offensive to him. As the saying goes, he “Shelved” her, without obvious brutality, but in a way which caused her grievous disappointment. When she reproached him he listened courteously and with apparent sympathy, but as soon as the sermon was over he blew away her exhortations as unconcernedly as the smoke of his cigarette, and continued to follow his own bent. This seeming amiability was more galling than open resistance. Since she was disarmed by his unfailing civility, her suppressed wrath found vent in other directions, and, above all, in railing at the servants, with reason or without. In less than two years, she had changed her domestic staff no less than sixteen times, having once used violence, and had to pay heavy compensation in order to avoid a lawsuit and public scandal.

Crescenz was the only one of the servants who could endure these storms of scolding unmoved, and stood stolidly while they raged, looking like a cab-horse in the rain. She never took sides, was unaffected by the frequent changes in the staff, hardly seemed to notice that her associates in the servants’ hall varied continually in name, aspect, and character. For she never passed the time of day with her workmates, was indifferent to the passionate slamming of doors, the frequent interruptions at mealtimes, her mistress’s fainting-fits and hysterical outbursts. She went on with her daily marketing expeditions and her work in the kitchen, unconcerned as to anything that happened outside the daily round of toil. Hard and insensitive as a flail, she threshed on as day followed day, and two years of her life in the metropolis passed by without effecting the slightest change in her mentality. As far as externals were concerned, the only difference to be noticed was that the pile of blue banknotes in her cash box had grown thicker by an inch;and that, when (licking her finger to facilitate the process) she counted them at the second year’s end, she found she was very close to the aim of her desire, the magical figure of a thousand.

But chance works with diamond-drills; and fate, cunning of hand, often produces strange modifications even in the rockiest of natures. In Crescenz’s case the manifest cause of change was as commonplace as she herself seemed. At the close of a ten-year cycle, the government was taking a new census and a complicated census-paper had to be filled in every dwelling-home. The baron, who had good reason to know that most of his domestics were unskilled in the use of the pen, decided to tabulate the information himself, and, in due course, Crescenz was summoned to his writing-table. When he asked her full name, age, and birthplace, the first item and the third proved of unexpected interest to the master of the house. A keen sportsman, he had often stayed with an old college-friend who was the owner of a Tyrolese shooting; and he had once done a fortnight’s mountaineering in pursuit of chamois, accompanied by a guide, Finkenhuber by name, who turned out to have been Crescenz’s uncle. Ledersheim had taken a fancy to the man. This fact, and his knowledge of the cook’s native village, led to a conversation between master and maid, with the resulting further disclosure that, in the inn where she had formerly worked, the baron had once partaken of an extraordinarily good haunch of venison. Trifling matters, no doubt; but the long arm of coincidence handles such trifles, and to Crescenz who for the first time encountered in Vienna a person acquainted with her home, they seemed wonderful. Her face flushed with unwonted excitement, she stood in front of the baron, curtseying in ungainly fashion, and highly flattered when he proceeded to crack jokes with her, asking her with an assumed Tyrolese accent, whether she knew how to yodel—and the like. At length entering into the spirit of the game, he spanked her with peasant familiarity on her hard behind, saying: “Be off with you now, my good Cenzi, and let me get on with my job; but take these two extra crowns with you because you hail from the Zillertal.”

The master had not shown any deep feeling. Nothing, one might have thought, to stir the old maid to the depths. But on her dull and unimpressionable nature those few minutes’ talk had the effect of a stone thrown into a stagnant pool, forming circular waves which moved, slowly widening, to lap upon the margin of consciousness. Not for years upon years had the taciturn creature had any sort of personal relations with one of her fellows; and it seemed to her almost uncanny that the first to show a friendly interest in her, from among the millions who lived in this wilderness of bricks and mortar, should be a man who knew her own mountains, and had actually eaten venison cooked there by her own hands. Super added came the clout upon the backside, which, to her peasant mind was a laconic invitation to the woman in her. Even though Crescenz did not make so bold as to fancy that the elegantly dressed and distinguished gentleman actually coveted her wizened body, still the physical familiarity stirred her slumbering senses.

Thus, thanks to this encounter, there began in the woman’s inmost being a transformation, obscure at the outset, but growing continually more definite—and culminating in a new feeling, akin to that sudden recognition which leads a dog to single out one from among the innumerable bipeds that surround it, and to look upon him thenceforward as master, nay as god. The dog thus transformed follows its master everywhere, wriggles with delight and wags a friendly tail when meeting him again after an absence, obeys, fetches, and carries with slavish subservience. Into the narrow chambers of Crescenz’s mind, which had hitherto been completely filled with a bare half-dozen of ideas—money, marketing, kitchen-fire, church, and bed—there had suddenly been thrust a new element, which demanded accommodation, and roughly elbowed the previous occupants aside. With the “Havingness” that makes the peasant so reluctant to surrender anything that has once been gripped, she interpolated this new element sedulously into the confused world of her lethargic impulses. It was a little while, of course, before the change in her habits became fully manifest, and the initial signs of the transformation were obscure. For instance, she brushed the baron’s clothes and cleaned his shoes with meticulous care, while leaving the baroness’s dresses and footgear to the lady’s maid to look after. Then she would often scurry forth into the hall the instant she heard the baron’s latch-key in the lock, eager to relieve him of hat, coat, and stick. In the kitchen, she worked harder than ever, and would sometimes laboriously ask her way to the big market, in search of a haunch of venison. She also began to pay more attention to the niceties of dress.

A week or two elapsed before this first shoot of her new feelings showed its leaves plainly above the ground. Several more weeks were needed until a second shoot pushed up from the seedling, and assumed a definite tint. The second feeling was the obvious complement of the first, hatred for the baroness, for the wife who could live with the baron, sleep with him, speak to him whenever she pleased, but nevertheless did not revere the master as she herself, Cenzi, did. It may have been because (having now learned to take notice) she had been shocked by one of the scenes in which the infuriated wife “Slanged” her husband unmercifully, or it may have been because she had become aware how painfully the cold and arrogant manners of the North German mistress contrasted with the geniality of the Viennese master of the house—in any case Crescenz began, in manifold ways, to show that she had conceived a spite against the baroness. Brigitta von Ledersheim had always to ring twice, at least, before Crescenz would deign to answer the bell; and then the maid came with irritating slowness and obvious reluctance. Her raised shoulders produced the same impression as the turning back of its ears by a stubborn and vicious horse, a conviction of insuperable antagonism. She said nothing in response to her mistress’s orders, so that the baroness never knew whether she had been understood and would be obeyed. A repetition produced only a contemptuous nod, or a “I heard you all right,” in her broad peasant accent. Again, just before a visit to the theater, when the mistress was dressing, the key of a drawer containing some indispensable trinket would have gone astray—to be discovered in a corner of the room after half an hour’s frantic search. Crescenz made a point of failing to deliver telephone messages to the baroness, and when scolded for the omission would pertly reply “I just forgot.” She never looked her mistress squarely in the face, perhaps, from fear lest her loathing should peep out.

Meanwhile these domestic discomforts led to continually more violent scenes between husband and wife—for there can be little doubt that the maid’s state of mind and uncivil manners reacted on the mistress to increase the latter’s uncontrol. Brigitta’s nerves had been overstrained by too long a period of spinsterhood; she had been further embittered by her husband’s neglect and by her failure to hit it off even with her servants; so that she now grew more and more unbalanced. The bromides and the veronal she took to relieve insomnia made matters worse; but no one sympathized with the poor woman in her nervous crises, or tried to help her to live more hygienically and to regain selfmastery. A neurologist whom she consulted advised a couple of months’ stay in a sanatorium, and her husband endorsed the proposal with such injudicious enthusiasm that the baroness at first refused to consider it. In the end, however, she gave way. She would take the lady’s maid with her, while Crescenz would be left alone to look after the baron in the roomy flat.

The news that the care of her beloved master was to be left wholly in her hands had an electrifying effect on Crescenz. She seemed to have been given the contents of a magic phial—a philtre which stirred the lees of her undischarged passions and modified her behaviour. Her limbs were no longer stiff and ungainly; she moved lightly, easily, and swiftly. When the time came for the baroness’s journey, the maid ran from room to room, packed the trunks without waiting to be told, shouldered them like a porter, and carried them down to the cab. When, late in the evening, the baron returned from seeing his wife off at the station, handed hat and overcoat to the expectant Crescenz, and, with a sigh of relief, said: “Well, I’ve got her safely away!”—a remarkable thing happened. Crescenz, as already explained, resembled the lower animals, in that she never laughed. But now her lips were animated by an unfamiliar phenomenon. Her mouth broadened into a grin so unrestrained that Ledersheim, to whom the awkward servant maid’s expression of countenance came as a painful surprise, felt ashamed of having been so open with a menial, and went into his bedroom without saying another word.

The discomfort lasted for a fleeting moment, and during the next few days master and maidservant were united in the enjoyment of a precious sense of quietude and agreeable ease. The wife’s exit from the scene had cleared the atmosphere. Rudolf freed from the burden of responsibility, and from the perpetual risk of being called to account for his movements came home late next evening, and Crescenz’s silent adoration was a welcome contrast to the loquacious inquisitiveness with which Brigitta was wont to receive him. Crescenz devoted herself to her work with more than customary zeal, got up earlier than usual, polished the furniture till you could see your face in it, was never satisfied with the brightness of the door-handles, provided exceptionally tasty meals—and, greatly to the baron’s surprise, served them on a dinner-set which was supposed to be kept for great occasions. Though as a rule he was blind to such matters, he could not but notice the peculiar and delicate attentions of this strange maidservant, and, being a good-natured fellow at bottom, he expressed his gratification. He praised her culinary skill, and, in a day or two, when his birthday came round and Crescenz had made him a jam tart in which the pastry was decorated with his initials and the family coat-of-arms, he said with a smile: “You are spoiling me, Cenzi. But what the devil shall I do when the mistress comes home again?”

To the inhabitants of other lands, such free and easy ways, such want of reserve in the remarks of a master to a servant, may seem incredible, but there was nothing out of the ordinary in them as far as pre-war Austria was concerned. They were, in fact, manifestations of the boundless contempt of the aristocracy for the mob, a contempt in witness whereof the gentry rode with a loose rein. Just as an archduke, stationed in some out-of-the-way Galician town, would send his orderly to the brothel to fetch him a bedfellow, and having satisfied his desires, would hand the girl over to the underling—regardless of the salacious gossip that would ensue when the cits got wind of the affair—so a man of title who was out shooting would be more inclined to hobnob over luncheon with his loader or his groom, than to be friendly with a university professor or a wealthy man of business. But these ostensibly democratic relationships, easy-going though they seemed, must not be taken at their face value; the master remained the master, and knew how to keep his distance once more, the instant he rose from his meal. Since, however, the minor gentry were always inclined to ape the manners of the feudal aristocracy, the baron made no bones about speaking derogatorily of his wife to a country wench who was in her service, assured that she would never give him away but failing to realize what a profound impression his words were producing in her simple mind.

All the same, he imposed some vestiges of restraint upon his tongue and his general behaviour for a few days. Then feeling confident that he could trust her, he began, unheeding dangerous possibilities, to resume bachelor habits. This was his own house, his wife was away, and he could amuse himself as he pleased. One day towards the close of the first week he spent as a grasswidower, he rang for Crescenz, and,as if the matter were of no moment, told her that that evening she was to lay a cold supper for two, and to go to bed without waiting up for his return. He would himself see to everything when he came in.

“Very good, Sir,” answered Crescenz, without the smallest change of expression to show that she understood what lay behind. But that she was sharper of wit than she seemed was plain to the amused Rudolf when, returning towards midnight accompanied by one of the young ladies of the opera, he found the supper-table decked with flowers;and, on going into his bedroom, discovered, not only that his own bed had been made ready as usual, but that the adjoining bed had been invitingly turned down, and that one of his wife’s silk nightgowns and her slippers were laid out ready for use. The husband whose marriage vows sat so lightly on his conscience could not but laugh at the length to which this extraordinary abigail was prepared to go in her attentions. Thenceforward she was his acknowledged confederate, and next morning he had no hesitation in ringing for Crescenz to act as lady’s maid to his light-of-love.

It was at this juncture that Crescenz was rechristened. The budding diva was understudy for the role of Donna Elvira, and found it congenial to call her lover Don Juan. On her next visit to the flat, she said merrily:

“Don Juan, I wish you’d send for that Leporella of yours.”

The name took his fancy, were it only for the reason that it was too grotesquely misapplicable to the withered Tyrolese peasantwoman, and from that time on he always addressed her as Leporella. Crescenz, though startled at first by her new appellation, accepted it as a compliment. She knew nothing of its Don Giovannesque associations, but it was euphonious to her untutored ears and her vanity was tickled that her master should give her a pet-name. Whenever she heard the impudent call “leporella!” her thin lips parted in a smile that showed her horse-like teeth; and, obsequiously, she hastened to fulfil the commands of her liege lord.

The name had been lightly chosen, and I have called it misapplicable. Nevertheless, it hit the mark, for “leporella,” like her namesake Leporello, was a sympathetic accomplice. An old maid who had known nothing of love, she took a vicarious pride in her lusty young master’s adventures. No matter whether the delight came from knowing that the detested baroness’s bed was dishonoured almost every night by some new illicit occupant, or from an imaginary participation in these sensuous pleasures—there could be no question as to its existence. Her bony frame, wasted and wizened by decades of arduous toil until it had been almost completely desexualized, thrilled with bawdy pleasure at sight of a second and then a third fleeting occupant of Baroness von Ledersheim’s rightful couch. Her confederateship and the unfamiliar erotic atmosphere were powerful stimulants to her slumbering senses. Crescenz became really and truly Leporella, became, like Leporello in Da Ponte’s libretto, vigorous and sprightly. Un-accustomed qualities, stirred up from the depths by this ardent co-partnership came to the surface, petty wiles and artifices, an inclination to spy and eavesdrop. She listened at the door, squinted through the keyhole, buzzed eagerly hither and thither, until her curiosity and alertness transformed what had been little better than an automaton into living flesh and blood. To the astonishment of the neighbours, Crescenz became sociable;she gossiped with the servants, cracked jokes with the postman, began to talk of miscellaneous subjects with the market-women. Then, one evening, when the lights in the attic (where the servants’ quarters were) had been extinguished, the maids in the rooms on the opposite side of the court heard a remarkable humming from her window usually so silent. Clumsily, mezzo voce, she was singing one of those folk-songs which dairymaids sing in Alpine pastures. Monotonously she produced the air, with untrained lips and vocal cords, like a child fingering the keys of a neglected piano-the effect being simultaneously touching and repulsive. Not since early youth had she tried to sing, but now something that came from the darkness of forgotten years seemed to be struggling towards the light.

This extraordinary transformation was least obvious to the man who had brought it about—for who troubles to notice his own shadow? We see, of course, with half an eye, how it dogs our footsteps, or sometimes runs in advance (like a wish of which we are not yet fully aware); but how rarely do we heed its parody of our form, or recognize in it a caricature of our personality. All that Ledersheim noticed in Crescenz was that she seemed ever ready to serve him diligently, silently, and self-sacrificingly. Her mute worship was agreeable to him. From time to time, as if patting a dog, he said a friendly word or two; sometimes he jested with her, took her good-naturedly by the ear, gave her a banknote or a theatre ticket-trifles he extracted from his waistcoat-pocket, but, for her, treasures of inestimable value, which she hoarded as relics in her cashbox. Gradually it became a habit with him to think aloud in her presence, and even to entrust her with difficult commissions; and the more marked these signs of his confidence, the more slavish became her devotion. She tried to anticipate his desires;to enter into his being as the executant of his will; to see with his eyes, hear with his ears; to enjoy his pleasures and share in his conquests. She beamed when a new bedfellow accompanied him on his return, and was visibly disappointed if he came back alone. Her brain now worked as unceasingly as aforetime her hands had done, and a new light of understanding sparkled in her eyes. The overdriven beast of burden had developed into a human being; though still reserved, tight-lipped, crafty, and dangerous, meditative and much occupied, restless and rancorous.

Once, when the baron came home earlier than usual, he was amazed on entering the hall to hear from behind the door of the kitchen, where inviolable silence usually prevailed, the noise of sniggering. The door was half-open, and in the aperture Leporella showed herself, rubbing her hands on her apron, simultaneously cheeky and embarrassed.

“Beg pardon, Sir, for being so free,” she said, with downcast eyes;“But I’ve got the pastrycook’s daughter in there; she’s such a pretty girl, and she’d be main glad to make your acquaintance.”

Ledersheim stared at Crescenz, not knowing whether to reject these impudent advances forthwith, or whether to grasp at the skirts of happy chance and accept the impromptu bawd’s offer. In the end, desire stirred within him, and got the upper hand.

“let’s have a look at the beauty,” he replied.

The girl, a fair-haired hussy of sixteen, whom Leporella had limed with flattering tales, emerged from the kitchen, blushing and giggling, and, revolving awkwardly showed off her charms to the stylish gentleman whom she had often furtively admired from the shop across the way. The baron was pleased with her looks, and invited her to drink tea with him in his room. She glanced towards Crescenz for a pointer, but Crescenz had vanished, and the pastrycook’s daughter, thus inveigled into an adventure, inquisitive and excited (for all her blushes and embarrassment), felt she had no option out to accept the invitation.“Will you walk into my parlour?” said the spider to the fly!

But nature makes no leaps. Although, under stress of a warped passion, a measure of spiritual mobility had resulted in this ossified personality, the new but limited thought-processes did not enable Crescenz to look ahead. She remained as unimaginative as the lower animals, whose actions are guided by short-sighted instincts. Concerned only with the longing to serve the master whom she loved with the fidelity of a dog, she completely forgot the absent wife. It came, therefore, like a bolt from the blue when, one morning the baron with knitted brows and holding a letter in his hand entered the kitchen and told her to devote the day to a general house-cleaning, for next afternoon his wife would be back from the sanatorium. Crescenz turned livid at the news, standing open-mouthed with the horrified aspect of one who has been stabbed. She stared dumbly at her master, until the baron, wishing her to pull herself together, said:

“You don’t look best pleased Cenzi; but there’s nothing we can do about the matter!”

At this her rigid countenance began to stir, as though something were at work in the depths. A wave seemed to rise from her inwards, and her pale cheeks flushed dark red. Her throat twitched, and, with immense difficulty she got out the words:

“After all...one might...one might...surely...”

She choked, and did not finish the sentence. Her face was contorted with malice, and so sinister was her expression, that it was Ledersheim’s turn to be frightened, and he shrank back in alarm. But Crescenz had resumed her work, and was scouring a copper saucepan with a violence that threatened to take the skin off her fingers.

With the return of the mistress, the sense of comfort that had prevailed during her absence was dispelled. Once more began the regime of banging doors and causeless scoldings. Maybe some of the neighbours had sent her anonymous letters to inform her of her husband’s “Goings-on” during her absence, or maybe the lack of warmth in his welcome had been enough to disclose the state of his feelings; in any case, she seemed worse instead of better for her two months’ treatment, since outbursts of weeping alternated with menaces and hysterical scenes. The relations between the couple grew more intolerable day by day. For a few weeks the baron confronted the storm of reproaches, answering evasively and consolingly, with his habitual civility, when she threatened to sue for a divorce or to write to her parents. But this indifferent attitude had an evil effect upon her. She was beginning to believe herself surrounded by secret enemies, and her nervous excitement verged upon persecution mania.

Crescenz had put on her old armour of silence. But now this silence became aggressive and menacing. When her mistress returned, she remained in the kitchen, from which she would not emerge even when summoned to welcome the baroness home. She stood like a figure carved out of wood, her shoulders raised stubbornly, giving such curt answers to questions that the impatient mistress soon ceased asking any and turned away, while Crescenz glared at her unsuspecting back with venom and hatred. Her avarice made her feel that she had been robbed by this return of the mistress of the house, had been deprived of the joys of companionable service and thrust back to toil in the kitchen, while her pet-name of Leporella had been stolen from her. For the baron was careful, in his wife’s presence, to avoid showing any marks of sympathy for Crescenz. Now and again, however, exhausted by the scenes the baroness made, and wanting to draw a breath of relief, he would steal into the kitchen, plump down on one of the hard wooden stools, and exclaim with a groan:

“I can’t stand it any longer!”

These moments in which her idolized master sought refuge in her sympathy were the happiest known to Leporella. She never dared to answer or to attempt consolation, but remained dumb, while looking compassionately at her enslaved god. This soundless sympathy did Ledersheim good for a time. But as soon as he left the kitchen, his worries came back to him with a rush, while Crescenz wrung her hands in impotent fury, or tried to work off her rage by a vengeful scouring of pots and pans and a polishing of silver.

At length the sultry atmosphere of the baroness’s return broke in a terrible storm. During one of the scenes, the baron lost patience, and, abandoning his customary attitude of courteous indifference (that of a schoolboy who is being scolded), he flung out of the room, and, before banging the door so that every window in the flat rattled, he yelled:

“I’m absolutely fed up.”

His face blue with wrath, he burst into the kitchen and shouted to the trembling Crescenz:

“Pack my portmanteau at once and take down my gun-case. I shall go for a week’s shooting. The devil himself could not stick it in such a hell as this.”

Crescenz looked up at him, her eyes shining with enthusiasm. He was master once more, had asserted himself! With a hoarse laugh she said:

“Quite right, Sir. Time and more to put a stop to this!”

Quivering with zeal, she hastened from room to room and got together all he could possibly want for the expedition. She carried portmanteau and gun-case to the cab. But when he was about to say a word of thanks, he was startled by her aspect. Her pinched lips were parted in the malicious smile which always alarmed him, reminding him as it did of what a beast of prey looks like when about to spring. But she curtsied becomingly, and, as he drove off, whispered with an air that was only impertinent because of the intimacy it implied:

“Have a good time, Sir, while you’re away. I’ll tend to everything.”

Three days later the baron was recalled by a laconic wire:

“Essential return home instantly.”

The cousin who had sent it met him at the station, and Ernst’s face was enough to show Rudolf that something terrible had happened. After a futile attempt to “Break the news,” he told the baron that Baroness von Ledersheim had been found dead in bed that morning, with the room full of gas from the unlighted gas-heater. Accident was out of the question. The death must have been intentional, for the gas-heater had not been used throughout the summer, and the weather was still warm. Besides, overnight the dead woman had taken a dozen or more tablets of veronal. Furthermore, Crescenz, the cook, who had been alone in the house with her mistress, testified to having heard the latter go into the dressing-room presumably in order to turn on the master-tap of the gas-stove which for safety was placed there instead of in the bedroom. In view of these facts, the police surgeon had certified the death to be suicidal.

The baron’s hands trembled. When his cousin mentioned Crescenz’s report, his flesh crept, for a distressing thought flashed into his mind. But he repressed the tormenting idea and silently accompanied Ernst to the flat. The corpse had already been removed. His relatives hostile of mien, were awaiting him in the drawing-room, and their condolences were icy. As if accusingly, they “Felt it their duty” to inform him that there would be no possibility of hushing up the scandal, for in the morning the servantmaid had rushed out on to the public staircase screaming, “The missus has killed herself!” They had arranged for a quiet funeral, but already “Society folk” were saying illnatured things. Rudolf listened confusedly, raised his eyes involuntarily towards the door leading from sitting-room into bedroom, and then quickly looked back at the floor. There was that haunting thought he wanted to think out to its logical conclusion-but this idle and hostile chatter made connected thinking impossible. For half an hour his relatives stayed, black-a-vised and reproachful; then, one after another, they bade farewell, leaving Rudolf alone in the darkening chamber stricken by the unexpected blow; with aching head and weary limbs. He still stood, too listless even to sit down.

Someone knocked at the door.

“Come in!” he cried.

The door behind him opened, and there was a sound of hesitating, shuffling footsteps-footsteps he recognized. He was horrified, had a feeling of strangulation in his throat and of goose-flesh all over his body and limbs. He tried to turn round, but his muscles would not obey his will. Thus he remained standing in the middle of th room, tremulous, silent, hands clenched, while fully aware how contemptible must be the aspect of this guilty silence. Then, still from behind, came in a dry, indifferent, matter-of-fact tone, the words:

“I only come to ask whether the master will dine at home or out.”

The baron trembled even more violently, and the icy chill gripped him at the heart. He made three attempts before he could answer:

“Thanks, I want nothing to eat.”

The shuffling footsteps receded before he found courage to look round. Then his immobility was broken. He shook like an aspen leaf, but had strength to leap towards the door and turn the key in the lock, resolved to hinder the re-entry of those detestable and ghostly footsteps. Then he flung himself on the sofa, and vainly tried to strangle the loathsome thought which obtruded itself into his reluctant mind. It was an obsession which kept him awake the livelong night, and would not leave him even when day returned, nor when, clad in the customary suit of solemn black, he stood as chief mourner at the head of his deceased wife’s coffin.

Directly the funeral was over the baron fled from the capital. He could not bear the way in which his friends and relatives looked at him. Their sympathy was tinged with an inquisitorial demeanour—or did he only fancy this to be so? Fancied or real, it was insupportable. Even inanimate objects looked at him accusingly. Every piece of furniture in the flat, and especially those in the bedroom (where the sickly-sweet odour of gas lingered), repelled him whenever he entered the place. But the insufferable hag-riding, whether by night or by day, was the imperturbability of his sometime confidante, who went about her business in the empty dwelling as if nothing untoward had happened. Since that moment at the station when his cousin had mentioned her name, he dreaded contact with her. Whenever he heard her step, it was difficult for him to control the impulse to run away. He was nauseated by the though of her: her harsh voice; her greasy hair; her dull, bestial pitilessness. Rage over-mastered him because he lacked strength to rid himself of the incubus, to tear the stranglehold of her fingers from his throat. His only resource was flight. He packed his trunk secretly, without saying a word to her; and stole away, having scribbled a note to the effect that he was going to stay with friends in Carinthia.

He did not return till the summer was over, except for one brief visit necessitated by matters connected with his late wife’s property. Then he stayed at a hotel, to avoid, having to set eyes upon the bird of evil omen at the flat. Crescenz, who kept herself to herself, never knew that he had been in Vienna. Unoccupied, gloomy as an owl, she spent her days in the kitchen, but went twice to Mass (instead of once only, as previously). The baron’s solicitor provided her with funds and checked her accounts. Of her master she heard not a word, for he neither wrote to her nor sent a message. During this time of silent waiting, her face grew harsher and leaner, her movements became wooden as of old. Thus the months passed for her in a strange condition of rigid apathy.

In the autumn, however, the baron was recalled to the flat by urgent business. He stood hesitant on the threshold. Many weeks spent with intimate friends had enabled him to forget a good deal; but now that he was about to see again in the flesh the woman who had perhaps been his accomplice, he was agitated and near to vomiting, as he had been the day after his wife’s death. Step by step, as he mounted the stairs, it seemed to him that an invisible hand was gripping his throat. He moved slower and slower and had to summon all his forces before he could bring himself to turn his latch-key in the lock.

At the sound, Crescenz rushed out of the kitchen in astonishment. When she saw her master, she urned pale and then, as if making an obeisance, stooped to pick up the hand-valise he had put down in the entry. She forgot to say a word of welcome, and the baron was equally remiss. No “Good day” passed his lips. Silently she carried the valise into his bedroom, and silently he followed. In silence he waited, looking out of the window, till she had left the room. Then he hurriedly locked the door.

That was their only greeting after his long absence.

Crescenz waited. The baron waited too, in the hope that these paroxysms of horror at sight of her would cease to trouble him. But there was no improvement. Even before he saw her, when he merely heard her shuffling footsteps in the passage, he became giddy and had a sensation of nausea. He could not eat a morsel of the breakfast she prepared for him. Morning after morning, he slipped from the house as soon as he was dressed, and did not return till late at night, his object being to avoid a glimpse of her, and to be out of hearing of her movements. The few orders he was obliged to give were given without looking at her. He was choked by the air she breathed.

Crescenz, for her part, spent her days sitting mumchance upon her stool in the kitchen. She did not trouble to prepare food for herself, having no appetite; and she would not say a word to anyone. She sat, timidly awaiting the master’s whistle, like a whipped cur that recognizes it has done wrong. How, precisely, she could have been at fault, she was too stupid to guess. All she knew was that her master, her god, had turned his face away from her, and that his displeasure was agony.

Th days after the baron’s return, the door-bell rang. A grey-haired man, with a quiet demeanour, clean-shaven, carrying a hand-bag, stood on the landing. Crescenz waved him away, but the newcomer explained that he was the valet, that the Herr Baron had ordered him to come at ten, and that Crescenz must announce him. She turned as white as chalk, and stood stock-still for a moment, hand raised and fingers outspread. Then this hand dropped like a winged bird.

“Go and announce yourself,” she said snappishly to the astonished valet, turned on her heel, and retreated into the kitchen, slamming the door behind her.

The manservant stayed on. Thenceforward Rudolf had no need to say a word to Crescenz, giving his orders through the instrumentality of this quiet fellow, who was elderly, and accustomed to service in the best families. Crescenz no longer knew what went on in the flat outside the kitchen, the life of the place flowing over her head like deep water over a stone.

This distressing state of affairs lasted a fortnight, and had upon Crescenz the effect of a wasting disease. Her face fell away, and the hair on her temples turned grey. If her movements had before been wooden, now she seemed turned into stone. She sat motionless as an idol, staring vacantly out of the window; but when she had work to do, she did it in furious, quasi-maniacal out-bursts.

When the fortnight was up, the manservant came one morning unsummoned into the master’s study, and waited discreetly to indicate that he had a communication to make. Once before he had ventured to complain about the offensive manners of the “Tyrolese baggage”, as he disdainfully called her, and had advised her being given notice. On that occasion, however, the baron, feeling sorry for Crescenz, had refused to act on the suggestion. The valet did not dare to press the point. This time, however, the man was more urgent in his representations. When Rudolf said that Crescenz had been a long time in his service, and he saw no adequate ground for dismissing her, the valet, instead of taking no for an answer, looked perplexedly at the baron, reiterated his request, and then, with considerable embarrassment, said:

“Sir, I’m afraid you’ll think me a fool, but the fact is...I’m afraid of the woman....She’s furtive, malicious....The Herr Baron really does not realize how dangerous a person he has as member of his household.”

Ledersheim was alarmed in spite of himself. But the information was too vague.

“Anton,” he said, you must speak more plainly, if I’m to do what you want.”

“Well, Herr Baron, I really can’t say anything definite. What I feel is that Crescenz is like a wild beast, or a beast only half-tamed; and that at any moment she might do me, or you, Sir, a mischief. Yesterday, when I was giving her your orders, she looked at me...it was something more than a look...she glared at me as if about to spring upon me and fix her teeth in my throat. I’m really afraid, Sir, to eat the food she cooks. She might poison me, or you, Sir, any day. The Herr Baron really doesn’t know how dangerous she is. It’s not what she says. She says nothing. But I’m positive she’s ripe for committing a murder.”

Rudolf looked at the accuser in alarm. Had the man heard some gossip? Had he conceived any definite suspicion? Rudolf became aware that his fingers were trembling, and he laid his cigar on the ash-tray, lest this tremor should betray him. But Anton’s face was impassive, and conveyed no sign of unuttered knowledge. The baron hesitated. The valet’s advice marched with his own wishes. He would like to get rid of Crescenz.

“I don’t want to be precipitate,” he said. “Perhaps you are right, but wait a little longer. If she is rude to you again, you can give her notice without consulting me, saying, of course, that you do so on my orders.”

“Very good, Sir,” answered Anton, and the baron went out with a sense of relief—though anything that reminded him of this enigmatical creature poisoned the day for him. The best thing would be, he thought, if Crescenz could be cleared out of the house while he was away—at Christmas, perhaps. The thought of being freed from the incubus did him a lot of good. Christmas would be most suitable. He was going to spend Christmas with friends.

The very next morning, however, immediately after breakfast, when he had seated himself in his study, there came a knock at the door. Unthinkingly he looked up from his newspaper, and called:

“Come in!”

Thereupon, with the hard yet shuffling step he had come to loathe, she entered, the figure that haunted his dreams. He was startled at the change in her. Always ill-favoured, her bony, wasted visage now looked like a death’s-head above her black garments. His detestation was tinged with compassion when he noticed how the down-trodden woman stopped short at the edge of the carpet, too humble to advance nearer. To hide his own emotion, he spoke as unconcernedly as possible:

“What is it, Crescenz?”

Yet, for all he could do, his tone, instead of being cordial, was repellent and angry.

Crescenz did not move, but stared gloomily at the carpet. After a long pause, she managed (like one kicking, something out of the way) to eject the words:

“Anton...Anton says that the Herr Baron gives me notice.”

Genuinely distressed, Rudolf von Ledersheim rose to his feet. He had never intended matters to take so swift a course. Stammeringly he explained that Anton ha been too precipitate. Everything could be smooth over if she could manage to be a little less cross-grained towards the valet. Servants must behave decently to one another; and so on.

Crescenz stood unheeding, her eyes boring into th carpet, her shoulders stubbornly raised, her head hanging disconsolately. She was awaiting a word that did not come. When at last, out of humour at having to assume an apologetic role towards a domestic, he stayed the flow of his eloquence, she still had no answer but mutinous silence.

After this awkward pause had lasted two or three minutes, she said:

“What I want to know is, whether the master himself told Anton to give me notice.”

She flung the words at him, fiercely, morosely. Was there an implied threat? A challenge? Both his cowardice and his sympathy took wings and vanished. Hatred for this woman, which had been accumulating for weeks and months, burst the dams and overflowed. His one desire was to see the last of her. With an abrupt change of tone, he assumed the cutting and circumstantial manner he had learned to use on occasions when he had been an under-secretary of State, and replied:

“Yes, Crescenz, such is the fact. To save trouble, I have put Anton in charge of household affairs. If he has given you notice, you must go. Unless, indeed, you can bring yourself to behave decently to him. Then I might say a word for you, and ask him to overlook your past boorishness. Otherwise, you’ll have to leave; and the sooner the better.”

If she meant to threaten him, she should get as good as she gave! He would stand no nonsense!

But the look which Crescenz now raised from the carpet had no menace in it. Merely that of a hunted beast, which sees the pack break from the coppice where it is about to take refuge.

“Thank you, Sir,” she said in a broken voice. “I’ll leave at once. I don’t want to be a trouble to you.”

Slowly turning, she shuffled out of the room.

That evening when, having returned from the opera, the baron went into his study to look at the letters delivered during the afternoon, he saw on the table an unfamiliar object-an oblong box of peasant workmanship. It was not locked. The contents, carefully arranged, were the trifles Crescenz had received from him: a few postcards sent when he had been away shooting, two theatre tickets, a silver ring. Besides these there was a pile of banknotes (the savings of a lifetime), and a snapshot taken in Tyrol twenty years before. In it her eyes, dazzled by the flashlight, had the distressful and whippedcur expression with which she had received his confirmation of her dismissal.

Much perplexed, the baron rang for Anton to ask why on earth Crescenz had placed her belongings on his study-table. The valet went to call his enemy to account. But Crescenz was not to be found in the kitchen, in her attic bedroom, or anywhere else in the building. Not until next day, when they read a news-item in the paper to the effect that a woman about forty years of age had drowned herself in the Danube, did master and man know what had become of Leporella.

THE RUNAWAY

ONE night during the summer of 1918, a fisherman, in his boat on Lake Geneva, not far from the little Swiss town of Villeneuve, caught sight of something unusual on the surface of the water. Drawing nearer to this object he perceived it to be a raft made of beams roughly tied together, which a naked man was awkwardly trying to paddle forward by means of a plank. The paddler was cold and exhausted, and the amazed fisherman was touched to pity. He helped the shivering voyager on board his own boat, wrapped him in some nets which were the only available covering, and tried to open up a conversation. But the rescued stranger, cowering in the bottom of the boat, answered in a tongue of which the fisherman could not recognize a syllable. Giving up the attempt as a bad job, the latter hauled in the net he had come to examine, and rowed with steady strokes towards the land.

When the outline of the shore grew plain in the gathering light of dawn, the naked man began to look more cheerful. A smile played about the large mouth half hidden in an exuberant and disorderly growth of moustache and beard. Pointing shoreward, he repeatedly exclaimed-half questioningly and half exultantly—a word which sounded like“Rossiya.” His tone grew ever more confident and more joyful as the boat came nearer to the land. At length the keel grated on the beach. The fisherman’s womenfolk, who ran down to help in the landing of the night’s catch, dispersed with cries of alarm, like Nausicaa’s maidens of old when they caught sight of the naked Ulysses. At the strange tidings of what the fisherman had found in the lake, the other men of the village flocked to the strand, among them the mayor of the little place. This worthy fellow, self-important and full of the dignity of office, called to mind all the instructions that had come from headquarters during the four years of the war. Convinced that the newcomer must be a deserter from the French shore of the lake, he promptly endeavoured to make a formal inquiry, but was soon baffled by an impenetrable obstacle—they could not understand one another. To all questions the stranger (rigged out by now in an old pair of trousers and a coat found for him by one of the villagers) made no other answer than his own query, “Rossiya? Rossiya?” uttered in imploring but ever more faltering tones. A trifle annoyed at his failure, the mayor strode off towards the court-house, signing imperatively to the refugee to follow. Amid the babble of the youngsters; who had by now assembled, the bare-footed man, his borrowed habiliments flapping loose about him, did as he was bid, and thus came to the court-house, where he was placed in safe custody. He made no protest; uttered no word; but his face was once more overcast with gloom, and he stooped timidly as if in expectation of a blow.

The news of the fisherman’s remarkable haul soon spread to the neighbouring hotels. Well-to-do visitors, delighted to hear of something which would help them to while away an hour, came in great numbers to inspect the wild man. A lady offered him some sweets, but with monkey-like suspicion he refused to touch them. A visitor with a camera took a snapshot. Crowding round the raree-show they all chattered merrily. At length there arrived upon the scene the manager of one of the largest hotels in the vicinity, a man who had lived in many lands and was a good linguist. He tried the stranger, who was by now bewildered and even frightened, in one tongue after another-German, Italian, English, and finally Russian. At the first word of Russian, the poor fellow started, and instantly plucked up heart. His homely but good-natured countenance was split by a smile reaching from ear to ear. Instantly, and with confident mien he began to pour out his history. It was long and confused and was not in all points intelligible to the chance interpreter. But substantially the story ran as follows.

He had fought in Russia. One day he and a thousand others had been packed into railway carriages, and had travelled a vast distance by train. Then they had all embarked on a ship, and had made a yet longer journey, a voyage across seas on which it was so hot that—as he phrased it—his very bones had been grilled. At length they had landed. Another railway journey, and immediately after leaving the train they had been sent to storm a hill. Of this fight he could say little, for at the very outset he had gone down with a bullet in the leg.

To the auditors, taking up the story as interpreted sentence after sentence by the hotel manager, it was at once obvious that this refugee had belonged to one of the Russian divisions sent across Siberia and shipped to France from Vladivostock. Curiosity mingled with compassion, and everyone wanted to know what had induced the man to start on the remarkable journey that had led him to the lake.

With a smile that was frank, and yet not free from cunning, the Russian explained that while in hospital with his wound he had asked where Russia was, and the general direction of his home had been pointed out to him. As soon as he was able to walk, he had deserted, and had guided his homeward course by sun and stars. He had walked by night; and by day, to elude the patrols, he had hidden in haystacks. For food, he had gathered fruit, and had begged a loaf of bread here a there. At length, after ten nights march, he had reached this lake. Now his tale grew confused. He was a Siberian peasant; his home was close to Lake Baikal; he could make out the other shore of Lake Geneva, and fancied that it must be Russia. He had stolen two beams from hut, and, lying face downwards on these and using board as a paddle, he had made his way far across the lake when the fisherman had found him. He finished his story with the eager question:

“Shall I be able to reach home to-morrow?”

The translation of this inquiry provoked an outburst of laughter from those whose first thought was “Poor simpleton!” But their second thought was tinged with sympathy, and everyone contributed a trifle when a collection was made for the timid and almost tearful deserter.

But now a police official of high rank, summoned by telephone from Montreux, put in an appearance, and with no small difficulty drew up a formal report. Not only was the chance-found interpreter often out of his depth, but the Siberian’s complete lack of culture imposed a barrier between his mind and that of these westerners. He knew little more of himself than that his name was Boris; he could give no surname. He had lived with his wife and three children fifty versts from the great lake. They were the serfs of Prince Metchersky (he used the word “Serfs”, although it is more than half a century since serfdom was abolished in Russia).

A discussion concerning his fate now ensued, while, with bowed shoulders and depressed visage, he stood among the disputants. Some considered that he ought to be sent to the Russian embassy in Berne, but others objected that this could only lead to his being shepherded back to France. The police official explained how difficult it was to decide whether he was to be treated as a deserter, or simply as a foreigner without identification papers. The relieving officer of the district was prompt to explain that this wanderer had certainly no claim to food and lodging at the cost of the local community. A Frenchman excitedly intervened, saying that the case of this wretched absconder was plain that enough: let him be put to work, or sent back across the frontier. Two women protested that the poor man was not to blame for his misfortunes; it was a crime to tear people away from their homes, and to convey them into foreign land. Political quarrels were imminent when an old gentleman, a Dane, suddenly declared his willingness to pay for the stranger’s keep throughout the ensuing week; meanwhile the local authorities could discuss matters with the Russian embassy. This unexpected solution put an end to the official perplexities, and made the lay controversialists forget their differences.

While the argument had been waxing hot, the timid eyes of the runaway had been riveted on the lips of the hotel manager, as the only person in the medley who could make his fate known to him. In a dull fashion, he seemed to understand the complications his coming had aroused. Now, when the tumult of voices ceased, he raised his clasped hands beseechingly towards the manager’s face, like a woman praying before a holy image. All were touched by the gesture. The manager cordially assured him that he could be quite easy in his mind. He would be allowed to stay here for a time. No one would harm him, and his wants would be supplied in the village hostelry. The Russian wanted to kiss the manager’s hand, but the latter would not permit the unfamiliar form of thanksgiving. He took the refugee to the inn were bed and board were to be provided, gave the man reiterated assurances that all was well, and, with a final nod of friendly leave-taking, made his way back to the hotel.

The runaway stared after the manager’s retreating form, and his face clouded over once more at the loss or the only person who could understand him. Regardless of those who were watching his strange demeanour with amusement, he followed the manager with his eyes until his friend vanished into the hotel some way up the hill. Now one of the onlookers touched the Russian compassionately on the shoulder, and pointed to the door of the inn. With hanging head the runaway entered his temporary abode. He was shown into the tap-room, and seated himself at the table, where the maid in welcome, served him with a glass of brandy. Here, overcast with gloom, he spent the rest of the morning. The village children were continually peeping at him through the window; they laughed, and they shouted to him from time to time, but he paid no heed. Customers looked at him inquisitively; but all the time he sat with his eyes fixed on the table, shame-faced and shy. When dinner was served, the room was filled with merry talkative people; but the Russian could not understand a word of their conversation. Painfully aware that he was a stranger among strangers, he was practically deaf and dumb amid folk who could all exchange ideas in lively fashion. His hands were so tremulous that he could hardly eat his soup. A tear coursed down over his cheek, and dropped heavily on to the table. He glanced timidly round. The other guests noticed his distress, and a silence fell upon the company. He was overwhelmed with shame; his unkempt head drooped nearer and nearer to the black wooden table.

He stayed in the tap-room till evening. People came and went, but he was no longer aware of them nor they of him. He continued to sit in the shadow of the stove, resting his hands on the table. Everyone had forgotten his presence. When, in the gloaming, he suddenly rose and went out, nobody marked his going. Like a dumb beast, he walked heavily up the hill to the hotel, and stationed himself humbly, cap in hand just outside the main door. For a whole hour he stood there without claiming notice from anyone. But at length this strange figure, stiff and black like a tree-trunk rooted in front of the brightly lit entrance to the hotel, attracted the attention of one of the porters, who went to fetch the manager. A flicker of cheerfulness came once more into the Siberian’s face at the latter’s first words.

“What do you want, Boris?” asked the manager kindly.

“Beg pardon, Sir,” said the runaway haltingly. “All I want to know is...whether I may go home.”

“Yes, Boris, of course you may go home,” said the manager with a smile.

“To-morrow?”

The other grew serious. The word was said so imploringly that the smile vanished.

“No, Boris, not yet....Not till the war is over.”

“How soon? When will the war be over?”

“God knows! No man can say.”

“Must I wait all that time? Can’t I go sooner?”

“No, Boris.”

“Is my home so far away?”

“Yes.”

“Many days’ journey?”

“Many, many days.”

“But I can walk there. I’m a strong man. I shan’t get tired.”

“You can’t do that, Boris. There’s another frontier to cross before you can get home.”

“A frontier?” He looked perplexed. The word had no meaning for him.

Then, with his marvellous persistency he went on:

“I can swim across.”

The manager could hardly restrain a smile. But he was grieved at the other’s plight, and he said gently:

“No, Boris, you won’t be able to do that. A frontier means a foreign country. The people who live there won’t let you through.”

“But I shan’t do them any harm. I’ve thrown away my rifle. Why should they refuse to allow me to go back to my wife, when I beg them to let me pass for Christ’ sake?”

The manager’s face became still graver. Bitterness filled his soul.

“No,” he said, “They will not let you pass, Boris, not even for Christ’s sake. Men no longer hearken to Christ’ words.”

“But what am I to do, Sir? I cannot stay here. No one understands what I say, and I do not understand anyone.”

“You’ll learn to understand them in time.”

“No, Sir.” He shook his head. “I shall never be able to learn. I can only till the ground, nothing more. What can I do here? I want to go home! Show me the way!”

“There isn’t any way, Boris.”

“But, Sir, they can’t forbid my going back to my wife and children! I’m not a soldier any more!”

“Yes, Boris, they can forbid you.”

“But the Tsar? Surely he will help me?” This was a sudden thought. The runaway trembled with hope, and mentioned the Tsar with intense veneration.

“There is no Tsar now, Boris. He has been deposed.”

“No Tsar now?” He stared vacantly at the manager. The last gleam of hope was extinguished, and the spark faded from his eyes. He said wearily: “So I can’t go home?”

“Not yet. You must wait, Boris.”

“Will it be long?”

“I don’t know.”

The face in the darkness grew ever more despondent.

“I have waited so long! How can I wait any longer? Show me the way. I will try.”

“There is no way, Boris. They will arrest you at the frontier. Stay here, and we will find you something to do.” “They don’t understand me here, and I can’t understand them,” he faltered. “I can’t live here! Help me, Sir!”

“I cannot, Boris.”

“Help me, Sir, for Christ’s sake! Help me, for otherwise I have no hope.”

“I cannot help you, Boris. Men can no longer help one another.”

The two stood gazing into each other’s eyes. Boris twisted his cap between his fingers.

“Why did they take me away from home? They said I had to fight for Russia and the Tsar. But Russia is a long way off, and the Tsar...what did you say they had done to the Tsar?”

“They have deposed him.”

“Deposed?” He repeated the word vaguely. “What am I to do, Sir? I must get home. My children are crying for me. I cannot live here. Help me, Sir, please help me!”

“I cannot, Boris.”

“Can no one help me?”

“No one, now.”

The Russian hung his head still more sadly. Suddenly he spoke in a dull tone:

“Thank you, Sir,” and therewith turned on his heel and departed.

Slowly he walked away down the hill. The manager watched him as he went, and wondered why he did not enter the inn, but passed onwards down the steps leading to the lake. With a sigh, the kindhearted interpreter went back to his work in the hotel.

As chance would have it, the very same fisherman who had rescued the living Siberian from the lake found the drowned man’s naked body in the morning. The runaway had carefully folded the borrowed coat and trousers, had laid them on the shore with the borrowed cap, and had marched down into the water, nude as he had come forth from it. Since the foreigner’s name was unknown, no memorial but a nameless wooden cross could be erected over his grave.

THE ROYAL GAME

THE big liner, due to sail from New York to Buenos Aires at midnight, was filled with the activity and bustle incident to the last hour. Visitors who had come to see their friends off pressed hither and thither, page-boys with caps smartly cocked slithered through the public rooms shouting names snappily, baggage, parcels and flowers were being hauled about, inquisitive children ran up and down companion-ways, while the deck orchestra provided persistent accompaniment. I stood talking to an acquaintance on the promenade deck, somewhat apart from the hubbub, when two or three flash-lights sprayed sharply near us, evidently for press photos of some prominent passenger at a lastminute interview. My friend looked in that direction and smiled.

“You have a queer bird on board, that Czentovic.”

And as my face must have revealed that the statement meant nothing to me he added, by way of explanation, “Mirko Czentovic, the world chess champion. He has just finished off the U.S.A. in a coast-tocoast exhibition tour and is on his way to capture Argentina.”

This served to recall not only the name of the young world champion but also a few details relating to his rocket-like career; my friend a more observant newspaper reader than I, was able to eke them out with a string of anecdotes. At a single stroke, about a year ago, Czentovic had aligned himself with the solidest Elder Statesmen of the art of chess, such as Alekhin, Capa-blanca, Tartakover, Lasker, Boguljobov; not since the appearance of the nine-year-old prodigy, Reshevsky, in New York in 1922, had a newcomer crashed int the famed guild to the accompaniment of such widespread interest. It seems that Czentovic’s intellectual equipment, at the beginning, gave small promise of so brilliant a career. The secret soon seeped through that in his private capacity this champion wasn’t able to write a single sentence in any language without misspelling a word, and that, as one of his vexed colleagues, wrathfully sarcastic, put it, “He enjoys equal ignorance in every field of culture.” His father, a poverty-stricken Yugoslavian boatman on the Danube, had been run down in his tiny vessel one night by a grain steamer, and the orphaned boy, then twelve, was taken in charge by the pastor of their obscure village out of pity. The good man did his level best to instill into the indolent, slowspeaking, low-browed child at home what he seemed unable to grasp in the village school.

But all efforts proved vain. Mirko stared blankly at the writing exercise just as if the strokes had not already been explained a hundred times; his lumbering brain lacked every power to grasp even the simplest subjects. At fourteen he still counted with his fingers, and it was only by dint of great strain that he could read in a book or newspaper. Yet none could say that Mirko was unwilling or disobedient. Whatever he was told to do he did: fetched water, split wood, worked in the field, washed up the kitchen, and he could be relied upon to execute—even if with exasperating slowness—every service that was demanded. But what grieved the kindly pastor most about the blockhead was his total lack of co-operation. He performed no deed unless specially directed, asked no questions, never played with other lads, and sought no occupation of his own accord; after Mirko had concluded his work about the house, he would sit idly with that empty stare one sees with grazing sheep, without participating in the slightest in what might be going on. Of an evening, while the pastor sucked at his long peasant pipe and played his customary three games of chess with the policesergeant, the fair-haired dull-wit squatted silent alongside them, staring from under his heavy lids, seemingly sleepy and indifferent, at the checkered board.

One winter evening, while the two men were absorbed in their daily game, a rapid crescendo of bells gave notice of a quickly approaching sleigh. A peasant, his cap covered with snow, stamped in hastily to tell the pastor that his mother lay dying and to ask his immediate attendance in the hope that there was still time to administer extreme unction. The priest accompanied him at once. The police-sergeant, who had not yet finished his beer, lighted a fresh pipe preparatory to leaving, and was about to draw on his heavy sheepskin boots when he noticed how immovably Mirko’s gaze was fastened on the board with its interrupted game.

“Well, do you want to finish it?” he said jocularly, fully convinced that the sleepyhead had no notion of how to move a single piece. The boy looked up shyly, nodded assent, and took the pastor’s place. After fourteen moves the sergeant was beaten and he had to concede that his defeat was in no wise attributable to avoidable carelessness. The second game resulted similarly.

“Balaam’s ass!” cried the astounded pastor upon his return, explaining to the policeman, a lesser expert in the Bible, that two thousand years ago there had been a like miracle of a dumb being suddenly endowed with the speech of wisdom. The late hour notwithstanding, the good man could not forgo challenging his half-illiterate helper to a contest. Mirko beat him too, with ease. He played toughly, slowly, deliberately, never once raising bowed broad brow from the board. But he played with irrefutable certainty, and in the days that followed neither the priest nor the policeman was able to win a single game.

The priest, best able to assess his ward’s various short comings, now became curious as to the manner in which this one-sided singular gift would resist a severer test. After Mirko had been made somewhat presentable by the efforts of the village barber, he drove him in his sleigh to the near-by town where he knew that many chess-players—a cut above him in ability, he was aware from experience—were always to be found in the cafe on the main square. The pastor’s entrance, as he steered the straw-haired, red-cheeked fifteen-year-old before him, created no small stir in the circle; the boy, in his sheepskin jacket (woollen side in) and high boots, eyes shyly downcast, stood aside until summoned to a chess-table.

Mirko lost the first encounter because his master had never employed the Sicilian defence. The next game, with the best player of the lot, resulted in a draw. But in the third game and the fourth and all that came after he slew them, one after the other.

It so happens that little provincial towns of Yugoslavia are seldom the theatre of exciting events; consequently, this first appearance of the peasant champion before the assembled worthies became no less than a sensation. It was unanimously decided to keep the boy in town until the next day for a special gathering of the chess club and, in particular, for the benefit of Count Simczic of the castle, a chess fanatic. The priest, who now regarded his ward with quite a new pride, but whose joy of discovery was subordinate to the sense of duty which called him home to his Sunday service, consented to leave him for further tests. The chess group put young Czentovic up at the local hotel, where he saw a water-closet for the first time in his life. The chess-room was crowded to capacity on Sunday afternoon. Mirko faced the board immobile for fours, spoke no word, and never looked up; one player after another fell before him. Finally a multiple game after was proposed; it took a while before they could make clear to the novice that he had to play against several contestants at one and the same time. No sooner had Mirko grasped the procedure than he adapted himself to it, and trod slowly with heavy, creaking shoes from table to table, eventually winning seven of the eight games.

Grave consultations now took place. True, strictly speaking, the new champion was not of the town, yet the innate national pride had received a fillip. Here was a chance, at last, for this town, so small that its existence was hardly suspected, to put itself on the map by sending a great man into the world. A vaudeville agent named Koller who supplied the local garrison cabaret with talent, offered to obtain professional training for the youth from a Viennese expert whom he knew, and to see him through for a year if the deficit were, made good. Count Simczic who in his sixty years of daily chess had never encountered so remarkable an antagonist, signed the guarantee promptly. That day marked the opening of the astonishing career of the Danube boatman’s son.

It took only six months for Mirko to master every secret of chess technique, though with one odd limitation which later became apparent to the votaries of the game and caused many a sneer. He never was able to memorize a single game, or, to use the professional term, to play blind. He lacked completely the ability to conceive the board in the limitless space of the imagination. He had to have the field of sixtyfour black and white squares and the thirty-two pieces tangibly before him; even when he had attained international fame he carried a folding pocket board with him in order to be able to reconstruct a game or work on a problem by visual means. This deficit, in itself not important, betrayed a want of imaginative power and provoked animated discussions among chess enthusiasts similar to those in musical circles when it discovers that an outstanding virtuoso or conductor is unable to play or direct without a score. This singularity, however, was no obstacle to Mirko’s stupendous rise, At seventeen he already possessed a dozen prizes, at eighteen he won the Hungarian mastery, and finally, at twenty, the championship of the world. The boldest experts, everyone of them immeasurably his superior in brains, imagination, and audacity, fell before his tough, cold logic as did Napoleon before the clumsy Kutusov and Hannibal before Fabius Cunctator, of whom Livy records that his traits of phlegm and imbecility were already conspicuous in his childhood. Thus it occurred that the illustrious gallery of chess masters, which included eminent representatives of widely varied intellectual fields—philosophers, mathematicians, constructive, imaginative, and often creative talents—was invaded by a complete outsider, a heavy, taciturn peasant from whom not even the cunningest journalists were ever able to extract a word that would help to make a story. Yet, however he may have deprived the newspapers of polished phrases, substitutes in the way of anecdotes about his person were numerous, for, inescapably, the moment he arose from the board at which he was the incomparable master, Czentovic became a grotesque, an almost comic figure. In spite of his correct dress, his fashionable cravat with its too ostentatious pearl tie-pin, and his carefully manicured nails, he remained in manners and behaviour the narrow-minded lout who was accustomed to sweeping out the priest’s kitchen. He utilized his gift and his fame to squeeze out all the money they would yield, displaying petty and often vulgar greed, always with a shameless clumsiness that aroused his professional colleagues’ ridicule and anger. He travelled from town to town, stopped at the cheapest hotels, played for any club that would pay his fee, sold the advertising rights in his portrait to a soap manufacturer,and oblivious of his competitors’ scorn—they being aware that he hardly knew how to write-attached his name to a Philosophy of Chess that had been written by a hungry Galician student for a businessminded publisher. As with all leathery dispositions, he was wanting in any appreciation of the ludicrous; from the time he became champion he regarded himself as the most important man in the world, and the consciousness of having beaten all those clever, intellectual, brilliant speakers and writers in their own field and of earning more than they, transformed his early unsureness into a cold and awkwardly flaunted pride.

“And how can one expect that such rapid fame should fail to befuddle so empty a head?” concluded my friend who had just advanced those classic examples of Czentovic’s childish lust for rank.“Why shouldn’t a twenty-one-year-old lad from the Banat be afflicted with a frenzy of vanity if, suddenly, by merely shoving figures around on a wooden board, he can earn more in a week than his whole village does in a year by chopping down trees under the bitterest conditions? Besides, isn’t it damned easy to take yourself for a great man if you’re not burdened with the slightest suspicion that a Rembrandt, a Beethoven, a Dante, a Napoleon, ever even existed? There’s just one thing in that immured brain of his—the knowledge that he hasn’t lost a game of chess for months, and as he happens not to dream that the world holds other values than chess and money, he has every reason to be infatuated with himself.”

The information communicated by my friend could not fail to excite my special curiosity. I have always been fascinated by all types of monomania, by persons wrapped up in a single idea; for the stricter the limits a man sets for himself, the more clearly he approaches the eternal. Just such seemingly world-aloof persons create their own remarkable and quite unique world-in-little, and work, termite like, in their particular medium. Thus I made no bones about my intention to examine this specimen of one-track intellect under a magnifying glass during the twelve-day journey to Rio.

“You’ll be out of luck,” my friend warned me. “So far as I know, nobody has succeeded in extracting the least bit of psychological material from Czentovic. Underneath all his abyssmal limitations this sly farm-hand conceals the wisdom not to expose himself. The procedure is simple: except with such compatriots of his own sphere as he contrives to meet in ordinary taverns he avoids all conversation. When he senses a person of culture he retreats into his shell; that’s why nobody can plume himself on having heard him say something stupid or on having sounded the presumably bottomless depths of his ignorance.”

As a matter of fact, my friend was right. It proved utterly impossible to approach Czentovic during the first few days of the voyage, unless by intruding rudely, which, of course, isn’t my way. He did, sometimes, appear on the promenade deck, but then always with hands clasped behind his back in a posture of dignified self-absorption, like Napoleon in the familiar painting; and, at that, those peripatetic exhibitions were carried off in such haste and so jerkily that to gain one’s end one would have had to trot after him. The lounges, the bar, the smoking-room, saw nothing of him. A steward of whom I made confidential inquiries revealed that he spent the greater part of the day in his cabin with a large chess-board on which he recapitulated games or worked out new problems.

After three days it angered me to think that his defence tactics were more effective than my will to approach him. I had never before had a chance to know a great chess-player personally, and the more I now sought to familiarize myself with the type, the more incomprehensible seemed a lifelong brain activity that rotated exclusively about a space composed of sixty-four black and white squares. I was well aware from my own experience of the mysterious attraction of the royal game, which among all games contrived by man rises superior to the tyranny of chance and bestows its palm only on mental attainment, or rather on a definite form of mental endowment. But is it not an offensively narrow construction to call chess a game? Is it not a science, a technique, an art, that sways among these categories as Mahomet’s coffin does between heaven and earth, at once a union of all contradictory concepts: primeval yet ever new; mechanical in operation yet effective only through the imagination; bounded in geometric space though boundless in its combinations; ever-developing yet sterile; thought that leads to nothing;mathematics that produce no result; art without works; architecture without substance, and nevertheless, as proved by evidence, more lasting in its being and presence than all books and achievements; the only game that belongs to all peoples and all ages; of which none knows the divinity that bestowed it on the world, to slay boredom, to sharpen the senses, to exhilarate the spirit? One searches for its beginning and for its end. Children can learn its simple rules, duffers succumb to its temptation, yet within this immutable tight square it creates a particular species of master not to be compared with any other—persons destined for chess alone, specific geniuses in whom vision, patience, and technique are operative through a distribution no less precisely ordained than in mathematicians, poets, composers, but merely united on a different level. In the heyday of physiognomical research a Gall would perhaps have dissected the brains of such masters of chess to establish whether a particular coil in the grey matter of the brain, a sort of chess muscle or chess bump was more conspicuously developed than in other skulls. How a physiognomist would have been fascinated by the case of a Czentovic where that which is genius appears interstratified with an absolute inertia of the intellect like a single vein of gold in a ton of dead rock! It stands to reason that so unusual a game, one touched with genius, must create out of itself fitting matadors. This I always knew, but what was difficult and almost impossible to conceive of was the life of a mentally alert person whose world contracts to a narrow, black-andwhite one-way street; who seeks ultimate triumphs in the to-and-fro, forward-and-backward movement of thirty-two pieces; a being who, by a new opening in which the knight is preferred to the pawn, apprehends greatness and the immortality that goes with casual mention in a chess handbook-of a man of spirit who, escaping madness, can unremittingly devote all of his mental energy during ten, twenty, thirty, forty years to the ludicrous effort to corner a wooden king on a wooden board!

And here for the first time, one of these phenomena, one of these singular geniuses (or shall I say puzzling fools?) was close to me, six cabins distant, and I, unfortunate, for whom curiosity about mental problems manifested itself in a kind of passion, seemed unable to effect my purpose. I conjured up the absurdest ruses: should I tickle his vanity by the offer of an interview in an important paper, or engage his greed by proposing a lucrative exhibition tour of Scotland? Finally it occurred to me that the hunter’s never-failing practice is to lure the woodcock by imitating its mating cry, so what more; successful way was there of attracting a chess master’s attention to myself than by playing chess?

At no time had I ever permitted chess to absorb me seriously, for the simple reason that it meant nothing to me but a pastime; if I spend an hour at the board it is not because I want to subject myself to a strain but, on the contrary to relieve mental tension. I “Play” at chess in the literal sense of the word, whereas to real devotees it is serious business. Chess, like love, cannot be played alone, and up to that time I had no idea whether there were other chess lovers on board. In order to attract them from their lairs I set a primitive trap in the smoking-room in that my wife (whose game is even weaker than mine) and I sat at a chessboard as a decoy. Sure enough, we had made no more than six moves before one passer-by stopped, another asked permission to watch, and before long the desired partner materialized. MacIver was his name; a Scottish foundation-engineer who, I learned, had made a large fortune boring for oil in California. He was a robust specimen with an almost square jaw and strong teeth, and a rich complexion pronouncedly rubicund as a result, at least in part surely, of copious indulgence in whisky. His conspicuously broad, almost vehemently athletic shoulders made themselves unpleasantly noticeable in his game, for this MacIver typified those self-important worshippers of success who regard defeat in even a harmless contest as a blow to their self-esteem. Accustomed to achieving his ends ruthlessly, and spoiled by material success, this massive self-made man was so thoroughly saturated with his sense of superiority that opposition of any kind became undue resistance if not insult. After losing the first round he sulked and began to explain in detail, and dictatorially, that it would not have happened but for a momentary oversight; in the third he ascribed his failure to the noise in the adjoining room; never would he lose a game without at once demanding revenge. This ambitious crabbedness amused me at first, but as time went on I accepted it as the unavoidable accompaniment to my real purpose—tempt the master to our table.

By the third day it worked—but only half-way. It may be that Czentovic observed us at the chess-board through a window from the promenade deck or that he just happened to be honouring the smokingroom with his presence; anyway, as soon as he perceived us interlopers toying with the tools of his trade, he involuntarily stepped a little nearer and, keeping a deliberate distance, cast a searching glance at our board. It was MacIver’s move. This one move was sufficient to apprise Czentovic how little a further pursuit of our dilettantish striving was worthy of his expert interest. With the same matter-of-course gesture with which one of us disposes of a poor detective story that has been proffered in a library—without even thumbing its pages—he turned away from our table and left the room. “Weighed in the balance and found wanting,” I thought, slightly stung by the cool, contemptuous look, and to give vent to my ill-humour in some fashion, I said to MacIver, “Your move didn’t seem to impress the master.”

“Which master?”

I told him that the man who had just walked by after glancing disapprovingly at our game was Czentovic, international chess champion. I added that we would be able to survive it without taking his contempt too greatly to heart; the poor have to cook with water. But to my astonishment these idle words of mine produced quite an unexpected result. Immediately he became excited, forgot our game, and his ambition took to an almost audible throbbing. He had no notion that Czentovic was on board: Czentovic simply had to give him a game;the only time he had ever played with a champion was in a multiple game when he was one of forty, even that was fearfully exciting, and he had come quite near winning. Did I know the champion personally?—I didn’t.—Would I not invite him to join us? I declined on the ground that I was aware of Czentovic's reluctance to make new acquaintances. Besides, what charm would intercourse with third-rate players hold for a champion?

It would have been just as well not to say that about third-rate players to a man of MacIver’s brand of conceit. Annoyed, he leaned back and declared gruffly that, as for himself, he couldn’t believe that Czentovic would decline a gentleman’s courteous challenge; he’d see to that. Upon getting a brief description of the master’s person he stormed out, indifferent to our un-finished game, uncontrollably impatient to intercept Czentovic on the deck. Again I sensed that there was no holding the possessor of such broad shoulders once his will was involved in an undertaking.

I waited, somewhat tensed. Some ten minutes elapsed and MacIver returned, not in too good humour, it seemed to me.

“Well?” I asked.

“You were right,” he answered, a bit annoyed. “Not a very pleasant gentleman. I introduced myself and told him who I am. He didn’t even put out his hand. I tried to make him understand that all of us on board would be proud and honoured if he’d play the lot of us. But he was cursed stiff-necked about it; said he was sorry but his contract obligations to his agent definitely precluded any game during his entire tour except for a fee. And his minimum is $250 per game.”

I had to laugh. The thought would never have come to me that one could make so much money by pushing figures from black squares to white ones. “Well, I, hope you took leave of him with courtesy equal to his.”

MacIver, however, remained perfectly serious. “The match is to come off at three to-morrow afternoon. Here in the smoking room. I hope he won’t make mincemeat of us easily.”

“What! You promised him the $250?” I cried quite taken aback.

“Why not? It’s his business. If I had a toothache and there happened to be a dentist aboard, I wouldn’t, expect him to extract my tooth for nothing. The man’s right to ask a fat price; in every line the big shots are the best traders. So far as I’m concerned, the less complicated the business, the better. I’d rather pay in cash than have your Mr. Czentovic do me a favour and in the end have to say ‘Thank you.’ Anyway, many an evening at the club has cost me more than $250 without giving me a chance to play a world champion. It’s no disgrace for a third-rate player to be beaten by a Czentovic.”

It amused me to note how deeply I had injured MacIver’s self-love with that “Third-rate”. But as he was disposed to foot the bill it was not for me to remark on his wounded ambition which promised at last to afford me an acquaintance with my odd fish. Promptly we notified the four or five others who had revealed themselves as chess-players of the approaching event and reserved not only our own table but the adjacent ones so that we might suffer the least possible disturbance from passengers strolling by.

Next day all our group was assembled at the appointed hour. The centre seat opposite that of the master was allotted to MacIver as a matter of course; his nervousness found outlet in the smoking of strong cigars, one after another, and in restlessly glancing ever and again at the clock. The champion let us wait a good ten minutes—my friend’s tale prompted the surmise that something like this would happen—thus heightening the impressiveness of his entry. He approached the table calmly an imperturbably. He offered no greeting. “You know who I am and I’m not interested in who you are” was what his discourtesy seemed to imply, but he, began in a dry, businesslike way to lay down the conditions. Since there were not enough boards on the ship for separate games he proposed that we should play against him collectively. After each of his moves he would retire to the end of the room so that his presence might not affect our consultations. As soon as our countermove had been made we were to strike a glass with a spoon, no table-bell being available. He proposed, if it pleased us ten minutes as the maximum time for each move. Like timid pupils we accepted every suggestion: un-questioningly. Czentovic drew black at the choice of colours, while still standing he made the first counter-move, then turned at once to go to the designated waiting place where he reclined lazily while carelessly examining an illustrated magazine.

There is little point in reporting the game. It ended, as it could not but end, in our complete defeat, and by the twenty-fourth move at that. There was nothing particularly astonishing about an international champion wiping off half a dozen mediocre or sub-mediocre players with his left hand; what did disgust us, though, was the lordly manner with which Czentovic caused us to feel, all too plainly, that it was with his left hand that, we had been disposed of. Each time he would give a quick, seemingly careless look at the board, and would look indolently past us as if we ourselves were dead wooden figures; and this impertinent proceeding reminded one irresistibly of the way one throws a mangy dog a morsel without taking the trouble to look at him. According to my way of thinking, if he had any sensitivity he might have shown us our mistakes or cheered us up with a friendly word. Even at the conclusion this sub-human chess automaton uttered no syllable, but, after saying “Mate,” stood motionless at the table waiting to ascertain whether another game was desired. I had already risen with the thought of indicating by a gesture—helpless as one always remains in the face of thick-skinned rudeness—that as far as I was concerned the pleasure of our acquaintance was ended now that the dollars-and-cents part of it was over, when, to my anger, MacIver, next to me, spoke up hoarsely: “Revanche!”

The note of challenge startled me; MacIver at this moment seemed much more like a pugilist about to put up his fists than a polite gentleman. Whether it was Czentovic’s disagreeable treatment of us that affected him or merely MacIver’s own pathological irritable ambition, suffice it that the latter had undergone a complete change. Red in the face up to his hair, his nostrils taut from inner pressure, he breathed hard, and a sharp fold separated the bitten lips from his belligerently projected jaw. I recognized with disquiet that flicker of the eyes that connotes uncontrollable passion such as seizes players at roulette when the right colour fails to come after the sixth or seventh successively doubled stake. Instantly I knew that this fanatical climber would, even at the cost of his entire fortune, play against Czentovic and play and play and play, for simple or doubled stakes, until he won at least a single game. If Czentovic stuck to it, MacIver would prove a gold-mine that would yield him a nice few thousands by the time Buenos Aires came in sight.

Czentovic remained unmoved. “If you please,” he responded politely. “You gentlemen will take black this time.”

There was nothing different about the second game except that our group became larger because of a few added onlookers, and livelier, too. MacIver stared fixedly at the board as if he willed to magnetize the chess-men to victory; I sensed that he would have paid a thousand dollars with delight if he could but shout “Mate” at our cold-snouted adversary. Oddly enough, something of his sudden excitement entered unconsciously into all of us. Every single move was discussed with greater emotion than before; always we would wrangle up to the last moment before agreeing to signal Czentovic to return to the table. We had come to the seventeenth move and, to our own surprise, entered on a combination which seemed staggeringly advantageous because we had been enabled to advance a pawn to the last square but one; we needed but to move it forward to c1 to win a second queen. Not that we felt too comfortable about so obvious an opportunity; we were united in suspecting that the advantage which we seemed to have wrested could be no more than bait dangled by Czentovic whose vision enabled him to view the situation from a distance of several moves. Yet in spite of common examination and discussion, we were unable to explain it as a feint. At last, at the limit of our ten minutes, we decided to risk the move. MacIver’s fingers were on the pawn to move it to the last square when he felt his arm gripped and heard a voice, low and impetuous, whisper, “For God’s sake! Don’t!”

Involuntarily we all turned about. I recognized in the man of some forty-five years, who must have joined the group during the last few minutes in which we were absorbed in the problem before us, one whose narrow sharp face had already arrested my attention on deck strolls because of its extraordinary, almost chalky pallor. Conscious of our gaze, he continued rapidly:

“If you make a queen he will immediately attack with the bishop, then you’ll take it with your knight. Meantime, however, he moves his pawn to d7, threatens your rook, and even if you check with the knight you’re lost and will be wiped out in nine or ten moves. It’s practically the constellation that Alekhin introduced when he played Boguljobov in 1922 at the championship tournament at Pistany.”

Astonished, MacIver released the pawn and, like the rest of us, stared amazedly at the man who had descended in our midst like a rescuing angel. Anyone who can reckon a mate nine moves ahead must necessarily be a first-class expert, perhaps even a contestant now on his way to the tournament to seize the championship, so that his sudden presence, his thrust into the game at precisely the critical moment,partook almost of the supernatural.

MacIver was the first to collect himself. “What do you advise?” he asked suppressedly.

“Don’t advance yet; rather a policy of evasion. First of all, get the king out of the danger line from g8 to h7. Then he’ll probably transfer his attack to the other flank. Then you parry that with the rook, c8 to c4; two moves and he will have lost not only a pawn but his superiority, and if you maintain your defensive properly you may be able to make it a draw. That’s the best you can get out of it.”

We gasped, amazed. The precision no less than the rapidity of his calculations dizzied us; it was as if he had been reading the moves from a printed page. For all that, this unsuspected turn by which, thanks to his cutting in, the contest with a world champion promised a draw, worked wonders. Animated by a single thought, we moved aside so as not to obstruct his observation of the board.

Again MacIver inquired: “The king, then; to h7?”

“Surely. The main thing is to duck.”

MacIver obeyed and we rapped on the glass. Czentovic came forward at his habitual even pace, his eyes swept the board and took in the countermove. Then he moved the pawn h2 to h4 on the king’s flank exactly as our unknown aid had predicted. Already the latter was whispering excitedly:

“The rook forward, the rook, to c4; then he’ll first have to cover the pawn. That won’t help him, though. Don’t bother about his pawns but attack with the knight c3 to d5, and the balance is again restored. Press the offensive instead of defending.”

We had no idea of what he meant. He might have been talking Chinese. But once under his spell MacIver did as he had been bidden. Again we struck the glass to recall Czentovic. This was the first time that he made no quick decision; instead he looked fixedly at the board. His eyebrows contracted involuntarily. Then he made his move, the one which our stranger had said he would, and turned to go. Yet before he started off something novel and unexpected happened. Czentovic raised his eyes and surveyed our ranks; plainly he wanted to ascertain who it was that offered such unaccustomed energetic resistance.

From this moment our excitement grew immeasurably. Thus far we had played without genuine hope, but now every pulse beat hotly at the thought of breaking Czentovic's cold disdain. Without loss of time our new friend had directed the next move and we were ready to call Czentovic back. My fingers trembled as I hit the spoon against the glass. And now we registered our first triumph. Czentovic, who hitherto had executed his purpose standing, hesitated, hesitated and finally sat down. He did this slowly and heavily, but that was enough to cancel—in a physical sense if in no other—the difference in levels that had previously obtained. We had necessitated his acknowledgment of equality, spatially at least. He cogitated long, his eyes resting immovably on the board so that one could scarcely discern the pupils under the heavy lids, and under the strained application his mouth opened gradually, which gave him a rather foolish look. Czentovic reflected for some minutes, then made a move and rose. At once our friend said half audibly:

“A stall! Well thought out! But don’t yield to it. Force an exchange, he’s got to exchange, then we’ll get a draw and not even the gods can help him.”

MacIver did as he was told. The succeeding manoeuvres between the two men—we others had long since become mere supernumeraries—consisted of a back-and-forth that we were unable to comprehend. After some seven moves Czentovic looked up after a period of silence and said, “Draw.”

For a moment a total stillness reigned. Suddenly one heard the rushing of the waves and the jazzing radio in the adjacent drawingroom; one picked out every step on the promenade outside and the faint thin susurration of the wind that carried through the windowframes. None of us breathed; it had come upon us too abruptly and we were nothing less than frightened in the face of the impossible: that this stranger should have been able to force his will on the world champion in a contest already half lost. MacIver shoved himself back and relaxed, and his suppressed breathing became audible in the joyous “Ah” that passed his lips. I took another look at Czentovic. It had already seemed to me during the later moves that he grew paler. But he understood how to maintain his poise. He persisted in his apparent imperturbability and asked, in a negligent tone, the while he pushed the figures off the board with a steady hand:

“Would you like to have a third game, gentlemen?”

The question was matter-of-fact, just business. What was noteworthy was that he ignored MacIver and looked straight and intently into the eyes of our rescuer. Just as a horse takes a new rider’s measure by the firmness of his seat, he must have become cognizant of who was his real, in fact his only, opponent. We could not help but follow his gaze and look eagerly at the unknown. However, before he could collect himself and formulate an answer, MacIver in his eager excitement, had already cried to him in triumph:

“Certainly, no doubt about it! But this time you’ve got to play him alone! You against Czentovic!”

What followed was quite extraordinary. The stranger, who curiously enough was still staring with a strained expression at the bare board, became affrighted upon hearing the lusty call and perceiving that he was the centre of observation. He looked confused.

“By no means, gentlemen,” he said halting, plainly perplexed.“Quite out of the question. You’ll have to leave me out. It’s twenty, no, twenty-five years since I sat at a chess-board and...and I’m only now conscious of my bad manners in crashing into your game without so much as a by your leave....Please excuse my presumption. I don’t want to interfere further.” And before we could recover from our astonishment he had left us and gone out.

“But that’s just impossible!” boomed the irascible MacIver, pounding with his fist. “Out of the question that this fellow hasn’t played chess for twenty-five years. Why, he calculated every move, every counter move, five or six in advance. You can’t shake that out of your sleeve. Just out of the question—isn’t it?”

Involuntarily, MacIver turned to Czentovic with the last question. But the champion preserved his unalterable frigidity.

“It’s not for me to express an opinion. In any case there was something queer and interesting about the man’s game; that’s why I purposely left him a chance.”

With that he rose lazily and added, in his objective manner: “If he or you gentlemen should want another game to-morrow, I’m at your disposal from three o’clock on.”

We were unable to suppress our chuckles. Everyone of us knew that the chance which Czentovic had allowed his nameless antagonist had not been prompted by generosity and that the remark was no more than a childish ruse to cover his frustration. It served to stimulate the more actively our desire to witness the utter humbling of so unshakable an arrogance. All at once we peaceable, indolent passengers were seized by a mad ambitious will to battle, for the thought that just on our ship, in mid ocean, the palm might be wrested from the champion—a record that would be flashed to every news agency in the world—fascinated us challengingly. Added to that was the lure of the mysterious which emanated from the unexpected entry of our saviour at the crucial instant, and the contrast between his almost painful modesty and the rigid self-consciousness of the professional. Who was this unknown? Had destiny utilized this opportunity to command the revelation of a yet undiscovered chess phenomenon? Or was it that we were dealing with an expert, who, for some undisclosed reason, craved anonymity? We discussed these various possibilities excitedly; the most extreme hypotheses were not sufficiently extreme to reconcile the stranger’s puzzling shyness with his surprising declaration in the face of his demonstrated mastery. On one point, however, we were of one mind:to forgo no chance of a renewal of the contest. We resolved to exert ourselves to the limit to induce our godsend to play Czentovic the next day, MacIver pledging himself to foot the bill. Having in the meantime learned from the steward that the unknown was an Austrian, I, as his compatriot, was delegated to present our request.

Soon I found our man reclining in his deck-chair, reading. In the moment of approach I used the opportunity to observe him. The sharply-chiselled head rested on the cushion in a posture of slight exhaustion; again I was struck by the extraordinary colourlessness of the comparatively youthful face framed at the temples by glistening white hair, and I got the impression, I cannot say why, that this person must have aged suddenly. No sooner did I stand before him than he rose courteously and introduced himself by a name that was familiar to me as belonging to a highly respected family of old Austria. I remembered that a bearer of that name had been an intimate friend of Schubert, and that one of the old Emperor’s physicians-in-ordinary had belonged to the same family. Dr. B. was visibly dumbfounded when I stated our wish that he should take Czentovic on. It proved that he had no idea that he had stood his ground against a champion, let alone the most famous one in the world at the moment. For some reason this news seemed to make a special impression on him, for he inquired once and again whether I was sure that his opponent was truly a recognized holder of international honours. I soon perceived that this circumstance made my mission easier, but sensing his refined feelings, I considered it discreet to withhold the fact that MacIver would be a pecuniary loser in case of an eventual defeat. After considerable hesitation Dr. B. at last consented to a match, but with the proviso that my fellow-players be warned against putting extravagant hope in his expertness.

“Because,” he added with a clouded smile, “I really don’t know whether I have the ability to play the game according to all the rules. I assure you that it was not by any means false modesty that made me say that I hadn’t touched a chess-man since my college days, say more than twenty years. And even then I had no particular gifts as a player.”

This was said so simply that I had not the slightest doubt of its truth. And yet I could not but express wonderment at his accurate memory of the details of positions in games by many different masters;he must, at least, have been greatly occupied with chess theory. Dr. B. smiled once more in that dreamy way of his.

“Greatly occupied! Heaven knows it’s true enough that I have occupied myself with chess greatly. But that happened under quite special, I might say unique, circumstances. The story of it is rather complicated and it might go as a little chapter in the story of our agreeable epoch. Do you think you would have patience for half an hour...?”

He waved towards the deck-chair next to his, I accepted the invitation gladly. There were no near neighbours. Dr. B. removed his reading spectacles, laid them to one side, and began.

“You were kind enough to say that, as a Viennese, you remembered the name of my family. I am pretty sure, however, that you could hardly have heard of the law office which my father and I conducted—and later I alone—for we had no cases that got into the papers and we avoided new clients on principle. In truth, we no longer had a regular law practice but confined ourselves exclusively to advising, and mainly to administering the fortunes of the great monasteries with which my father, once a Deputy of the Clerical Party, was closely connected. Besides—in this day and generation I am no longer obliged to keep silence about the Monarchy—we had been entrusted with the investment of the funds of certain members of the Imperial family. These connections with the Court and the Church—my uncle had been the Emperor’s household physician, another was an abbot in Seitenstetten—dated back two generations; all we had to do was to maintain them, and the task allotted to us through this inherited confidence—a quiet, I might almost say a soundless, task—really called for little more than strict discretion and dependability, two qualities which my late father possessed in full measure; he succeeded, in fact, through his prudence in preserving considerable values for his clients through the years of inflation as well as the period of collapse. Then, when Hitler seized the helm in Germany and began to raid the properties of churches and cloisters, certain negotiations and transactions, initiated from the other side of the frontier with a view to saving at least the movable valuables from confiscation, went through our hands and we two knew more about sundry secret transactions between the Curia and the Imperial house than the public will ever learn of. But the very inconspicuousness of our office—we hadn’t even a sign on the door—as well as the care with which both of us almost ostentatiously kept out of Monarchist circles, offered the safest protection from officious investigations. In fact, no Austrian official had ever suspected that during all those years the secret couriers of the Imperial family delivered and fetched their most important mail in our unpretentious fourth floor office.

“It happened that the National Socialists began, long before they armed their forces against the world, to organize a different but equally schooled and dangerous army in all contiguous countries—the legion of the unprivileged, the despised, the injured. Their so-called ‘cells’ nested themselves in every office, in every business; they had listening-posts and spies in every spot, right up to the private chambers of Dollfuss and Schuschnigg. They had their man, as alas! I learned only too late, even in our insignificant office. True, he was nothing but a wretched, ungifted clerk whom I had engaged, on the recommendation of a priest, for no other purpose than to give the office the appearance of a going concern;all that we really used him for were innocent errands, answering the telephone, and filing papers, that is to say papers of no real importance. He was not allowed to open the mail. I typed important letters myself and kept no copies. I took all essential documents to my home, and I held private interviews nowhere but in the priory of the cloister or in my uncle’s consultation-room. The measures of caution prevented the listening-post from seeing anything that went on; but some unlucky happening must have made the vain and ambitious fellow aware that he was mistrusted and that interesting things were going on behind his back. It may have been that in my absence one of the couriers made a careless reference to ‘His Majesty’ instead of the stipulated ‘Baron Fern,’ or that the rascal opened letters surreptitiously. Whatever the reason, before I had so much as suspected him he managed to get a mandate from Berlin or Munich to watch us. It was only much later, long after my imprisonment began, that I remembered how his early laziness at work had changed in the last few months to a sudden eagerness when he frequently offered, almost intrusively, to post my letters. I cannot acquit myself of a certain amount of imprudence, but after all, haven’t the greatest diplomats and generals of the world too been out-maneuvered by Hitler’s cunning? Just how precisely and lovingly the Gestapo had long been directing its attention to me was manifested tangibly by the fact that the S.S. people arrested me on the evening of the very day of Schuschnigg’s abdication, and a day before Hitler entered Vienna. Luckily I had been able to burn the most important documents upon hearing Schuschnigg’s farewell address over the radio, and the other papers, along with the indispensable vouchers for the securities held abroad for the cloisters and two archdukes, I concealed in a basket of laundry which my faithful housekeeper took to my uncle. All of this almost literally in the last minute before the fellows stove my door in.”

Dr. B. interrupted himself long enough to light a cigar. I noticed by the light of the match a nervous twitch at the right corner of his mouth that had struck me before and which, as far as I could observe, recurred every few minutes. It was merely a fleeting vibration, hardly stronger than a breath, but it imparted to the whole face a singular restlessness.

I suppose you expect that I’m going to tell you about concentration camp to which all who held faith with our old Austria were removed;about the degradations, martyrings and tortures that I suffered there. Nothing of the kind happened. I was in a different category. I was not put with those luckless ones on whom they released their accumulated resentment by corporal and spiritual degradation, but rather was assigned to that small group out of which the National Socialists hoped to squeeze money or important information. My obscure person in itself meant nothing to the Gestapo, of course. They must have guessed, though, that were the dummies, the administrators and confidants, of their most embittered adversaries, and what they expected to compel from me was incriminating evidence, evidence against the monasteries to support charges of violation by those who had selflessly taken up the cudgels for the Monarchy. They suspected, and not without good reason, that a substantial portion of the funds that we handled was still secreted and inaccessible to their lust for loot—hence their choice of me on the very first day in order to force the desired information by their trusted methods. That is why persons of my sort, to whom they looked for money or significant evidence, were not dumped into a concentration camp but were sorted out for special handling. You will recall that our Chancellor, and also Baron Rothschild, from whose family they hoped to extort millions, were not planted behind barbed wire in a prison camp but, ostensibly privileged, were lodged in individual rooms in a hotel, the Metropole, which happened to be the Gestapo headquarters; the same distinction was bestowed on my insignificant self.

“A room to oneself in a hotel—sounds pretty descent doesn’t it? But you may believe me that they had not in mind a more decent but a more crafty technique when, instead of stuffing us ‘prominent’ ones in blocks of twenty into icy barracks, they housed us in tolerably heated hotel rooms, each by himself. For the pressure by which they planned to compel the needed testimony was to be exerted more subtly than through common beating or physical torture: by the most conceivably complete isolation. They did nothing to us; they merely deposited us in the midst of nothing, knowing well that of all things the most potent pressure on the soul of man is nothingness. By placing us singly, each in an utter vacuum, in a chamber that was hermetically closed to the world without, it was calculated that the pressure created from inside, rather than cold and the scourge, would eventually cause our lips to spring apart.

“The first sight of the room allotted to me was not at all repellent. There was a door, a table, a bed, a chair, a wash-basin, a barred window. The door, however, remained closed night and day; the table remained bare of book, newspaper, pencil, paper; the window gave on a brick wall; my ego and my physical self were contained in a structure of nothingness. They had taken every object from me: my watch, that I might not know the hour; my pencil, that I might not make a note; my pocket-knife, that I might not sever a vein; even the slight narcotic of a cigarette was forbidden me. Except for the warder, who was not permitted to address me or to answer a question, I saw no human face, I heard no human voice. From dawn to night there was no sustenance for eye or ear or any sense; I was alone with myself, with my body and four or five inanimate things, rescuelessly alone with table, bed, window, and basin. One lived like a diver in his bell in the black ocean of this silence—like a diver, too, who is dimly aware that the cable to safety has already snapped and that he never will be raised from the soundless depths. There was nothing to do, nothing to hear, nothing to see; about me; everywhere and without interruption, there was nothingness, emptiness without space or time. I walked to and fro, and with me went my thoughts to and fro, to and fro, ever again. But even thoughts, insubstantial as they seem require an anchorage if they are not to revolve and circle around themselves; they too weigh down under nothingness. One waited for something from morn to eve and nothing happened. Nothing happened. One waited, waited, waited; one thought, one thought, one thought until one’s temples smarted. Nothing happened. One remained alone. Alone. Alone.

“That lasted for a fortnight, during which I lived outside of time, outside the world. If war had broken out then I would never have discovered it, for my world comprised only table, door, bed, basin, chair, window and wall every line of whose scalloped pattern embedded itself as with a steel graver in the innermost folds of my brain every time it met my eye. Then, at last, the hearings began. Suddenly I received a summons; I hardly knew whether it was day or night. I was called and led through a few corridors, I knew not whither; then I waited and knew not where it was, and found myself standing at a table behind which some uniformed men were seated. Piles of papers on the table, documents of whose contents I was in ignorance; and then came the questions, the real ones and the false, the simple and the cunning, the catch questions and the dummy questions; and whilst I answered, strange and evil fingers toyed with papers whose contents I could not surmise, and strange evil fingers wrote a record and I could not know what they wrote. But the most fearsome thing for me at those hearings was that I never could guess or figure out what the Gestapo actually knew about the goings on in my office and what they sought to worm out of me. I have already told you that at the last minute I gave my housekeeper the really incriminating documents to take to my uncle. Had he received them? Had he not received them? How far had I been betrayed by that clerk? Which letters had they intercepted and what might they not already have screwed out of some clumsy priest at one of the cloisters which we represented?

“And they heaped question on question. What securities had I bought for this cloister, with which banks had I corresponded, do I know Mr. So-and-so or do I not, had I corresponded with Switzerland and with God-knows-where? And not being able to divine what they had already dug up, every answer was fraught with danger. Were I to admit something that they didn’t know I might be unnecessarily exposing somebody to the axe, if I denied too much I harmed myself.

“The worst was not the examination. The worst was the return from the examination to my void, to the same room with the same table,the same bed, the same basin, the same wall-paper. No sooner was I by myself than I tried to recapitulate, to think of what I should have said and what I should say next time so as to divert any suspicion that a careless remark of mine might have aroused. I pondered, I combed through, I probed, I appraised every single word of testimony before the examining officers. I restated their every question and every answer that I made. I sought to sift out the part that went into the protocol, knowing well that it was all incalculable and unascertainable. But these thoughts, once given rein in empty space, rotated in my head unceasingly, always starting afresh in ever-changing combinations and insinuating themselves into my sleep.

“After every hearing by the Gestapo my own thoughts took over no less inexorably the martyrizing questions, searchings and torments, and perhaps even more horribly, for the hearings at least ended after an hour, but this repetition, thanks to the spiteful torture of solitude, ended never. And always the table, chest, bed, wallpaper, window;no diversion, not a book or magazine, not a new face, no pencil with which to jot down an item, not a match to toy with—nothing, nothing, nothing. It was only at this point that I apprehended how devilishly intelligently, with what murderous psychology, this hotel-room system was conceived. In a concentration camp one would, perhaps, have had to wheel stones until one’s hands bled and one’s feet froze in one’s boots; one would have been packed in stench and cold with a couple of dozen others. But one would have seen faces, would have had space, a tree, a star, something, anything, to stare at, while here everything stood before one unchangeably the same, always the same, maddeningly the same. There was nothing here to switch me off from my thoughts, from my delusive notions, from my diseased recapitulating. That was just what they purposed: they wanted me to gag and gag on my thoughts until they choked me and I had no choice but to spit them out at last, to admit-admit everything that they were after, finally to yield up the evidence and the people.

“I gradually became aware of how my nerves were slacking under the grisly pressure of the void and, conscious of the danger, I tensed myself to the bursting point in an effort to find or create any sort of diversion. I tried to recite or reconstruct everything I had ever memorized in order to occupy myself—the folk songs and nursery rhymes of childhood, the Homer of my high-school days, clauses from the Civil Code. Then I did problems in arithmetic, adding or dividing, but my memory was powerless without some integrating force. I was unable to concentrate on anything. One thought flickered and darted about: how much do they know? What is it that they don’t know? What did I say yesterday—what ought I to say next time?

“This simply indescribable state lasted four months. Well, four months; easy to write, just about a dozen letters! Easy to say, too: four months, a couple of syllables. The lips can articulate the sound in a quarter of a second: four months. But nobody can describe or measure or demonstrate, not to another or to himself, how long a period endures in the spaceless and timeless, nor can one explain to another how it eats into and destroys one, this nothing and nothing and nothing that is all about, everlastingly this table and bed and basin and wall-paper, and always that silence, always the same warder who shoves the food in without looking at one, always those same thoughts that revolve around one in the nothingness, until one becomes insane.

“Small signs made me disturbedly conscious that my brain was not working right. Early in the game my mind had been quite clear at the examinations; I had testified quietly and deliberately; my twofold thinking—what should I say and what not?—had still functioned. Now I could no more than articulate haltingly the simplest sentences, for while I spoke my eyes were fixed in a hypnotic stare on the pen that sped recordingly across the paper as if I wished to race after my own words. I felt myself losing my grip, I felt that the moment was coming closer and closer when, to rescue myself, I would tell all I knew and perhaps more; when, to elude the strangling grip of that nothingness, I would betray twelve persons and their secrets without deriving any advantage myself but the respite of a single breath.

“One evening I really reached that limit: the warder had just served my meal at such a moment of desperation when I suddenly shrieked after him: ‘Take me to the Board! I’ll tell everything! I want to confess! I’ll tell them where the papers are and where the money is! I’ll tell them everything! Everything!’ Fortunately he was far enough away not to hear me. Or perhaps he didn’t want to hear me.

“An event occurred in this extremest need, something unforeseeable, that offered rescue, rescue if only for a period. It was late in July, a dark, ominous, rainy day: I recall these details quite definitely because the rain was rattling against the windows of the corridor through which I was being led to the examination. I had to wait in the ante-room of the audience chamber. Always one had to wait before the session; the business of letting one wait was a trick of the game. They would first rip one’s nerves by the call, the abrupt summons from the cell in the middle of the night, and then, by the time one was keyed to the ordeal with will and reason tensed to resistance, they caused one to wait, meaningless meaningful waiting, an hour, two hours, three hours before the trial, to weary the body and humble the spirit. And they caused me to wait particularly long on this Thursday, the 27th of July; twice the hour struck while I attended, standing, in the ante-room; there is a special reason, too, for my remembering the date so exactly.

“A calendar hung in this room—it goes without saying that they never permitted me to sit down; my legs bored into my body for two hours—and I find it impossible to convey to you how my hunger for something printed, something written, made me stare at these figures, these few words, ‘27 July,’ against the wall; I wolfed them into my brain. Then I waited some more and waited and looked to see when the door would open at last, meanwhile reflecting on what my inquisitors might ask me this time, knowing well that they would ask me something quite different from that for which I was schooling myself. Yet in the face of all that, the torment of the waiting and standing was nevertheless a blessing, a delight, because this room was, after all, a different from my own, somewhat larger and with two windows instead of one, and without the bed and without the basin and without that crack in the window-sill that I had regarded a million times. The door was painted differently, a different chair stood against the wall, and to the left stood a filing cabinet with documents as well as a clothes—stand on which three or four wet militia coats hung—my torturers’ coats. So that I had something; new, something different to look at, at last something different for my starved eyes, and they clawed greedily at every detail.

“I took in every fold of those garments; I observed for example, a drop suspended from one of the wet collars and, ludicrous as it may sound to you, I waited in an inane excitement to see whether the drop would eventually detach itself and roll down or whether it would resist gravity and stay put; truly, this drop held me breathless for minutes, as if my life had been at stake. It rolled down after all, and then I counted the buttons on the coats again, eight on one, eight on another, ten on the third, and again I compared the rank marks; all of these absurd and unimportant trifles toyed with, teased, and pinched my hungry eyes with an avidity which I forgo trying to describe. And suddenly I saw something that paralysed my gaze. I had discovered a slight bulge in the side-pocket of one of the coats. I moved closer to it and thought that I recognized, by the rectangular shape of the protrusion, what this swollen pocket harboured: a book! My knees trembled: a book!

“I hadn’t had a book in my hand for four months, so that the mere idea of a book in which words appear in orderly arrangement, of sentences, pages, leaves, a book in which one could follow and stow in one’s brain new, unknown, diverting thoughts, was at once intoxicating and stupefying.

Hypnotized, my eyes rested on the little swelling which the book inside the pocket formed; they glowered at the spot as if to burn a hole in the coat. The moment came when I could no longer control my greed;involuntarily I edged nearer. The mere thought that my hands might at least feel the book through the cloth made the nerves of my fingers tingle to the nails. Almost without knowing what I did, I found myself getting closer to it.

“Happily the warder ignored my singular behaviour; indeed it may have seemed to him quite natural that a man wanted to lean against a wall, after standing erect for two hours. And then I was quite close to the coat, my hands purposely clasped behind me so as to be able to touch the coat unnoticed. I felt the stuff and the contact confirmed that here was something square, something flexible, and that it crackled softly-book, a book! And then a thought went through me like a shot:steal the book! If you can turn the trick, you can hide the book in your cell and read, read, read-read again at last. The thought, hardly lodged in me, operated like a strong poison; at once there was a singing in my ears, my heart hammered, my hands froze and resisted my bidding. But after that first numbness I pressed myself softly and insinuatingly against the coat; I pressed—always fixing the warder with my eye—the book up out of the pocket, higher and higher, with my artfully concealed hands. Then: a tug, a gentle, careful pull, and in no time the little book was in my hand. Not until now was I frightened at my deed. Retreat was no longer possible. What to do with it? I shoved the book under my trousers at the back just far enough for the belt to hold it, then gradually to the hip so that while walking I could keep it in place by holding my hands on the trouser-seams, military fashion. I had to try it out, so I moved a step from the clothes-stand, two steps, three steps. It worked. It was possible to keep the book in place while walking if I but kept pressing firmly against my belt.

“Then came the hearing. It demanded greater attention than ever on my part, for while answering I concentrated my entire effort on securing the book inconspicuously rather than on my testimony. Luckily this session proved to be a short one and I got the book safely to room, though it slipped into my trousers most dangerously while in the corridor on my way back and I had to simulate a violent fit of coughing as an excuse for bending over to get it under my belt again. But what a moment; that, as I bore it back into my inferno, alone at last yet no longer alone!

“You will suppose, of course, that my first act was to seize the book, examine it and read it. Not at all! I wanted, first of all, to savour the joy of possessing a book; the artificially prolonged and nerveinflaming desire to day-dream about the kind of book I would wish this stolen one to be: above all, very small type, narrowly spaced, with many, many letters, many, many thin leaves so that it might take long to read. And then I wished to myself that it might be one that would demand mental exertion, nothing smooth or light; rather something from which I could learn and memorize, preferably—oh, what an audacious dream!—Goethe or Homer. At last I could no longer check my greed and my curiosity. Stretched on the bed so as to arouse no suspicion in case the warder might open the door without warning, tremblingly I drew the volume from under my belt.

“The first glance produced not merely disappointment but a sort of bitter vexation, for this booty, whose acquirement was surrounded with such monsterous danger and such glowing hope, proved to be nothing more than a chess anthology, a collection of one hundred and fifty championship games. Had I not been barred, locked in, I would in my first rage, have thrown the thing through an open window; for what was to be done—what could be done—with nonsense of the kind? Like most of the other boys at school, I had now and then tried my hand at chess to kill time. But of what use was this theoretical stuff to me? You can’t play chess alone, and certainly not without chess-men and a board. Annoyed I thumbed the pages, thinking to discover reading matter of some sort, an introduction, a manual; but besides the bare rectangular reproductions of the various master games with their symbols a1-a2, Kt.-f1-Kt.-g3, etc.-to me then unintelligible, I found nothing. All of it appeared to me as a kind of algebra the key to which was hidden. Only gradually I puzzled out that the letters a, b, c stood for the vertical rows, the figures 1 to 8 for the rows across, and indicated the current position of each figure; thus these purely graphic expressions did, nevertheless, attain to speech.

“Who knows, I thought, if I were able to devise a chess-board in my cell I could follow these names through; and it seemed like a sign from heaven that the weave of my bedspread disclosed a coarse checker-work. With proper manipulation it yielded a field of sixty-four squares. I tore out the first leaf and concealed the book under my mattress. Then, from bits of bread that I sacrificed, I began to mould king, queen, and the other figures (with ludicrous results, of course), and after no end of effort I was finally able to undertake on the bedspread the reproduction of the positions pictured in the chess book. But my absurd bread-crumb figures, half of which I had covered with dust to differentiate them from ‘white’ ones, proved utterly inadequate when I tried to pursue the printed game. I was all confusion in those first days; I would have to start a game afresh five times, ten times, twenty times. But who on earth had so much unused and useless time as I, slave of emptiness, and who commanded so much immeasurable greed and patience!

“It took me six days to play the game to the end with out an error, and in a week after that I no longer required the chess-men to comprehend the relative positions and in just one more week I was able to dispense with the bedspread; the printed symbols, a1, a2, c7, c8, at first abstractions to me, automatically transformed themselves into visual plastic positions. The transposition had been accomplished perfectly. I had projected the chess-board and its figures within myself and, thanks to the bare rules, observed the immediate set-up just as a practised musician hears all instruments singly and in combination upon merely glancing at a printed score.

“It cost me no effort, after another fortnight, to play every game in the book from memory or, in chess language, blind; and only then did I begin to understand the limitless benefaction which my impertinent theft constituted. For I had acquired an occupation—a senseless, a purposeless one if you wish—yet one that negated the nothingness that enveloped me; the one hundred and fifty championship games equipped me with a weapon against the strangling monotony of space and time.

“From then on, to conserve the charm of this new interest without interruption, I divided my day precisely: two games in the morning, two in the afternoon, a quick recapitulation in the evening. That served to fill my day which previously had been as shapeless as jelly; I had something to do that did not tire me, for a wonderful feature of chess is that through confining mental energy to a strictly bounded field the brain does not flag even under the most strained concentration; rather it makes more acute its agility and energy. In the course of time the repetition of the master games, which had at first been mechanical, awakened an artistic, a pleasurable comprehension in me. I learned to understand the refinements, the tricks and feints in attack and defence; I grasped the technique of thinking ahead, planning combinations and riposting, and soon recognized the personal note of each champion in his individual method as infallibly as one spots a particular poet on hearing only a few lines. That which began as a mere time-killing occupation became a joy, and the personalities of such great chess strategists as Alekhin, Lasker, Boguljobov and Tartakover entered into my solitude as beloved comrades.

“My silent cell was constantly and variously peopled, and the very regularity of my exercises restored my already impaired intellectual capacity; my brain seemed refreshed and, because of constant disciplined thinking, even keenly whetted. My ability to think more clearly and concisely manifested itself, above all, at the hearings;unconsciously I had perfected myself at the chess-board in defending myself against false threats and masked dodges, from this time on I gave them no openings at the sessions and I even harboured the thought that the Gestapo men began, after a while, to regard me with a certain respect. Possibly they asked themselves, seeing so many others collapse, from what secret sources I alone found strength for such unshakable resistance.

“This period of happiness in which I played through the one hundred and fifty games in that book systematically, day by day, continued for about two and a half to three months. Then I arrived unexpectedly at a dead point. Suddenly I found myself once more facing nothingness. For by the time that I had played through each one of these games innumerable times, the charm of novelty and surprise was lost, the exciting and stimulating power was exhausted. What purpose did it serve to repeat again and again games whose every move I had long since memorized? No sooner did I make an opening move than the whole thing unravelled of itself; there was no surprise, no tension, no problem. At this point I would have needed another book with more games to keep me busy, to engage the mental effort that had become indispensable to divert me. This being totally impossible, my madness could take but one course: instead of the old games I had to devise new ones myself. I had to try to play the game with myself or, rather, against myself.

“I have no idea to what extent you have given thought to the intellectual status of this game of games. But one doesn’t have to reflect deeply to see that if pure chance can determine a game of calculation, it is an absurdity in logic to play against oneself. The fundamental attraction of chess lies, after all, in the fact that its strategy develops in different wise in two different brains, that in this mental battle Black,ignorant of White’s immediate manoeuvres, seeks constantly to guess and cross them, while White, for his part, strives to penetrate Black’s secret purposes and to outstrip and parry them. If one person tried to be both Black and White you have the preposterous situation that one and the same brain at once knows something and yet does not know it;that, functioning as White’s partner, it can instantly obey a command to forget what, a moment earlier as Black’s partner, it desired and plotted. Such cerebral duality really implies a complete cleavage of the conscious, a lighting up or dimming of the brain function at pleasure as with a switch; in short, to want to play against oneself at chess is about as paradoxical as to want to jump over one’s own shadow.

“Well, briefly, in my desperation I tried this impossibility, this absurdity, for months. There was no choice but this nonsense if I was not to become quite insane or slowly to disintegrate mentally. The fearful state that I was in compelled me at least to attempt this split between Black ego and White ego so as not to be crushed by the horrible nothingness that bore in on me.”

Dr. B. relaxed in his deck-chair and closed his eyes for a minute. It seemed as if he were exerting his will to suppress disturbing recollection. Once again the left corner of his mouth twitched in that strange and evidently uncontrollable manner. Then he settled himself a little more erectly.

“Well, then, I hope I’ve made it all pretty intelligible to this point. I’m sorry, but I doubt greatly that the rest of it can be pictured quite as clearly. This new occupation, you see, called for so unconditional a harnessing of the brain as to make any simultaneous self-control impossible. I have already intimated my opinion that chess contest with oneself spells nonsense, but there is a minimal possibility for even such an absurdity if a real chess-board is present, because the board, being tangible, affords a sense of distance, a material extraterritoriality. Before a real chess-board with real chessmen you can stop to think things over, and you can place yourself physically first on this side of the table, then on the other, to fix in your eyes how the scene looks to Black and how it looks to White. Obliged as I was to conduct these contests against myself—or with myself, as you please—on an imaginary field, so I was obliged to keep fixedly in mind the current set-up on the sixty four squares, and besides, to make advance calculations as to the possible further moves open to each player, which meant—I know how mad this must sound to you—imagining double, triply, no, imagining sextuply, duodecibly for each one of my egos, always four or five moves in advance.

“Please don’t think that I expect you to follow through the involutions of this madness. In these plays in the abstract space of fantasy I had to figure out the next four or five moves in my capacity of White, likewise as Black, thus considering every possible future combination with two brains, so to speak, White’s brain and Black’s brain. But even this auto-cleaving of personality was not most dangerous aspect of my abstruse experiment; rather it was that with the need to play independently I lost my foothold and fell into a bottomless pit. Then mere replaying of championship games, which I had been indulging in during the preceding weeks, had been, after all, no more than a feat of repetition, a straight recapitulation of given material and, as such, no greater strain than to memorize poetry or learn sections of the Civil Code by heart; it was a delimited, disciplined function and thus an excellent mental exercise. My two morning games, my two in the afternoon, represented a definite task that I was able to perform coolly; it was a substitute for normal occupation and, moreover, if I erred in the progress of a game or forgot the next move, I always had recourse to the book. It was only because the replaying of others’ games left my self out of the picture that this activity served to soothe and heal my shattered nerves; it was all one to me whether Black or White was victor, for was it not Alekhin or Boguljobov who sought the palm, while my own person, my reason, my soul derived satisfaction as observer, as fancier of the niceties of those jousts as they worked out. From the moment at which I tried to play against myself I began, unconsciously, to challenge myself. Each of my egos, my Black ego and my White ego, had to contest against the other and become the centre, each on its own, of an ambition, an impatience to win, to conquer, after each move that I made as Ego Black I was in a fever of curiosity as to what Ego White would do. Each of my egos felt triumphant when the other made a bad move and likewise suffered chagrin at similar clumsiness of its own.

“All that sounds senseless, and in fact such a self-produced schizophrenia, such a split consciousness with its fund of dangerous excitement, would be unthinkable in a person under normal conditions. Don’t forget, though that I had been violently torn from all normality, innocently charged and behind bars, for months martyrized by the refined employment of solitude—a man seeking an object against which to discharge his long-accumulated rage. And as I had nothing else than this insane match with myself, that rage, that lust for revenge, canalized itself fanatically into the game. Some-thing in me wanted to justify itself, but there was only this other self with which I could wrestle; so while the game was on, an almost maniac excitement waxed in me. In the beginning my deliberations were still quiet and imposed; I would pause between one game and the next so as to recover from the effort;but little by little my frayed nerves forbade all respite. No sooner had Ego White made a move than Ego Black feverishly plunged a piece forward; scarcely had a game ended but I challenged myself to another, for each time, of course, one of my chess-egos was beaten by the other and demanded satisfaction.

“I shall never be able to tell, even approximately, how many games I played against myself during those months in my cell as a result of this crazy insatiability; a thousand perhaps, perhaps more. It was an obsession against which I could not arm myself; from dawn to night I thought of nothing but knights and pawns, rooks and kings, and a b and c, and ‘Mate!’ and ‘Castle’; my entire being and every sense embraced the checkered board. The joy of play became a lust for play;the lust for play became a compulsion to play, a frenetic rage, a mania which saturated not only my waking hours but eventually my sleep, too. I could think only in terms of chess, only in chess moves, chess problems; sometimes I would wake with a damp brow and become aware that a game had unconsciously continued in my sleep, and if I dreamt of persons it was exclusively in the moves of the bishop, the rook in the advance and retreat of the knight’s move.

“Even when I was brought before the examining Board I was no longer able to keep my thoughts within the bounds of my responsibilities; I’m inclined to think that I must have expressed myself confusedly at the last sessions, for my judges would glance at one another strangely. Actually I was merely waiting, while they questioned and deliberated, in my cursed eagerness to be led back to my cell so that I could resume my mad round, to start a fresh game, and another and another. Every interruption disturbed me; even the quarter-hour in which the warder cleaned up the room, the two minutes in which he served my meals, tortured my feverish impatience; sometimes the midday meal stood untouched on the tray at evening because the game made me forgetful of food. The only physical sensation that I experienced was a terrible thirst; the fever of this constant thinking and playing must already have manifested itself then; I emptied the bottle in two swallows and begged the warder for more, and nevertheless felt my tongue dry in my mouth in the next minute.

“Finally my excitement during the games rose—by that time I did nothing else from morning till night—to such a height that I was no longer able to sit still for a minute; uninterruptedly, while cogitating on a move, I would walk to and fro, quicker and quicker, to and fro, to and fro, and the nearer the approach to the decisive moment of the game the hotter my steps; the lust to win, to victory, to victory over myself increased to a sort of rage; I trembled with impatience, for the one chess-ego in me was always too slow for the other. One would whip the other forward and, absurd as this may seem to you, I would call angrily,‘quicker, quicker!’ or ‘Go on, go on!’ when the one self in me failed to riposte to the other’s thrust quickly enough. It goes without saying that I am now fully aware that this state of mine was nothing less than a pathological form of overwrought mind for which I can find no other name than one not yet known to medical annals: chess poisoning.

“The time came when this monomania, this obsession, attacked my body as well as my brain. I lost weight, my sleep was restless and disturbed, upon waking I had to make great efforts to compel my leaded lids to open; sometimes I was so weak that when I grasped a glass I could scarcely raise it to my lips, my hands trembled so; but no sooner did the game begin than a mad power seized me: I rushed up and down, up and down with fists clenched, and I would sometimes hear my own voice as through a reddish fog, shouting hoarsely and angrily at myself,‘Check!’ or ‘Mate!’

“How this horrible, indescribable condition reached its crisis is something that I am unable to report. All that I know is that I woke one morning and the waking was different from usual. My body was no longer a burden, so to speak; I rested softly and easily. A tight, agreeable fatigue, such as I had not known for months, lay on my eyelids; the feeling was so warm and benignant that I couldn’t bring myself to open my eyes. For minutes I lay awake and continued to enjoy this heavy soddenness, this tepid reclining in agreeable stupefaction. All at once I seemed to hear voices behind me, living human voices, low whispering voices that spoke words; and you can’t possibly imagine my delight, for months had elapsed, perhaps a year, since I had heard other words than the hard, sharp, evil ones from my judges. 'You’re dreaming,’ I said to myself. ‘You’re dreaming! Don’t, in any circumstances, open your eyes. Let the dream last or you’ll again see the cursed cell about you, the chair and wash-stand and the table and the wall-paper with the eternal pattern. You’re dreaming—keep on dreaming!’

But curiosity held the upper hand. Slowly and carefully I raised my lids. A miracle! It was a different room in which I found myself, a room wider and more ample than my hotel cell. An unbarred window emitted light freely and permitted a view of trees, green trees swaying in the wind, instead of my bald brick partition; the walls shone white and smooth, above above me a high white ceiling. I lay in a new and unaccustomed bed and—surely, it was no dream—human voices whispered behind me.

“In my surprise I must have made an abrupt, involuntary movement, for at once I heard an approaching step. A woman came softly, a woman with a white head-dress, a nurse, a Sister. A delighted shudder ran through me: I had seen no woman for a year. I stared at the lovely apparition, and it must have been a glance of wild ecstasy, for she admonished me, ‘quiet, don’t move.’ I hung only on her voice, for was not this a person who talked! Was there still somebody on earth who did not interrogate me, torture me? And to top it all—ungraspable wonder!—a soft, warm, almost tender woman’s voice. I stared hungrily at her mouth, for the year of inferno had made it seem to me impossible that one person might speak kindly to another. She smiled at me—yes, she smiled; then there still were people who could smile benevolently—put a warning finger to her lips, and went off noiselessly. But I could not obey her order; I was not yet sated with the miracle. I tried to wrench myself into a sitting posture so as to follow with my eyes this wonder of a human being who was kind. But when I reached out to support my weight on the edge of the bed something failed me. In place of my right hand, fingers, and wrist I became aware of something foreign—a thick, large, white cushion, obviously a comprehensive bandage. At first I gaped uncomprehendingly at this bulky object, then slowly I began to grasp where I was and to reflect on what could have happened to me. They must have injured me, or I had done some damage to my hand myself. The place was a hospital.

“The physician, an amiable elderly man, turned up at noon. He knew my family and made so genial an allusion to my uncle, the Imperial household doctor, as to create the impression that he was well disposed towards me. In the course of conversation he put all sorts of questions, one of which, in particular, astonished me: Was I a mathematician or a chemist? I answered in the negative.

“‘Strange,’ he murmured. ‘In your fever you cried out such unusual formulas, c3, c4. We could make nothing of it.’

“I asked him what had happened to me. He smiled oddly.

“‘Nothing too serious. An acute irritation of the nerves,’ and added in a low voice, after looking carefully around, ‘And quite intelligible, of course. Let’s see, it was March 13, wasn’t it!’

“I nodded.

“‘No wonder, with that system,’ he admitted. ‘You’re not the first. But don’t worry.’ The manner of his soothing speech and sympathetic smile convinced me that I was in a safe haven.

“A couple of days thereafter the doctor told me quite of his own accord what had taken place. The warder had heard shrieks from my cell and thought, at first, that I was disputing with somebody who had broken in. But no sooner had he shown himself at the door than I made for him, shouted wildly something that sounded like ‘Aren’t you ever going to move, you rascal, you coward?’ grasped at his windpipe, and finally attacked him so ferociously that he had to call for help. Then when they were dragging me, in my mad rage, for medical examination, I had suddenly broken loose and thrust myself against the window in the corridor, thereby lacerating my hand—see this deep scar. I had been in a sort of brain fever during the first few days in the hospital, but now he found my perceptive faculties quite in order. ‘To be sure,’ said he under his voice, it’s just as well that I don’t report that higher up or they may still come and fetch you back there. Depend on me, I’ll do my best.’

“Whatever it was that this benevolent doctor told my torturers about me is beyond my knowledge. In any case, he achieved what he sought to achieve: my release. It may be that he declared me irresponsible, or it may be that my importance to the Gestapo had diminished, for Hitler had since occupied Bohemia, thus liquidating the case of Austria. I had merely to sign an undertaking to leave the country within a fortnight, and this period was so filled with the multitude of formalities that now surround a journey—military certificate, police, tax and health certificates, passport, visas—as to leave me no time to brood over the past. Apparently one’s brain is controlled by secret, regulatory powers which automatically switch off whatever may annoy or endanger the mind, for every time I wanted to ponder on my imprisonment the light in my brain seemed to go off; only after many weeks, indeed only now, on this ship, have I plucked up enough courage to pass in review all that I lived through.

“After all this you will understand my unbecoming and perhaps strange conduct to your friends. It was only by chance that I was strolling through the smoking-room and saw them sitting at the chessboard; my feet seemed rooted where I stood from astonishment and fright. For I had totally forgotten that one can play chess with a real board and real figures, forgotten that two physically separate persons sit opposite each other at this game. Truly it took me a few minutes before I remembered that what those men were playing was what I had been playing, against myself during the months of my helplessness. The cipher-code which served me in my worthy exercises was but a substitute, a symbol for these solid figures; my astonishment that this pushing about of pieces on the board was the same as the imaginary fantastics in my mind must have been like that of an astronomer who, after complicated paper calculations as to the existence of a new planet, eventually really sees it in the sky as clear white, substantial body. I stared at the board as if magnetized, and saw there my setup, knight, rook, king, queen, and pawns, as genuine figures carved out of wood. In order to get the hang of the game I had voluntarily to transmute it from my abstract realm of numbers and letters into the movable figures. Gradually I was overcome with curiosity to observe a real contest between two players. Then followed that regrettable and impolite interference of mine with your game. But that mistaken move of your friend’s was like a stab at my heart. It was pure instinct that made me hold him back, a quite impulsive grasp like that with which one involuntarily seizes a child leaning over a banister. It was not until afterwards that I became conscious of the impropriety of my intrusiveness.”

I hastened to assure Dr. B. that we were all happy about the incident to which we owed his acquaintance and that, after what he had confided in me, I would be doubly interested in the opportunity to see him at tomorrow’s improvised tournament.

“Really, you mustn’t expect too much. It will be nothing but a test for me—a test whether I—whether I’m at all capable of dealing with chess in a normal way, in a game with a real board with substantial chess-men and a living opponent—for now I doubt more than ever that those hundreds, they may have been thousands, of games that I played were real games according to the rules, and not merely a sort of dreamchess, fever-chess, a delirium in which, as always in dreams, one skips intermediate steps. Surely you do not seriously believe that I would measure myself against a champion, that I expect to give tit for tat to the greatest one in the world. What interests and fascinates me is nothing but the humous curiosity to discover whether what went on in my cell was chess or madness, whether I was then at the dangerous brink or already beyond it—that’s all, nothing else.”

At this moment the gong summoning passengers to dinner was heard. The conversation must have lasted almost two hours, for Dr.B. had told me his story in much greater detail than that in which I assemble it. I thanked him warmly and took my leave. I had hardly covered the length of the deck when he was alongside me visibly nervous, saying with something of a stutter:

“One thing more. Will you please tell your friends beforehand, so that it should not later seem discourteous, that I will play only one game....The idea is merely to close an old account—a final settlement, not a new beginning....I can’t afford to sink back a second time into that passionate play-fever that I recall with nothing but horror. And besidesbesides, the doctor warned me, expressly warned me. Everyone who has ever succumbed to a mania remains for ever in jeopardy, and a sufferer from chess poisoning—even if discharged as cured—had better keep away from a chess-board. You understand, then—only this one experimental game for myself and no more.”

We assembled in the smoking-room the next day promptly at the appointed hour, three o’clock. Our circle had increased by yet two more lovers of the royal game, two ship’s officers who had obtained special leave from duty to watch the tourney. Czentovic, too, not as on the preceding day, was on time. After the usual choice of colours there began the memorable game this homo obscurissimus against the celebrated master.

I regret that it was played for thoroughly incompetent observers like us, and that its course is as completely lost to the annals of the art of chess as are Beethoven’s improvisations to music. True, we tried to piece it together from our collective memory on the following afternoons but in vain; very likely, in the passion of the moment we had allowed our interest to centre on the players rather than on the game. For the intellectual contrast between the contestants became physically plastic according to their manner as the play proceeded. Czentovic, the creature of routine, remained the entire time as immobile as a block, his eyes unalterably fixed on the board; thinking seemed to cost him almost physical effort that called for extreme concentration on the part of every organ. Dr. B., on the other hand, was completely slack and unconstrained. Like the true dilettante, in the best sense of the word, to whom only the play in play—the diletto—gives joy, he relaxed fully,explained moves to us in easy conversation during the early intervals, lighted a cigarette carelessly, and glanced at the board for a minute only when it came his turn to play. Each time it seemed as if he had expected just the move that his antagonist made.

The perfunctory moves came off quite rapidly. It was not until the seventh or eighth that something like a definite plan seemed to develop. Czentovic prolonged his periods of reflection; by that we sensed that the actual battle for the lead was setting in. But, to be quite frank, the gradual development of the situation represented to us lay observers, as usually in tournament games, something of a disappointment. The more the pieces wove themselves into a singular design the more impenetrable became the real lie of the land. We could not discern what one or the other rival purposed or which of the two had the advantage. We noticed merely that certain pieces insinuated themselves forward like levers to undermine the enemy front, but since every move of these superior players was part of a combination that comprised a plan for several moves ahead, we were unable to detect the strategy of their back-and-forth.

An oppressive fatigue took possession of us, largely because of Czentovic’s interminable cogitation between moves, which eventually produced visible irritation in our friend too. I observed uneasily now the longer the game stretched out, he became increasingly restless, moving about in his chair, nervously lighting a succession of cigarettes, occasionally seizing a pencil to make a note. He would order mineral water and gulp it down, glass after glass; it was plain that his mind was working a hundred times faster than Czentovic’s. Every time the latter, after endless reflection, decided to push a piece forward with his heavy hand, our friend would smile like one who encounters something long expected and make an immediate riposte. In his nimble mind he must have calculated every possibility that lay open to his opponent;the longer Czentovic took to make a decision the more his impatience grew, and during the waiting his lips narrowed into an angry and almost inimical line. Czentovic, however, did not allow himself to be hurried. He deliberated, stiff and silent, and increased the length of the pauses the more the field became denuded of figures. By the forty-second move, after one and a half hours, we sat limply by, almost indifferent to what was going on in the arena. One of the ship's officers had already departed, another was reading a book and would look up only when a piece had been moved. Then, suddenly at a move of Czentovic’s, the unexpected happened. As soon as Dr. B. perceived that Czentovic took hold of the bishop to move it, he crouched like a cat about to spring. His whole body trembled and Czentovic had no sooner executed his intention than he pushed his queen forward and said loudly and triumphantly, “There! That’s done with!”, fell back in his chair, his arms crossed over his breast and looked challengingly at Czentovic. As he spoke his pupils gleamed with a hot light.

Impulsively we bent over the board to figure out the significance of the move so ostentatiously announced. At first blush no direct threat was observable. Our friend’s statement, then, had reference to some development that we short-thoughted amateurs could not prefigure. Czentovic was the only one among us who had not stirred at the provocative call; he remained as still as if the insulting “Done with” had glanced of him unheard. Nothing happened. Everybody held his breath and at once the ticking of the clock that stood on the table to measure the moves became audible. Three minutes passed, seven minutes, eight minutes—Czentovic was motionless, but I thought I noticed an inner tension that became manifest in the greater distension of his thick nostrils.

This silent waiting seemed to be as unbearable to our friend as to us. He shoved his chair back, rose abruptly and began to traverse the smoking room, first slowly, then quicker and quicker. Those present looked at him wonderingly, but none with greater uneasiness than I, for I perceived that in spite of his vehemence this pacing never deviated from a uniform span; it was as if, in this awful space, he would each time come plump against an invisible cupboard that obliged him to reverse his steps. Shuddering, I recognized that it was an unconscious reproduction of the pacing in his erstwhile cell; during those months of incarceration it must have been exactly thus that he rushed to and fro, like a caged animal; his hands must have been clenched and his shoulders hunched exactly like this; it must have been like this that he pelted forward and back a thousand times there, the red lights of madness in his paralysed though feverish stare. Yet his mental control seemed still fully intact, for from time to time he turned impatiently towards the table to see if Czentovic had made up his mind. But time stretched to nine, then ten minutes.

What occurred then, at last, was something that none could have predicted. Czentovic slowly raised his heavy hand, which, until then, had rested inert on the table. Tautly we all watched for the upshot. Czentovic, however, moved no piece, but instead, with the back of his hand pushed, with one slow determined sweep, all the figures from the board. It took us a moment to comprehend: he gave up the game. He had capitulated in order that we might not witness his being mated. The impossible had come to pass: the champion of the world, victor at innumerable tournaments, had struck his colours before an unknown man, who hadn’t touched a chess-board for twenty or twenty-five years. Our friend the anonymous, the ignotus, had overcome the greatest chess master on earth in open battle.

Automatically, in the excitement, one after another rose to his feet;each was animated by the feeling that he must give vent to the joyous shock by saying or doing something. Only one remained stolidly at rest:Czentovic. After a measured interval he lifted his head and directed a stony look at our friend.

“Another game?” he asked.

“Naturally,” answered Dr. B. with an enthusiasm that was disturbing to me, and he seated himself, even before I could remind him of his own stipulation to play only once, and began to set up the figures in feverish haste. He pushed them about in such heat that a pawn twice slid from his trembling fingers to the floor; the pained discomfort that his unnatural excitement had already produced in me grew to something like fear. For this previously calm and quiet person had become visibly exalted; the twitching of his mouth was more frequent and in every limb he shook as with fever.

“Don’t,” I said softly to him. “No more now; you’ve had enough for to-day. It’s too much of a strain for you.”

“Strain! Ha!” and he laughed loudly and spitefully. “I could have played seventeen games during that slow ride. The only strain is for me to keep awake.—Well, aren’t you ever going to begin?”

These last words had been addressed in an impetuous, almost rude tone to Czentovic. The latter glanced at him quietly and evenly, but there was something of a clenched fist in that adamantine stubborn glance. On the instant a new element had entered: a dangerous tension a passionate hate. No longer were they two players in a sporting way; they were two enemies sworn to destroy each other. Czentovic hesitated long before making the first move, and I had a definite sensation that he was delaying on purpose. No question but that this seasoned tactician had long since discovered that just such dilatoriness wearied and irritated his antagonist. He used no less than four minutes for the normal, the simplest of openings, moving the king’s pawn two spaces. Instantly our friend advanced his king’s pawn, but again Czentovic was responsible for an eternal, intolerable pause; it was like waiting with beating heart for the thunder-clap after a streak of fiery lightning, and waiting—with no thunder forthcoming. Czentovic never stirred. He meditated quietly, slowly, and as I felt, increasingly, maliciously slowly—which gave me plenty of time to observe Dr. B. He had just about consumed his third glass of water; it came to my mind that he had spoken of his feverish thirst in his cell. Every symptom of abnormal excitement was plainly present: I saw his forehead grow moist and the scar on his hand become redder and more sharply outlined. Still, however, he held himself in rein. It was not until the fourth move, when Czentovic again pondered exasperatingly, that he forgot himself and exploded with, “Aren’t you ever going to move?”

Czentovic looked up coldly. “As I remember it, we agreed on a tenminute limit. It is a principle with me not to make it less.”

Dr. B. bit his lips. I noticed under the table the growing restlessness with which he lifted and lowered the sole of his shoe, and I could not control the nervousness the that overcame me because of the oppressive prescience of some insane thing that was boiling in him. As a matter of fact, there was a second encounter at the eighth move. Dr. B., whose self-control diminished with the increasing periods of waiting, could no longer conceal his tension; he was restless in his seat and unconsciously began to drum on the table with his fingers. Again Czentovic raised his peasant head.

“May I ask you not to drum. It disturbs me. I can’t play with that going on.”

“Ha, ha,” answered Dr. B. with a short laugh, “One can see that.”

Czentovic flushed. “What do you mean by that?” he asked, sharply and evilly.

Dr. B. gave another curt and spiteful laugh. “Nothing except that it’s plain that you’re nervous.”

Czentovic lowered his head and said nothing. Seven minutes elapsed before he made his move, and that was the funereal tempo at which the game dragged on. Czentovic became correspondingly stonier;in the end he utilized the maximum time before determining on a move, and from interval to interval the conduct of our friend became stranger and stranger. It appeared as if he no longer had any interest in the game but was occupied with something quite different. He abandoned his excited pacing and remained seated motionlessly. Starring into the void with a vacant and almost insane look, he uninterruptedly muttered unintelligible words; either he was absorbed in endless combinations or—and, this was my inner suspicion—he was working out quite other games, for each time that Czentovic got to the point, a move he had to be recalled from his absent state. Then it took a minute or two to orient himself. My conviction grew that he had really forgotten all about Czentovic and the rest of us in this cold aspect of his insanity which might at any instant discharge itself violently. Surely enough, at the nineteenth move the crisis came. No sooner had Czentovic executed his play than Dr. B., giving no more than a cursory look at the board, suddenly pushed his bishop three spaces forward and shouted so loudly that we all started.

“Check! Check, the king!”

Every eye was on the board in anticipation of an extraordinary move. Then, after a minute, there was an unexpected development. Very slowly Czentovic tilted his head and looked—which he had never done before—from one face to another. Something seemed to afford him a rich enjoyment, for little by little his lips gave expression to a satisfied and scornful smile. Only after he had savoured to the full the triumph which was still unintelligible to us did he address us, saying with mock deference:

“Sorry—but I see no check. Perhaps one of you gentlemen can see my king in check!”

We looked at the board and then uneasily over at Dr. B. Czentovic’s king was fully covered against the bishop by a pawn—a child could see that—thus the king could not possibly be in check. We turned one to the other. Might not our friend in his agitation have pushed a piece over the line, a square too far one way or the other? His attention arrested by our silence, Dr. B. now stared at the board and began, stutteringly:

“But the king ought to be on f7—that’s wrong, all wrong—Your move was wrong! All the pieces are misplaced-the pawn should be on g5 and not on g4. Why, that’s quite a different game – that’s—”

He halted abruptly. I had seized his arm roughly, or rather I had pinched it so hard that even in his feverish bewilderment he could not but feel my grip. He turned and looked at me like a somnambulist.

“What—what do you want?”

I only said “Remember!” at the same time lightly drawing my finger over the scar on his hand. Automatically he followed my gesture, his eyes fixed glassily on the blood-red streak. Suddenly he began to tremble and his body shook.

“For God’s sake,” he whispered with pale lips. “Have I said or done something silly? Is it possible that I’m again...?”

“No,” I said, in a low voice, “But you have to stop the game at once. It’s high time. Recollect what the doctor said.”

With a single movement Dr. B. was on his feet. “I have to apologize for my stupid mistake,” he said in his old, polite voice, inclining himself to Czentovic. “What I said was plain nonsense, of course. It goes without saying that the game is yours.” Then to us: “My apologies to your gentlemen, also. But I warned you beforehand not to expect too much from me. Forgive the disgrace-it is the last time that I yield to the temptation of chess.”

He bowed and left in the same modest and mysterious manner in which he had first appeared before us. I alone knew why this man would never again touch a chess-board, while the others, a bit confused, stood around with that vague feeling of having narrowly escaped something uncomfortable and dangerous. “Damned fool,” MacIver grumbled in his disappointment. Last of all, Czentovic rose from his chair, half glancing at the unfinished game.

“Too bad,” he said generously. “The attack wasn’t at all badly conceived. The man certainly has lots of talent for an amateur.”